[ Silence ]
>> Hello, good afternoon,
welcome to session 505,
"Harnessing Metadata
in Audiovisual Media".
I've heard we are competing
with the "Intro to Swift" talk
so get intimate with
your neighbors here.
My name is Adam Sonnanstine.
I'm an engineer on
the AVFoundation team
and today we are going to talk
about, of course, metadata.
So what do I mean by metadata?
Well, for the purposes
of this talk we're going
to define metadata to mean
any data that is stored
in movie files, streaming
presentations, any other sort
of audiovisual presentation
that describes the primary data,
like the audio and video that
we think about when we think
of those sorts of presentations.
Some examples are
always helpful.
One you should be familiar
is iTunes metadata,
when you have this sort of
the song names and the artists
and the album artwork
in your iTunes library.
All these things are stored
as the sort of metadata
that I'm talking about
today in the files
in your iTunes library.
Besides iTunes metadata,
we also have things
like location information.
If you have a movie that
you took with your iPhone
or some other location-enabled
device and you played it
in QuickTime player, that will
show up in the info window
to tell you where you were
when you took that movie.
That's also stored as
the kind of metadata
that we are talking about today.
Some new features, we know that
you're not always standing still
when you are taking your videos.
So new in iOS 8 and OS X
Yosemite, we have features
that support things like dynamic
location, that's a location
that changes over time.
So these are some new features
that we are going to be talking
about later on that we are
pretty excited about and,
in addition to location, this
really applies to any sort
of metadata that you might
want to add that changes
over time in your movie.
This is a screen shot of a
demo app we'll show you later
but the circle and the
annotation text that's all
stored as the same sort of timed
metadata as a timed location.
So hopefully that whets
your appetite a little bit.
We'll talk about what
we're going to cover today,
we're going to start, I'm going
to give you an intro to metadata
and AVFoundation, some of
the classes that have been
around for a while for
describing all sorts
of metadata, how to inspect
that and how to author it.
We're going to talk more
about those new timed
metadata features
and then I'll give you some best
practices including some privacy
things to keep in mind and
some other best practices.
So our first topic: metadata
in AVFoundation..What kind
of classes are we going to be
using to describe our metadata?
Well our primary model
objects that we use
to describe both movie files
or HLS streams is AVAsset.
AVAsset can contain any
number of AV metadata objects
and each AVMetadataItem instance
represents a single piece
of metadata, either your
track name or your album mark,
even your location stuff that's
going to be separate pieces
of metadata in our
runtime environment.
So a closer look at
AVMetadataItem: at its core,
it has two properties.
The first is identifier, which
is actually a new property
and that is going
to describe the kind
of metadata that you have.
In this example we have the
song name and it's represented
by this long symbol name,
AVMetadataIdentifieriTunes
MetadataSongName,
and then you have the value
which is the actual payload
of the metadata item.
So for song name, it's the
name of the song as a string.
As an example for cover art,
you can see that the
value doesn't have
to be a string it can be an
image or any other object
that supports both the NSObject
and NSCopying protocols.
Now if you've used
AVMetadataItem
in the past you might
be familiar with the key
and key space properties.
Well the identifier I
mentioned that was new,
it's new because
it is a combination
of the old properties,
key and key space.
So I'm not going to talking much
about key and key space today
but mostly going to be talking
about identifier going forward
as the way to describe
your metadata.
Take a look at some of the
built-in identifiers we have;
this is just a tiny sampling.
There's a lot of them.
You can find them
in AVMetadataIdentifiers.h. I've
arranged them here according
roughly to the old notion of
key space so that's just sort
of a sampling of the kind of
metadata that we already know
that you might want
to represent.
Going back to the
metadata item itself,
we have a property that's
also new called dataType,
which describes the
native data type
that your metadata
is representing.
So for the case of our song
name it's stored as a string
so we see that the data
type is a UTF8 string;
and these string constants
that represent the different
data types are all defined
in CMMetadata.h. And besides
the data type property,
we also have several
type coercion properties
that you can use if you know
you want to get your payload
in the form of a certain
type of Objective C object.
So you have string value, number
value, date value and data value
and those are going to give
you exactly what you'd expect.
For the case of where our
native payload is a string,
only string value is going to
give you an interesting answer.
The rest will give you NULL.
For our artwork example where
the payload is a JPEG image,
the top three are
going to give you NULL
and the data value is going
to give you the NSData
that you're looking for to grab
the bytes of the JPEG image.
There are examples
where you can have more
than one non-nil
tech coercion method.
And one is creation date if
you have the date represented
as a standard string
format for dates.
You can either get the actual
string that was stored that way
or you can ask the metadata
item to give you an instance
of NSDate that describes
the same thing
in a more convenient
representation.
So that's your brief
intro to AVMetadataItem,
we're going to be talking a lot
about it throughout the talk.
Let's go back to AVAsset
so we can see how we actually
get these metadata items.
So the easiest way is just to
ask for all of the metadata
that applies to the
entire asset.
There are types of metadata that
apply to just parts of the asset
but this is how you get the
metadata to, like, the location
and the song title that
applies to the entire asset.
There's also a way to get
just a subset of the metadata.
We have this notion of metadata
format but I'm not going
to be talking about too much
today but you can use it
to get just that
subset of the metadata.
So for our example, when we
are getting iTunes metadata,
we're going to use that
AVMetadataFormatiTunesMetadata
and grab all of that using
the metadataForFormat method.
And then from there we can
use this filtering method,
metadataItemsFromArray,
filtered by an identifier
to get just the items
that correspond
to the song name identifier.
You might be wondering
why you can have more
than one song name
in a single asset?
We'll get back to that in just
a little bit but first I want
to talk about how you load the
payload of your metadata items.
AVMetadataItem conforms
to the
AVAsynchronousKeyValueLoading.h
protocol.
This is a protocol we define
ourselves in AVFoundation
and a lot of our core
model objects conform to it
because a lot of times
when you get an AVAsset
or an AVMetadataItem we haven't
actually loaded the data behind
it yet.
So you can use this method, load
values asynchronously for keys
to load the specific values
you want and they'll do
that asynchronously so you're
not blocking your main thread
with some sort of synchronous
I/O or something like that.
So for this case we
have our metadata item.
We're looking for the value so
we just load the key value and,
when we get our completion
handler,
we're going to check
the status to make sure
that that loading succeeded
and, assuming that we did,
we can then just go
ahead and grab the value
and use it however we see fit.
So back to that whole multiple
titles in one asset string.
Well, one reason we
might have that is
if we have the asset localized
in multiple languages.
So an asset can have
the same metadata items
in multiple languages.
The example that
we're going to talk
about is
QuickTimeUserDataFullName
dat identifier.
If you use this identifier
in your files,
then QuickTime Player, for
example, can pick up the title
and display it in the title bar.
So this is just yet
another example
of how metadata is used
in our applications.
This particular example
of the movie actually has the
title available in both English
and Spanish so here we have the
English as the system language
so QuickTime Player picks that
up, picks up the English title
but if we set our system
language to Spanish it will pick
up the Spanish localization
of that title instead.
These are represented as two
distinct pieces of metadata
within the file and the way that
you distinguish between them is
that they'll have
different values
for these final two properties
of AVMetadataItem locale
and extendedLanguageTag.
ExtendedLanguageTag is
new in this release.
It's a BCP 47 language tag
and it's particularly useful
when you want to
distinguish written languages.
So that's one reason
why you might have more
than one metadata item
with the same identifier.
So I mentioned before that
not all metadata applies
to the entire asset, well one
example of that is metadata
that only applies to
a particular track,
so for this example we have
a special label attached
to our subtitle track called
SDH, that stands for Subtitles
for the Deaf or Hard of Hearing
and that's basically just a
more rich form of subtitles
that includes things like
labeling who's talking
and mentioning sound effects
that are vital to
the understanding.
We talked a little bit more
about SDH and accessibility
in general last year in our
"Preparing and Presenting Media
for Accessibility" talk so check
that one out for more details.
For the purposes of this talk,
just know that to get
this SDH label here,
it involves setting
track-specific metadata.
So let's talk about
how you actually find
out if your track has
this metadata in it,
well you're going
to use AVAsset track
and it has pretty much
the exact same API
as AVAsset for reading metadata.
You have your metadata property;
you have your metadataForFormat
method and so if we want
to find all the tagged
characteristics that are
in an asset track, we're
going to ask the track
for its metadata for the
FormatQuickTimeUserData.
Once we have that we use
that same filtering method we
saw before in order to get all
of the items that
have the identifier,
QuickTimeUserDataTagged
Characteristic.
So this is one example of tagged
characteristics is the SDH
that I just talked about
and it's the payload
of the metadata items
that tells you what kind
of tagged characteristic
you're dealing with.
We'll talk a little bit
more detail about SDH
and how you author it
in just a little bit.
So going back to our list
of identifiers you might
have noticed some patterns
if you were looking closely.
Each of these groups has
their own version of a title
or a song name or
something like that.
We noticed that and come up
with our own special kind
of identifier called
a CommonIdentifier
which can be used when
you want to look up, say,
for this example a title without
caring exactly how it's stored
in your file.
Same for copyright here; we
also have a common identifier
that represents copyright.
These are not the only
common identifiers;
there's a whole list of them
but these are just two examples.
So if we go back to our
example where we're looking
for our iTunes song name,
if we don't actually care
that the title of our asset
is stored as iTunes metadata
and we just want a title so
we can display it somewhere,
you can ask the asset for
its array of commonMetadata
and this is all the
metadata items
that can be represented
using a common identifier.
Then you use that same filtering
method we've been using
to filter down to just the ones
that have the
CommonIdentifierTitle
and you can go from
there with your title.
Also worth noting is
that AVAssetTrack has the
same property, commonMetadata,
so you can do the same
thing over there as well.
So that is your brief
introduction
to inspecting metadata
with AVFoundation.
Let's talk a little
bit about authoring.
If you want to make your own
files that have say location
or iTunes metadata in them, we
have several different classes
that can write movie
files, AVAssetExportSession,
AVAssetWriter and the capture
movie and audio files outputs
and these all have the exact
same redirect property called
simply, metadata.
So you give an array of
metadata items and then
that will be written
out to the file.
Similarly for track-specific
metadata
like those tagged
characteristics,
you can use an AVAssetWriter
input
which also has the
exact same property.
Now you are not limited to
just writing out metadata
that you got from somewhere
else, like another file
through the APIs
we've been looking at.
You can also create
your own metadata items
with a mutable subclass
of metadataItem.
And as you might expect, this
just has read/write properties
for all of the properties
in AVMetadataItem.
So if we use an example of
writing a subtitle track
that is marked as SDH, well
it's actually two different tag
characteristics that
you have to use
and so we'll create two
different metadata items,
set both of their identifiers
to the identifier we just saw,
the QuickTimeUserData
tag characteristic,
but one of them will
set the value
to TranscribesSpokenDialogue
ForAccessibility
and the other will be
DescribesMusicAndSound
ForAccessibility.
Then we get the subtitle
AssetWriterInputthat's going
to write our subtitle track and
set that array of the two items
on our asset writer input.
So that's how you would
author a subtitle track
that is marked as SDH.
Just one example of
using tag characteristics
in AVMutableMetadataItem.
Special note about
AVAssetExportSession:
by default the ExportSession
is actually going to take any
of the metadata that's
in the source asset
that you're exporting.
It's going to copy that
over to the output file.
Now that's not the case
if you set metadata
on its metadata property.
That will be the signal
to tell the ExportSession
to ignore the metadata
in the source file
and instead write just what
you put on the property.
So if you want to do
augmentation of the metadata
or some other sort of
modification you'll want to grab
that array of metadata,
make a mutable copy
and do any adjustments
that you want and then set
that on the metadata property.
So that's just a quick
note about ExportSession.
The last note about authoring
metadata is HTTP Live Streaming,
this is actually a new
feature in iOS 8, OS X Yosemite
and you can use a new tag
called session-data tag
in your playlist, which
has two required fields:
the data ID which is a
lot like our identifiers
that we're talking about, a URI
which can point to the payload
or a value which directly
specifies the payload and,
optionally, some
language information.
So here's an example
that shows very similar
to what we saw before
with the titles
in two different languages but
this is the markup you'd use
for HTTP Live Streaming.
So for more information
on reading
and writing metadata we
do have some sample code,
it's called AVmetadataeditor
and for more information
about the details of writing
HTTP Live Streaming metadata see
the documents at this URL.
All right so that is your
crash course in metadata
in AVFoundation, our next
topic is timed metadata.
So timed metadata, although I
mentioned we have new features,
it is not a new concept.
We supported the notion of
chapters for quite some time
and conceptually chapters
are just an example
of times metadata.
Each of these chapter markers
is just a piece of metadata
that is describing
a particular range
of the timeline of the movie.
That's all that timed
metadata is,
it's just metadata associated
with a range of time.
So similarly, with our
dynamic location example,
we have the path that's drawn
here that's really just composed
of a number of pieces
of metadata indicating
the current location,
each one of them associated
with a particular time
in the movie's timeline.
So to demonstrate
QuickTime Player's features
with dynamic location
in Yosemite,
I want to bring my
colleague, Shalini,
up to the stage for a demo.
>> Hi, I'm here to
demonstrate how to read
and play back metadata
using QuickTime Player.
Here I have a movie file
which has both audio and video
and timed locations data
stored in a different track.
So now if I bring this
up in QuickTime Player,
this is the usual UI
for audio and video.
New in OS X Yosemite:
in the Movie Inspector
you can see a map view
if your movie file
has location data.
Your map view is presented
along with the route
where you have recorded
this video.
So here the blue line
indicates the path
where we recorded the video and
the red pin is an indication
of the current location
or the location
on the timeline of the movie.
So if I zoom in a little
bit and start play,
you can see as the movie
progresses the pin's location is
being updated to be in
sync with the video.
I can drag the scrubber around
and you can see the pin
moving back and forth.
I can also go and click
at any point in the map
and you see the video seek
to that location to present
where your video was when
you were at that location.
This is map view in QuickTime
Player on OS X Yosemite.
>> Thank you, Shalini.
So let's talk about
what we just saw there.
So that location information
was stored as timed metadata
in the file and in order to
have QuickTime Player draw
that information on the map, we
use AVAssetReader to read all
of the location information
from that asset.
And because timed metadata
is stored in its own track,
we use an
AVAssetReaderTrackOutput to read
that data and we use a new
class called AVAssetReaderOutput
MetadataAdaptor that knows how
to give us that data in the
from of a class called
AVTimedMetadataGroup.
Then from there we
can grab each location
and draw that path on the map.
So AVTimedMetadataGroup
is a very simple class.
It's really just
these two properties:
an array of metadata items
combined with a time range
that describes where in the
movie that data applies.
So to see a little bit of
code for using AssetReader
for this purpose, the
first thing you want
to do is find the track
that contains your location
information and we'll talk more
about how to do that
in just a second.
Then you use that track to
create an AssetReaderTrackOutput
and you use nil output settings
and then you'll create
your metadataAdaptor
with that trackOutput.
And then, in a loop we just
take your metadataAdaptor
and call the
nextTimedMetadataGroup method
over and over again, doing
something with each piece
of data, like drawing
it on the map
until that method returns nil.
Then you know there's
no more data to draw.
So in terms of finding
the right track to read,
the way you're going to do
that is by examining the tracks
in your asset and looking
through the format description
of each track to find the
identifiers you're looking for.
So you first start
by getting the tracks
with the MediaTypeMetadata
and then for each
of those tracks you're
going to loop through all
of its format descriptions,
usually there's only one
and for each format description
you're going to grab its list
of identifiers using this
function and check whether
that identifier array
contains the identifier you're
looking for.
In this case we're looking
for the location
ISO 6709 identifier.
So once we've found it we're
good to go and we can resume
with the code on
the previous slide.
So that's how QuickTime
Player is drawing the map
or drawing the path on the
map before you start playback.
The other thing that QuickTime
Player does, as you saw,
is it can update the current
location while you're doing
playback or even scrubbing
around and the way it does
that while it's already playing
the asset using an AVPlayerItem
and we're going to
use a new class called
AVPlayerItemMetadataOutput that
you attach to your PlayerItem,
which also notes how to
vend this data in the form
of TimedMetadataGroups.
But unlike the asset reader,
instead of getting all the data
up front you're going
to be getting it piece
by piece as the movie plays.
So a little bit of code,
you first create your
metadata output using the
initWithIdentifiers method
and in this case we're only
interested in metadata that has
that location identifier so
that's all we're going to get
by opting into this way.
Then you create a
delegate that you define
and that's what's going
to receive the metadata
during playback and you set
that delegate on your output
and tell us what cue you
want us to send the data on.
Then you create or grab your
AVPlayerItem and call addOutput
to attach your output, to attach
your output to the playerItem
and finally make your player
and associate your item
with the player as the current
item and start playback.
It's important to get the
smoothest playback experience
possible, we highly recommend
that you do all of this sort
of setup work before
you start playback
or even attach the
item to the player.
So a little bit of look at
what your delegate method might
look like.
There's only one delegate
method; it's the metadataOutput,
didOutputTimedMetadataGroups,
fromPlayerItemTrack method.
And the first thing you
want to do is grab an item
that you can get your
payload data from.
In this case, to
keep things simple,
I'm just grabbing the first item
from the first group but keep
in mind there could
be multiple items,
there could even
be multiple groups.
One reason there could
be multiple groups given
to this method is that the
metadata output will keep track
of whether the metadata
is coming faster
than you're processing it and,
if it is, it will start to batch
that up and give you
the metadata in batches
when you're done with the
previous batch of metadata.
So moving on with your
item; you're going
to do this
LoadValueAsynchronouslyForKeys
dance that we talked
about before.
In this case, we're
interested in the value
and data type properties
so we're going
to load both of those.
I've admitted the error
checking for brevity here
which you'll probably want
to do that error checking
like we had in the other slide.
And once we have the completion
handler we can ask the item
for its data type and make
sure that's the data type we're
prepared to handle, in this
case my code only knows how
to handle location information
in ISO 6709 format so we got
to make sure that's the right
data type and from there we go
and dispatch our code
to the main thread
that will update our UI.
So that's how QuickTime Player
is updating the location
metadata during playback.
Of course this is not the
first API that we have offered
for reading timed
metadata during playback.
There is an existing
property called timedMetadata
on AVPlayerItem but
I'm here to say
that the
AVPlayerItemMetadataOutput
replaces that property for
all of these use cases.
Now we're not deprecating
the property yet
but we do recommend, if
you're new to timed metadata,
just adopt the metadataOutput
and not worry about
the property.
If you're already using the
property version we do recommend
that you move over but just you
know that you should make sure
that your code is working
properly after that transition,
in particular I'll point
out that the metadataOutput
will give you, for certain kinds
of HLS content, will give
more specific identifiers
than the old property did.
So just make sure your code
is prepared to handle that.
The last topic on reading
timed metadata is Chapters.
Chapters, like I said, have
been supported for some time;
they even have their own API:
chapterMetadataGroupsBest
MatchingPreferredLanguages.
This is on AVAsset.
This will give you an array
of timed metadata groups
that contain items
with the identifier,
QuickTimeUserDataChapter,
and we've supported this
for some time for QuickTime
movie files and M4Vs and,
new in iOS 8 is the-and OS X
Yosemite-is support for chapters
in HTTP Live Streams
as well as MP3 files.
And I'll tell you more about how
to author those HLS chapters
in just a little bit.
So for more information,
we have some sample code
that does approximately what
QuickTime Player is doing,
where it can show your
location during play back.
We also have a previous session
about AssetReader that goes
into much more detail than I did
here, called "Working with Media
in AVFoundation" from 2011.
So that's how you read and
play back timed metadata.
Our next timed metadata topic
is how you can create your own
movies that contain
timed metadata.
We saw the screenshot
before and I mentioned
that these annotations are
stored as timed metadata and,
to show you this demo app, I'd
like to invite Shalini back
up on stage to demo it.
>> This time let's
look at an app on how
to author your own custom
metadata movie files.
Here I have a video and if I
would like to share some notes
with my friend, who is good
at fixing colors in a movie,
I can now do that
within the app.
To add annotations, I
use a two-finger gesture,
I can use a pinch gesture to
resize and then add a comment
which is enough for my whoever
looks at the video later
to fix the colors there
and then I begin playback.
And as playback progresses,
I track the circle
to where I want this
to be fixed.
And now that I have this
annotation and I can write it
out along with the audio and
video to do that, I hit "export"
and now we see an AV
player view controller
which shows the exported
movie along with the metadata
which was written to it.
So if I start playback you see
the annotation is moving along
the timeline in the
part in which I traced.
So if I scrub back in time you
can see the annotation moving.
You might wonder that
the annotation is baked
into the video frame; it is not.
It is being rendered real-time
using AVPlayerItemMetadataOutput
and you can change the color
or the font of the annotation.
So if I begin playback, you
see the rendering is happening
in real time.
That's AVTimedAnnotationWriter,
we have this available
as a sample code
as well, thank you.
>> So that was a
great demonstration
of not only the playback part
of it but also how to write
that data into the file,
so let's take a look at how
that was accomplished.
So we're going to use an
AVAssetWriter to write the file
and we're going to use an
AVAssetWriterInput in order
to write that metadata
track to the file.
Just like the reader side,
the writer has a new class
that's a metadataAdaptor
and that class knows how
to interpret instances
of AVTimedMetadataGroup and
write that into the file.
See a little bit of code;
first thing we're going
to do is create our
AssetWriter Input.
We're going to use the media
type AVMediaTypeMetadata,
once again nil outputSettings
and we're going to have
to provide a clue to
the source format, well,
the format of the data that
we're going to be appending.
We'll talk more about this
and why it's required
on the next slide.
Then you simply create
your metadataAdaptor
with the reference to that
input and, as you generate
or receive your timed
metadata groups,
you simply use the
appendTimedMetadataGroup method
to continue to append those
and write them to the file.
So what's the deal with
that source format thing.
Well, it turns out in order
for AVAssetWriter to be able
to write your metadata in the
most efficient way possible,
it needs to know up
front exactly what kind
of metadata it is
going to be writing.
This will result in the most
lowest storage overhead in terms
of the number of bytes
your file takes up
and it also has a effect
on how efficient it is
to play back this
kind of contents.
You don't want to be
using too much power
when you're playing this
kind of content back.
So you do have some
options in terms
of how you actually construct
one of these format hits.
If you're reading
from AVAssetReader you
can actually ask the track
that you are reading
from to give you its list
of format descriptions
and use one of those.
If you're creating the metadata
group yourself or getting it
from some other source then
you can use a new method called
copyFormatDescription that
will give you back an instance
of CM format description that
will do this job for you.
It's important to note that
if you go this route you need
to make sure that the contents
of your metadata group
are comprehensive in terms
of it containing
every combination
of identifier data
type and language tag
that you are going
to be appending.
That is. it contains an item
with each of those combinations.
Of course, since the CM format
description is a CF type,
you'll need a CFRelease
app when you're done.
Of course, there's one
more way you can do this:
you can create the format
description directly using
CoreMedia APIs.
And here you use this long name
CMMetadataFormatDescription
CreateWith
MetadataSpecifications function.
You're going to pass in
the metadataType box.
That's the sort of
metadata we've been talking
about this whole time
with timed metadata.
And these metadata
specifications it's just an
array of dictionaries.
Each dictionary contains those
combinations I was talking
about before.
The identifier dataType and
optionally extended language tag
so you want to make one of
these metadata specifications
dictionaries for each
combination you plan to append.
So the one thing that was not
obvious about that demo is
that we're actually writing
metadata timed metadata
that describes one
particular other track.
So for the example
of these annotations,
we're really just talking about
the video track of the movie
and not the sound or
anything else like that.
So just like we had a way of
making track-specific metadata
that applied to the
entire track,
with those tagged
characteristics
that we saw before, you
also have the ability
to formerly mark
your metadata track
as describing one
particular other track.
You do that with the
addTrackAssociationWith
TrackOfInput method using as the
parameter the AssetWriterInput
that you are using to
write your video track.
And your receiver is the
input that you are using
to write your metadata track.
You use the
AssociationTypeMetadataReferent.
So that's how your create
metadata that's timed
but also specific to
a particular track.
The next thing we did that was
interesting in that demo is
that we actually used our
own custom identifiers.
So we had that big list
of built in identifiers.
Well, you don't have
to use those;
you can actually build your own
and as I mentioned before an
identifier is just a combination
of key space and key and
it has a particular format:
it's just a string but it
is in a particular format
so to help you make your
own custom identifiers,
we have this method,
identifierFor Key, and keySpace,
it's a class method
on AVMetadataItem.
There are some rules to
follow: your key space needs
to be four characters
long if you want to use it
for timed metadata
so we actually recommend you
use our built-in key space,
the QuickTimeMetadata keySpace.
We also highly recommend
you use reverse DNS notation
for your custom keys
to avoid collisions
with other kinds of metadata.
So a brief code snippet you
can see you can simply use this
method to make your custom
identifier and then set
that on the identifier property
of your mutableMetadataItem.
So in addition to custom
identifiers you can also create
your own custom data types.
So we're all familiar by now,
through this presentation,
with some of the built-in
data types that we defined;
there's a lot more than these
but we've been using these
quite heavily already.
These are really useful
but sometimes you want
your data type information
to express more, maybe about
the domain you're working in,
so if you are doing a serial
number or a bar code kind
of thing you might want
to define a data type that's
this sort of serial number
as string data type or
barcode image as JPEG data type
so you have more
specific information
about what your metadata
actually contains.
The way that this works is,
you have to tell us exactly how
to serialize that custom
data type and the way you do
that is you tell us that your
custom data type conforms to one
of our built-in data types.
So in this case the
serial number conforms
to the UTF8 data type so under
the hood it's UTF8 string,
but we know that it really
represents a serial number
and the same with
the barcode image.
The way that you do this is you
register your data type using
the CMMetadataDataTypeRegistry
RegisterDataType function that's
defined in Core Media.
You can't create your
own custom base types
but you can create your own
custom type that conforms
to our raw data built-in type
if your data type really is
just a custom sequence of bytes.
So there are some rules
to using AVAssetWriter
for writing timed metadata.
Most importantly, every metadata
item that you append has
to have non-nil values for
identifier, data type and value.
Your identifier has to conform
to the format that we specify,
so we highly recommend
using that utility method
that we just talked about.
The value has to be
compatible with the data type
so you can tell us that your
NSString value is an UTF8 string
but don't try telling us
that your custom class is a UTF8
string because we won't know how
to serialize that properly
and the AssetWriter will fail.
As I mentioned before, you have
to create your AssetWriterInput
with a format hint and
that must be comprehensive
and we described that before.
So the last topic
about AssetWriter
and timed metadata is a recipe
for creating your own movies
that have the same sort
of dynamic location
that we've seen a
couple of times already.
To do this, you can
use AVCapture audio
and video data outputs
and target that data
at twin instances of
AssetWriterInput and,
at the same time, grab
information from Core Location
that represents the location
information and write
that to its own
AssetWriterInput.
For more detail about how to do
that we've actually implemented
that and made it
available as sample code,
so see AVCaptureLocation if you
want to make your own movies
that contain dynamic location.
We also have sample code
as Shalini mentioned
for the demo we just showed you,
that's called
AVTimedAnnotationWriter.
And, of course, for more
information about AssetWriter
in general, see that same
talk I referenced earlier:
"Working with Media
in AVFoundation".
Last two quick topics about
timed metadata: ExportSession.
Just like we've said the
asset ExportSession will
by default pass through any
of your metadata that applies
to the entire asset or
entire track, it will pass
that through, copy it
to the output file.
It will do the same thing with
timed metadata that exists
in the source file provided
that your destination file
type is QuickTime Movie.
We'll talk more about file
types in just a little bit
but basically ExportSession
behaves exactly
as you would expect.
In our last timed metadata
authoring topic is HTTP Live
Streaming chapters so if
you want to author chapters
in your HLS stream, you can use
the session-data tag we talked
about earlier and the special
data ID, com.apple.hls.chapters.
Your URL should point
to a JSON file
that describes the chapter
information for that stream and,
of course for more detail
on this, see that same link
that I referenced earlier
for HTTP Live Streaming.
All right, so that
is timed metadata,
our next topic is privacy.
Why is privacy important
in this context?
Well, any time that you
are writing your users data
to a file you need to
be at least considerate
about their privacy and be aware
that the metadata that you write
out to these movie files can
contain user identifiable
information, the most obvious
example of that is location.
And so because movie files
can be distributed and we want
to protect the privacy
of our users,
for our built-in sharing
services, we do our best
to strip out any potentially
user identifiable information,
such as this location and we
recommend that you do the same.
So we've given you a utility
for that called
AVMetadataItemFilter.
Right now there is only one
filter that we make available
but it is geared
towards privacy,
it is the metadata item filter
for sharing and that will strip
out any of this sort of
user identifying information
that we're talking about;
location is only one example.
But it will also strip out
anything it doesn't recognize,
because it doesn't know whether
that might contain user
identifiable information.
So that includes any
metadata that uses identifiers
that you define yourself.
It will leave in some things
like metadata that's important
to the structure of the movie
and chapters are the
best example of that,
and also any commercial
related data like your Apple ID.
So to use the MetadataItemFilter
you're going to first
of all create your filter and
feed it your original array
of metadata items using
this metadataItemsFromArray
filteredByMetadataItemFilter
method.
This is a companion to that
other filtering method based
on identifiers we've
been using all day
and then once you have
your filtered array
of metadata items just set
that on your AssetWriter
or ExportSession as
you normally would.
Well actually I mentioned
ExportSession
but things can be simple if
you're using the ExportSession
and only want to
copy the metadata
from the source asset
and not add your own.
You just set the filter
on the ExportSession
and it will actually do
the filtering for you,
this will filter both
static and timed metadata
but it will only filter the
metadata from the source asset.
If you set your own metadata
on the metadata property,
it won't filter that for you;
you'll need to do the process
that I just described of
doing the filtering yourself.
The only other thing
to keep in mind is
that the export may
take more time
when the filter is being used
because it has to go through
and examine all of
the metadata items.
So that's privacy.
Our last section of the talk
today is some assorted best
practices when you are
writing your own files
that contain metadata.
First up, what if you're
writing timed metadata
and you have multiple
streams of metadata
that use different identifiers.
How do you get those
into the same file?
Well, we actually have the
situation in the demo app,
we have that circle is comprised
of two different pieces
of information, the
position and the radius.
So we're representing these
and the demo app is two
distinct streams of metadata.
And so the most obvious way
I can think of to get this
into a file is to use two
different AVAssetWriterInputs,
which result in having
two metadata tracks
in the output file,
pretty simple.
But there is another
way you can do it,
you could instead combine those
two different types of metadata
into one timed metadata
group and write
that to a single
AssetWriterInput
and that will result in
only one metadata track
in the output file that contains
multiple different kinds
of identifiers.
There are some advantages to
this approach, not the least
of which is it can result
in lower storage overhead
and therefore as we always
see more efficient playback.
But there are of course
pros and cons to everything.
So you'll definitely want
to consider combining
into one track your
different metadata
if they are used
together during playback
and they have identical timing.
This is definitely the case
with the example we just saw
with the circle center
and the circle radius.
If these are not true then
you might not want to combine.
And in fact one instance where
you definitely do not want
to combine, is if
you have one type
of metadata that's associated
with another track in the file,
so that's like our
annotations are associated
with the video track, but
then you have another type
of metadata like location
that is associated
with the entire asset.
You don't want to combine
those into one track,
otherwise your location in that
example will become mistakenly
associated with just
the video track,
and that's not what you want.
So that's how to deal
with multiple streams
of timed metadata.
Next topic is duration of
your timed metadata groups,
when you get a timed
metadata group
from AVFoundation
it's always going
to have a fully formed
time range.
So that means it will have
a start time and a duration.
We actually recommend when you
make your own timed metadata
groups for a pending
with the AVAssetWriter
that you don't bother
giving us a duration.
And to see how that works,
here's an example of a group
that starts at time 0 but
it doesn't have a duration
so how do we know when it ends?
Well, of course we'll wait
until you append the next one
and then we'll say that,
"Okay, the end time
of the first group is the same
as the start time
of the next one."
So this ensures that your
metadata track is going
to have a continuous stream of
contiguous metadata and we think
that for most cases this is the
best way to store your metadata.
The way you accomplish this is,
when you're making
your time range,
you just use KCMTimeInvalid
for your duration
and we'll take care of the rest.
We do recognize that there are
cases where you might not want
to have contiguous
metadata, you might want
to author an explicit gap into
your metadata stream and so,
for that, our recommendation
is that you give us
in the middle there a group
that contains zero items.
This is the best way to
author a gap in the metadata.
And you can see we just do that
by presenting an empty array
when we're creating our
timed metadata group.
Notice that we're still
using KCMTimeInvalid
for our duration here.
Just tell us when the beginning
of the metadata silence,
so to speak, is and we'll figure
out how long it lasts based
on when you append your
next non-empty group.
So that's how you write
gaps in your metadata.
Our last best practice,
I mentioned output
file type before
and here's the longer
explanation.
Well, AssetWriter
and AssetExportSessions
support writing
to a wide variety of file types.
You've got QuickTime
movie, MPEG4, and all sorts
of other kind of file types
and those file types can carry
different kinds of metadata;
some have more restrictions
than others about what kind
of metadata can go
into that file type.
So the easiest situation, say
if you have an ExportSession
and you're going from one,
from the same file type
as your source to the output,
so for this example they're
both QuickTime movie files.
This is the easiest
way to ensure that all
of that data is actually going
to make it into the output file.
If instead you're using a
different output file type,
like MPEG4 in this example,
then some different things
are going to have to happen.
You notice those last few
items didn't quite make it
into the output file;
it's because they have no
equivalent representation
that works with an MPEG4 file.
If you're looking
closely you'll also notice
that those top two
items have changed,
although they sound very similar
they are slightly different
identifiers because that's
the kind of identifier
that works with MPEG4.
So both AssetExportSession and
AssetWriter will do the sort
of three step process.
First, they'll try to pass
that data through directly
if possible and, if not, they'll
try to convert the identifier
into an equivalent
representation
in the output file type.
If neither of those work, we
have no choice but to just drop
that piece of metadata
on the floor.
So in terms of guidance on how
to choose an output file type,
well, my two recommendations
are,
if you are using say an
ExportSession to copy all
of the metadata, timed or
otherwise, from the source asset
to your destination file,
the best way is to try
and use the same file type
that you started with,
and if you don't know what the
file type is you can use the
NSURLTypeIdentifierKey
to find out.
You can also always use
the QuickTime Movie file
because that is going to
have the greatest chance
of supporting your metadata
no matter where it came from.
If AVFoundation supports
it, there's a good chance
that it will be supported
by the QuickTime movie file.
Of course, this is the only way
if you're writing
timed metadata,
to get your timed
metadata into a file is
to use QuickTime Movie file;
it's the only file form
that supports it right now.
Of course good advice is always
to check the results,
no matter what.
Check that your output files
contain the kind of metadata
that you expect, all the
metadata that you expect
and you can choose to
use some of the APIs
that we've already
talked about if you want
to do that at runtime.
Some guidance if that
doesn't end up being the case:
if you don't get all the
metadata that you expect, well,
you can try to do the
conversion yourself.
Especially if you have a
custom identifier and are going
to a file type that doesn't
support your custom identifier,
take a look at that long list
of built-in identifiers we have
and see if there is something
that's roughly equivalent
to what you're trying
to store and you can do
that conversion yourself.
One particular example
I want to call
out that involves only
built-in identifiers is
when you're trying to
go from ID3 to iTunes,
well AVFoundation
currently isn't going to do
that conversion for you.
But there's no reason you
couldn't do that yourself,
so once again just take a look
at our long list of identifiers
and match them up and do the
conversion in your own code.
So that is the end of the talk.
See what we covered: we talked
obviously a lot about metadata
in AVFoundation,
we talked about all
of the different classes
you can use for inspection,
we talked about AVAsset
and AVMetadataItem
and how those work
together and also authoring,
we talked about the AssetWriter,
the AssetExportSession even
briefly on the capture audio
and movie file outputs.
We dove into timed metadata,
including all the new features
that enable things like
the dynamic location
and your own timed metadata
like the annotation demo.
We also talked about
privacy considerations
and some best practices like how
to choose the right file type.
So for more information, you
can contact our evangelism team
or see our programing guide,
there are some other
related sessions you might be
interested in.
If you missed this
morning's presentation
on "Modern Media
Playback", you can catch
that on the video recording.
Tomorrow there is also a
camera capture talk focusing
on manual controls.
And on Thursday we'll have
a talk about direct access
to video encoding and
decoding, which I'm sure a lot
of you will be interested in.
[ Silence ]