[ Music ]
>> Good evening, developers, and
welcome to the 2019 Apple Design
Awards.
Now, here's your host, Senior
Director of Evangelism, John
Geleynse.
[ Music ]
>> Hello. Well, hello, and
welcome to another Apple Design
Awards.
Thanks for joining us this
afternoon, especially after a
long, but exciting day.
And I just want to particularly
thank all of you who have joined
us from around the world online
on the live stream for the
ceremony right now.
We've got a huge group.
You know, it's great for us to
join as a community, and gather
like this to take a few moments
to celebrate and acknowledge
excellence in innovation and
design.
Because at Apple, we've been
awarding excellent design for
more than two decades now.
What started originally as the
Apple Human Interface Design
Excellence Awards, or HIDE
Awards for short, was renamed a
few years later to what is now
known as the Apple Design
Awards.
You know, the world around us is
stunningly beautiful, and as
humans, we're attracted to
beautiful things, and to
incredible designs.
We're drawn to these things, and
we respond to them deeply.
And at Apple, we believe the
true -- the beauty -- that
beautiful design is both
appearance and function, and
something that works well with
each component deeply
considered, and each aspect
carefully crafted -- that that
can be profoundly beautiful.
And so, simply judging something
by how it looks isn't enough.
It's how it works.
It has to work as beautifully as
it looks, and great design
reflects the broader definition
of beauty.
And it runs deeper than the
interface.
It's coherent, and it's
cohesive.
And it helps us to engage with
each other in new, and
innovative, and life-enhancing
ways, and like compelling
beauty, great design draws us
in.
And the Apple Design Awards have
always been about this --
recognizing great design, and
then celebrating the developers
who positively impact everyone
else, and real people with the
things that they create, the
things that you create.
Now, we select our winners each
year by evaluating them in
basically three key areas.
The first area is design.
We're looking for apps that are
-- that have strong visual
design, that are efficient and
easy to use, that have great
game play, that have attention
to detail and polish, that are
internally coherent.
On the technology front, we're
evaluating technology usage, and
so we're looking for apps that
are fast and responsive.
We're looking for apps that take
full advantage of all of the
capabilities of our latest
devices, and we're looking for
apps that use the latest Apple
technologies to do really great
new things.
And on the innovation front,
we're looking for brilliance.
We're looking for new ideas.
We're looking for uniqueness,
platform differentiation, and
things that just weren't
possible before.
And the developers of our
winning apps this evening have
done an outstanding job, and
outstanding work in these three
areas, and more, and we want to
honor that work.
We want to acknowledge the
distinct joy and the challenges
of the app creation process that
we're all so familiar with.
We want to honor the endless
hours, the late nights, and the
dedication that goes into the
pursuit of excellence.
We want to recognize the
dead-ends, and the frustration,
and the exhaustion sometimes
that often goes unseen, and
we're all familiar with that.
And we want to honor the
unconventional thinking, the
creativity, and the new ideas
that lead to breakthroughs and
innovative solutions.
So let's get started.
Winners tonight are going to win
some pretty great -- some pretty
amazing prizes, and each prize
package includes a 512 gigabyte
iPhone XS with a set of AirPods,
a 512 gigabyte 12.9-inch iPad
Pro with Apple Pencil 2,
a 64 gigabyte 4K Apple TV, an
Apple Watch Series 4,
a top-of-the-line MacBook Pro,
and a fully-loaded iMac Pro.
In addition --
in addition -- and this is what
all of you want -- each winner
will -- each winning develop --
each winning app will be
highlighted on the App Store,
similar to what we did last year
on the Today tab for the Apple
Design Award winners, and what
we did throughout the year
following the ceremony.
So this year's winners will be
highlighted in prominent ways on
the App Stores.
And lastly, each winner will
take home one of the coveted
Apple Design Award trophies,
except that we thought it was
time for a refresh.
And so, we have a completely new
trophy this year, redesigned
from the Apple Design Team.
It retains the integrity and
recognizable qualities of the
original award, but reinterprets
these with the qualities of our
latest products.
It's made out of 100% recycled
aluminum, and featured a
mirror-finished stainless steel
Apple logo inlay.
It's pretty sweet, if you ask
me.
All right.
So we have nine -- we have nine
winners today, and each winner
will be announced and demoed by
a colleague -- by colleagues of
mine from the Apple -- from the
-- from Apple's World Wide
Developer Relations Team.
Now, a little bit differently
than other years -- if we
announce your app, if we
announce you as a winner, please
stay in your seat because we're
going to first talk about your
app, and explain it to the
community.
And we're going to demo it, and
when we've completed the demo,
we're going to call you forward
on stage, and ask that you'd
come up on stage using these
stairs here at this location.
So, let's find out who the
winners are.
To present our first winners,
I'd like to invite my
colleagues, Si Ching and Oscar
on stage.
[ Music ]
>> Thanks, John.
For our first award today, we
have a gorgeous platform game
designed for the mobile screen
from the ground up.
It's optimized for the portrait
orientation with simple
drag-and-release controls.
Oscar and I had so much fun with
this game, and we can't wait to
show it to you.
The first award goes to Ordia by
Loju.
[ Applause ]
Okay, let's get the demo up.
Okay, Oscar, let's take this
game for a spin.
Ordia tells the story of a first
life form emerging from this
gooey primordial soup, and then
goes on a precarious trip to
start its journey as a living
being.
It needs to jump through caves,
gather nutrition, while also
avoid being eaten or killed.
Ordia has its amazingly-rich and
vibrant design style, a lovely
blobbiness and bounciness
throughout -- not just with the
visuals, but also the sound
design.
[ Game Sounds ]
What we love about this game is
that it's intuitive enough so
you simply start playing, and it
introduces rules and challenges
gradually as you go through the
levels.
It uses colors to communicate
the roles of each element.
Green and yellow things are
friendly, while pink things must
be avoided.
It also leverages our Taptic
Engine just the right amount, so
you get this subtle and
satisfying feedback while you
play.
Ordia has three universes.
They are immersive, consistent,
yet also distinct from each
other, with carefully balanced
color palette, different game
elements, and soundtracks.
Now, let's have a look at the
jungle universe.
This is actually a really tough
level.
I've never been able to go
through without dying, so good
luck, Oscar.
I love the pacing of this game.
The challenges alternate
smoothly between speed, timing,
and accuracy, while also offers
you these little resting pods,
where your Ordia can regenerate
if it dies, so you can breathe a
little.
The balance between difficulty
and satisfaction is very well
managed, so you just feel like
you have to play one more level.
Ordia caters for accessibility
with great care.
Its colorblindness mode has even
been tested on monochrome.
Now, what if you want to do a
challenge on a level where you
catch every single nutrition, or
race for your fastest completion
time?
No problem.
You can also play on an iPad
with a much larger screen.
The game automatically syncs
your progress via iCloud.
Loju is the creator of Ordia, a
very small and talented game
studio based in London.
They spent two years building
this game, and have just
launched it a month ago.
Please, go ahead.
Download it today and have a
play.
I'm sure you'll get so much
inspiration from it.
And now, let's welcome Team Loju
to the stage.
Congratulations.
[ Music and Singing ]
[ Applause ]
>> That's a fun game.
Alright. To award our next
winner, I'd like to bring up
Dave and Mike.
[ Music ]
>> Notebooks are one of the most
successful designs humanity has
ever produced.
They're simple inventions --
just a stack of pages bound
together, and protected by a
cover.
But from the earliest notebooks,
there's always been a sense of
excitement, starting with a
blank page.
When inspiration strikes, you
grab a pen, and let the ideas
flow.
Our next winner captures the
essence of this experience in
digital form.
Please help me congratulate Flow
by Moleskine.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Dave.
This demo was really hard to
prepare.
Every time I would launch Flow,
and try to figure out what I
would share with you today, I
would start drawing, and
completely lose track of what I
was supposed to be doing, which
is a testament, I think, to how
well this app is designed.
Now, to help you to get into and
stay in a state of creative
flow, they encourage you to set
up everything in advance, like
picking the color of the paper,
or the patterns that you want to
use.
They also encourage you to set
up the drawing tools in advance,
so you're not messing around
with interface later, and they
have some really great drawing
tools, like this mechanical
pencil.
Now, as you can see here,
drawing is very realistic, and
by supporting Apple Pencil 2
gestures, iOS drawing APIs, and
Metal, you can get some really
realistic shading effects.
It looks pretty true-to-life.
They have a great felt-tip pen
that looks basically like you
would expect a pen to look, and
they have great markers with
really nice buildup of ink for
realistic marker-like
experience.
They also have an awesome
calligraphy pen.
Now, playing with these tools --
it kind of -- it takes me back
to when I was a kid.
My mom -- she was a really great
calligrapher, and she had a
business called Inklings.
And -- yeah, I thought that was
a pretty clever name, by the
way.
And when she would get supplies
for her business, she would
often take me with her, and I
would have so much fun just
playing with all of the markers
and pens.
Drawing tools here really kind
of takes me back to that
experience, but the real heart
of the interface here is
customizing the drawing tools.
Everything in this interface is
animated, and they even have
these really great optional
sound effects.
Check out when you change the
brush size, how the nibs change
in response, or when you change
the nibs, they pop on and pop
off.
But the heart of this interface
is changing the color.
You adjust the value on the side
here on the right, swipe side to
side to adjust saturation, and
color by just spinning the color
wheel.
And check out how all of these
-- all of these colors have
unique names.
There's 1400 names in all.
It's just like a real marker
set.
Now, I'm feeling inspired to
actually draw something, so to
extend the canvas and stay in a
state of flow, I just swipe over
to the side.
I'll draw something in the theme
of calligraphy in front of a
couple thousand people, so
hopefully I do this all right.
I'm going to draw a little
feather pen.
So I'm just going to trace in
the outline with a felt-tip
marker.
It's looking pretty good.
It's a little bit flat, so I
think I'm going to add in some
shading.
It's a little bit more
realistic.
And then zoom in here -- whoops
-- add in some color for the
feather pen, and then touch
things up with the eraser.
All right.
That's looking pretty good, but,
you know, no drawing is complete
until you sign your name.
All right.
I think we're done.
Dave?
>> Thanks, Mike.
Please help me welcome to the
stage the team from Moleskine to
accept their award for Flow.
[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Yeah, the attention to detail
in that app is amazing, and
that's one of the things that we
look for when we evaluate for
design.
All right, help me to welcome my
-- our next presenters, Lauren
Stralo and T.C. Chan.
[ Music ]
>> Thanks, John.
The next award goes to The
Gardens Between.
[ Applause ]
Now, we absolutely love this
game because it captures the
magic of time.
Have you ever wanted to travel
back in time, or maybe just
relive a moment that you
reminisce about?
Well, technology hasn't quite
gotten us there yet, but playing
this game gives you a sense of
what that might be like.
And you play as these two main
characters, named Arina and
Frendt.
This game tells a special story
about friendship, and we
absolutely love it for its
cinematic moments and its
immersive experience.
Let's take a closer look.
T.C.?
[ Music ]
>> Let's have a moment to take
in this whole island.
Now, beyond the stunning imagery
that you see, what really
impressed us about this game is
that this kind of attention to
detail actually extends to its
bespoke soundtrack, its
natural-feeling haptics, and
more than that, the
storytelling.
Notice how Frendt is taken aback
when Arina's able to walk over
the clouds, and then he catches
up, still a little unsure.
And here, I just stopped time,
and I do that by just not
tapping anything.
This means that I'm never
feeling rushed or under any kind
of time pressure.
We think this game play mechanic
is really simple, yet effective.
Now, because you move both
characters at once, and only
control the flow of time, an
interesting interplay happens
between the two characters.
Here, you will notice that Arina
is no longer able to move any
more forward in time, and that's
because Frendt has fallen
behind.
So let's go back in time, and
see what we can do differently
to help him out.
Now, you might notice that with
each time I hop over the saw
handle, it continues to cut
through the plank.
So let me go back and forth in
time a few times.
[ Music ]
>> Nice. I see what you did
there, T.C.
>> Yeah. All right.
So now, Frendt is able to catch
up, and they continue their
journey.
Just around the island, there
are these bells.
They're highlighted because
they're interactive.
So I just need to tap the
screen.
Frendt hits the bell, and in
this case, the light is given
back to Irina.
The objective is to bring the
light to the top of each island.
Now, let's move away from game
play for a while, and have a
look at this heartwarming scene.
>> As you play this game, you
will learn that things are
considered and deliberate, and
probably a hint.
So we're not going to spoil any
more of this for you today.
So please help us welcome The
Gardens Between creators to the
stage, The Voxel Agents.
Congratulations.
[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> I mean, how cool is that?
That is an app that is crafted
with care.
All right, for our next winner,
I'd like to invite Adrian and
Corinne.
[ Music ]
>> Thanks, John.
Great apps combine seamless
onboarding, intuitive controls,
and stunning visuals to create a
truly immersive experience.
And when it comes to games, it's
these elements that can make
even a novice player feel like a
pro.
Next up, the award goes to
Gameloft for Asphalt 9 Legends.
[ Applause ]
Asphalt 9 is a hyper-realistic
arcade racing game with
incredible graphics.
Let's take a look.
My colleague Corinne's going to
jump in to see if she has what
it takes to become a legend.
There are over 50 of the world's
most amazing high-speed vehicles
available to select.
Each is a meticulously-detailed
version of the vehicle, with
endless customization.
We're going with one of my
personal favorites, the Chevy
Camaro, and of course, we had to
make it purple.
With 70 courses spanning the
globe, from Cairo to the
Himalayas, today, we're going to
be racing the streets of
Shanghai.
All right, here we go.
And she's off.
You'll immediately notice the
realistic details due to some
post-processing effects,
including motion blur,
reflection, color grading, even
god rays-- Gameloft was able
to achieve these console-style
graphics with their custom
engine and with Metal 2
integration, all with an
impressive 60 frames per second
of smooth performance.
Controls are easy to pick up
with Touch Drive.
Acceleration and braking are
handled for you, so that you can
focus on navigating the course,
but don't let the simple
controls fool you.
Players are responsible for
timing drifts, nitro boosts, and
finding shortcuts in order to
beat the competition.
The team was inspired by
skateboarding, and wanted the
vehicle maneuvers to reflect
that stunting style.
So you'll see 360-degree spins,
barrel rolls, and tons of
fearless jumps.
Add in a bit of nitro boost, and
hold on.
[ Game Sounds ]
Speaking of style, have a listen
to that soundtrack.
[ Music ]
Asphalt 9 mixes over two hours
of music to keep your heart
racing as you cut those close
corners.
Three control styles, endless
customizations, single and
multiplayer mode -- Asphalt 9
truly has something for
everyone.
And with a combined 4.8-star
rating from over 300,000
players, it certainly does.
The question is, like Corinne
here, do you have what it takes
to become a legend?
Please welcome to the stage
Gameloft.
Congratulations.
[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> That's an incredibly
innovative game with the new
type of driving, and the
technology integration's
phenomenal with that kind of
performance.
All right, up next, for our next
winner, my colleagues Ennis and
Eric.
[ Music ]
>> Do you sometimes find that
you take a photo, and it doesn't
quite capture the feeling of the
moment?
The secret is, professional
photographers adjust their
photos after the shoot, and
create the desired effect.
But that takes time, and for
most of us, we don't even know
where to start -- what colors
need adjusting, or how do you
find that perfect composition.
But this is exactly where this
app truly shines.
The award goes to Pixelmator
Photo.
[ Applause ]
Eric will show you now what can
be achieved with this incredible
app exclusively on the iPad.
>> Thank you, Ennis.
I'm really excited to show you
all just how easy it is to edit
photos on your iPad using
Pixelmator Photo.
Let's get started.
I've got this great image of
this boy playing soccer on a
beach in India, but I think with
a few simple adjustments, we can
really make this photo pop.
I'm first going to hit the
Auto-Enhance button, which is
already making this look quite a
bit better.
But I want it to have a more
vintage look to it, and for
that, I'm going to have a look
at some of the many built-in
presets within this app.
I love all these different film
looks, and the urban looks, but
I specifically like these
classic films.
So I'm going to choose number 2.
I think that looks really good,
and there's one more thing I
want to do to this image, which
is to crop it before I share it
with my friends.
And what's really unique about
the cropping in Pixelmator Photo
is, the team trained a custom
Core ML model on thousands and
thousands of images to gain a
deep understanding of the
content of the photos.
And by doing that, they let me,
as their customer, just simply
enable this Smart Cropping
feature, and I can choose a
different aspect ratio, like a
square frame.
And there, in two taps, I have
this perfectly-cropped image
ready to share.
Let's take a look at one more
photo.
I'm going to tap on the Files
button here on the top, and I'm
going to choose this photo of
this lovely couple in New York.
And this is indicative of a lot
of the photos we have in our
personal libraries.
It's a really sweet moment, but
it suffers from a very
unfortunate lighting situation.
I'm going to use the ML Enhance
again to immediately improve the
image, but what I want to show
you is what's happening behind
the scenes.
The Pixelmator team spent months
training a custom Core ML model
on over 20 million image pairs,
and from that, they learned how
to automatically control over 32
different adjustments, from
white balance, hue and
saturation, lightness, color
balance.
Understanding all these
individual adjustments on your
own can be very daunting, but
with the ML Enhance feature,
it's a perfect place to start.
I can do something like simply
bump the black point just a
little bit more, and I think
that looks great.
I can deep-press on this photo
to compare it, and I think
you'll agree that's a much
better version of this image.
So that's just a very quick tour
of the simplicity of Pixelmator
Photo.
By leveraging Metal and Core ML,
the app is fast, and it's
intelligent.
And with this beautiful, simple
UI, and direct integration with
files, it really is easy photo
editing for everyone.
Amazing app.
>> Well, as we seen, Team
Pixelmator's native Lithuanian
[foreign language].
Congratulations, and please,
welcome to the stage.
[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> You know, we love how
Pixelmator Photo uses Apple
technologies to do new things,
and this isn't the first time
that this team has been on
stage.
And that's not without good
reason.
The Pixelmator Team is
consistently in lockstep with
new devices that we release, and
new technologies.
Phenomenal, phenomenal work.
All right, to present our sixth
award, I'd like to bring on
Lauren and Paolo Verani.
[ Music ]
>> Now, we love the game ELOH
for its beautiful animation,
illustration, and creative
approach to throwing a ball at a
block.
While you play, you learn basic
physics and geometry with rhythm
and music.
Now, music and sound effects are
key elements to helping you
solve this chilled-out puzzle
game.
You can play, relax, and
decompress all while finding
your groove.
Now, I absolutely love playing
this game, and I know you do,
too, Paolo.
>> Yeah, I do.
>> Will you help us take a look?
>> I do, actually, Lauren.
I actually love playing this
game with my son, Luca.
It's his favorite game right
now, and the reason for that is
that the first time you launch
ELOH, you realize that there is
no onboarding.
There are no instructions.
Just like many great iOS games,
you just learn by playing.
Now, the goal of the game is to
get the little ball that emits
from this speaker down to the
target, and you do that by --
you achieve that by tapping on
these tribal masks, and moving
them around the screen.
Great.
I think my reputation is saved.
Level four is done.
Now, the game has 99 levels, and
as you would expect, things can
get more complicated.
Yet, the game still offers a
very relaxing experience, and I
think the key component here is
the sound effects, and the
soundtrack, which complements
the beautiful graphics and
delightful animations.
And the other fun aspect is
that, while you're playing,
you're actually composing your
very own soundtrack.
Cool.
Let's get through level 12.
Great.
Now, level 12 is special,
because we get rewarded with a
little totem animation.
What is also fun about this game
is that there is no score.
There is no -- there are no time
constraints.
Therefore, a little six-year-old
kid can play without any time
pressure, or fear of making
mistakes.
ELOH is the result of a great
team collaborating from across
the world with the creator and
developer of the game, which is
an Italian guy based in Vienna,
a sound designer based in
Seattle, an artist in New York,
and a Portuguese animator.
Whether you're six or 96 years
old, ELOH will deliver hours of
relaxing fun.
>> Please help me welcome the
Broken Rules Team to the stage.
Congratulations.
[ Music ]
>> Now, that is a game with
personality, which is a great --
characteristic of great design.
All right, up next, we have an
app that sets a new bar for
innovation, and to tell us more
about it, I'd like to introduce
Alexis from the Health Team and
Chris from Developer Relations.
[ Music ]
>> At Apple, we believe a
powerful combination of hardware
and software, combined with a
delightful user experience, can
change the world.
>> Our next winner combines
their innovative device with a
beautiful iOS app to create an
experience that is changing
medicine.
>> The winner is Butterfly IQ
from Butterfly Network.
[ Applause ]
>> As a cardiologist, the
ability to see inside the body
provides me with insights that
simply aren't possible through
other means, and 2/3 of the
world has no imaging at all.
This is Butterfly IQ.
It's a handheld ultrasound, and
it costs $2000.
>> The current state of a common
ultrasound machine is $60,000+,
and is about the size of a
refrigerator.
This device is built on the
premise that you can move
ultrasound to a microchip, and
move the compute to an iOS
device.
>> Let's get started with a
quick scan of Chris's heart.
All right, let's take a look.
You'll notice the design is made
to work well with one hand, no
click wheel or keyboard.
We love the attention Butterfly
paid to this one-handed
experience.
I can adjust how deep the
ultrasound can see with the
swipe of a finger, and take a
video clip of the image.
Okay, don't breathe.
All right.
Congratulations, Chris.
Your heart looks good.
All right.
[ Applause ]
Being able to take this device
and plug it into an iPad or an
iPhone helps make imaging
simple.
And now, I want to show you
something truly amazing.
On the screen, you are going to
see Butterfly's AI and ML-backed
technology helping me take a
measurement called an ejection
fraction that I use regularly.
As I start to get the image,
you'll see that slider at the
bottom, hinting to me, guiding
me, helping me get a
diagnostically-useful image.
We love this thoughtful design
cue that is helpful, subtle, and
powerful.
After I get a useful image, I
can have the app calculate
ejection fraction.
Isn't that spectacular?
[ Applause ]
And one of the things I love
about this design is that it
shows you the data behind the
calculations.
So you saw on the screen there
that outline of the heart.
If I saw a point that looked
off, I could just correct it.
What Butterfly has done with
this app and hardware is truly
an exceptional display of
design, from the design of the
chip, to the design of the
device, to the design of the
app, and all the technologies
involved.
Congratulations to Butterfly IQ.
[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Now, that is an inspiring
example of innovation, bringing
healthcare to -- all over the
world, to places where it would
not be available otherwise,
using this new technology.
All right, I'd like to call on
my next -- on -- next up, my
colleagues Mark and Corinne to
talk about our next winner.
[ Music ]
>> Thanks, John.
Our next winner is a music
rhythm game, but it's unlike any
rhythm game I've ever played.
In fact, it's unlike any game
I've ever played, period.
Our next winner is Thumper.
Thumper -- here's my best
attempt to describe it.
You play as a metallic space
beetle matching a dark,
industrial beat, which propels
you down a narrow track towards
psychedelic alien space
monsters.
Yeah, you've got to see this for
yourself.
Thumper does a terrific job
introducing new game play
mechanics one by one.
Now, in this case, we're
learning to change lanes, but
just to get you up to speed
quickly, we've already learned
to tap when we pass over a
glowing pad, swipe left and
right to turn, and swipe up to
jump.
Now, audio cues actually guide
our swipe timing, but just when
you think you have it figured
out, the cadence switches.
[ Music ]
The custom soundtrack in Thumper
plays a key role in defining the
tone of the game, which the
developer describes as dread on
a cosmic scale.
Now, in this low-level boss
battle, if you make a mistake,
the level will seamlessly reset
and advance toward you.
With ceaseless levels and a
pulsating beat, Thumper is an
intense, continuous experience.
[ Music ]
Thumper's visuals are difficult
to describe, but easy to
appreciate.
Inspired by psychedelic rock,
pinball machines, and more,
these graphics rival those on
any other platform.
In fact, the developer created a
custom engine which is powered
by Metal and renders at 60
frames per second -- very
impressive.
[ Music ]
Now, we hardly have time to talk
about all the careful design
decisions that the developer
made, like supporting real-time
portrait and landscape
switching.
Haptic feedback to emphasize a
crash, tilt controls to change
lanes -- they created a custom
gestural system to detect swipes
for the turns, and then, of
course, they have a pause button
that fades away until just the
moment when you need it.
It's incredibly satisfying to
beat a level in Thumper, but
there's no time to celebrate, as
the next level comes screaming
toward you.
Thumper also supports Game
Center leader boards, and iCloud
Sync to save games across
devices.
All right, let's turn the volume
up so you can really appreciate
how well the graphics and
soundtrack are orchestrated.
[ Music ]
Thumper's striking graphics,
driving soundtrack, and unified
design make it a deserving
winner of an Apple design award.
Congratulations to Drool.
Please welcome them to the
stage.
[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> That is pretty great.
I think it's super-fun, and
super-compelling, with great
game play and deep system
integration.
All right, to present our final
award tonight, I'd like to
introduce Doug Lemoine and Larry
Moss.
[ Music ]
>> So this last app shows that
you don't need to be a big team
to create an experience that's
truly groundbreaking.
>> It solves a new problem using
powerful technology that's so
seamless, it's almost invisible.
>> When Larry and I first saw
this, I think we had the same
reaction.
This must be fake.
>> This must be fake [laughter].
The winner of the next Apple
Design Award is HomeCourt by NEX
Team.
[ Applause ]
>> All right, let's take a look.
The core of the experience is a
list of drills and workouts.
These drills are super-easy to
set up, and require no special
equipment, unless you count this
headband, which I carry
everywhere.
Let's do a dribbling drill.
>> In this case, we're going to
use a tripod, but it's just as
common to use your iPhone popped
up against a water bottle.
>> So the drill will get started
when I'm in the frame.
>> The iPhone camera, Core ML,
and Vision frameworks are doing
all the work, not Doug.
But to be fair, Doug is really
good, but even non-experts can
benefit from HomeCourt's ability
to make them a better basketball
player.
Lower and faster dribbling will
make you score more points.
Faster, Doug, faster.
Good job.
>> So at the end of the drill, I
get a nice little summary.
>> And in addition to doing
these dribbling workouts,
HomeCourt is also great for
tracking shooting drills.
In fact, you can see up here on
the screen, it has tracked your
makes and your misses, as well
as where you shot the ball from.
In fact, it also gives you this
nice video where you can see
your shots, and where you took
them from.
You know, Doug, this is really
revolutionary.
>> It's true, Larry [laughter].
Before HomeCourt, you would have
to do this stuff manually.
You'd have to have someone track
it for you.
>> Absolutely.
And today, you see kids, and
even adults, using HomeCourt to
improve their skills.
>> So when you finish a drill,
you can actually share your
results with your friends, your
teammates, your coaches, or with
people around the world.
>> But you know, Doug,
basketball is way more fun when
you play against someone else.
>> And HomeCourt has competitive
drills, too.
Do you want to show them?
>> Oh, totally.
You're on.
[ Laughter ]
[ Music ]
>> So the objective in this
drill is to not hit the red
targets.
[ Music ]
Your shoe's untied.
>> Yeah, that's what you think.
Get into frame, man.
[ Music ]
>> You beat me again.
[ Applause ]
HomeCourt's use of amazing Core
ML technology really makes it so
that everyone can become a
better basketball player.
Come on up.
[ Music ]
>> All right, well done.
Well done.
Incredible work.
All right, so that's a wrap.
Please join me in thanking my
colleagues who were here on
stage showing you the apps this
evening.
[ Applause ]
And more importantly, let's
thank our winners one last time.
So please stand.
If you're in the rest of the
house, please stand as well if
you're one of the winners.
Give them a big round of
applause.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
So nine great apps and games
that stand on the shoulders of
88 winners before them, and
raise the bar even higher.
We look forward to what you're
going to do for next year based
on all of the technologies that
you learned about today, and
that you're going to learn about
throughout this week.
Thanks for coming again.
We hope you have a great WWDC.
Good night.
[ Applause ]