[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Hi, everyone.
Thank you for coming to this
session.
I know it's been a long day.
My name is Alexander Jakobsen
and I'm an engineer on the
MapKit team.
Apple Maps helps millions of
people around the world to
navigate and explore the world
every single day.
And thousands of developers like
you are using MapKit to
integrate Apple Maps in your
apps where you help your users
with all kinds of amazing
location services.
And last year, we introduced
MapKit JS allowing you to bring
Apple Maps to your websites as
well.
Hopefully you watched the
keynote this Monday and saw all
the great new features we're
adding to Maps in iOS 13.
We're very excited about where
Maps is going.
But on top of everything you saw
in the keynote, we have been
very busy this year building a
number of new features in MapKit
and MapKit JS that you have been
asking for.
So, I'm very excited to finally
be able to tell you what's new
in MapKit and MapKit JS.
But before we get into all the
new features, I want to take a
moment and talk about our
brand-new base map.
As mentioned in the keynote, we
have rebuilt our map from the
ground up covering more than 4
million miles of road so far in
our fleet of custom cars and
planes.
The new map is incredibly
detailed and you'll see more
features than ever before like
baseball fields, running tracks,
walking paths and swimming
pools.
And you will see major
improvements to the richness and
details in parks, greenways,
beaches and rural areas, as well
as improved roads, buildings,
city parks and so much more.
And we've also improved the
address detail a lot, which
means more accurate search and
direction results.
And the best part is as we roll
out these improvements to Apple
Maps, they become automatically
available to you through MapKit
and MapKit JS.
The updated map will be
available in the entire US at
the end of 2019 and we're adding
additional countries in 2020.
We're also making the map
available to you in Dark Mode on
iOS, tvOS, macOS and the web.
And in this session, we will be
using a fictitious WWDC
companion app to demonstrate
some of the topics we're going
to cover.
This app will be available as
sample code from the session web
page, but let's take a quick
look at what this app is all
about.
There are three main features
intended to bring additional
value to conference attendees
like yourself.
The first feature is the
accommodation feature or
accommodation finder where
attendees can find accommodation
for the duration of the
conference through the companion
app partners.
This view is simply a map with a
number of annotations added to
it.
The second feature is called
After Hours.
And it's a feature where
attendees can find a restaurant
or a bar where they're meeting
up with other attendees after
conference hours.
As the user types in the search
field, relevant suggestions on
restaurants and bars are shown
us suggestions and search
results are displayed as
annotation views on the map.
And the last feature is the
event view.
The event view shows a simple
map of the companion app event
that takes place the evening
before the official WWDC Bash.
This feature focuses the map
view on the location of the
event and renders a number of
annotations and overlays to
represent the food and drinks
tents, as well as the stage.
So, for the remainder of this
session, we'll go through a
little bit more details on the
most exciting new features in
MapKit and MapKit JS.
And we have a lot of things to
cover today like our new
snapshot service, new APIs for
filtering and increased map view
camera control.
So, let's start out with talking
about snapshots.
Snapshots are simply static
images of the map and you may be
familiar with the map
snapshotter that has been
available in MapKit for a number
of years.
We use snapshots in our apps but
we don't need user interaction
in our maps, like in contacts,
and messages, and calendar.
But since the snapshotter is
part of MapKit, you can only
create the snapshots in native
apps.
But this week, we announced a
new service that lets you create
and use snapshots in other
environments as well.
And this new service is called
Maps Web Snapshots.
To fetch a Maps Web Snapshot,
all you need is a URL.
And the parameters of that URL
dictates the characteristics of
the image such as its center
coordinate, its size.
And if you want this same
snapshots but with the map in
Dark Mode, you can add the color
scheme parameter with the value
dark.
All snapshot URLs requires a
signature which you can generate
after obtaining a MapKit JS API
key through the apple developer
program.
As part of the MapKit JS beta,
you can now request 25,000
snapshots per day, which we're
hoping it will be more than
enough to cover the needs of
people out there.
You can use map snapshots any
place where you would use a URL
to display an image like in an
email, in a URL preview and of
course web pages.
And to help you get started with
generating snapshot URLS, we
have built this tool for you and
you can find that one and more
information about the MapKit JS
beta program on the MapKit JS
developer page.
So, that's how you can create
Maps Web Snapshots.
So, let's move on and talk a
little bit more about the map in
Dark Mode.
Last year, we introduced the map
in Dark Mode for-- on macOS.
And this year, we're bringing it
to iOS, tvOS and the web.
So, what do you need to do to
use the map in Dark Mode in your
apps?
Well, MKMapView will
automatically adapt to the user
interface style in the trait
collection applied to its view
hierarchy.
So, if your view is dark, the
map view will adapt
automatically.
And this should be familiar to
you if you have used MapKit on
tvOS in the past.
And for those of you who are
wondering, yes, this improved
map will replace the old one
automatically.
As I mentioned before, if you
don't need user interaction in
your maps, the right tool to use
is the snapshotter.
But unlike the map view, the
snapshotter is not aware of the
view hierarchy in your apps.
It's therefore important that
you configure your snapshotter
to ensure that the snapshot
matches the user interface style
of your view hierarchy.
And you do this using the
snapshotter options.
So, let's look an example of how
to do this.
First, you need to create your
snapshotter options and you need
to configure what area of the
world you want to snapshot.
You also need to provide the
size of the snapshots.
Similar to a view, you configure
the appearance of your snapshot
using a user interface style in
a trait collection.
So, if you have a view where you
intend to present your snapshot,
the easiest way to configure
your options is to grab the
trait collection of that target
view.
This will ensure that the
snapshot you create actually
matches a user interface style
of your view hierarchy.
But remember that users can
switch in or out of iOS's Dark
Mode as they're using your app.
So, make sure that you observe
changes to the trait collection
in your view hierarchy so you
can regenerate your snapshot if
the user interface style
changes.
In some cases, you may not
actually have a target view for
your snapshot, maybe because
you're sharing it to another
device.
In that case, you can instead
just create a UITraitCollection
with the appropriate user
interface style.
And once you have configured
your options, you simply path
into your snapshotter at
creation time and then you tell
your snapshotter to create that
snapshot for you.
And that's how easy it is to use
the map in Dark Mode in your
apps.
So, the next thing I want to
talk about is a set of new APIs
in MapKit and MapKit JS that
lets you take control over the
point of interest icons that are
shown in your map views.
If you've ever looked at our
maps, you've probably seen that
apart from all the roads,
buildings, parks and water,
there's all these little icons
representing restaurants,
museums, parking and so on.
And this information is great
for users to better understand
what the area they're looking at
is all about.
But if you're building a feature
where you're promoting hotels
and hostels for example, you
probably have your own data that
you will be adding to the map
view as annotation views.
And in that case, you may not
want these built-in icons to
show either because they're
duplicating the information
you're adding or because you
don't want to show businesses
that are not connected to your
service.
In the past, your only option
has been to turn off all the
point of interest icons but that
means that your users are losing
out on a lot of valuable
context.
So what you want to do instead
is to filter those point of
interest icons based on their
categories.
So, MapKit and MapKit JS now
expose a list of categories that
we think you will find useful
when you're building your apps
[applause].
And this is obviously not an
all-inclusive list.
So if you see one that is
missing, come by our lab
tomorrow or send us your
feedback and most importantly,
tell us about your use case.
So, you use these categories to
create a pointOfInterestFilter.
And when you create your filter,
you can configure it to either
include categories or exclude
categories.
So let's take a look at a few
examples of this.
By default, the map view does
not apply any filter at all.
So, all the point of interest
icons are showing.
But in our case, we wanted
hotels and hostel and the like
to not actually show.
And you can achieve this by
creating an exclusion filter
with the category hotel.
This ensures that no hotels or
hostels are shown but the rest
of the context is preserved.
If you instead know which
categories are relevant in your
use case, you can create an
inclusion filter with those
categories.
So, this filter for example will
filter out the courthouse, and
the beauty and barber shop
around the corner and only show
point of interest from the
selected categories,
restaurants, night life, and
parking and cafés.
And if you do want to turn off
all the point of interest icons,
you can still do that using an
excluding all filter.
Point of interest filtering
support is also coming to MapKit
JS this fall, and it works in a
very similar way.
We're adding a
pointOfInterestFilter to the
MapKit object and you create a
filter using a list of point of
interest category values.
Once you've created your filter,
you apply it to the
pointOfInterestFilter property
on your map.
So, the map view is definitely
MapKit and MapKit JS's most
prominent feature.
But another important
cornerstone is the support for
search and autocompletion.
So, the next thing I'm going to
talk about is how you can
improve the results from search
and autocompletion using
filtering.
The companion app uses search
and autocompletion support from
MapKit for its After Hours
feature.
So, as the user is typing, the
autosuggest-- autocompletion
suggestions are coming from
MKLocalSearchCompleter.
And the results shown on the map
are fetched using MKLocalSearch.
But if we take a step back and
look at those suggestions again,
we realize that in a feature
where we expect our users to
search for bars and restaurants,
a middle school is not a very
relevant suggestion.
Fortunately, the
pointOfInterestFilter we used to
filter our map view before also
works both for search and
autocompletion.
So, you can create your filter
for your search feature and
apply it to your
MKLocalSearhCompleter and apply
it to your
MKLocalSearch.Request.
And this will narrow down your
results to a much more relevant
set.
But there's still addresses
showing in this list.
And that's because addresses are
distinctly different from point
of interest, which generally
represents landmarks or
businesses.
So, to further improve the
results in this list, we want to
focus the search and
autocompletion results to just
point of interest.
Up until now, MapKit has only
supported result type filtering
for MKLocalSearchCompleter.
And you did this using the
filterType property.
But the value locations only
still meant that you will get
both addresses and point of
interest, which is not enough to
help us here.
So to address this, we have
introduced two new option sets
called ResultType.
And you use these option sets to
configure the type of results
you want from both search and
autocompletion.
So the option set for
MKLocalSearchCompleter that you
pick any combination you want
from addresses, points of
interests and queries.
And for MKLocalSearch.Request
you can pick and choose between
addresses and point of
interests.
So you can now easily just
configure your completer and
your request to only request
point of interests.
And the result you get back from
MKLocalSearch is an array of
MKMapItems.
And MapItems contain a lot of
useful information like the
location coordinate of that
result, and address.
And in some cases, you can also
have a name for that place, a
phone number, or even a URL.
To make it easier for you to
reason about the type of results
you're getting, we have added a
new property called point of
interest category.
So if you make a search for ABC,
if you make a search for ABC,
you might get the results Al's
Beet Canteen and ABC Brewing,
for example.
And if you inspect the point of
interest categories of these
results, you will see that they
are a restaurant and a brewery
respectively.
If you would apply an inclusion
filter with the category
brewery, Al's Beet Canteen will
no longer show up.
However, ABC Brewing also runs a
restaurant as part of their
business, which means if we
apply an inclusion filter with
the category restaurant, we may
still see ABC Brewing in our
search results.
And if we inspect the point of
interest category, it will still
be brewery because that's ABC
breweries-- ABC Brewing's
primary category.
The same search and
autocompletion filtering support
is coming to MapKit JS this
fall.
And you filter the point of
interests by applying your
pointOfInterest filter directly
to the search object.
And to narrow down the type of
results you're getting, you use
the new properties
includeAddresses,
includePointOfInterest, and
includeQueries also found on the
search object.
All right.
And with that I will hand it
over to my colleague Nalini, who
will show you how quick and easy
it is to improve the relevance
of your search results using
these new APIs.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Alexander.
Hi. I'm Nalini and I'm a
software engineer in the MapKit
Framework team.
Alexander already showed the
WWDC companion app we'll be
building throughout the session.
We already have a version of the
application that implement some
of the functionality but isn't
quite there yet.
Let me show it to you.
Here, we are looking at the
After Hours feature where we'll
be exploring places around San
Jose.
We have a map view set up with a
search bar.
The search bar uses
MKLocalSearchCompleter and
MKLocalSearch to search Apple
Maps later.
This functionality has existed
since iOS 9.3.
Let's go ahead and search for
something.
As I'm typing we receive
autocomplete suggestions.
As an attendee at the
conference, we are not
interested in some of these
results.
Let's go ahead and issue a
search.
We observed a similar
experience.
We get back results that are not
relevant for our use case.
Let's see how to improve this
experience using
pointOfInterestFilter and result
types APIs.
Here we are looking at the After
Hours view controller where
autocompletion and search are
set up.
We'll declare a
pointOfInterestFilter that we
will leverage for both
autocompletion and search.
The categories we are interested
in are night life and restaurant
for our use case.
We'll apply the
pointOfInterestFilter to the
searchCompleter.
Address results are not relevant
for our use case.
We limit the result types to
pointOfInterest.
The changes we just did affect
autocompletion.
Let's see how to apply the same
filter to search.
When user issues a search, we
form a local search request.
We'll apply the
pointOfInterestFilter to the
search request.
We limit the result types to
pointOfInterest.
Now that we have
pointOfInterestFilter and result
types applied to both
autocompletion and search, let's
execute our application.
Looking at the After Hours
feature, we'll go ahead and
search for the same source
string.
As you can see, we get results
relevant to our use case.
And when we issue a search, we
also get relevant results which
are displayed as annotations on
the map view.
We just saw how to improve the
autocompletion and search
experience using
pointOfInterestFilter and result
types APIs.
With that, I hand over back to
Alexander.
[ Applause ]
>> OK. So that was five lines of
code to get rid of all those
irrelevant results.
So if you're using search for
autocompletion in your apps
today, I strongly recommend you
to try out these new APIs.
And that's all we're going to
cover for search and
autocompletion filtering today.
So next I want to tell you about
some really nice improvements we
have made to our overlay APIs in
MapKit.
Overlays are used to layer
custom content over a wider area
of your map view and they
generally represent geometric
shapes like lines or polygons.
And to show you these
improvements we're going to take
a quick look at the event view
of the companion app.
So for this feature we want to
render this simple event map in
our map view.
And we'll use overlays to
represent the food and drinks
tents and the stage.
As these-- they're all
rectangular in shape we can
model them using MKPolygons.
And so this map is so simple and
we're kind of short on time in
this session, we will style them
all the same way.
But for every overlay that you
add to your map view, you need
to provide a render object in
your delegate method.
If you're adding a lot of
similar styled overlays like
this, that means you will be
creating a lot of render objects
that are configured exactly the
same way, and that's kind of
wasteful.
This will obviously not lead to
any noticeable performance
impact in an app with seven
overlays.
But if you are like adding a lot
of a large number of overlays,
you can actually notice the
performance impact of this.
So to address this, we have
introduced a few new classes in
MapKit.
There are two new overlay
classes, MKMultiPolygon and
MKMultiPolyline that you can use
to group polygons and polylines
respectively.
And as I said before, every time
you add an overlay you need to
provide a render object.
So we have introduced two new
matching render classes,
MKMultiPolygonRenderer and
MKMultiPolylineRenderer.
Using these classes, you can
dramatically reduce the number
of render objects need-- that
you need to create in your apps
and thereby improve the
performance.
So let's look at a simple
example of this.
So here we're creating the
polygon for the stage using the
coordinates above.
And after creating all the other
polygons, we're adding them
straight to the map view.
But this means, like I said
before, the delegate will be
asked to create seven renderers.
So what you instead want to do
is to take all those polygons
and group them into an
MKMultiPolygon and then simply
add that MultiPolygon to your
map view.
Once you have updated your code
to add MultiPolygons instead,
you also need to update your
delegate method to expect
MultiPolygons.
And when you get one you need to
create a MKMultiPolygonRenderer
object.
And this is done the exact the
same way as the old
MKPolygonRenderer.
Apart from saving memory by
creating a fewer number of
render objects, this also
improves the rendering
performance because MapKit can
now be smarter and batch up the
rendering of those polygons for
you.
Another improvement we have made
is that MapKit will now
automatically render all your
overlays that you create using
the built-in MapKit render
objects as vector graphics
instead of bitmaps.
And vector rendering greatly
improves the look of your
overlays when the user interacts
with the map because they scale
much more nicely when the user
zooms in and out in the map
view.
If you're adding very large and
complex overlays and they're for
some reason not looking quite
right when rendered as vector
graphics, you can opt out of
vector rendering using the
shouldRasterize property on the
renderer.
And that's how you use the new
overlay APIs in MapKit.
[ Applause ]
So the next thing I want to
cover is MapKit's new support
for GeoJSON.
GeoJSON is a widely used storage
and wire format for representing
geometric objects like points,
lines and polygons.
And a lot of vendors publish
their data as GeoJSON.
So some of you may already have
written code to parse that
GeoJSON, create annotations and
overlays that you're adding to
your map view.
So with these new APIs, we're
hoping that working with GeoJSON
will be easier than ever and
maybe you can even delete some
of that code you have written.
[ Applause ]
For those of you who are not
familiar with GeoJSON, here's a
very simple example of how it
can represent a location.
At the top level there's the
type member that lets us know
that this is a feature and a
feature can have an optional
identifier which you can use to
uniquely identify this feature
among others.
And this feature is defined by a
single geometry, a point, but a
feature can also have multiple
geometries.
And in addition to the geometry
there's the properties member
which in this case just contains
the name of this location, the
stage.
So to represent this feature in
MapKits, we have introduced a
new class called
MKGeoJSONFeature.
And this class is simply a data
container that holds the
identifier, the decoded geometry
and the properties.
So to get from your GeoJSON to
actual MapKit classes, we have
introduced another class called
MKGeoJSONDecoder.
If you've ever used Swift's JSON
decoder, MKGeoJSONDecoder should
feel pretty familiar to you.
You simply create your decoder,
you passage your data and it
will return an array of either
MKGeoJSONFeatures or MapKit's
geometry such as MKPolygon or
MKPolylines and so on.
And this depends on how your
GeoJSON is structured because
you can either have features in
your top level or geometry in
your top level GeoJSON.
So if you take a look at how
this example GeoJSON from before
would be decoded by the
MKGeoJSONDecoder, we can realize
that since this one has a single
feature, our resulting array
will just have one item.
But the decoder also decodes the
geometry into MapKit classes.
So the point location here will
be decoded as an
MKPointAnnotation and the
feature itself will be decoded
as an MKGeoJSONFeature with a
reference to that
MKPointAnnotation.
So with the introduction of
MKMultiPolygon and MultiPolyline
that I've talked about before,
MapKit now has a complete
mapping from GeoJSON geometry
into MapKit classes.
And this means that once you
have decoded your GeoJSON, you
will have annotations and
overlays that are more or less
ready to be added to your map
views.
So let's look at a simple
example of this.
First, you create your decoder
and you passage your data.
And as I said, depending on how
your GeoJSON is structured, you
can then either work with your
top level features or your
geometries.
If you're doing additional
parsing of a feature, you use
the geometry property to get
access to those polygons and
polylines.
In our example, we knew that the
GeoJSON would only have a single
feature and a point geometry.
So this code is making some
assumptions.
In most cases, you would want
this part of your code to also
take MKPolygons, MultiPolylines
and so on into consideration.
In the GeoJSON specification,
the properties member can be any
valid JSON or even null.
And this means that MapKit
cannot really make any
assumptions about how to parse
this data.
So MKGeoJSONFeature exposes its
properties as the data type.
So if you know the structure of
your properties, you can use the
JSON decoder to map up data into
an appropriate model class.
In our case we know that the
properties contained a string
mapping to a string.
So we will simply map it to a
dictionary, which makes it
really for us to read out the
value for the name key.
But in some cases, you may not
be in control over your
GeoJSONs.
You may not actually know the
structure of your properties.
In that case, you can instead
use the JSON serialization API
to dynamically explore the
properties depending on its
type.
So what about MapKit JS?
We actually already support
GeoJSON in MapKit JS.
So you can map your GeoJSON into
an existing MapKit JS item such
as annotations, overlays and
ItemCollections.
And let's have a look at a quick
example of that.
So you simply pass either a URL
or a valid GeoJSON object to the
import GeoJSON function on the
MapKit object.
This function will return an
item collection that contains
one or many MapKit JS items
which you can then easily add to
your map object using either add
items or show items.
All right, and I will now hand
it back over to Nalini one more
time.
And now she's going to show us
how you can get that event map
rendered in the map view.
[ Applause ]
>> Let's continue building the
WWDC Companion app.
Here we are looking at the
Concert in The Park feature
where we have a map you set up
for the concert area.
What concert would be complete
without food and drinks?
We need tents for these food and
drinks.
We'll be rendering these tents
as overlays and annotations on
the map view.
Our data is provided to us in
GeoJSON format.
Let's have a quick look at the
data.
In our JSON we have two
features.
The top level is grouped in
feature collection.
Our first feature is event
tents.
We'll be rendering many tents,
which means more options for
food and drinks.
The geometry of our tent is
MultiPolygon.
These are the different
coordinates of the tents.
We'll be using this data to
render overlays on the map view
which will represent the tent
outlines.
Our second feature is point,
which describes the names of the
various food and drink tents.
We'll be using this data to
render annotations on the map
view, which will represent the
tent labels.
Let's see how to parse these two
features in code.
Here, we are looking at the
event data source where we will
load the JSON and subsequently
parse it.
Let's go ahead and load the
JSON.
Once the JSON is loaded, we will
use the MKGeoJSONDecoder to
decode this into an array of
MKGeoJSON objections.
We'll subsequently parse these
objects.
Let's go ahead and implement the
parse function.
We'll iterate through the
GeoJSON objects.
We saw in our JSON that the top
level is feature, so we will
treat this object as
MKGeoJSONFeature.
In a generic parser, we would
want to handle other geometry
objects as well.
We'll iterate through the
feature.geometry and we'll
filter this into native MapKit
types, which is MKMultiPolygon.
We will add this to an array of
overlays.
This is the array we will
leverage to add the overlays to
the map view.
So let's go to the event view
controller where the map view is
set up and add the overlays.
For every overlay that we add to
the map view, we need to provide
a renderer in the map view's
delegate method.
Let's go ahead and set up the
We are past the MKOverlay in the
delegate method and we are
expected to return our
MKOverlayRenderer.
So let's go ahead and set up the
renderer.
We saw that our geometry of our
tent is MultiPolygon.
So we'll treat this overlay as
MKMultiPolygon.
Here we specify the visual
representation of the polygon
overlay and we specify how we
want our tents to be rendered.
So now that we have the overlays
added and the visual
representation specified for the
same, let's go ahead and execute
our application.
Looking at the Concert in the
Park, and there you go.
We now see the tent outlines
rendered as overlays on the map
view.
It would be helpful to display
the tent labels so we know where
we can get the food and the
drinks from.
We'll be displaying these labels
as annotations on the map view.
So let's go back to the event
data source.
The way the map view handles
annotations is different than
overlays.
So we'll separate the
annotations from the overlays.
The names of the annotations is
parsed in feature.properties.
This is the data we will use to
configure the annotation.
So let's go ahead and implement
the configure function.
The properties of our points is
a dictionary mapping of string
to string.
We will use Swift's JSONDecoder
to decode this into a dictionary
of strings.
We'll add this configured data
to an array of annotations.
This is the array we will
leverage to add the annotations
to the map view.
So let's go to the event view
controller and add the
annotations to the map view.
Let's set up the view for the
annotation.
We will use the
MKMapViewDefaultAnnotation
ViewReuseIdentifier constant to
register our custom annotation.
Now that we have the model and
the view set up for our
annotations, let's execute our
application.
So we now see the tent labels
which are rendered as
annotations on the map view.
We just saw how to render
annotations and overlays from
GeoJSON data.
However, in our map view, we've
seen numerous points of interest
which are displayed which are
interfering with our map.
Let's leverage the
exclude all point of interest filter that
Alexander was talking about to
turn these off.
Now that we have the
pointOfInterestFilter applied,
let's execute our application.
And we just saw how easy it is
to enable users to focus on
information relevant to our use
case.
With that, I hand over back to
Alexander.
[ Applause ]
>> As you saw in this demo, the
new MKGeoJSONDecoder can make it
a lot easier for you when
working with GeoJSON.
So it was pretty straightforward
to get this event map rendered
in the map view.
But in some use cases like when
you're dealing with indoor data
for large venues, your data is
much more complex.
So, to standardize and simplify
work with this kind of complex
indoor data, we have developed
the indoor mapping data format,
IMDF.
The IMDF specification is built
on top of GeoJSON that we just
talked about and it provides a
comprehensive model for indoor
data that lets you deal with any
conforming JSON in a generalized
way.
And to learn more about how to
render rich indoor data in your
maps, I strongly recommend
watching this session, Adding
Indoor Maps to your App and
Website, which is tomorrow at 2
p.m. And that session will cover
the IMDF specification in much
more detail.
And that's all I'm going to talk
about the new GeoJSON support in
MapKit.
So the last big topic I want to
cover is a set of new APIs in
MapKit and MapKit JS that lets
you really take control over the
map view's camera.
And to show you this, we'll take
another look at the event view
in the companion app.
So this view is intended to show
this event map.
There's very little reason for
users to pan away to San
Francisco, for example.
So, to focus the map view on the
region that matters, you can add
a boundary that limits the area
where the user can pan.
So we introduced a new class
called Camera Boundary that
defines a region within which
the center point of your map
view always needs to remain.
There are two ways to create a
camera boundary, either using a
coordinate region or a MapRect.
Now once you've created your
camera boundary, you apply it to
the map view's new
cameraBoundary property.
But before you do, make sure
that your map view is centered
over a location inside that
camera boundary.
You know your apps better than
anyone else and if your map view
is located outside of the camera
boundary that you're applying,
the map view will update to a
location inside the boundary.
And in most cases this will not
be the location you would have
chosen for your users.
And once the cameraBoundary has
been applied, the map view will
strictly enforce it.
This means that if you call
setRegion for example with a
location that would force the
map view to move outside of the
camera boundary it will instead
move as close as it can but it
will not violate its camera
boundary.
And this is of course not just
true for setRegion but any API
that modifies the center point
of your map views.
And we've also added support for
camera boundaries in MapKit JS
and there's a slight difference
in how it works.
You use either a
CoordinateRegion or a MapRect as
your camera boundary.
So you simply apply either your
CoordinateRegion or your MapRect
to the new cameraBoundary
property on your map object.
So we now have a mechanism for
keeping our map views in the
region that matters.
But users can still zoom out to
the point where that region is
no longer visible.
And that's possible because the
camera boundary only ensures
that the center point of the map
is inside that region.
And we're still centered over
that park.
We're just really, really zoomed
out.
So we also need a way to limit
the zoom in the map views.
And the map view zoom is
controlled by its camera.
And if you use the MKMapCamera
in your apps in the past, you've
probably worked with the
altitude API.
However, if you work with pitch
cameras, it's much more
intuitive to think about the
distance from the center
coordinate of your map up to the
camera.
And this is also the distance
that controls the zoom in your
map views.
So for this reason we have
introduced a new property on
MKMapCamera called Center
Coordinate Distance.
And I would like to encourage
you to move away from thinking
about altitude and instead
thinking about the distance from
the center coordinate up to the
camera.
And when you make this
transition in your code, there's
one important thing to keep in
mind.
In an altitude centric model
like we've used in the past, a
change to the pitch of the
camera has meant that the camera
moves farther away from the
center point while preserving
its altitude.
But in a distance centric model,
when you change the pitch of
your camera, the expectation is
instead that the distance will
be preserved and as a result the
altitude will change.
MKMapCamera has now been updated
so the behavior of the pitch
property will change if you set
a Center Coordinate Distance.
So you now know that the Center
Coordinate Distance is what
controls the zoom of your map
view.
But how do you actually
constrain it?
For this purpose we've
introduced another new class
called CameraZoomRange.
And the CameraZoomRange defines
a minimum and a maximum Center
Coordinate Distance.
And when you apply the
CameraZoomRange to your map
view, the camera will be forced
to stay in that range.
So you simply create your
CameraZoomRange with a minimum
and a maximum distance and then
you apply it to the new
CameraZoomRange property on your
map view.
And if you want, you can also
create a CameraZoomRange with
only a minimum or only a maximum
distance.
As you've probably noticed in
the past, even without the
CameraZoomRange there are
restrictions on how far in and
out you can zoom in a map view.
And these restrictions may
change depending on what region
of the world you're viewing or
what map type you're using.
In some cases there are
technical limitations for these
restrictions but in some cases
there are legal reasons.
What this means is even if you
apply a CameraZoomRange with a
minimum distance that is shorter
than the default of the MapView,
your users will not be able to
zoom in any farther.
And similarly a larger max
distance will not allow your
users to zoom out any farther.
And if your camera is outside of
the CameraZoomRange you're
applying, the MapView will
update the Center Coordinate
Distance of your camera.
So just like with the
cameraBoundary, the map view
will strictly enforce the
CameraZoomRange once you're
adding it.
And we've also added support for
camera zoom ranges in MapKit JS.
So there's a new CameraZoomRange
object added to the MapKit
object.
And in the same way you can
create it with a minimum and a
maximum or just one of the two.
You then apply it to the new
CameraZoomRange property on your
map object.
All right, and I will now hand
it back one more time to my
colleague Nalini.
And this time she will show you
how to use these camera zoom
ranges and camera boundaries to
improve the experience in your
map views.
[ Applause ]
>> Here we are looking at the
concept map where we just
rendered annotations and
overlays.
I'm zooming out of the concept
area and users can zoom out to
San Jose and all of California.
We want to control the zoom
range of the map view.
Let's leverage the
CameraZoomRange API that
Alexander was talking about.
The min and the max are
specified in meters.
By applying a CameraZoomRange to
the map view, we restrict how
far in and out users can zoom in
the map view.
Let's execute our application
with the CameraZoomRange
applied.
I'm trying to zoom out again.
OK, I cannot zoom out.
Let's try to zoom in.
I'm zooming in.
I can get to the stage.
I can get to the different tents
in the concert area.
So this zoom range is perfect
for our use case.
However, as you can see, users
can pan away.
We want users to focus on the
concert area.
Let's leverage the
cameraBoundary API that
Alexander was talking about.
We set up our MKCoordinateRegion
with the eventCenter as its
center point and a span of
latitudinalMeters: 20 and
longitudinalMeters: 10.
We use this coordinateRegion to
apply the CameraBoundary.
By applying a CameraBoundary to
the map view, we ensure the
center point of the map view
lies within this region.
Let's execute our application
with the CameraBoundary applied.
I'm going to try to pan away.
As you can see I cannot pan
away.
Let's try zooming in.
I really want to get to that
fancy stage area.
Rumor has it Lady Gaga may be
performing but it seems I cannot
get to it.
Let's try with some updated
numbers.
Let's try with
latitudinalMeters: 100 and
longitudinalMeters: 80 and let's
execute our application with
these updated numbers.
OK, I'm going to zoom in again
and try to get to the stage
area.
And as you can see I can get to
the stage area, I can get to the
restrooms.
We just saw how to leverage the
cameraBoundary and the
CameraZoomRange APIs and ensure
that users can focus on
information relevant to our use
case.
With that, I hand it back to
Alexander.
[ Applause ]
>> So, once again, just a few
lines of code change and you get
a completely different map view
experience.
So, try this out in your apps.
And that was actually the last
thing we wanted to cover for the
map view in camera APIs.
But like I said before we have
covered quite a lot of stuff
today.
So before we wrap up I want to
summarize the key points we have
talked about today that I hope
you will bring with you from
this session.
So with the introduction of the
new snapshot service you can now
create snapshots and use them on
the web as well.
So if you don't need user
interaction in your maps don't
waste resources loading a full
blown map.
And every app is unique and
different data is relevant in
different context.
So tailor your map views to your
needs in your apps using the new
pointOfInterestFilters.
And make sure that your search
and autocompletion results are
as relevant as possible for your
users using the new
pointOfInterestFilters and the
result type filters.
And if you're adding a lot of
polygons and polylines in your
map views, group them using the
new multipolygons and
multipolylines.
And if you're working with
GeoJSON, take advantage of the
new support in MapKit and in
MapKit JS, that way you will
need to write less code and
maintain less code.
And if your map view is really
all about a fenced off area, try
out the new camera boundaries
and camera zoom ranges to really
focus your map views on the
region that matters.
And for more information and
sample code for both MapKits and
MapKit JS, visit this session's
web page.
And if you have any questions,
come by our lab tomorrow at 3
p.m. And with that, I will--
want to thank you for coming and
I hope you will have a very nice
evening and enjoy the last day
of Dub Dub tomorrow.
[ Applause ]