[ Music ]
>> Hi. My name is Jared McGann.
I'm an engineering manager in
watchOS.
In watchOS 5, Apple released the
new Infograph clock faces with
graphic complications.
In watchOS 6, we've enhanced
graphic complications with a new
tinted mode.
Any clock face with graphic
complications supports tinted
complications.
Here's some more examples from
our new watch faces in watchOS
6.
These graphic complications are
composed of three data types;
gauges, text, and images.
The system alters the appearance
of each into contexts.
Let's walk through each one.
In tinted context, gauges are
displayed as a solid color
rather than a color gradient.
The color of the gauge is
determined by the system, as
informed by the customer's color
selection.
If your complication relies on
color to communicate information
within the gauge, you may need
to reconsider how you display
that information in your
complication.
Text is also displayed with a
single color in tinted contexts.
Again, the color is determined
by the system, based on the
customer's color choice.
Multicolor text providers are
reduced to a single color, as
seen in the activity rings
complication.
Lastly, images are desaturated
by default in tinted contexts,
but we also have new API to
provide alternate images in this
mode.
Before we dive into the new API,
I'd like to take a step back and
talk about data providers
generally.
ClockKit includes a number of
data providers for
complications.
These providers manage the data
you supply to ClockKit for
display within a complication.
Let's take a look at the full
color image provider.
The image property specifies a
full-color image to be displayed
by a complication.
Then there's an accessibility
label property, which is a
succinct label that identifies
the purpose of the image.
So how do you provide an
alternate image for tinted
contexts?
In watchOS 6 there's a new
property in
CLKFullColorImageProvider called
tintedImageProvider.
It's an optional property where
you can provide a separate image
for tinted contexts if you don't
want the full color image to be
desaturated.
This property is of the type
CLKImageProvider.
We chose this class because it
allows you to provide both
one-piece and two-piece template
images for tinted contexts.
Let's take a closer look at
CLKImageProvider, which has been
around since watchOS 2.
The first thing to note is that
CLKFullColorImageProvider is not
derived from CLKImageProvider.
These are two distinct classes.
This class, CLKImageProvider,
manages template images for
display in a complication.
The clock face displaying the
complication determines how to
display the image and what tint
color to apply.
The first property is one-piece
image, which is a single
template image.
This is the only required
property.
Next up is tint color.
In some classic complication
contexts, this color is applied
to the template image within a
complication.
In graphic complications, tint
color is ignored because color
is determined by the system as
influenced by the customer's
color selection.
Then, there are two-piece
images, which are composed of
the two-piece image background
and two-piece image foreground
properties.
Classic complications use
two-piece images in multicolor
contexts, as seen here.
Graphic complications use
two-piece images in some tinted
contexts.
When applicable, two-piece
images take priority over
one-piece images.
A two-piece image consists of a
foreground image layered on top
of a background image.
Both images are template images.
In classic complications, the
color and the tint color
property is applied to the
background image and white to
the foreground image.
In tinted graphic complications,
as previously mentioned, tint
color is ignored.
The system will determine the
foreground and background colors
as informed by the customer's
color selection.
Let's walk through a few
scenarios for displaying images
within a tinted graphic
complication.
The first is for the full color
image to appear desaturated in
tinted contexts.
Here, we see the full color
image desaturated, more or less
gray scale on the right.
To achieve this in code, merely
initialize a
CLKFullColorImageProvider
without a tintedImageProvider,
as seen here.
When the tintedImageProvider
property is nil, the system
displays a desaturated version
of the full color image.
In other scenarios, you may want
to display an alternate template
image in tinted contexts.
Perhaps your full color image
doesn't desaturate well, or
maybe you're concerned about a
logo being displayed in
undesirable colors.
To do this in code, create a
CLKImageProvider with the
desired one-piece template
image.
Then supply that in the
CLKFullColorImageProvider
initializer alongside the full
color image.
In full color context, ClockKit
will utilize the full color
image.
In tinted contexts, the
one-piece image from the
CLKImageProvider will be
utilized.
It's worth noting that you can
also provide the same full color
image within the
tintedImageProvider, and that
image will be templatized
instead of desaturated.
We use this technique in many of
the standard watchOS
complications.
Lastly, you may want to provide
an alternate two-piece image in
tinted contexts.
To achieve this, create a
CLKImageProvider with both
one-piece and two-piece template
images.
Then supply this object in the
CLKFullColorImageProvider
initializer alongside the full
color image.
In tinted contexts, ClockKit
will determine if the one-piece
or two-piece image should be
utilized.
Here's a chart from the Human
Interface Guidelines with
various graphic complication
layouts.
And here you can see the same
layouts in a tinted environment.
Remember that ClockKit will
alter the appearance of
complications in tinted
contexts.
Tint color in tinted graphic
complications is determined by
the system, as informed by the
customer's color selection.
And lastly, we've supplied new
API that allows you to provide
alternate template images to be
displayed in tinted contexts.
If you're new to complications
or would like to learn more,
check out these videos on
developer.apple.com.