[ Music ]
>> Hi. I'm Neha Agrawal, and I'm
a software engineer working on
speech recognition.
In 2016, we introduced the
Speech Recognition framework for
developers to solve their speech
recognition needs.
For anyone who is new to this
framework, I highly recommend
watching this Speech Recognition
API session by my colleague
Henry Mason.
In this video, we're going to
discuss exciting new advances in
the APIs.
Let's get started.
Speech recognition is now
supported for macOS.
The support is available for
both AppKit and iPad apps on
Mac.
Just like iOS, over 50 languages
are supported.
You need approval from your
users to access the microphone
and record their speech, and
they also need to have Siri
enabled.
In addition to supporting speech
recognition on macOS, we are now
allowing developers to run
recognition on-device for
privacy sensitive applications.
With on-device support, your
user's data will not be sent to
Apple servers.
Your app no longer needs to rely
on a network connection, and
cellular data will not be
consumed.
However, there are tradeoffs to
consider.
Accuracy is good on-device, but
you may find it is better on
server due to a continuous
learning.
A server-based recognition
support has limits on number of
requests and audio duration.
With on-device recognition,
these limits do not apply.
The number of languages
supported on server are more
than on-device.
Also, if server isn't available,
our server mode automatically
falls back on on-device
recognition if it is supported.
All iPhones and iPads with Apple
A9 or later processors are
supported, and all Mac devices
are supported.
There are over 10 languages
supported for on-device
recognition.
Now, let's look at how to enable
on-device recognition in code.
To recognize pre-recorded audio,
we first create an
SFSpeechRecognizer object and
check for availability of speech
recognition on that object.
If speech recognition is
available, we can create a
recognition request with the
audio file URL and start
recognition.
Now, in order to use on-device
recognition, you need to first
check if on-device recognition
is supported and then set
requiresOnDeviceRecognition
property on the request object.
Now that we have looked at this
in code, let's talk about the
results you get.
Since iOS 10 in speech
recognition results, we have
provided transcriptions,
alternative interpretations,
confidence levels and timing
information.
We're making a few more
additions to the speech
recognition results.
Speaking rate measures how fast
a person speaks in words per
minute.
Average pause duration measures
the average length of pause
between words.
And voice analytics features
include various measures of
vocal characteristics.
Now, voice analytics gives
insight into four features.
Jitter measures how pitch varies
in audio.
With voice analytics, you can
now understand the amount of
jitter in speech expressed as a
percentage.
Shimmer measures how amplitude
varies in audio, and with voice
analytics, you can understand
shimmer in speech expressed in
decibels.
Let's listen to some audio
samples to understand what
speech with high jitter and
shimmer sounds like.
First, let's hear audio with
normal speech.
>> Apple.
>> Now, audio with perturbed
speech.
>> Apple.
>> Next feature is pitch.
Pitch measures the highness and
lowness of the tone.
Often, women and children have
higher pitch.
And voicing is used to identify
voiced regions in speech.
The voice analytics features are
specific to an individual, and
they can vary with time and
circumstances.
For example, if the person is
tired, these features will be
different than when they're not.
Also, depending on who the
person is talking to, these
features may vary.
These new results are part of
the SF transcription object and
will be available periodically.
We will have them at the end
when the isFinal flag is sent,
but we could also see them
before.
You can access speakingRate and
averagePauseDuration as shown.
To access voice analytics, you
would have to access the SF
transcription segment object,
and then you can access it as
shown here.
To summarize, we have made three
key advances.
You can now build apps on macOS
using speech recognition APIs.
Speech recognition can be run
on-device in a privacy-friendly
manner.
And you now have access to voice
analytics features for getting
insight into vocal
characteristics.
For more information, check out
the session's web page and
thanks for watching.