[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Good afternoon and welcome to
our session on Developing a
Great Profiling Experience.
I'm Daniel Delwood and I'll be
joined by Kasper Harasim
[phonetic].
And today we're here to talk
about making great Custom
Instruments packages.
Now as developers, we all strive
to create excellent,
maintainable, modular and
reusable code.
And we've all used frameworks
designed by others and created
code that we want others to be
able to use well.
And good API design and
documentation are critical to
the user's experience with your
framework.
But my hope is today that you
consider developing an
Instruments package as well.
To see why, take Metal as an
example.
API design is central and the
calls are organized around a set
of core concepts, devices,
command buffers, textures and
more.
But that's not the whole story.
An API surface expresses what's
possible, but documentation and
example code are how others
learn to compose these concepts
into a great app.
But that's not the whole story
either.
Both of the first two help
developers write code using your
classes or framework.
But what happens when something
goes wrong?
Well, custom Instruments are a
way for you as the author to
teach others how to debug,
optimize and really get the most
out of your APIs.
If you've used the Metal System
Trace template in Instruments,
then you've seen some of what's
possible.
Creating visual tools designed
specifically for the concepts
and APIs that you define.
An Instruments package is a way
for you to build transparency
that under the hood your
framework is tested,
understandable and
well-supported.
And investing that time to
create a custom instrument helps
create confidence and trust that
the code's doing exactly what
you expect.
Tools are also a great way to
develop a cost model to know
which calls are expensive and
which are inexpensive.
And when there's a performance
problem, they're the best way to
differentiate between a
framework bug or a bug in the
client code.
Most importantly though, an
instrument is an opportunity for
you to tell your story.
An Instruments package is your
chance to explain what's going
on to help visualize important
metrics and help users quickly
find problems when they arise.
So today, we're going to cover
how to build great
instrumentation from the inside
out, starting from the inside
out of developing great trace
points in your framework, and
then building on them with
schemas, modeling and structure
inside Instruments before
finally moving on to talking
about visualization and the
instrument's UI.
So with tracing, modeling and
visualization as our roadmap for
today, let's dive right in and
talk about OSSignpost.
Now OSSignpost is a low-cost
tracing primitive introduced in
2018.
And signposts come in two
different kinds: .events and
intervals.
Now they support recording any
kind of data through their
printf like formatString in
arguments.
And different from printf, all
signposts are named with a
static string.
Now in Swift, OSSignpost is just
one core API with three
different types: begin, end and
event.
And in C, their interface is
exposed through three helpful
macros.
Now it's important to note that
OSSignpost is built on OSLog
which means that much of the
tracing behavior and
configurability is determined by
the provided log handle.
Now log handles are effectively
named spaces for your tracing.
They allow you to specify
subsystem and category and
together with that static name
for each signpost, this provides
the logical structure and
hierarchy for your trace points.
Now custom Instruments are built
on OSSignpost for two main
reasons.
First, they're temporal.
All signposts, whether .events
or intervals, implicitly record
a high-accuracy timestamp.
It's also important to have
first class support for
overlapping intervals in our
highly-concurrent world.
And OSSignpost does this with
Signpost IDs.
These record enough context for
matching up the related events,
even when the begin or end event
happen on different threads or
different dispatch queues.
Now the second reason for
OSSignpost is that they're
low-cost.
The logging mechanism is
designed with efficiency in mind
and it records a minimal amount
of data whenever you admit an
OSSignpost.
Now there are optimizations
around static strings, so things
like your format string and your
signpost name are actually
emitted as just an offset into
your binary text segment.
Now in fact the overhead of
OSSignpost is low enough that in
most cases you can leave them in
production code.
So this is what makes them
useful for building tools that
debug optimized code in addition
to helping you solve problems at
your desk.
Now when Instruments record
signpost data, you'll get access
to all the explicitly specified
fields including that format
string and then the arguments
you provide.
But in Instruments you'll also
get access to all of the
implicitly specified fields.
Things like the timestamp or the
calling thread which comes in
really useful.
If you're using a log handle
that has backtraces enabled,
then the call stack will also be
recorded and made available to
you in Instruments.
So when adding tracing to your
code, it's important to note
that OSLog and OSSignpost
behaves in three different
modes.
By default, OSLog is -- each
OSLog handle has signposts
enabled.
And so they're still low-cost
and only logged to a ring
buffer.
Now when Instruments or another
client requests to display this
data immediately, the OSLog
system goes into a streaming
mode which is a bit higher-cost.
This year though there are two
new dynamic categories that are
only enabled when Instruments is
recording.
Now these dynamic categories are
configured to record stack
traces for the second one which
adds a little bit of additional
overhead.
So with this in mind, what is
the actual cost of OSSignpost?
Well, many factors impact the
real-world performance.
Things like device type,
hardware model, OS version,
system load, thermals and more.
So it's hard to give an exact
number.
But I'd like to give some order
of magnitude approximations on a
logarithmic scale, because I
think it's useful for
understanding the relative
costs.
If we look at Signposts in a
release build, all of them clock
in at under a microsecond.
The new off-by-default dynamic
categories are actually in the
low nanosecond range.
Now when Instruments is
recording in deferred or last
few second mode, these dynamic
categories turn on to match the
behavior of the on-by-default
categories.
And they are the same expense
except for that dynamic stacks
category which is a little bit
more expensive in the low
microsecond range due to the
recording a call stack.
Now when streaming mode is
required though, all of these
become significantly more
expensive, moving into the tens
of microseconds range.
So with this in mind, what can
you do to minimize the
OSSignpost overhead while
recording if you're concerned
about that runtime cost or they
start showing up in your
profiles?
Well, there's two easy things
you can do.
First of all, you can use
Instruments' deferred or last few
seconds mode instead of
immediate mode.
This keeps OSSignpost out of
that streaming mode and reduces
the overhead.
And it's easy to configure a
template to record in one of
these modes when you open it.
Also, if you use the new dynamic
tracing categories, that's a
great way to minimize overhead
while not recording.
Because the signposts will be
off by default.
They can only be enabled by
custom instruments, so this data
also won't crowd the tracks in
the built-in OSSignpost tool.
So as the author of a framework
or a subsystem, just how many
signposts is it reasonable to
emit while you're profiling?
Well, you can emit a lot.
But let's assume a very
conservative goal of staying
under 1% CPU of even a single
core while you're profiling.
And then let's assume that the
signposts have a rough cost,
about half a microsecond per
signpost enabled.
Well, that math works out to
20,000 signposts per second.
And even in a display-link
context on an iPad Pro running
at 120 frames per second, that's
still enough for 83 intervals
per frame.
Now again, the real-world
performance will change and
these are just estimates.
So it's important to remember
that signposts are a shared
resource.
The more you use, the more it
will impact the logging system.
That said, they're designed to
allow for this high-rate tracing
and it can come in really useful
sometimes.
Sometimes it's the key to
figuring out a pipeline install
or an ordering issue in your
code.
Keep in mind though that you may
want to separate signposts out
into different categories per
audience.
It's likely that your clients of
your framework will need less
detail than contributors of your
framework who might need tracing
of more implementation details.
And if you split your trace
points across multiple log
handles, this allows your tools
to only enable the necessary
subset.
Now as tracing is the basis for
instrumentation, I want to
quickly cover four best
practices.
First and most importantly,
always end any intervals you
begin.
It's critical for correctness
and permanently open intervals
can really slow down
Instruments' analysis as well.
In this example, we have
OSSignpost calls wrapping an
expensive and potentially
error-throwing piece of code.
The problem is that if an error
is thrown, then control flow
jumps to the catch scope and
skips our end signpost entirely.
Now Swift's defer statement is
really a great way to handle
this, making sure that
regardless of early returns or
errors being thrown, that
OSSignpost end call will still
be called when we exit the
current scope.
So second, for efficiency, avoid
logging identical data in both
the begin and end trace points
and log it in the first point
it's available.
This avoids that duplicate work
and it gives Instruments a value
as soon as possible.
In this example, we don't need
to repeat the request number or
raw size, and instead of using
the request number to match up
the intervals in case of
overlap, these points could
actually use and generate a
unique Signpost ID for this log
handle per interval pair.
So third, avoid doing
unnecessary work when signposts
aren't enabled.
If your log handle is configured
to use one of the dynamic
tracing categories, then the
signposts enabled property will
indicate whether or not
Instruments is recording at the
time, which means it's a great
way to put your expensive data
computation behind that
OSSignpost-enabled check.
Fourth, only trace data that you
actually need for your tools.
Think about your guard
statements and preconditions,
because sometimes you'll want to
trace these to include the short
intervals.
For example, if you've got a
method and you want to see the
difference between a cash hit
and a cash miss.
But other times these early
returns will be uninteresting.
And for these cases, consider
moving the signpost after the
preconditions to reduce the
amount of data you send to the
signpost system.
Now with all these tips, it's
important to remember that trace
points are really the basis for
all of the tools that you build
on top.
And most of the time they'll be
present in your production code.
So that's why it's important to
think about performance and
maintainability of your trace
points.
And since they're at the core,
changes to your signpost calls
might result in needing to
change the tools that you build
on top.
So to keep your trace points
stable, avoid tracing
implementation details and try
to add your OSSignpost calls
closer to the API layer when
possible.
Now moving your trace points
around your code base isn't a
problem.
Now you don't need to worry
about compiler optimizations
like inlining that might move
them for you.
The things that you need to make
sure don't change are the static
strings, specifically I mean the
subsystem, the category, the
signpost name or the format
string.
If you change any of these,
you'll need to remember to
update your Instruments package
as well.
So with that, let's move on to
talking about modeling and
adding structure to your data
within Instruments.
Instruments' architecture is
based on everything being stored
in tables.
And schemas define the
structures of those tables, all
of which are measured by
Instruments instant analysis
core.
For more in-depth intro to
Instruments architecture, I'd
recommend the Creating Custom
Instruments talk from 2018.
For now though, let's look at
where modeling fits into
creating a profiling experience.
On the left, we've covered
OSSignpost which is one of the
main data sources that
Instruments records from.
This data is filled in the
tables with the pre-defined
schema for use by your Custom
Instruments.
Modeling is that next phase in
the middle.
A modeler observes data from one
or more input tables, reasons
about it and then emits data to
one or more output tables of
your specification.
The modeler is where your
domain-specific logic resides,
and the schemas of the output
tables are yours to specify
which types and formatters to
apply to your data.
The final step on the right is
visualization which is described
in XML to the standard UI in
Instruments.
It's where you specify how to
graph and display the data in
your modeler's output tables.
Things like which columns to
plot and uses the value.
Or which columns to use for
labels in color.
Since all of the custom
instrument's visualization is
based on your schemas and your
modelers' output, it's important
to talk through that process of
checking that your OSSignpost
trace point are good, and then
how to get this data into your
custom-defined schema.
So all data in a custom
instrument must be stored in
tables that handle data in one
of two ways.
Point schemas have a timestamp
column, and interval schemas
have both a timestamp and a
duration column.
This means you'll need to define
at least one pointer interval
schema and then give names and
types to the rest of the
columns.
Now the data will be filled in
by modeling rules that operate
on the input data.
And these rules are expressed in
Eclipse language.
The good news is that
Instruments provides a few
schemas that will auto-generate
modelers.
So you don't have to jump into
writing Eclipse code until you
want to.
In fact, if you're just starting
and you want to make sure that
your data's correct, Instruments
provides a built-in OSSignpost
tool in the library that's great
for recording and checking that
your OSSignpost intervals look
reasonable.
And the inspector can help you
verify that the raw data is
exactly what you expect.
Now once you've checked your
data, a new instruments target
is a great way to start for
building your own tool.
With Xcode's built-in XML
snippets for custom instruments,
you're only a few elements away
from an automatic modeler and an
instrument in the library.
And the best way to see what
this looks like is with a demo.
And for that, I'd like to invite
up Kasper.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Daniel.
And hello, everyone.
Our Solar System application on
the Mac is dealing with a large
amount of data about planets,
images, videos and binary data.
In order to optimize this usage,
I built a framework called solar
compression that uses samples
compression library to
efficiently encode and decode
data from the disk.
Now I want to build
instrumentation for my framework
to provide insights to the
future users.
We have two concepts that are
worth tracking and presenting
visually.
Firstly, CompressionManager is
an object that coordinates
compression tasks.
It's created with a number of
channels which specifies how
many tasks can be executed
concurrently.
Secondly, I would like to
measure how well compression did
for specific file types and
algorithms by capturing
compression ratio.
By examining this, users can
decide whether it's worth it to
compress their data.
I wrote intervals that represent
this concept of my framework in
OSSignpost API, so let's jump to
the CompressionManager Swift
file to take a look.
Firstly, let's take a look at
the log handle.
My log handle specifies my
framework's bundle identifier as
a subsystem and my class name as
a category.
Compress and decompress are part
of the public interface of
compression manager.
They both start by creating
compression work item instance
which encapsulates information
about certain compression tasks.
Next, they call into private
SubmitWorkItemMethod.
Because compression channels can
be busy with work, there might
be significant time between
compression item creation and
execution on the channel.
And this is the perfect place to
start measuring this delay.
We'll do it by calling our
signpost of type begin with
CompressionItemWait name.
Next, we can see our guard
condition here which ensures
that source file exists before
we proceed any further.
Following Daniel's advice, I
will move it to the top of the
function to ensure that my
intervals are always closed.
Next, we have
ExecuteWorkItemMethod which is
called when the compression task
is ready to be executed on the
channel.
At first we need to indicate end
of the wait time for the item by
calling our signpost of type end
with the same name as before.
Next, we indicate beginning of
the compression with
CompressionExecution signpost.
In the metadata, we have such
things like algorithm, the kind
of operation, information about
the source, destination, channel
and calling thread.
As we learned before, OSSignpost
implicitly records several
parameters including thread so
you are safe to remove the
thread now.
Next, we create destination file
and synchronously execute
compression operation.
After it's finished, we log it
and attach destination file
size.
This is another place where I
can improve on my signpost
invocations.
You can notice that
StartCompressionMethod over here
is a throwing one.
And if it does throw an error,
the signpost invocation here
will not be called.
To prevent this from happening,
I can introduce the defer block
over here and move my code to be
sure that the intervals are
always closed.
Now let's see our signpost in
Instruments by using Xcode's
Profile action.
Let's start with a blank
template, add our signpost
instrument to it and record for
just a few seconds.
We can now examine the data.
I will expand our signpost
instrument to see all of the
recorded subsystems.
Here's our Solar Compression
one.
I can extend it further to see
my Compression Manager category.
Now I can resize this track to
fit all of the contained graphs
by using Control-Z.
Let's pinch to zoom to examine
the data in more detail.
On the top we have all of the
Compression Execution signposts.
And on the bottom we see all of
the intervals for the waiting
tasks.
And we can notice some patterns
over here.
For example, at most two tasks
are executing at once, so
probably application code is
using two compression channels.
Also we can see some spikes over
here that indicate that a lot of
tasks are waiting to be
compressed.
OSSignpost is a great tool for
analysis of your own signposts,
but usually doesn't provide
enough context for analyzing
them by your framework's
audience.
To improve on this, I built
Solar Compression instrument
that uses custom instruments.
But putting these two signposts
into two separate tables and
adjusting instrument-standard
UI, I managed to improve on our
visualization.
Let's open trace document
containing this instrument now.
On the bottom line we see all of
the waiting tasks which are
represented similarly to the
OSSignpost instrument.
On the top we see all of the
execution intervals now
separated by a channel so we can
indeed see that there are two
channels available.
On the bottom over here I see
all of the compression tasks
with information on the
interval, source path, file
sizes, compression ratio, et
cetera.
There's one task that brings my
attention.
It's pretty long and it's
colored in red, which means that
the compression for this ratio
for this task was slow.
To easily see what kind of task
it is, I can switch to active
tasks detail which is set up to
only show intervals that are
intersecting my inspection head.
I can move my inspection head
and analyze a task.
It seems that we are trying to
compress zip archive and the
file size decreased by a bit
over 1%.
That doesn't seem much and maybe
you shouldn't be compressing it
at all.
Next, let's see task summary
detail which aggregates all of
the compression tasks.
It provides three aggregation
levels: compression kind, source
extension and algorithm.
On the right we see different
statistical information such as
average compression ratio,
duration or total saved space.
This detail is very useful for
comparing between different
algorithms or looking at how
compression ratio changes along
with the file type.
For example, we can see that our
JPEG file size decreased by on
average by 34% which seems
pretty good for already
heavily-compressed file.
Now let's take a look at how it
all looks in the Instrument
Inspector.
We have OSSignpost table over
here which is a point schema.
It looks at all of our begin and
end events.
We also have two tables for our
signposts.
Here is our execution table.
It contains all of the data
about tasks that we logged, but
now it's formatted according to
the engineering types that we
assigned.
On the right over here we can
see that this table is directly
consumed by the UI.
I'm pretty happy about my
instruments so far.
One thing I would like to
improve on is how the waiting
tasks are represented.
Instead of seeing specific
intervals, I would like to have
some way of summarizing them to
clearly point out the areas of
higher load.
I think that Daniel might have
some ideas on how to achieve it.
Daniel?
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Kasper.
As Kasper showed, the OSSignpost
instrument in the library and
the Inspector are great ways to
visualize your raw data and to
check that instrument sees the
data you expect.
And even without diving into
writing a custom Eclipse
modeler, Kasper was able to
present an instrument that
presented his data in a more
meaningful way using his
framework's compression
concepts.
There were just four trace
points and two OSSignpost
interval schemas.
That said, it wasn't quite the
profiling experience he wanted
to create.
Now custom modelers are a great
way for tailoring that
experience.
They all you to fuse data for
multiple log handles and even
use data from built-in tables.
They enable you to embed more
complex logic, to maintain
state, and the reason about the
order of events.
Writing your own custom modeler
can also be useful for some of
the more custom graphing and
detailed use schemas.
The point schema, interval
schema and modeler tags are a
great way to get started, but
it's a deep subject we don't
have time to cover in this
session.
For more on custom modeling
though, the 2019 Modeling and
Custom Instruments talk goes
into a lot more depth and it
comes with sample code.
So let's move on to talking
about the UI part of a profiling
experience, visualization.
Visualization is all about the
chance for you as the author to
tell your story to the
developers who will use your
code.
And the most important principle
to remember is that data is not
the same thing as a story.
Just as Kasper showed by looking
at the built-in OSSignpost
graphs, raw intervals are only
good at conveying meaning to
their author.
Users of your tool aren't going
to intuitively know whether a
gap in the timeline is good or
bad or what processing phase was
supposed to come next but
didn't.
As the developer of an
instruments package, you get to
go beyond just building
visualization showing what
happened.
You get to teach and diagnose.
You get to help your users find
problems even when you're not
there.
And visualization isn't just
about the graph either.
Sometimes the best way to
communicate a problem is with a
right set of statistical data or
with a well-crafted textual
narrative of exactly what went
wrong.
The reason that graphing is so
important though is that most of
the time it's the user's
starting point.
It's the first page to your
story's book.
Visualization should help others
learn, understand and debug, and
the selfish motivation is that
good tools also speed up triage.
That's the goal of
visualization, making problems
apparent.
Graphs are the first summary
that you'll see and they should
draw your eyes to areas of
importance.
And once you've started digging
in, that's where detail views
and metrics should be centered
around those core concepts in
your code.
Now since Instruments deals with
two types of time-ordered data,
points and intervals, I want to
talk through ways of displaying
both.
To summarize .events, it helps
to evaluate their importance.
If they're all relatively equal,
then a histogram is a really
great way to show the density of
events on a timeline.
The taller bars immediately
convey at a quick glance where
to start and where to zoom in.
And for custom instruments, the
graphing behavior is easy to
customize.
The histogram element allows you
to specify the width of each
time bucket and there's a best
for resolution element that lets
you use a histogram when the
user zooms out and then swap for
a plot of the individual events
when the user zooms in.
Now, when .events vary in
importance, it's sometimes
helpful to dedicate a lane to
the critical events.
Multiple graphs and detail views
can reference data from the same
table, so specifying the top
plot just means describing to
Instruments how to slice and
choose which values to display
from the table.
Now both of these can be
accomplished purely in XML and
without a custom modeler.
Tabular summaries of either
point or interval data are your
opportunity to define what
metrics are important.
Within aggregation detail view,
there are functions like Min,
Max, Average and Standard
Deviation for combining values.
And new users will look to these
summaries that you provide for
guidance on what's important and
what to optimize.
So even display attributes like
what the title of the columns
are or what order they appear in
really matter.
Now when users dig further into
the details, the narrative
engineering type is a great way
to explain what's going on.
It allows you to use natural
language and other type
formatters to explain runtime
behavior in a way that's
approachable.
These views are a great way to
tell users what was expected to
happen and didn't, or when
something interesting happened
that they might want to
investigate further.
So plotting interval data can be
a bit trickier.
Unlike points, intervals won't
usually fit within a single
vertical space because of
overlap.
If you can plan for a fixed or
bounded number of overlapping
intervals, there are two ways to
split a lane into multiple
visual areas vertically.
Qualified plots are useful for
splitting lanes into multiple
spaces with a single title,
while instance plots are useful
for each getting their own
title.
Now the OSSignpost tool uses
both of these techniques
together, but it only works well
when there is a limited number
of overlapping intervals to
display.
When there are a lot,
hierarchies, new in Instruments
11, may be the way to go.
Separating trace data into
nested tracks makes it easier to
filter, to find and even pin
just what you're looking for,
especially when the number of
graphing contexts is large.
But whether or not you provide a
hierarchy of tracks, it's
important to plan for
summarizing your interval data
either at each level of your
hierarchy or as the primary
graph of your instrument.
For simple interval data, it
might be tempting to apply the
same solution as for points,
using a histogram element.
However, this only works well if
you have short intervals as the
histogram element aggregates by
start time.
With longer intervals, this can
cause a left-sided skew and it
produces very large values.
More importantly, when you graph
things that have duration, don't
graph time on the Y axis as it's
already the X axis.
Metrics like percent utilization
are better for displaying this
kind of data.
Now in more real-world usage,
intervals overlap a lot more,
and so I want to show three
examples of summary graphs and
how the represented concept in
your framework and usage
patterns that you want can
impact your table schemas and
held determine the presentation
style.
So for some scenarios,
persistent overlap indicates
high resource utilization.
And for this kind of data, a
quantized load average is a good
way to visualize it, even
coloring some extreme values.
Now Eclipse modelers and
Instruments are great at
maintaining state and fusing
data, so combining that
OSSignpost event stream with the
input from an internal timer
tag, a modeler can calculate and
emit a quantized utilization
average when a timer signal
arrives.
Now the output table of a
modeler might look like this,
expressing just four columns of
data to draw the plot that you
see, including a utilization
column for determining the
plot's value and a severity
column for determining color.
Now for other scenarios, lots of
quickly running intervals might
be more important because they
represent inefficient use of
your framework.
Looking at the same data as the
last example, a better graph
might be based on the modeler
counting the number of unique
intervals seen within a specific
time period.
Now the modeler's output table
would look very similar to the
last, but the user's eye is
immediately drawn to a very
different area of the timeline
which helps with zooming in and
investigating the cause of these
short intervals.
And both of the first two
examples summarize the data into
10-millisecond groups.
But what if the exact periods of
the overlap are important,
differentiating between one, two
or more concurrent intervals?
Well, instead of quantizing
based on time, a more helpful
graph might categorize these by
degree of overlap and show the
exact durations.
A modeler tracking just the
OSSignpost events could output
an additional table with a
custom interval schema.
And this time, the schema would
be filled in with a variable
duration and a description
column for use as a label.
So all three of these are just
examples but hopefully they help
to show that when it comes to
the presentation of your data,
the concepts matter when you're
designing a graphing schema.
Now for many cases an
automatically generated modeler
will give you the power and
flexibility you need to create
the right experience.
But there will definitely be
times when you want to have more
than one input or output.
And for those cases in some of
the example tables I've showed,
custom modelers can provide that
additional control and
flexibility to express their
concepts visually or textually,
enrich narratives and graphs and
details.
So now I'm excited to hand it
back to Kasper to see what
visualizations he's come up
with.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Daniel.
I played around with custom
modelers and managed to improve
on our existing instrumentation.
Let's take a look.
I will start with the Solar
Conversion template that I
crafted.
It now includes a file system
activity instrument to provide
some additional information
about I/O operations overhead
when using compression library.
Let's record.
Now I'm recording in the
windowed mode to reduce the
overhead of the recording.
Instrument is transferring all
the data from the host and
running the modelers.
Let's examine the data now.
I can immediately see that
there's some correlation between
file system activity and my
execution signpost over here.
Let's focus on the longer zip
compression task that we
analyzed before.
It was good to have it colored
on the red to get the user's
attention.
But even better it would be to
provide some additional
information by using narratives.
I wrote modeler to detect low
compression ratio situations and
present some possible solutions.
Let's take a look at the
suggestions detail to take a
look at the output of this
modeler.
This modeler -- and we get one
suggestion.
It's saying that file size for
archive zip deceased by a bit
over 1%.
And compression may not be
necessary for this file.
It's also hinting that if speed
is not an issue, I should try
using LZMA algorithm which may
provide higher compression
ratio.
That seems useful.
I can now try to change the
algorithm, record again and
reevaluate the results.
Let's take a look at how the
waiting tasks are summarized.
I'm calculating average load of
the waiting tasks.
This way users can clearly point
out the areas of higher load.
Let's take a look at this area
which is colored in red.
It seems that a lot of tasks are
waiting on average, but as they
get executed on the channels
here, the number is going down.
Users can analyze areas like
that and if necessary increase
the number of compression
channels to achieve higher level
of concurrency.
Actually, this conclusion would
be a good candidate for another
suggestion in our detail.
Now let's take a look at how it
all plays out in Instrument
Inspector.
Let's search for our Solar
Compression execution table and
take a look at the binding
solution.
OSSignpost point schema data is
transferred by OSSignpost
auto-generated modeler into our
Solar Compression execution
table.
It's right here as we saw before
consumed by the UI.
We also have this new entity
over here which is our
suggestions modeler.
It's transferring intervals from
the compression execution table
into the suggestions in the
point schema which is later
driving the narrative detail.
Now I'm happy about how this
Instruments conveys the concepts
of my library and I feel that we
are ready to ship it to our
users.
Let's go back to the slides.
[ Applause ]
Creating great profiling
experience is about giving your
users a path to explore.
They should start with a useful
template which is set up to
provide necessary instruments
for looking at the issue.
Remember that if your code is
sensitive to information that is
exposed by other instrumentation
such as sampling, system tracing
or priority activity, you should
include this in your template.
When analyzing the recording,
top-level graphs should quickly
draw user attention to where the
problems might be in the
execution timeline.
And details should lead them to
the main cause of the issue,
often providing meaningful
hints.
To help you develop even better
profiling experience, this year
we've introduced two new
features in Instruments, the
first of which is the concept of
hierarchical tracks.
One example is OSSignpost
instrument visible here which
exposes underlying subsystem and
category name space through the
hierarchy.
Hierarchies are part of custom
instruments and any hierarchy
that you saw today can be
created by your own instrument.
We also have a new way of
customizing your profiling
workflow through creating custom
track scopes.
These allow you to take a look
at data gathered in your trace
document from different
perspectives by applying track
filters or choosing different
track branches for each scope.
If I'm only interested in seeing
system calls and signposts for
compression library, or
analyzing virtual memory impact
of the application, I can create
scopes that filter out other
tracks and keep coming back to
them.
Like here I can save them in my
template to share with my team
or instrument audience.
Tools in the form of
instrumentation are a way to
take experience of interacting
with your framework from good to
great and from unknown to
trusted.
They are your opportunity to
tell stories about concepts
existing in your framework.
They should educate people and
help catch easy mistakes.
Whenever clients get performance
debugging issues, they should
turn to tools to see the answer.
And this interaction will
increase their confidence and
trust in your library.
To learn more about Custom
Instruments, please visit
Instruments Developer Help.
We also recommend looking at
these other sessions.
Thank you and have a great rest
of the conference.
[ Applause ]