[ Music ]
>> Hello, and welcome to our
session about Modernizing Your
Audio App.
My name is Peter Vasil, and I'm
a software engineer in the Core
Audio Team.
Let's start with audio units.
Support for
Carbon-Component-Based Audio
Units will be removed in a
future macOS release.
We encourage hosts to use the
AudioComponent API for audio
unit discovery.
With the next OS release,
AudioHardwarePlugIn-based
plugins are disabled by default.
We recommend using the
AudioServerPlugin API instead.
For now, disabled plugins can be
re-enabled in the Audio MIDI
Setup utility, but support will
be removed completely in a
future macOS release.
With the next OS release, we
will introduce some
deprecations.
AUGraph, Inter-App Audio, and
OpenAL will be deprecated.
We encourage developers to
switch over to AVAudioEngine, as
replacement for AUGraph and
OpenAL.
For Inter-App Audio, please use
Audio Unit Extensions instead.
The 3D Mixer parameters have
been unified across all
platforms.
For details, please refer to the
AudioUnitParameters header file
for a list of new and deprecated
parameters.
For more information, please
visit the developer website.
Thank you for your attention.