[ Music ]
>> Hello and welcome to our
session about modernizing your
audio app.
My name is Peter Vasil and I'm a
software engineer in the core
audio team.
Let's start with audio units.
Support for carbon
component-based audio units will
be removed in a future MacOS
release.
We encourage hosts to use the
AudioComponent API for audio
unit discovery.
With the next OS release,
AudioHardwarePlugin-based
plugins are disabled by default.
We recommend using the
AudioServerPlugin API instead.
For now, disabled plugins can be
reenabled in the audio MIDI
setup utility.
But support will be removed
completely in a future MacOS
release.
With the next OS release, we
will introduce some
deprecations.
AUGraph, Inter-App Audio and
OpenAL will be deprecated.
We encourage developers to
switch over to AVAudioEngine as
a replacement for AUGraph and
OpenAL.
For Inter-App Audio, please use
audio unit extensions instead.
The 3D mixer parameters have
been unified across all
platforms.
For details, please refer to the
AudioUnitParameters header file
for a list of new and deprecated
parameters.
For more information, please
visit the developer website.
Thank you for your attention.