[ Music ]
>> Hello, I'm Tim Hatcher an
engineer on the WebKit Team.
I'm going to talk about
Supporting Dark Mode in Web
Content.
When macOS Mojave introduced
Dark Mode, users and developers
naturally began to ask about web
content.
Over the decades web content has
traditionally been light in
color leading to a very bright
experience when mixed among
newly Dark Mode aware apps.
The WebKit team has been working
to standardize a way for
developers to style web content
for Dark Mode, which I'm happy
to announce is available in
Safari 12.1 on macOS Mojave and
with iOS 13's system wide dark
appearance, you will see the
same Dark Mode styling for web
content in Safari for iOS.
Throughout this video I'll be
using Safari in my examples, but
this support is not just
available in Safari.
It is also available in mail and
in your app when showing content
in web views.
There are three areas I want to
cover in this video.
One, general styling support for
Dark Mode on the web.
Two, some specific cases that
apply to email messages.
And, three, tools you can use to
debug web content in Dark Mode.
Let's get started.
I've been working on a new blog
to document some recent trips
I've taken around California.
While designing the site to be
responsive for mobile and
desktop visitors, this would be
a good time to add support for
Dark Mode.
Dark mode can be viewed as a
progression of responsive web
design, another way to adapt to
the circumstances of the device.
It is important to note that
Safari and WebKit will not auto
darken your content.
As the web developer, you are in
control of how your content will
appear to users using the dark
system appearance.
Let's take a look at how we can
transform this light page design
into a Dark Mode ready site.
The main way to signal that your
content supports Dark Mode is to
adopt the new color scheme style
property currently being
specified for inclusion in the
CSS standard.
Specifying the values light and
dark on the root element lets
the rendering engine known both
modes are supported by the
document.
This changes the default text
and background colors of the
page to match the current system
appearance, standard form
controls, scrollbars and other
named system colors also change
their look automatically.
Let's take a look at how adding
that property to my blog
affected things.
You can see the background color
changed from white to black and
most of my text completely
disappeared into the black
background; that was not what I
was expecting.
Let's take a look at some of the
style rules for this page to see
what is happening.
Here are the main style rules
for the affected areas of the
page.
For the text that disappeared
the black was being set as the
text color on the body.
I also have a dark gray text
color for the level 1 headings,
which doesn't have a high enough
contrast with the black
background.
By default, the text color of
the body will be black and light
mode.
Since that is what I wanted on
this page I can just delete the
color property override from my
style sheet.
Now that I'm using the color
scheme property, the default
text and background color will
both automatically change to the
Dark Mode values.
For the other colors in my style
sheet that I want to keep, I can
use something called CSS custom
properties otherwise known as
CSS variables to centrally
define them for use throughout
my site style sheets.
Using CSS variables makes it
very easy to later adapt the
style sheet for Dark Mode.
Let's see how that will work.
We simply take the color values
and move them to a central place
like the root element rule we
added for the color scheme
earlier.
For these colors we define a
variable name signified by a
double hyphen prefix.
Now we can return to the
original style rules where I am
still using the static color
values and change them to use
the variables we defined
referencing them by name using
the VAR function which looks
like this.
This style sheet is now ready to
support a dark color scheme.
Like responsive design
breakpoints for different device
widths, we can use a media query
to conditionalize for Dark Mode.
Specifically, if the user
currently prefers a dark color
scheme.
We can override the same CSS
variables we defined earlier for
light mode with Dark Mode
appropriate color values.
Now let's take a look at what
the page looks like with these
changes applied.
We go from this where we only
added the color scheme property
to this where the text and
header colors properly adapt to
the dark appearance, but what
about images?
Like the hero picture here of
the Mojave Desert.
The Mojave Desert image is
included by an image element
that is sourcing a JPEG on my
server.
We can easily adapt this code
using another responsive design
technique.
Specifically, the picture
element, which is a great way to
source multiple versions of an
image based on various device
characteristics using the same
media queries.
Here I specify an alternate
image of the Mojave Desert at
night using the same media query
that was used earlier for the
Dark Mode colors I can
conditionally load a night image
for users that prefer a dark
color scheme.
So we go from this where I was
using one image for both color
schemes to this where the desert
image is adapted to the dark
appearance and now the site is
ready for both dark and light
appearances.
To recap you want to use the new
color scheme property to declare
support for light and Dark
Modes.
This informs the rendering
engine what color schemes your
content was designed for so it
can adapt the default colors and
controls to match.
When the default colors are not
enough, use the
prefers-color-scheme media query
for custom values.
You can use the same media query
along with other responsive
images in the picture element
for Dark Mode ready sources and
consider using CSS variables
when adopting color schemes.
It will be easier to maintain
both appearance modes across
your content.
That brings us to Dark Mode and
email messages.
Just like mail in macOS Mohave
simple email messages composed
directly in mail on iOS 13 are
ready to go in both light and
dark appearances even if they
include in-line image
attachments like you see here.
This is the case because of
mail's auto darkening
transformations that get applied
to these simple email messages.
However, if you are an email
template designer creating
designs for a campaign that
includes remotely loaded images,
you will need to adopt the same
styling techniques I covered
earlier for web content.
Without adopting the color
scheme property mail will
display your email message in
the light appearance and will
not employ any auto darkening
transformations that simple
email messages receive.
Here is the same email message
with Dark Mode styling including
the color scheme declaration.
It is now perfectly adapted to
the dark system appearance.
To recap simple email messages
will auto darken even if they
include in-line image
attachments and rich email
messages with remote images like
custom email marketing campaigns
will use the light color scheme
by default.
You can declare support for the
dark color scheme in your
marketing email messages and use
the media query for custom color
and image customizations.
Now let's talk about tools to
debug Dark Mode content
specifically Web Inspector.
In macOS, we added the dark
appearance to Web Inspector when
your system is in Dark Mode.
This was a very popular request
from web developers, and I'm
very happy we have it now.
Not only did we add the dark
appearance there are a couple
tools to help you debug your own
content in Dark Mode.
The first is a new color scheme
toggle in the elements tab that
will change the page appearance
without requiring you to toggle
the entire system appearance
every time.
So if you like using Dark Mode,
you can quickly test how your
pages will look in the light
appearance with this button.
Like before the style sidebar
shows any rules that match for
the selected element including
any media queries.
In this case, you can see the
prefers color scheme media query
definitions of color variables
on the WebKit.org site.
And that is Dark Mode and Web
Inspector.
Check out some of the other
Safari and WebKit sessions for
details about other great new
features in Web Inspector for
Safari 13.
In summary, remember that web
pages and rich email messages
need to opt into Dark Mode.
Safari and WebKit will not auto
darken your content.
For simple email messages you
don't have to worry.
Mail darkens them to match the
system appearance automatically
and now you can use Web
Inspector to test your content
in light and Dark Modes with the
new color scheme toggle in the
elements tab.
I look forward to seeing what
you will do with this support
and how your sites and apps will
look in Dark Mode on Mac and
iOS.