[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Good morning and welcome
everyone.
I am Guillem Vinals Gangolells
from the Metal Ecosystem Team.
This past year, we have been
working with many game
developers and identified some
common issues.
As a result, we decided to put
this talk together.
Today, I will be presenting a
total of 18 best practices to
help you improve your Metal app.
Notice that I will not present
OK practices or acceptable
practices, and most definitely
not practices that will just do
the trick.
The focus today will be on Metal
Best Practices.
So, please follow them.
Before we get started, I would
like to thank our friends at
Digital Legends, our very
talented team from Barcelona.
They are the developers of
Afterpulse.
Afterpulse is an awesome great
looking game.
It uses many rendering
techniques such as cascaded
shadow maps, a fully-featured
deferred render as well as
post-process such as bloom and
FXAA.
We will use Afterpulse
throughout this presentation to
demo our tools and highlight
some of our best practices.
We have split the talk into
three sections, general
performance, memory bandwidth,
and memory footprint.
So, let's get started with some
general performance advice.
In this section, I will talk
about choosing the right
resolution, avoiding overdraw,
reduce the amount of fragment
shader invocations per pixel
written.
We'll also talk about GPU
submissions, resource streaming,
and also a bit about thermals.
So, let's get started with the
first best practice.
Choose the right resolution.
Notice that each effect in your
game may require a different
resolution.
So, it is very important that
you consider the image quality
and performance trade-off of
each resolution and choose them
carefully.
Also, composite the game UI at
native resolution or close to
native, so the UI will look
crisp no matter the display
size.
We can check the resolutions
with the Metal Frame Debugger.
Within the metal frame debugger,
we will want to use the
Dependency Viewer, which will
show a graph of every render
pass.
In this case, we are using a
Metal example application.
To access the Dependency Viewer,
we will select the command
buffer.
And, in this case, you can see
that this example Metal
application is using several
effects within different
resolution each.
For example, Shadow Maps and
SSAO have a different resolution
than the main lighting pass.
Also, the UI is composed of
native resolution, so it will
always look sharp.
These resolutions look great and
perform well for this Metal
application.
We're asking for you to do a
similar choice for your game.
So, let's move on to best
practice number 2.
Minimize non-opaque overdraw.
Overdraw is the amount of
fragment shader's process for
each pixel written.
iOS GPUs are excellent at
reducing opaque overdraw.
We just need to help a bit.
So, the best practice here is to
render opaque meshes first and
translucent meshes later.
Also, do not render fully
transparent or invisible meshes.
We will, once again, use the
Metal Frame Debugger to help us.
This time, we will look at the
GPU Counters gauge to verify the
overdraw for a given render
pass.
We will want to focus on the
main lighting pass of our Metal
Demo application.
In order to calculate overdraw,
we will look at the number of
fragment shader invocations
divided by the amount of pixel
store.
We can use the filter bar at the
bottom to quickly look for
performance counters where
after.
In this case, it's a fully
opaque scene.
So, there's nothing else to
verify.
There's no overdraw and we are
good to go.
We're asking for you to do
something similar with your game
and verify that you're also good
to go.
So, let's move on to the next
best practice.
Submit GPU work early.
Scheduling all the off-screen
GPU work early is very
important.
It will improve the latency and
responsiveness of your game and
it will also allow the system to
adapt to the workload much
better.
So, it is important that you
have multiple GPU submissions in
your frame.
In particular, you will want an
early GPU submission before
waiting for the drawables and
some would stall the render set.
And after you get the drawable
which will be as late as
possible in the frame, you will
then have a late GPU submission
where you will schedule all the
on-screen work, potentially, the
UI Composition Pass.
Since, it's a bit tricky to
explain, we have demo prepared.
So, let's do a quick demo and
I'll show you how to identify
this with Metal System Trace.
Cool. What we see here is a
capture of Afterpulse which we
took last year with an older
build of the game.
This was taken with a game
performance template.
We introduced this template last
year.
So, you're already familiar with
some of the instruments here.
New this year, we have added the
Thermal State as well as the
Metal Resource Allocations.
We'll talk about this later.
For now, what we want to focus
on, our potential stutters or
issues.
In this case, we want to look at
the Display panel and see that
there's lots of events at the
bottom with-- where surfaces
have been on-screen for longer
than expected.
So, maybe that's a problem and
we should look at it.
What we will do is zoom in to
one of these regions holding the
Option key and dragging the--
our cursor over it.
So, in this case, we can see
that there's two frames that
seem to be later than we would
expect, at the same time, that
the GPU is idle for a long time.
So, that potentially is the
cause of the issue we are trying
to debug here.
So, let's look into more detail.
We'll do that by disclosing all
the tracks in Metal System Trace
which you're already familiar
with.
So, what we are seeing here are
how our application is encoding
work and also how our GPU is
processing this work.
So, let's focus on this orange
frame.
As you can see here, there's a
lot of work being encoded by the
apps, so we have the Shadow
Maps, the Deferred Pass as well
as part of the bloom chain, et
cetera.
So, the GPU is not actually
processing that work, at the
same time that the threat is
waiting for the drawable.
So that's what this causing this
idle gap, but we already have
some work encoded.
We just didn't submit it.
So, that's what the best
practice was about you
submitting all the off-screen
work which you can encode ahead
of time before waiting for the
drawable.
So, the solution would be to do
one GPU submission here.
Notice that there's only one GPU
submission which we can see here
towards the end of the frame.
So, all the GPU work just
happens at the end.
Unfortunately, this is very easy
to simple-- very easy to fix.
And, in fact, Digital Legends
has already fixed it.
So, let's look at the new trace
of Afterpulse and see how it
looks like.
OK. So, let's zoom in.
In this case, we can see that
there's no idle time while we
are waiting for the drawable.
So, let's disclose the Metal
System Trace tracks as we did
before.
And, in this case, we can see
that the GPU is processing the
work that we have already
scheduled before getting the
drawable.
So, in this case, the idle time
is much smaller.
So, this allows the system to
adapt to the workload much
better and there's no problems.
So, after this, we know we are
good to go and we are-- we
already have multiple GPU
submissions which do not cause
any stall because we do them
before waiting for the drawable.
So, let's go back to the slides.
OK. So, the fix for that is
actually quite simple much
easier than explaining the
problem in the first place.
What we will want to do is
simply create multiple command
buffers per frame.
So, we'll want to first create
the command buffer to encode all
the off-screen work which will
be our early GPU submission.
We will commit the command
buffer and then wait for the
next drawable, which will stall
our thread.
After we have the drawable, we
will create one final command
buffer where we will encode all
the on-screen work and present
the drawable.
This will be our final CPU-- GPU
submission.
And this will also ensure that
the frame pacing is actually
good enough as well.
It's as simple as that.
Just use multiple command
buffers.
So, let's move on to the best
practice number 4, stream
resources efficiently.
Allocating resources does take
time.
And streaming resources from the
render thread may cause stalls.
So, the best practice here is
for you to consider the memory
and performance trade-off of
your resource streaming
algorithm and make sure that you
allocate and load GPU resources
at launch time since you will
not need to allocate them at
runtime.
And any resource that you need
to stream at runtime, make sure
you do so from a dedicated
thread.
It is very important that you do
so in order to avoid stalls.
We will revisit resource
streaming later on in the memory
footprint section and reevaluate
the memory and performance
trade-off.
For now, let's just use Metal
System Trace to tune our
resource streaming.
New this year, we're having an
Allocations Track which will
show you an event for each
resource allocation and the
allocation in the same timeline
as all the other instruments.
This will allow you to identify
all those resources which you
are streaming from the main
render thread which could
potentially cause a stall.
Something else you should tune
as well is for thermals.
It is important that you design
your game for sustained
performance.
This will improve the overall
thermals of the system as well
as the stability and
responsiveness of your game.
So, the best practice will be
for you to test your game under
serious thermal state.
Also, consider tuning your game
for this serious thermal state
since that will hopefully help
you to know the thermal
throttle.
So, new this year, we're adding
Device Conditions into Xcode,
which will allow you to set the
serious thermal state directly
from the device's window.
There is a talk at the bottom
where this topic we'll be
covering to more detail and I
encourage you to watch.
Also, we can use the Xcode
Energy Gauge to verify the
thermal state that the device is
running at.
In this example, we are
conditioning our device to run
at serious thermal state and we
are effectively verifying that
the device get into serious
thermal state.
It just takes a couple of
seconds to ramp-up to that.
Cool. So, now let's move on to
the second part of our talk.
In this section, we'll talk
about memory bandwidth.
Memory bandwidth is very
important.
That is because memory transfers
are costly.
They consume power and generate
heat.
To help mitigate in that, iOS
devices have shared system
memory between the CPU and the
GPU as well as dedicated Tile
Memory for the GPU.
Metal is designed to help you
leverage both.
So, now, let's see how by start
looking into textures.
Texture sampling is probably the
main bandwidth consumer in your
game.
So, we have some best practices
for you to configure your
textures correctly.
In this section, we will talk
about offline texture
compression for game assets, GPU
texture compression as well as
how to choose the correct pixel
format.
So, let's start with texture
assets.
It is very important for you to
compress your texture assets.
That is because sampling large
textures may be inefficient and
your assets may also be
arbitrarily large.
So make sure they are all
compressed and also generate
midmaps for all the textures
which may be minified.
So, let's see the memory savings
of texture compression.
This is one of the largest
textures of Afterpulse.
If this texture were to be
uncompressed, it would take
about 16 megabytes of memory to
load.
By using texture compression, we
can lower let-- this to less
than 3 megabytes including the
full mipmap chain.
Those are great memory savings.
Notice though, that Afterpulse
is using PVRTC because it runs
on A7 devices such as the iPhone
5S.
If your game targets newer
devices, using STC instead since
it offers better compression
ratio in image quality.
To verify that our assets our
compressed correctly, we can use
the Memory Viewer.
The Metal Memory Viewer is a
great tool which I will fully
introduce in the memory
footprint section.
For now, will you-- we will use
it to inspect all of our assets.
We can double check they are
compressed, mipmapped, and also
look great.
But what happens with all those
textures which you cannot
compress ahead of time such as
render targets or all the
textures generated at runtime?
The latest iOS GPU support
lossless texture compression,
which allows the GPU to compress
textures for faster access.
So, the next best practice is
for you to optimize your
textures so the GPU can have
faster access.
It is very important that you
configure your textures
correctly.
You will want to use private
storage mode, so only the GPU
has access to the texture data
and it allows it to optimize the
contents.
Also, do not set the unknown
usage flag and avoid setting
unnecessary usage flag such as
shaderWrite or pixelView, since
those may disable this
compression.
Shared textures which can be
acces by the CPU and the GPU
should explicitly be optimized
after any CPU update on their
data.
It is also important for you to
do so.
So, let's see how can we do both
things with a little bit of
code.
And it really is just a little
bit of code.
To create an optimal texture, we
will want to set the storage
mode as private.
So, only the GPU has access to
it.
And also, we will want to set
explicit yet conservative usage
flags.
In this case, we want to use the
texture as an intermediate
render targets so we do not need
any other usage flag.
But what about shared textures?
Well, those are a bit trickier.
So, shared textures can be
accessed by both the CPU and the
GPU.
So, if the CPU updates a region
of the texture or any of the
texture data, we may need to
explicitly ask the GPU to
optimize its contents.
Notice that there is a trade-off
here between how many times does
the CPU update the data and how
many times does the GPU need to
access it afterwards.
So the Memory Viewer will
actually be a great tool again
to help us with this.
That is because we can configure
the Memory Viewer to show both
the Storage Mode and Usage flag
for all of our textures.
From this single screen we can
see our compressed textures and
identify all of those which
could be configured correctly.
It is a great tool.
At this point we are almost done
configuring our textures.
We just need to choose the right
pixel format.
Larger pixel format will use
more bandwidth, so the best
practice will be for you to
avoid using pixel formats with
unnecessary channels and also
try to lower precision whenever
possible.
Notice though that the sampling
rate itself will also depend on
the pixel format.
In this case, we can see how the
pixel format has a direct impact
on the texture sampling rate of
our GPUs.
Particularly, you will want to
watch out for 128-bit formats
such as RGBA 32-bit float, since
those are sampled at quarter
rate.
Oftentimes these high precision
formats are used for noise
textures or lookup tables for
the post-process effects.
Once again we can use the Memory
Viewer to help us with that.
The Memory Viewer will let us
filter textures by name or pixel
format.
So, we will verify that our
Metal Demo is using 16-bit
formats for the SSAO
implementation.
This is very important for the
noise textures.
Notice something else though,
and this that in this example
most of the textures are
actually render targets.
So as games become more complex,
the texture used as render
targets may actually consume a
lot of bandwidth as well, so
let's have a closer look.
In this section, we will review
render pass load and store
actions, paying close attention
to MSAA and also talk a bit
about Tile Memory.
So let's get started with
optimizing load and store
actions.
You should avoid loading or
storing render targets
unnecessary.
Render target load and store
actions are very easy to
overlook and may actually quite
quickly become a problem.
So please make sure to keep
those in check.
And it is actually quite easy to
do so, with again just a little
tiny bit of code.
In this case, we are configuring
a render pass descriptor and we
want the color attachment 1 to
be transient, which means we
don't want to load or store
anything from it.
It is a simple as setting the
correct load and store actions.
We want the load action to be
clear, so no later gets transfer
to the on chip GPU.
And we want to store action to
be, DontCare.
So no data needs to be written
at the end of the render pass.
That's all there is to it,
verifying that we have done the
right thing is also very simple,
we can use the Dependency
Viewer.
In this case, our Metal example
is storing the color attachment
1, even though it's not used
later on.
The Dependency Viewer will show
an issue icon to highlight this
problem.
We should simply set the
DontCare store action as we have
just seen in the previous slide
and the problem will go away.
It is really as simple as that.
This is particularly important
for multi-sampled render
targets.
iOS devices have very fast MSAA,
that is because the result
happens from Tile Memory, so it
does not consume any extra
bandwidth.
This also allows us to declare
the multisampled textures fully
transient.
In fact, we don't even need a
system memory allocation to back
it in the first place.
So the best practice will be for
you to consider MSAA over native
resolution, since it's very
efficient, and also make sure to
not load or store the
multisample texture.
And since you're at it set the
storage mode of the multisample
texture to memoryless.
I will fully introduce
memoryless later on the talk.
For now, let's see how can we
configure a multisample texture
and the render pass that uses
it.
In this case, we just need to
set the memoryless storage mode,
and also make sure that the
render pass is using it, clears
its contents and discards the
samples.
We only want the multisample
texture to resolve from.
We do not need to store it.
We do not want that intermediate
data to be stored.
Only the final resolve texture
should be stored.
We can once more use the
Dependency Viewer to help us
verify that we are doing the
right thing.
In this case, our Metal example
is loading and starting the
multisample texture which is
very costly.
After setting the correct flag
just as I've shown you, we will
save our 85 memory, sorry, 85
megabytes of memory bandwidth
and also footprint.
And this is very important for
you to verify the multisample
attachments.
But notice that those savings
are only possible because we are
implicitly leveraging Tile
Memory by using MSAA.
So the next best practice is for
you to explicitly leverage Tile
Memory.
Metal provides access to Tile
Memory for several features such
as programmable blending, image
block, and tile shaders.
The best practice is for you to
explicitly utilize it,
particularly to implement more
advanced rendering techniques.
The Modern Rendering with Metal
talk will cover-- has covered
some of these techniques in
detail.
For now we will just have a
quick look at deferred shading.
Deferred shading is considered
to be very bandwidth heavy that
is because traditionally it
requires the application to
store the geometry information
or G-Buffer as a set of textures
representing several pixel
properties.
Those textures are then sampled
in the second lighting pass,
where the final color is
accumulated in a render target.
Notice that we are storing and
then loading all this data from
the G-Buffer, so that's why it's
bandwidth heavy.
iOS allows you to be much more
efficient than that.
On iOS, we can leverage
programmable blending, a feature
that allows fragment shaders to
access pixel data directly from
Tile Memory.
This means that the G-buffer
data can be stored on Tile
Memory and access within the
same render pass by all the
light accumulation shaders.
It is a very powerful feature
which Digital Legends has been
utilizing for years.
This is how the single pass
deferred render of Afterpulse
looks like through the
Dependency Viewer, it's
beautiful.
The four G-Buffer attachments
are fully transient, and only
the final color and depth are
stored, so it's not only
beautiful it's also efficient.
So, now, please let's welcome
Samuel on stage for the demo of
the Dependency Viewer.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks Guillem.
So, we've just captured an old
version of Afterpulse and want
to see if there are any
optimizations that we can make
to improve its performance.
I'm now going to use the
Dependency Viewer in the Metal
Frame Debugger to show some of
the issues that Guillem just
mentioned.
So to begin, let's click on the
CommandBuffer to open the
Dependency Viewer.
The Dependency Viewer shows us
all of the GPU passes encoded by
an app.
We can see that Afterpulse has
one CommandBuffer and begins its
frame by rendering a Shadow Map.
Followed by Deferred Phase, this
feeds into Luminance
Calculations, Particle
Simulations, and a Bloom Chain
which is used by the final
screen pass.
Now, the Dependency Viewer is
much more compact this year if
you have groups, and it's really
easy to see at a high level, how
the frame is rendered.
We can even go deeper into any
group if we want more detail.
So, in reality this Bloom Chain
is actually 12 passes.
Now, the Dependency Viewer is a
great place to find some of the
issues that Guillem mentioned.
And we can see a few on this
final screen pass.
So let's click on the issue icon
to find out more.
So, it looks like one of the
load store action issues that
Guillem mentioned earlier.
So they've set the store action
to store, but they're not using
this texture again in this
frame.
So the issue recommends we
should instead set it to
DontCare and we'll get back
almost 14 megabytes of memory
bandwidth for these two textures
combined.
So this year we've made it even
easier to find all of the issues
in the graph, simply click on
the new issues button on the
bottom right to see a list of
issues.
Now, another best practice that
Guillem mentioned was choosing
the correct pixel format.
So this year on iOS we've
introduced the new Depth 16
Format, so let's use the new
search to look for Depth 32
textures.
So it looks like they're using
36 megabytes of memory for the
Shadow Map texture.
So when the team at Digital
Legends gets back to Barcelona
after Dub-Dub, they can
investigate using this new
format and potentially save half
the memory if their shadow
requirements allow for it.
If we continue searching through
the graph, where you can see
that there's plenty of potential
memory savings.
So if you use the Dependency
Viewer in the Metal Frame
Debugger to find and diagnose a
few issues in the old version of
Afterpulse.
So, Digital Legends have
actually made some of these
improvements.
So let's take a quick look.
We can immediately see that they
are now using multiple command
buffers.
So this will fix the issue that
Guillem showed us earlier where
the CPU was blocked waiting for
the next drawable and the GPU
was idle.
If we zoom in to the final
screen pass, we can see that
they've fixed the store action
issue.
In fact, because these two
textures are fully transient and
they've set the storage mode to
memoryless, they're not using
any system memory at all.
So, Dependency really is a great
place to start debugging your
render pipeline.
Back to Guillem who will talk
about some amazing best
practices in optimizing your
apps memory footprint.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you Sam that was an
awesome demo.
I hope you guys will also use
the Dependency Viewer.
Cool. So, let's move on to the
last part of the talk, memory
footprint.
Memory footprint is actually
very important for your game.
That is because iOS enforces a
strict application memory limit
in order to keep both the system
on your application responsive.
As some of you may have noticed
iOS 12 introduce some changes in
the way memory is accounted.
This accounting change affects
mostly Metal resources.
Metal resources such as buffers
or textures may be the bulk of
your application's memory
footprint.
So, it is important for you to
measure the memory footprint of
your game.
You will want to do, so using
the Xcode Memory Gauge.
The Xcode Memory Gauge will
report the existing number that
the system also uses to measure
your game's memory footprint.
It is very important that you
use it to verify where your
games at.
Now, new this year it will also
display the application memory
limit as your game gets closer
to it.
But what if we want to focus
specifically on the memory used
by our Metal resources?
New this year, we are
introducing the Memory Viewer.
We have added it into the Metal
Frame Debugger.
The Memory Viewer itself has two
parts, first, a bar chart at the
top which shows resources, group
by categories such as type,
storage mode, and usage.
We can also use this bar chart
to quickly navigate through the
largest resources which are then
highlighted and the time they
were shown.
Second, there is a table at the
bottom which will show the
resources that we have filtered.
It includes several properties
specific to resource type such
as pixel format and resolution
for textures.
There is also filter bar at the
bottom to help you narrow down
your investigation even further.
It is a very powerful tool and
we hope that you will utilize it
to understand the memory
footprint of all your GPU
resources.
Also another great tool that we
are introducing this year is the
Metal Resource Allocation
Instrument.
It has three different
components, a Metal Resources
Allocations track which will
show the current Metal memory
footprint of your game, an
allocations track which will
show an event for each resource
allocation and deallocation as
well as some information.
And also a detailed table view
which will show you more
information about all the
allocations captured.
Both these tools are very
powerful and will give you great
overview of the memory footprint
in your game and how-- well,
also how it changes over time.
But some of you have also been
asking for other features, in
particular, one of them you have
been asking for a long time.
And I'm very happy to tell you
that new this year, we have a
C-based API to query available
memory at runtime.
This will enable your game to
stream resources more
effectively and also avoid
memory spikes which may cause
the game to go over the
application limit.
Another cool API that we're
introducing this year is the
on-device GPU capture, which
will allow you to
programmatically trigger a GPU
capture for which Xcode is not
required.
So we think it will be ideal for
game testers in the QA process.
To enable it you will just need
to add MetalCaptureEnabled into
the info.plist.
It's very simple.
So, now, let's see how we can
combine both APIs into some
short piece of code.
In this case, we will want to
check if the application is
close to the memory limit, maybe
because of a memory spike and
capture a GPU trace of our game,
so we can use the Memory Viewer
to fully debug it.
So let's go for it.
First, we'll check if the
application is getting close to
the limit.
And if it is we will then want
to capture the next frame, which
we will just render normally as
we would do so otherwise.
By the end of the frame, if we
captured it, we will then stop
the capture and handle the GPU
trace, it's up to you how you
handle the GPU trace.
Potentially you may also want to
either exit the game or disable
the GPU captures for this
session, since you may not want
to capture every single frame at
that point.
So this will give you a great
way to use both APIs and to, you
know, like further drill down on
memory footprint.
Which is great, so let's do
exactly that.
Let's look into how can we
reduce memory footprint.
For that we also have a bunch of
best practices.
In this section, we will talk
about memoryless render targets,
resource streaming, a bit more
about game assets and also
memory-intensive effects.
So, let's get started with
memoryless render targets.
This is kind of where we left it
in the memory bandwidth section.
Notice the transient render
targets are not loaded or stored
on system memory.
So they actually do not need a
system memory allocation in the
first place, that's why you
should use memoryless storage
mode, in particular, for all the
multisampled attachments.
So let's see how can we do that
with, again, just a little bit
of code.
In this case, is as simple as
setting memoryless into the
texture descriptor.
Also we will want to make sure
that our render pass configures
that render target as fully
transient.
In this case, we want to
configure the G-Buffers
transients.
So, we just need to set the load
action clear and the store
action to DontCare.
So we are not storing the
G-buffer.
So we can see how Digital
Legends did it by having another
look at Afterpulse.
At the top we can see an older
version of Afterpulse, it has a
transient G-buffer but it's
being backed by system memory.
At the bottom, we can see a
newer version of Afterpulse
which actually has a larger
G-buffer.
But this G-buffer though is
fully transient and this time
not backed by system memory,
they are utilizing memoryless
storage mode for all the
intermediate G-buffer
attachments.
And this is great because the
newer version of Afterpulse is
saving about 60 megabytes of
memory footprint just by setting
that one flag, it's awesome.
And it comes with no compromise,
there is nothing being lost
here, there's no trade-off to be
made, it just works.
And it's great.
So, now, let's move on to the
rest of the best practices,
which some of those we will do
come with a, you know, memory
and performance trade-off or
memory and image quality
trade-off.
In this case, we are back to
resource streaming.
Notice that loading all the
assets into memory will increase
the memory footprint, so you
should consider the memory and
performance trade-off and only
load all the assets that you
know will be used, particularly
when you are memory limited.
Also you may want to free all
the resources as long-- as soon
as they are not used anymore,
potentially like splash screen
or tutorial UI would be great
candidates for that.
And this is a hard decision to
make but fortunately the Memory
Viewer is also a great tool to
help us with that.
We can use the filters to
quickly focus on unused
resources.
By doing so, the table at the
bottom will be updated and then
we can focus on all these
resources which are not used in
this frame.
And we will talk more about this
and use them off the Memory
Viewer towards the end of the
talk.
So, now, let's move on to best
practice number 14.
Use smaller assets.
In fact, you should only make
the assets as large as necessary
and consider again the image
quality and memory trade-off of
your asset sizes.
Make sure that both textures and
meshes are compressed.
And potentially if you are
getting memory limited you may
want to only load the smaller
mipmap levels of your textures,
or the lower LODs for your
meshes.
But there is a trade-off here
that we are making, between
image quality and memory.
It's up to you to decide, when
do you want to take it?
The next best practice number 15
is very similar.
We will want to simplify
memory-intensive effects.
Some effects may require large
off-screen buffers, such as
Shadow Maps and SSAO.
So the best practice will be for
you to consider the image
quality and memory trade-off of
all of those effects.
Potentially lower the resolution
of all these large off-screen
buffers.
And if you are very memory
constrained then just disable
all those effects all together.
That is a trade-off to be made
here and you need to be
conscious about it.
But sometimes there's no other
choice.
The next best practices that we
are going to cover here are
slightly different.
In this last section, I will
introduce a couple of more
advanced concepts that will help
us further reducing the memory
footprint.
We will talk about metal
resource heaps, purgeable memory
as well as pipeline state
objects.
So, let's get started with metal
resource heaps.
metal resource heaps will allow
your application to take
explicit control over the large
memory allocation that happens
up front.
In this case, we will go from
three separate textures which
have their own allocation into a
single metal resource heap which
is a single allocation that will
hold these three textures
separately.
This will also allow the system
to pack those textures together,
so we're already saving some
memory.
But the great memory savings
will come from using aliasing.
So, notice that rendering a
frame may require a lot of
intermediate memory, in
particular, is your game scales
in the post-process pipeline.
So it is very important for you
to use metal resource heaps for
those effects and alias as much
of that memory as possible.
For example, you may want to
reutilize the memory for all
those resources which have no
dependencies, potentially like
those you would find in SSAO and
Depth of Field.
So, now, let's look how would
that look like.
In this case, we have the same
metal resource heap as before.
But if the three textures are
not used at the same time we can
potentially alias them.
And by doing so, we will save a
lot of memory.
And this will really help your
game scale with a much more
complex post-process pipeline
without having to pay a huge
memory price for all those
intermediate render targets and
all the intermediate memory.
So it is great, it's a great
feature that you should consider
leveraging.
Now, let's talk about another
advanced concept that of
purgeable memory.
Purgeable memory has three
states, non-volatile, volatile,
and empty.
Notice that volatile and empty
allocations do not count towards
the application memory
footprint.
That is because the system can
either reclaim that memory at
some point, in the case of
volatile or has already
reclaimed it in the past, in the
case of empty.
So you may need to regenerate
those resources.
But that makes this kind of
memory ideal for resource
caches.
So the best practice number 17
is for you to mark resources as
volatile.
Temporary resources may become a
large part of your game's
footprint.
And Metal will allow you to
explicitly manage those, set the
purgeable state of all the
resources explicitly.
So you will want to focus on
your caches particularly all of
those which hold mostly idle
memory and carefully manage
their purgeable state, so they
will not count towards the
game's footprint.
Let's see a very short bit of
code that will give you an
example on how to do so.
In this case, we have a texture
cache, could have also been a
buffer cache.
And we will set the purgeable
state of all the textures in
that cache as volatile because
we know that cache is mostly
idle.
We only use a texture from now
and then but not very often.
So if we need to use a resource
from that cache, we will then
need to mark it as non-volatile
that will ensure that the system
doesn't remove its backing data.
And in the case, it was empty
which was the previous state
that the one we just said.
We may actually need to
regenerate the data potentially
not.
It depends on what type of cache
you're managing.
But after we do so, we can just
utilize the resource normally as
we would otherwise.
A very good practice will be for
you to also check the common
buffer completion and get to
handle when the common buffer is
completed and then potentially
you flag that resource as
volatile again.
So it does not keep counting
towards your memory footprint.
You can be explicit and in fact
you should be very aggressive
particularly when you have lots
of caches of mostly idle memory.
So let's introduce one last
concept that of pipeline state
objects.
Most of you are already familiar
with those.
PSOs encapsulate most of the
Metal render state.
They are constructed with a
description-- a descriptor which
contains vertex and fragment
functions as well as other
states such as the blend state
and the vertex descriptor.
All of these will get compiled
into final Metal PSO.
We only need this final Metal
PSO in order to render.
So the next best practice is for
you to explicitly leverage that.
Since Metal allows your
application to load most of the
rendering state up front, you
should do so.
That will be great for
performance.
But then consider the memory
trade-off of doing that.
If you are getting memory
limited make sure do not hold on
to PSO references that you know
they are not needed anymore.
And very important also do not
hold on to Metal function
references after you have
created the PSO cache.
Since those are not needed to
render they are only needed to
create new PSOs.
So let's see what I mean by
looking at the descriptor again.
This is the pipeline state
object as well as the pipeline
state object descriptor.
And what this best practice is
asking you to do is to free the
reference of both the vertex and
fragment functions after you
create the PSOs, potentially
only hold on to those when
you're populating the main PSO
cache at load time.
And then consider also freeing
the PSO itself when you are
getting memory limited if you
know that that PSO is no longer
needed.
Now, let's, please welcome
Onyechi on stage for an awesome
demo of the Memory Viewer.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you Guillem.
Hello everyone.
So you already have the brief
introduction to the Memory
Viewer from the previous slides.
Now, I'm going to show you how
to use it to understand your
memory footprint that's
optimized for better memory
performance.
So here we are again with a
capture of a frame from the same
early version of the game
Afterpulse.
Then the top left there are the
debug navigates that you'll find
in your Memory Gauge which when
I click on it, it takes me into
the Memory Viewer.
Now this shows us the state of
all live Metal resources for the
captured frame.
And my goal is to find
opportunities to reduce its
memory footprint.
So to begin, let's take a look
at the orange bars in the graph.
This shows how our resources are
distributed by type.
And we can see that textures
make up the largest proportion,
right?
There's about 440 megabytes of
them.
Now, I want to focus in these
sections and I can simply do
that by clicking on the filter
button.
Now, both the graph and the
table have been updated to show
textures only.
So, next, Guillem mentioned that
when looking to reduce our
memory footprint starting at
unused resources that was a
great place to begin.
So, let's do that.
Let's look at the blue bars this
time.
This represents our usage and we
see that we have about 200
megabytes, so unused texture.
So as a reminder, unused
resources are resources that do
not contribute to the final
output of this rendered frame.
That means they're not accessed
by the GPU.
OK. So, I can easily do that
again by just clicking on the
unused filter, so that we're
looking on unused textures now.
Next, I will sort the table by
allocated size, so that we're
focused in our largest texture.
And we can see straight away
that our largest texture which
is about 13 megabytes has an
issue.
So, issues work here just like
in Dependency Viewer you saw in
the previous demo.
So let's click it to see what
it's about.
OK. So, this says we have a
large unused texture.
It's not accessed by the CPU and
has never been bound to a
command encoder with a
recommendation to avoid loading
the resource or to make it
volatile.
So, we can also confront this by
looking at the properties, CPU
Access and Times since Last
Bound.
And we can clearly see that this
section is definitely never been
accessed by either the CPU or
the GPU.
So, therefore, we can say with
confidence now this is a
resource that it should be under
down, till it's actually needed.
OK. So, that's encouraging, we
very quickly identify 13
megabytes of memory savings.
Let's check out the next issue.
So, in this case, texture has
been identified as a temporary
resource.
It's not accessed by the CPU and
has not been bound to a command
encoder for over 47 seconds.
So, in other words, this texture
has not been using this frame or
in any other frame in the last
47 seconds.
So this is a pretty good
candidate for a resource that
should be made volatile if
possible since it occasionally
contributes to a frame.
OK. So, this is fantastic.
We've very quickly found about
14 megabytes of memory savings
and indeed when looking to
reduce our memory footprint
looking at unused resources is a
great place to begin on issues
that will help you to quickly
identify the best candidates to
remove.
But you should also pay
attention to the properties
Times since Last Bound to figure
out which of your unused
resources have never been
submitted to the GPU even though
they may have been accessed by
the CPU.
OK. Let's switch things up a
bit.
Let's see what issues or what
memory savings we can discover,
where textures are actually in
used.
OK. I'm going to switch to the
used filter this time, so we're
looking at used textures.
And we see that one of our
largest textures which is about
18 megabytes has two issues.
So, let's see what they are.
OK. So, the first one is about
lossless compression.
Texture has opted out of
lossless compressions because of
the presence of a ShaderWrite
usage flag, even though it's
being used exclusively as a
render target.
The second issue is about
storage mode.
Our texture the render target
has been identified as being
transient which obviously means
that no loads to actions are
required for this texture.
But unfortunately it has a
storage mode shared when really
it should be memoryless.
So, we have two different
recommendations here.
And if you think about it, we
can only really choose one of
them.
But at this point I should
emphasize that these
recommendations presented by the
Memory Viewer are based on data
gathered up to the current
frame.
However, you know better by how
you intend to use your resource
beyond the current frame.
So, with that said if we are
certain that this texture will
remain transient and say a
future render passes then
switching to memoryless is the
superior option.
And doing so would reduce our
memory footprint by the size of
the texture which is 18
megabytes.
If on the other hand, our
texture will not be transient in
future render passes then we
should seriously consider opting
into lossless compression
because doing so would have a
positive impact on our memory
bandwidth as suggested by
Guillem.
And, in this case, simply
removing the redundant
ShaderWrite flag should do the
trick.
So, we've only just scratched
the surface of what's possible
with the Memory Viewer.
You've seen how with just a few
mouse clicks it makes it very
easy for you to understand your
memory usage and also it makes
it very quick for you to
identify those hard to find
issues that may affect your
performance.
And with that I'm going to
welcome Guillem back to the
stage.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you that was also an
awesome demo.
Cool. So, we have seen a lot of
best practices today.
We've been through a total of 18
of them which is quite a lot of
content to go through really.
Notice that most of this best
practices are actually quite
related, right?
So, most of the memory bandwidth
best practices, will also help
you reducing the memory
footprint.
So, maybe the best way to
actually think about all this
content, this is a checklist of
optimizations for your Metal
gamer application.
And when you carefully take all
of these elements, you too will
be delivering optimized Metal
games and apps, which was all
that this talk is all about.
For more information please see
our documentation online and
come visit us at the lab today
at 3.
Thank you very much and I hope
you enjoy the rest of the show.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]