[ Music ]
>> Hello, my name is James
Kelly, and I'm a Software
Engineer on the Game
Technologies Team at Apple.
In this video, we'll be talking
about the new features and
changes coming to the Game
Controller framework this year
to help you adopt newly
supported game controllers.
The Game Controller framework
has been making it easy to add
support for MFi Game Controllers
to your games on iOS, tvOS, and
macOS.
By abstracting controller
hardware through a common API,
the Game Controller framework
lets you write your code once
without you having to worry
about how controller data is
mapped.
And this year, we're excited to
announce new support for some
fantastic controllers.
First is the Bluetooth-enabled
Xbox Wireless controller from
Microsoft.
This will now seamlessly
integrate into any Game
Controller framework-enabled
game.
And that's not all.
The DualShock 4 Controller from
Sony is now supported by the
Game Controller framework.
It will just work with any games
that already have controller
support through the Game
Controller framework.
Many developers have already
been creating some great games
with controller support.
Rayman Adventures, Transistor,
Sky Force Reloaded, and Alto's
Adventure are some great
examples, and just a few of the
games on the App Store that
support controllers.
By using the Game Controller
framework, games will
automatically support the Xbox
Wireless and DualShock 4
Controllers in iOS 13, tvOS 13,
and macOS Catalina.
In this video, we'll talk about
how to grab a reference to these
new controllers through the Game
Controller framework, how to
access their inputs, some UI
best practices for probably
supporting MFi, Xbox Wireless,
and DualShock 4 Controllers, and
our recommendations for how to
update your games on macOS, if
they previously supported Game
Controllers through lower level
frameworks such as IOKit.
First, let's talk about changes
coming to the Game Controller
framework in support of these
new controllers.
As a quick reminder, games that
already use the Game Controller
framework will gain support for
free, meaning if your game
supports MFi controllers, it
will also automatically support
the Xbox Wireless controller and
the DualShock 4.
The controller's inputs can be
accessed via a GCController's
GCExtendedGamepad profile.
For those of you who are new to
the Game Controller framework,
let's talk briefly about how to
detect a controller.
Each controller is represented
by a class named GCController.
It's the same class for all
controllers, MFi, Xbox Wireless,
and DualShock 4 controllers, as
well as the serial remote, are
all instances of GCController.
The first thing you want to do
is get a list of currently
connected controllers.
To do this, use GCController's
controllers class method.
It returns an array of
GCController instances
representing all connected
controllers.
The array will be empty if no
controllers are connected.
You should check this array when
your app launches and set up the
controllers as appropriate.
Now it's common for controllers
to connect and disconnect while
your app is running.
For example, the player may turn
on their controller after
launching your game, their
controller may run out of
batteries, or they may just take
the controller out of range.
To be notified of these events,
add observers for GCController
did connect notification and
GCController did disconnect
notification.
Your application did finish
launching with options method is
a great place to do this.
So, now that you've grabbed onto
an instance of a connected
controller, let's talk about the
buttons and other inputs it may
have and how to access them.
First, let's recap what inputs
are available on a controller.
There are two triggers, a
directional pad, two
thumbsticks, a menu button, four
face buttons, a programmable
4-LED strip, and two shoulder
buttons.
Let's take a closer look at how
physical buttons map to the API
using the four face buttons as
an example.
Here we can see a table listing
the four face button properties
found on a controller's extended
gamepad profile.
The face buttons of MFi
controllers map directly to this
API as do the face buttons of an
Xbox Wireless controller.
Note that there is some subtlety
to consider with DualShock 4
controllers as they use symbols
instead of letters to represent
their face buttons.
In cases where there may be
ambiguity when mapping an input
to API, we use the notion of
positional equivalents to
resolve these mappings.
For example, if we consider the
face buttons to be four buttons
arranged in a diamond on the
right side of a controller, then
the bottom cross button is
positionally equivalent to the
bottom A button of an MFi
controller.
So, it maps to the button A
property.
The right face button with a
circle button maps to the button
B property and so on.
Next, let's talk about clickable
thumbsticks or L3 and R3.
We added support for these
inputs to the Game Controller
framework in iOS 12.1, tvOS
12.1, and macOS Mojave 10.14.1.
While the Xbox Wireless and
DualShock 4 controllers all have
clickable thumbsticks,
thumbsticks on some models of
MFi controllers may not be
clickable.
Let's dive into a code example
to see how we can handle this.
Let's say we want to make the
player character crouch when the
player clicks L3.
If we're supporting older
versions of iOS, tvOS, or macOS,
we should first check to see if
we have the clickable
thumbsticks API available to us.
Even if we do though, the
specific controller we're
mapping may not physically have
clickable thumbsticks.
So, we check to see if the left
thumbstick button is new.
And if it is, we should ensure
that the user interaction we
were intending to map to L3, in
this case, crouching the player,
is available through some other
means.
Once we are working with a
controller that we know has
clickable thumbsticks, we can
just assign our behavior to the
press handler of L3.
Now, when a player clicks the
left thumbstick button, the game
will toggle the player
character's crouch.
If our game is running on
versions of iOS, tvOS, or macOS
that don't have this API, we
still need to code an
alternative path to the player
crouch.
Next, let's talk about some new
buttons that have been added to
the API in support of the Xbox
wireless and DualShock 4
Controllers, what we're calling
the auxiliary buttons.
These buttons are typically
found in the middle of
controllers.
First, we have the menu button.
It should be used to pause
gameplay and bring up the
in-game pause menu.
All supported controllers have
this button.
Now let's look at the options
button.
It's a general purpose button,
but you should avoid using it
for time critical actions, as
it's generally positioned out of
the way.
Note that not all controllers
have this button.
Let's take a look at how these
new APIs map to existing MFi
controllers.
The center menu button maps
directly to the button menu
property of GCExtendedGamepad.
Note that in this example, this
MFi controller doesn't have an
options button.
So, the button options property
of GCExtendedGamepad is new.
Next up is the Xbox Wireless
controller.
When a controller has multiple
auxiliary buttons, we determine
its button mapping using
positional equivalents.
The right auxiliary button, in
this case, the Xbox Wireless
controller's menu button maps
directly to the button menu
property, whereas the left
Auxiliary button or the Xbox
Wireless controller's view
button maps to the button
options property.
The Xbox button in the center of
the controller has been reserved
for system use.
The same approach can be applied
for the DualShock 4.
Again, we can use positional
equivalents to determine the
button mappings.
The right auxiliary button or
the DualShock 4's options button
maps to the button menu
property, whereas the left
auxiliary button, the DualShock
4's share button maps to the
button options property.
The PS button in the center of
the controller has also been
reserved.
Note that we've deprecated the
controller paused handler.
You should now use the new
button menu API instead.
Let's dive into a code example
to see how we can handle this.
Let's say we want to pause or
unpause the game whenever the
player presses the menu button.
If we're supporting older
versions of iOS, tvOS or macOS,
we should first check to see if
we have the new menu button API.
If we do, we simply register a
pressed changed handler on the
extended gamepad's button menu
property.
Within the handler, we toggle
the pause menu.
Typically, when players want to
pause the game, they want to do
it as fast as possible, so we
make sure to trigger this
behavior on button press rather
than button release.
If the new API isn't available,
we should still register our
functionality with the old
controller PausedHandler.
This will trigger whenever the
menu button is pressed.
So that was the menu button.
Now let's look at the options
button.
Again, remember that not all
controllers may have this
button.
Let's dive into another code
example to see how we should
handle this.
Here, we want to bring up an
in-game settings menu whenever
the player presses the options
button.
If we're supporting older
versions of iOS, tvOS, or macOS,
we should first check to see if
we have the new options button.
But even if we do, the
controller we're mapping may not
physically have an options
button.
So we check to see if the
options button is new.
And if it is, we need to ensure
that the settings menu is
accessible via some other means.
For example, we can list it as
an item in the pause menu.
If the controller has an options
button, we can just assign our
behavior to the button options
pressed handler.
Now, when a player clicks the
options button, the game will
toggle the settings menu.
If the new API isn't available,
we still need to make sure
there's an alternative path to
reach the settings menu.
So that was a quick look at the
new API coming to the Game
Controller framework this year
in support of the newly added
Xbox Wireless and DualShock 4
controllers.
Now, let's talk about some UI
best practices for handling
different controllers so that
your users can experience your
game in the best possible way.
With the Game Controller
framework being expanded to
support more than just MFi
controllers, a new consideration
arises.
Buttons and other inputs may no
longer be visually consistent
between controllers.
In this example, the B button in
the prompt only matches the MFi
controller while the Xbox
Wireless controller's B button
is red and the DualShock 4 has a
circle button instead.
Let's dive deeper into this
example to see how we could
handle this.
Let's say you're introducing
your player to the base
mechanics of your game and you
want to display an in-game
prompt that tells them how to
block.
In this case, your block
function is mapped to the button
B property of GCExtendedGamepad.
For an MFi controller, we
display our MFi B button asset
as we did before.
For the Xbox Wireless
controller, however, we need to
slightly tweak the asset, in
this case, by making the B
button red.
Finally, we display a circle
button when the DualShock 4 is
the active controller.
Now, regardless of what
controller the player is using,
they can easily understand your
in-game prompts.
Let's take a look at a code
example to see how we can
achieve this.
Here, we have a simple function
called getBlockButtonAsset that
returns the appropriate art
asset for the block button.
First, we switch over the
controller's product category, a
new property added this year to
GCController to determine what
kind of controller it is.
If it's an Xbox Wireless
controller, we will return the
red B button asset.
If it's a DualShock 4
controller, we'll return the red
circle button asset.
And finally, by default,
overturn the MFi green B button
asset.
This way, your game will support
the diverse range of MFi
controllers currently available
and gracefully fall back to a
sensible asset should new
controller support be added in
the future.
Let's return to our previous
block example.
Instead of creating unique art
assets for each type of
controller, another option is to
use generic symbols in your
in-game tutorials and prompts.
By providing a generic prompt
that doesn't rely on anything
other than positional
equivalents, you can rest
assured knowing that your
players will be able to easily
understand your in-game guidance
regardless of what type of
controller is connected.
In this example, it's clear that
the players should press the
right face button.
One last note, players may have
multiple controllers connected
to their device at the same time
even if they're playing alone.
You should gracefully support
all connected controllers in
this case, as a player may
switch between them at any
moment.
This means that you'll need to
recognize input from all
connected controllers either by
pulling them each frame or
registering input handlers with
each of them.
You should also update your
in-game guidance and visuals to
match the most recently used
controllers.
For example, if a player is
using their MFi controller,
display the appropriate MFi art
assets.
But if the player pressed an
input on their connected
DualShock 4, all in-game visuals
should automatically adjust to
use the DualShock 4 art assets.
By dynamically adapting your
visuals to the most recently
used controller, you will
provide your players an
intuitive and polished
controller-driven experience.
Now, for those of you who have
previously implemented the game
controller support outside of
the Game Controller framework on
macOS, we have some new guidance
for your games.
When you adopt the Game
Controller framework, game
controllers will just work, so
you should use it for MFi, Xbox
Wireless, and DualShock 4
controller support on macOS.
As we abstract away any hardware
intricacies that may differ
between controllers, we provide
you consistency in your app
across iOS, tvOS, and macOS.
This will also help to ensure
that your apps remain compatible
with current and future OS
updates.
For those of you who have
previously hardcoded support for
these controllers through lower
level APIs such as IOKit, we
highly recommend that you move
your implementation over to the
Game Controller framework.
As new controllers will appear
in both IOKit and the Game
Controller framework, you should
drop your IOKit implementation
to ensure there are no
conflicts.
This will allow you to code to a
single interface and receive new
game controller support for
free.
So let's summarize what we've
discussed in this video.
The Game Controller framework
abstracts hardware through a
common API, letting you write
your code once without having to
worry about the low-level
differences between controller
models.
This has the great benefit of
allowing your game to
automatically support newly
added controllers such as the
Xbox Wireless and the DualShock
4 controllers.
However, in order to provide the
best user experience for your
players, you should take care to
adapt your game's UI and
on-screen indicators to the
active controller.
And finally, ensure your macOS
apps stay compatible with future
OS updates by migrating existing
controller support from lower
level APIs to the Game
Controller framework.
More information about this
year's game controller update
can be found on the Apple
developer site.
That's it for this year's game
controller's update.
Thank you for watching.
We hope you found this
information helpful and you can
use it to create some awesome
games with game controller
support.