[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Hello and welcome to Advances
in Networking Part 2.
If you couldn't join us for Part
1, it will be available for
streaming soon on the app and on
the web.
I'm Eric Kinnear from Internet
Technologies.
I'll be joined today by my
colleagues Tommy and Stuart.
We've got a lot to cover in Part
2.
We're going to start by
expanding the horizons of what
you can do with Bonjour
browsing.
We'll talk about how you can
achieve efficient and easy
message transport by building
framing protocols.
We'll take a look at some new
and improved metric collection.
And we'll finish off with some
status updates and some best
practices to help networking in
your app become the best it can
be.
Before we begin, a brief
reminder.
If you're using URLSession and
Network.framework, you'll be
able to take advantage of
everything we're talking about
today.
If you're not, these are some
additional reasons why you
should switch to a more modern
networking API.
Let's jump right in with Bonjour
browsing.
Bonjour is how you advertise and
discover services on the
network.
It's used anytime you print with
AirPrint, connect to an
airplane-enabled device, use
HomeKit to automate your home,
really anytime you are
connecting to something without
typing in an IP address or a
host name.
And as you know, Bonjour is
available on all Apple
platforms.
And it's also available on
Linux, Android, Chrome OS, it's
how Chromecast does discovery.
What you may not know is that
Microsoft also quietly added
Bonjour support to Windows 10
back in 2015.
And since then the
implementation has matured.
This means that Bonjour is now
available on every major
platform.
Today, we've got some exciting
enhancements to share in this
area.
Sometimes you're on one network
and you'd like to discover
services that are available on a
different network.
Say you've got a device and
you'd like to print to a printer
that's on a different subnet and
multiple hops away.
Right now, you would send
multicast packets on your local
network and you wouldn't hear
anything back.
A discovery proxy solves this
problem.
You can now send unicast packets
over to the discovery proxy.
It will send out the multicast
packets on the destination
subnet, receive the response and
proxy the results back to you.
Now you can connect directly to
your printer and voila, we've
got our document.
[ Applause ]
We're excited to announce that
the code for this on the client
side is included in your
developer seed and a server
implementation along with
instruction for setting it up
are available on GitHub.
Let's take a look at what this
means for your app.
Previously, it's been the
recommendation that when
browsing you should specifying
nil for a domain.
And this continues to be the
case and the right answer for
almost every situation.
In the past you may not have
noticed much difference, but now
this starts to have a bigger
effect, specifying local will
explicitly prevent discovery of
any remote or proxied services.
This is probably not what you
want.
So double check that your browse
calls aren't inadvertently
specifying a domain.
And while you're browsing
services while building your
app, let's take a look at how
some new features in
Network.framework can make
browsing for Bonjour even easier
especially in Swift.
Last year, we introduced
NWListener and NWConnection
along with Network.framework.
For example, you can have an
NWListener advertising a Bonjour
service and you can have an
NWConnection connects to a
Bonjour service endpoint.
But you had to use one of the
other Bonjour browsing APIs to
discover the available services.
And once you found one, you had
to do a bunch of work to convert
it into an endpoint that you
could use with your connection.
Today, we are thrilled to
announce native browsing support
in Network.framework via the
NWBrowser object.
Browser joints connection and
listener to cover the entire
workflow from advertise to
discover to connect, all using
the Network.framework objects
that you're already familiar
with.
Browser provides native service
discovery in Network.framework
using a modern dispatch-based
API that's optimized to work
incredibly well in Swift.
It also includes optional
support for TXT records.
So if your application needs it,
you can ensure that a TXT record
is requested for every
discovered endpoint.
Let's take a look at how we use
our browser.
We can init it using a Bonjour
service type that we'd like to
discover and some NWParameters
which is how you tell it what
you'd like to-- how you'd like
to browse, the same way you do
all other Network.framework
objects.
Next, you can set a
browseResultsChangedHandler
which will be called to deliver
the list of available endpoints
that have been discovered.
And finally, just like other
Network.framework objects, you
start the browser on a dispatch
queue where you'd like to
receive those callbacks.
Let's take a closer look at the
browseResultsChangedHandler.
You have two options.
First, you can provide a handler
that receives the detailed list
of all changes that have
happened in that update.
This aligns very closely with
the lower level APIs and
provides you full visibility
into everything that changed.
Endpoints can be added or
removed and they can also have
their inner details changed.
Those changes are represented by
flags.
And in this case, we'll check
for interfaces being added or
removed as endpoints are
discovered over additional
interfaces.
You can also choose to provide a
handler that just looks at the
latest list of results that have
been discovered.
Be careful if you do this
because this handler will be
called repeatedly as the list of
available endpoints changes.
So make sure that you're
updating the state and the rest
of your application
appropriately.
Let's see an example of the
NWBrowser in action.
We're going to make an app that
provides a service discovery and
secure connectivity between two
devices.
In our case we're going to make
it a tic-tac-toe game.
But you could use this for
pretty much anything else.
We're going to use an NWListener
to advertise games to nearby
players, we're going to use
NWBrowser to browse for the
games that are available nearby,
and we're going to take one of
those browse results once the
user picks a game they'd like to
join.
And we're going to pass it an
NWConnection to connect back to
our listener.
Let's take a look at this in
Xcode.
Here I've got my application and
we've already written a bunch of
code to handle doing some
different views displaying a
list of available games to the
user, letting them host the
game, stuff like that.
So, here we can just focus on
the browser.
I've got a class called
PeerBrowser, which I'm going to
use to manage my NWBrowser and
provide a PeerBrowserDelegate
that will pass the list of
discovered endpoints too so the
UI can display them to the user.
First, I need to add my
NWBrowser as an instance
property on the PeerBrowser.
Next, we see that when the
PeerBrowser is initted, it will
immediately call startBrowsing.
We need to fill that in.
First, I'm going to create some
NWParameters which is the same
objects that you use with other
Network.framework objects to
describe how you'd like to
interact with the network.
In this case the default
parameters are just fine but
we'll set includePeerToPeer to
true so that we can discover
other available games even if
the devices aren't on the same
physical network.
Next, we'll create our NWBrowser
browsing for a service type of
tictactoe.tcp.
And we'll make sure to specify
nil for the domain.
We'll use the parameters that we
created earlier and save it off
into our peer browser.
Next, we'll set a
stateUpdateHandler just like we
do with other Network.framework
objects to receive updates about
the state of our browser if
there's any errors, how it's
going, things like that, and
then we'll set our
browseResultsChangedHandler.
Here it's really simple.
We take the list of results, we
pass them off to our delegate to
be displayed in the UI, and we
make sure that our delegate is
coded in such a way that it
refreshes the UI every time this
happens so we can always
represent the latest list of
discovered endpoints.
Finally, we start the browser on
the main queue since that's
where we'd like to receive our
updates.
And that's it.
With just that code, we're able
to bring up an NWBrowser, have
it discover nearby games
potentially over peer to peer
links and display a list of
available games to the user so
they can choose which one to
connect to.
We'll talk a little bit later
about our listener and
connection, but all of this code
is available for download as
sample code off the website.
And there's one thing I want to
touch on before we try it out.
We've got our NWParameters that
we're going to use with our
listeners and connections.
And earlier I mentioned that we
want to make sure that our
connection between these devices
is secure so that nobody else
can see what moves we're making
or worse, modify one of the
player's moves.
We're going to do that by
defining an extension to
NWParameters and creating a
convenience initializer.
It takes a passcode as a string.
We're going to display to the
host of the game a passcode and
ask the person that wants to
play with them to type in that
passcode and then use that to
derive a pre-shared key that we
can use to secure the connection
with TOS.
In order to this, we need to
create both TCP and TLS options
in our initializer.
Let's start with TLS.
Here we defined a function that
creates TLS options.
We pass at the passcode and for
now we start with just the
default TLS options.
Next, we use the new CryptoKit
framework, which is available
this year, to derive an
authentication key and code from
that passcode.
We'll add that pre-shared key to
our set protocol options and
we'll also make sure to add a
TLS cipher suite that supports
the use of pre-shared keys.
We can return our TLS options.
And up here we're ready to go
with our TCP options.
We'll use a default TCP options
for most things but we'll also
enable keepalive.
We then init our NWParameters
with the TLS options that we
just created down below, and
those pretty much default TCP
options.
Finally, the last thing we want
to do is set include peer to
peer here so that our connection
and our listener will also be
able to connect to nearby
devices even when they're not on
the same network.
So that's it, let's try it out.
If I go over here, we can see
that I've got two devices
running the app and we've
already got our UI there for
hosting a game.
And the browser has already
started browsing and is
displaying searching for games
since we haven't found anything
yet.
If I come up and type in my name
and tap host game, you can see
I'm given the passcode and our
browseResultsChangedHandler has
been called with the list of
discovered endpoints, in this
case the game that I'm hosting,
and we've displayed that for the
user.
It's that easy.
If I tap on join game, I'm
presented the opportunity to
type in the passcode.
And now when I confirm that,
we'll see that we've created the
pre-shared key, used it to
connect back to the listener,
and hopefully the game will flip
around and ready to play.
There we go.
[ Applause ]
So far, we've built the
beginnings of our app and
established connectivity between
the two devices.
We used an NWListener to
advertise a Bonjour service of
tictactoe.tcp.
We used an NWBrowser to browse
for available games and display
those to the user.
And we were able to take the
result that we got back from the
browser and pass it directly to
our NWConnection to connect back
to the listener and establish a
secure connection between those
two devices.
Of course in order to play the
game, the two devices actually
have to be able to communicate
to share the game state, tell
each other about moves that the
players making, and things like
that.
In order to that, I'd like to
invite Tommy up to the stage to
walk us through building custom
framing protocols.
[ Applause ]
>> All right.
Thank you, Eric.
So today, I'd like to share with
you an exciting new way that you
can extend your network
connections with custom protocol
framing code that you write that
runs on the same thread as the
rest of the protocols in the
networking stack.
So, in order to finish the game
that Eric just started, we need
to define a way for the two
games to send commands between
each other.
When one player wants to make a
move, he needs to send a message
to the other side.
To do this we're going to need a
protocol.
So here's what our protocol is
going to look like.
It's a simple type-length-value
or TLV protocol.
So we have a 4-byte type which
may be make a move.
The player wants to put a given
character at a given location on
our tic-tac-toe board.
We have a 4-byte length which
indicates the length of the rest
of the message.
And then after that we have the
body of the message.
And in this case it could be
place the monkey face at row 1
column 2.
And then it's going to repeat
like that on TLS byte-stream.
So you may have noticed that
this protocol, even though we're
running on top of a TLS
byte-stream which itself is not
structured is using structured
messages.
The application is not thinking
in terms of byte-streams but
well-delineated pieces of
information.
And almost all networking
applications do this.
They either have a header and a
body or they have a delimiter
that goes somewhere to define
the boundaries of their
messages.
However, traditional transport
networking APIs like sockets
didn't give you a way to easily
read out messages on a
connection.
You had to do that all yourself
in the application.
So, to take a look at how this
problem plays out let's look at
the relationship of your
application to the rest of the
networking stack.
So up on top you have your
application.
And it is communicating with the
networking stack via the API.
So in Network.framework, we have
running TLS and TCP all within
one shared thread inside your
application.
This is the user space
networking stack that we
introduced last year.
Let's zoom in to see how your
application reads messages when
it's on top of a byte-stream.
So if you have a protocol like
the one that we're using for
tic-tac-toe, you may have a
fixed-length header.
And the simple thing you can do
here is to read exactly the
length of your header.
Receive 8 bytes.
So this is a fixed length.
You know what's going to happen.
And the stack will call you back
when you have your full header.
This allows you to determine the
length of the rest of the
message.
So you can read exactly that and
then go back and forth reading
body, header, body, header,
body.
So this is great, but you may
have noticed that we have
multiple back and forths at
least two for every single
message.
If you have a more complex
protocol, maybe you have a
variable-length header or you
have a delimiter, this can
become even more inefficient,
even though it's simple for your
application to write its logic.
If you care about efficiency a
lot, you have another option.
You could receive as much as
possible at one time.
But now you have a bunch of
other problems to deal with.
Now, you need to handle the case
in which you don't receive a
complete message all in one
chunk.
Or maybe you receive multiple
messages in one go, or maybe you
receive only part of your
header, you only have two or
three bytes of your length
field.
You need to save it off,
reconstruct the field and parse
it out again.
Getting this fully correct and
handling every possible edge
case can be really difficult.
And it's common to have subtle
bugs that only show up when your
users actually use your
application in the field.
All right.
So, it's a bit of a bleak
picture at this point.
How do we get the best of both
worlds?
How can we have a way to be both
efficient and have simple code
that's easily testable and
composable?
Well, I'm really excited to
share that now in iOS 13 and
macOS Catalina, you'll be able
to write your own protocol code
that runs on the same networking
thread to handle this problem.
So, this is an unprecedented
step forward in the amount of
flexibility that you have to
define your messages within a
transport networking API
[applause].
Thank you.
And you get to do this all
within NWConnection.
And so, to the application on
top, it's just as if you're
reading and writing datagrams
like a basic connection.
So let's look at the world now.
Still have your application.
It's still sending and receiving
but now you have your framing
code that's running within the
same thread as TLS and TCP.
So you can now call
receiveMessage.
And it will get exactly one
callback when you have a
complete message that your
application can fully process.
You can do this over and over
again.
One call per message and really,
really easy to debug and
understand what's going on.
So, this is great.
And if your-- You may be asking
right now what can I actually
implement as one of these
framing protocols?
What are the restrictions?
So, the good news is, is that
pretty much anything that
encapsulates or encodes
application data to transform it
can be written as a framing
protocol.
You can even send your own
messages that do not correspond
to application data, if you need
to do a handshake or if you need
to implement some sort of
keepalive on the connection.
And the protocols that you're
implementing here can be
standard IETF official protocols
or they could be something
custom just for your app like
what we're going to be doing for
a tic-tac-toe game.
So if you want to build a
protocol, you have two steps.
First, you implement a reusable
piece of code that defines your
message framing.
This is the protocol.
And then you add that protocol
into your connection's protocol
stacks so that you can use it
for connection establishment as
well as sending and receiving
message.
All right.
So let's go on to step 1.
We're going to start
implementing framing protocols.
What you do here is create a
class that conforms to
ProtocolFramerImplementation.
And there are many things you
can do within this class.
But the two most important
things to remember are to
handleOutput, to send messages;
and to handleInput, to parse
messages.
If you can do these two things,
hooray, you are a framer.
Let's take a look at the code.
So, here we have my protocol.
It's going to conform to
ProtocolFramerImplementation.
And the first thing that I
recommend you do is create a
definition object.
And this is a handle to your
protocol that you can use
throughout the rest of your app.
It refers to your protocols you
can add it into connections.
Next you can handle a lot of the
basic callback events.
One of the most important ones
here is start.
Start will get called anytime
your protocol is loaded into a
connection as being used to
bring it up.
If you need to do a handshake to
exchange something with the
other side, you can implement it
here.
Or if like our tic-tac-toe game
you have a very simple protocol,
you don't need to do any setup,
just mark the connection ready
immediately.
So once you've done this, you
now have to handleOutput and
handleInput.
Let's dive into these.
So here is what handleOutput
looks like.
You will get called with
handleOutput every time the
application sends a message.
And you'll be given the message
metadata with some custom values
if you need them, along with the
length of the message the
application is trying to send.
So, if you have a header body
protocol, like what we're using,
you can first create your header
structure and try to serialize
some data.
So this can include your type
that you get maybe from the
message metadata along with the
length that was passed to you
into handleOutput.
You combine these into data and
then you call writeOutput.
WriteOutput will queue your
bytes on to the output stream,
but they won't get sent quite
yet.
Next you need to write the body.
And in this case we don't need
to transform the application
data at all.
We can just call
writeOutputNoCopy.
This allows us to just take the
direct application bytes and
then queue them on the stream.
When we return from
handleOutput, all of the bytes
will be sent out to connection.
All right.
So let's move on to handling
input.
Handling input is similar but a
little bit more complicated.
You'll be called with
handleInput anytime your
application has received new
bytes on the connection.
And if you're doing a header
body type protocol, you have two
jobs.
You need to parse the header and
then you need to parse the body.
So, let's start with parsing the
header.
Here we have a fixed-length
header for our protocol.
We're going to have exactly 8
bytes.
And what we do is we call
parseInput to start inspecting
the stream of bytes that have
come into the connection.
And we can call it with a
minimum and a maximum of 8 bytes
because we want to look exactly
at that 8-byte header.
If this succeeds, you'll be
called in the block and you'll
be able to look at the actual
buffer bytes, parse out your
values, save them off into local
variables if you need to.
The return value to parse input
indicates how many bytes you
want to increment the input
cursor by.
You say, I am done handling
these 8 bytes.
We don't need to see them again.
We don't need to deliver them to
the application.
Move on. Now you can handle the
case in which not all 8 bytes
were available yet.
In this case, the parseInput
function will fail and you can
just wait for more bytes to
become available.
The return value from
handleInput indicates the number
of bytes that need to be present
before you can successfully do
more work.
So in this case we're telling
the connection, make sure
there's 8 bytes before you wake
me up again.
If you are able to successfully
read out your header, you can
create a message object that you
can deliver up to the
application along with the data.
This allows you to put in any
custom values, types or other
indicators that you want to send
up to your application.
And then lastly you call
deliverInput or
deliverInputNoCopy in this case.
This allows you to mark the next
certain range of bytes as
application data that should be
delivered directly up to the
application.
And this returns Boolean value
to indicate whether or not all
of the bytes were available and
successfully were sent up or if
the connection is going to wait.
So you can actually deliverInput
of a message that's a megabyte
long, a gigabyte long if you
need to, and will keep on
streaming those bytes up as part
of that one message and you
don't need to wait for all the
bytes to be present or handle
them yourself.
OK. So, I know it's a lot of
code, but I think we're ready to
go and implement the protocol
for our game tic-tac-toe.
OK. All right.
So this is the same game that
Eric began earlier.
But I'm now creating a new class
which I'm calling game protocol
and this is going to conform to
ProtocolFramerImplementation.
I have defined two different
types for my game.
I want to have two different
commands that we send.
One is to select the character.
So the first step of the game is
that the player will decide
which emoji family they want to
be.
Do they want to be a monkey or a
bird?
And then once each character has
selected their character, they
can start sending moves.
And this would be a longer body.
It will include the character
along with the row and column
values.
All right.
So, I remember that the first
thing I need to do when I'm
implementing a protocol is
create a definition.
And this is a handle based on my
object that registers my object
with the system and allows me to
use this in connections.
Next, I handle all of the basic
callbacks.
And here again, because I don't
need to have my own handshake,
when I get called with start, I
can return a start result of
ready.
Next, let's handle sending and
encapsulating my messages.
Here I'm going to define my
implementation of handleOutput.
So my header is an 8-byte header
that includes a type and a
length.
So first I need to know what is
my type, and this I get from the
message that the application
sent.
And we'll see that later on.
I've created a custom extension
to the framer message to extract
my particular enum type out so
that I can know if this is a
character selection or a move.
So once I have the type, I can
instantiate my struct, my game
protocol header with the type
and the length that I was passed
in handleOutput.
I've already written code to
encode that data that I got the
type and the length as an 8-byte
range of bytes.
And I call writeOutput to queue
that in the output stream.
And the last thing I need to do
now that I've written my header
is write the body.
And here I just call
writeOutputNoCopy and indicate
that the next range bytes are
going to be the body of this
message.
And so once this returns, those
bytes will be sent and I'm ready
to handle more messages either
in or out.
OK. So that was writing.
Now on reading, I'm going to
handleInput.
So first I want to read out and
parse my header.
So have a fixed sized header.
It's going to be 8 bytes.
I'm going to try to parse out a
minimum of eight and a maximum
of eight and I'll get called
with my buffer whenever those 8
bytes are available.
So here I validate that the
buffer is valid and then I
create my structure to parse out
those 8 bytes into the type and
length field.
Once I've successfully done
that, I indicate that I want to
increment my input cursor by 8
bytes to say that I've consumed
these bytes.
I'm done with them.
Now, I do need to also handle
the case in which I didn't
successfully parse all 8 bytes.
Maybe only 5 bytes were
available.
And so parse will have failed
and I will return from handle
input and indicate that I need
to wait for 8 bytes to be
available before I do more work.
But if I did get past this
point, I know that I have a
valid header that I can use to
deliver up the rest of the
application data.
So now I'm going to create a
message object.
I'm going to store within that
message object my specific
message type.
And lastly, I will call
deliverInput with no copying and
just tell the connection those
next bytes that I parsed out
based on the length, those are
going to be the application
data, and when your application
receives a message, they'll
receive exactly that chunk.
So that's all I need to do.
That's my full protocol.
I am ready to learn how to int
input that into my game
connections.
[ Aapplause ]
All right.
So, the good news is that this
part is really easy.
So all you have to do to add
your protocol into your
connections and reuse it is take
that definition you made earlier
and create some protocol options
using that definition.
So protocol options are the
things that protocol stacks are
made out of.
You have your TCP options, your
TLS options, and now you have
your own custom protocol
options.
So when you create your
parameters for your connection,
let's say you're using TLS as
you should to be secure,
alongside TLS in your protocol
stack, you can add directly into
that array of application
protocols your own protocol on
top.
And you can add multiple of
these to have multiple layers of
framing going on.
And this is the same place that
if you want to use WebSocket,
which is a new system
implementation that we have for
you this year, you can add it
into your connection.
So WebSocket itself is
implemented as a protocol framer
using exactly the same API that
you have available to you now.
So it shows you just how
powerful a framing protocol can
be.
But if you don't want to go
through the work of writing your
own, you can use WebSocket.
So one point I want to make here
is that some applications need
to use different protocol stacks
in different situations.
And framing protocols are a
really great way to make the
contract between your
application and the networking
connection the same even when
you're using different protocol
stacks.
So to give you an example of
this, we use this on our system
for DNS.
So DNS usually sends datagram
messages over UDP.
But occasionally, DNS needs to
run on top of the stream like
TCP.
And when it does this, there's a
protocol that just has a very
basic length body format to
encode DNS over TCP.
So we wrote a framer to define
this simple encapsulation so
that we can have the same code
on top that sends DNS datagrams
that doesn't have to care about
whether it's going over UDP or
TCP and it can just be the same
logic.
So this is a great way to
separate out the concerns and be
able to debug the parts of your
application separately.
So now that we've added our
framing protocol onto our
connections, we're ready to send
and receive messages and we can
use custom values as we're going
to be using in our game.
So Framer.Message lets you store
key value pairs of any object
type so that you can add in your
own custom values to decorate
your send operations and receive
that information inside your
protocol.
So you can create a message and
then when you've set it up how
you like, you can add it to the
context that you're sending your
data on.
So every send operation already
has content along with context.
And so the context describes how
you want to send your data.
So your Framer.Message is just a
new way to send data.
Receiving is very similar.
When you call receiveMessage,
you receive along with your
content the context that
describes how this data was
received.
And you can look using the
definition of your protocol at
the specific message values that
your protocol framer delivered
to you.
OK. I think we are ready to go
finish our tic-tac-toe game.
All right.
So we've already finished our
game protocol.
To add it into our connections,
I'm going to go back to the
parameters that Eric set up
earlier.
So he already set up our
connections to use TCP and TLS
with our passcode.
Now, all I need to do is just
add these two lines in.
We're going to create some
options based on my game
protocol definition and just
insert them into the array of
application protocols I want to
use in my connection.
Now when the connection starts
up between those two devices, it
will be ready to start encoding
messages over that stream.
Now I'm also going to do a
couple convenience functions
within my connection to make it
easier for my application to
send and receive my custom
message types.
So here I have a connection
object that sets up an
NWConnection using the
parameters that we just defined.
Whenever the connection becomes
ready, it's going to start
receiving messages from the
peer.
So we need to receive next
message and implement this.
So what I'm going to do here is
take my connection and call
receiveMessage on it.
I'm going to get the content
along with the context.
So I'm going to take that
context and look at the specific
metadata for my protocol, the
game protocol definition.
And that will give me my message
object and allow me to deliver
the message type along with the
data up to the application.
And then of course once I've
successfully received one
message, I'm going to call
receiveNextMessage to do it all
over again.
I'm also going to define some
helpers for sending.
So whenever the application
decides that the player is
selecting a character, we can
create a message and add the
selected character type to it,
add that on to our context and
send it.
I can do the same thing for
sending a move, have a
convenience here to say that I
wanted to send a move, and then
just take the application data
and send it down the connection.
So that's all we need to do.
I think we're ready to play the
game and I think we're going to
need some help to this.
So Eric, come back on stage.
All right.
So here Eric had already started
hosting a game but I want to be
the one hosting this one.
Here we go.
So Eric, how about you type in
that passcode, 5176.
Don't tell anyone [laughter].
All right.
So now we have a secure
connection set up.
It's using TLS.
And when Eric selects a
character-- he chose birds--
he's sending the select
character message across and I
call receiveMessage over here, I
receive that he selected that,
I'm going to choose to be
monkeys, why not.
At this point, Eric will select
a box to play and choose a
character.
All right.
So he sent the move message over
to me.
I can receive a message.
I get that it's a move.
I know where he's placed it and
I can decide, all right, there's
a monkey up in the top corner,
what's he going to do next?
Uh-oh, he's looking like he's
racing for the win.
I don't know.
I can't look at this.
Tic-tac-toe is hard.
It sounds like birds got the
day.
But as you can see, it's really
easy to build this type of game
and there's hopefully a lot more
nuanced games you can build with
this and lots of other
applications.
So we're really excited to see
what you do.
[ Applause ]
All right.
So before I move on, I want to
make one last comment about
framing protocols.
So, many of you have been asking
how you can use techniques like
STARTTLS with your
NWConnections.
So STARTTLS is a technique that
comes from the SMTP mail
protocol.
And it allows you to talk to a
legacy server that you don't
know whether or not it supports
TLS and secure connections and
do an initial handshake with it.
And then if TLS is supported,
you can add it part way through
your connection.
Now there wasn't a good way to
do this before, but framing
protocols gives you a great
solution.
So, if you create a STARTTLS
framing protocol and add it into
your connection, when your
application starts, you can
begin a handshake with the
server to determine whether or
not it supports TLS.
And then we allow you to
dynamically add in other
protocols onto the stack above
your framing protocol before you
call ready.
This way the application can
remain unchanged and not have to
worry about adding TLS part way
through.
It can just happen automatically
with your framing protocol.
So we think it's a really
elegant solution.
All right.
Let's move on.
So, we've talked about Bonjour,
how we can make better
peer-to-peer connections and use
wide-area discovery.
We talked about framing
protocols.
But now I want to take a bit of
a step back and look at how you
can collect metrics about the
connections within your app.
So collecting metrics is really,
really critical.
It allows you to validate that
when you add new features into
your app or onto your server
that are supposed to help you
get better performance that
they're really doing it, like
you're having the effects that
you want.
But it also helps you identify
problems that your users may be
encountering out in the real
world that you don't notice on
your desk.
So this year, we have a lot of
great new metrics to help you
analyze your connections even
more.
URLSession already has many
fantastic metrics but you'll be
able to get even more.
And for the first time in
Network.framework, you will
inspect your connections to
understand many aspects of their
performance.
So in URLSession, you can
already get a timing breakdown
of DNS, TCP, TLS, and HTTP
messages within your app.
Now you'll be able to introspect
even more connection properties
along with the amount of data
that you're sending for
individual requests and
responses.
And in Network.framework, you'll
be able to access a connection
establishment report that
summarizes everything that
happened during your connection
bring up along with data
transfer reports that allow you
to look at the performance of
individual periods of time over
your connection.
And you have multiple of these
running at the same time.
So let's start with URLSession.
As a reminder, all of the
metrics in URLSession are
available in the
didFinishCollectingMetrics
delegate call.
So, here are some of the new
things that you can access are
the endpoints of the connection,
the local and remote addresses
and ports.
You can also check out the
security properties.
Are you using TLS 1.3, the
latest most secure and most
performant version of TLS?
You can also check the path
properties.
So, this tells you things like
did your connection use a
constrained low data mode
network, or did you use an
expensive cellular network?
The equivalent metrics within
Network.framework are in the
establishment report.
So this is available to you any
time after your connection has
moved into the ready state.
And this gives you a breakdown
if your DNS times, your protocol
handshakes for TCP and TLS, as
well as whether or not you used
a proxy.
Here's how it looks in code.
So you take your connection and
you call
requestEstablishmentReport.
And this takes a queue on which
it will deliver the report.
Once you have that you can check
the overall time that the
connection took.
You can check the individual
resolution steps.
So if you were connecting by a
Bonjour name, it may be
resolving Bonjour names into
host names and host names into
addresses, and you can look at
the timing breakdown on each of
those steps.
And you can also look at the
individual timings for a TCP,
TLS, as well as the round-trip
times they observed.
One point that I want to
highlight that's really
important to the overall
performance of your connection
establishment is the amount of
time that it takes to resolve
DNS and the source of where your
DNS resolution came.
So, many servers have a very
short time to live configured on
their DNS records.
And they do this such that if a
server goes down or the server
wants to load balance over
another IP address, it can
quickly change the IP address
record and have clients adjust
and start using the new address.
The downside, though, is that
this really can hurt client
performance.
With a short time to live, a
client will almost always have
to take the round trip to do
DNS, to request the address for
the host name that you are
connecting to.
And this can be particularly bad
for clients that have a high
latency link.
This is going to add hundreds of
milliseconds or even seconds on
to their connection times.
And the worst part is most of
the time, the server address has
not changed at all, and so this
is a wasted round trip.
So, optimistic DNS is a solution
that we released last year that
solves this problem.
Optimistic DNS allows your
connection to optimistically
connect to the last known good
IP address for that host name,
in parallel with issuing a new
query for the host name's
current address.
If nothing has changed, which is
almost always the case, the
connection will just establish
to the old IP address.
But if something has changed
you'll still get the new IP
address and connect to it
instead.
We have been doing a lot of
measurements on this and testing
and it is a really great
solution.
And so this year, it is on by
default for connections using
Network.framework and
URLSession.
When you're looking at your
establishment report, you can
tell whether or not you used
optimistic DNS by looking at the
source.
And if it says it's from the
expired cache, that means we
ended up using and benefiting
from optimistic DNS.
I want to show you a bit how you
can use metrics to look at the
performance of your connections
and the benefit of optimistic
DNS and TLS 1.3.
OK. So here I have an
application that's a very basic
app to collect connection
metrics.
All it does is run a probe to a
given website.
All right.
So here it is.
I clicked Run Probe and I
connected and it's pretty fast.
I'm doing this on a great Wi-Fi
network.
But if you want to test a more
realistic scenario or see the
effects of different network
conditions, you are now able to
within the devices and
simulators panel of Xcode access
device conditions and simulate
different network link
conditions.
So you can see what it's like
potentially for your users in
different scenarios [applause].
Yes, it's great.
So let's see what it looks like
to have a high latency DNS link.
So I clicked Start and you can
tell that it's running because I
have this gray box up in the
upper left hand corner.
So now, let's run that probe
again.
So it was fast.
That's great.
But you'll notice that it came
from the expired cache.
So this means that we ended up
using optimistic DNS.
So optimistic DNS is on by
default but you-- we let you
turn it off if you don't think
it's appropriate for your
server.
So let's run the probe again.
You can feel the seconds go by.
So, this is potentially a bit
exaggerated.
Hopefully your users don't have
three seconds of DNS latency but
it can make a huge difference.
Let's go to a bit more realistic
scenario now, something like an
average 3G network.
I'm going to start this and run
the probe one more time.
So it wasn't quite as snappy as
the first time I ran it.
Overall you can see that I have
about 600 milliseconds for the
connection to establish.
And TLS alone took around little
bit less than 300 milliseconds,
so about half of that time.
So our server is configured to
support TLS 1.3.
Now TLS 1.3 generally only takes
one round trip to do the full
handshake.
It's great improvement.
But if your server doesn't
support TLS 1.3, if it only
supports TLS 1.2 or if you're
using an API on your app that
doesn't support TLS 1.3, you may
see scenarios more like this in
which TLS alone is now taking
over 500 milliseconds, taking an
extra round trip.
And you can see that the
connection time is almost-- it's
over three-quarters of a second,
almost at a second.
And if you have many
connections, this can really add
up to perceivable user latency.
So we encourage you that
whenever you're testing your
app, do a run through network
link conditioner and try out
some of these scenarios and
validate that your app performs
well.
So the other category of
metrics, have to do with the
data transfer after the
connection is established.
So in URLSession, you are now
going to be able to access more
metrics about the number of
bytes that you sent in the
header and the body of your
requests as well as the number
of bytes that your receive in
the headers and bodies of your
responses.
And this is really important if
you are choosing a different URL
to download less data in a low
data mode network scenario, use
this to validate that you're
actually saving your user's
bytes.
In Network.framework, you can
now access a data transfer
report that summarizes the
performance in terms of bytes
and packets and round trip times
for a given period of time on
your connection.
You can have multiple of these
running at the same time and
they should correspond to your
application's activity.
So if you send a burst of
traffic, have that be within a
data transfer report.
And it's not as interesting to
take reports of idle periods.
The way that you do this is that
at any point you can call start
data transfer report on your
connection.
This begins gathering data about
your connection's performance.
And when you're done sending a
bunch of data, you can call
collect.
This will summarize all of the
data and give you a report.
Now, if you're using multipath
protocols, this will give you a
breakdown of the amounts that
were sent over each link that
the multipath protocol was
using.
But many of you may be
interested just in the aggregate
path report.
Here you can look at the number
of packets that you sent and
received, the number of bytes
that were transferred, as well
as the round-trip time details
that you observed.
So this is metrics we were
really excited to see people
adopt more metrics and help
improve the performance of their
apps.
And to leave us with some great
advice and new updates, I'd like
to invite Stuart up to the
stage.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Tommy.
It is my pleasure and privilege
to present the wrap-up for what
has been two hours of really
great networking information
from my fellow presenters.
I'm going to start off with iPad
apps for Mac.
I know a lot of you are excited
about this.
When it comes to networking,
there are very little
differences on Apple platforms.
One thing you will want to be
aware of is in your Xcode
settings, when you check the box
for Mac, you will now see some
new options.
By default, outgoing connections
are allowed but if you want
incoming connections for your
app as well, you have to check
that box.
On watchOS, we have new
networking capabilities.
Applications that do audio
streaming using AVFoundation can
now use direct networking, as
long as they're using URLSession
or Network.framework.
Sockets is not available.
We are also introducing TLS 1.3
which gives you lots of
benefits.
TLS 1.3 has better connection
performance.
TLS 1.2 typically has two round
trips to set up a connection.
TLS 1.3 almost always does it in
one round trip.
TLS 1.2 used cryptographic
algorithms that were believed to
be good at the time but have
since been shown type of
weaknesses.
And this is not just an academic
concern.
These have been exploited in
practice.
Those have all been removed in
TLS 1.3 and all the
cryptographic algorithms in TLS
1.3 support authenticated
encryption with associated data
and forward secrecy.
And finally, you all know that
privacy is very important to
Apple.
TLS 1.3 has much better privacy.
Many of their header fields and
certificates in TLS 1.2 was sent
in the clear.
Those are now all encrypted in
TLS 1.3.
So, the call to action is start
using TLS 1.3 on your
applications and of course, make
sure your servers are updated to
support TLS 1.3 too.
Now, you all know the importance
of privacy to Apple.
And one of the things we
realized is that accessing Wi-Fi
information can be used to infer
locations.
So starting now, to access that
Wi-Fi information, you will need
the same kind of privileges that
you need to get other location
information.
The first step is in Xcode you
have to add the capability to
access Wi-Fi information to add
the entitlement to your project,
and then your app must meet one
of three other criteria.
If the user has given your app
location access, then you can
access the Wi-Fi network
information.
If your app is the currently
enabled VPN app on the device,
you can access the information.
And finally, if your app is in
any hotspot configuration app,
then it can also access the
information but only for the
networks that it has configured.
For more information you can
also see the Wi-Fi framework.
You've heard many times today
I'm going to finish with a
reminder about the importance of
using the network link
conditioner.
It's very easy when you're
developing your application in
the simulator on a Mac with
gigabit ethernet in it or
talking to a local server on
loop-back.
When you have a server with zero
latency and infinite bandwidth,
it's not surprising that it
performs well.
But if you build your
application that way, it can be
very misleading and you can find
out later when your app is in
the hands of real users that it
doesn't perform very well.
If you get in the habit of going
to device conditions and
selecting a realistic network
link condition, right from the
start when you're developing
your application and always test
and run your application
simulating realistic network
conditions, then those bugs will
not even happen in the first
place.
Another message we've been
giving you for many years is to
avoid pre-flight checks.
Using constraints such as allow
cellular or allow expansive
networks gives you much better
control.
It's much easier to use.
Once you start writing your apps
this way, you'll wonder why you
ever did pre-flight checks.
And besides, pre-flight checks
can never work reliably because
they always have raised
conditions.
So to illustrate that, I'm going
to use an example.
This is an app that I really
like.
And to illustrate this, I've
given them a deliberately
exaggerated example of what it
might do if it was a badly
written app.
This is telling the user to make
sure that we're on Wi-Fi then
click the button.
But the user has no way to
control what path the network
connection will take, what they
will typically do is look for
the Wi-Fi bars and hope for the
best.
But as you learned today,
knowing in advance how Wi-Fi is
going to perform until you try
is impossible.
And the device may think it's on
Wi-Fi but when it tries to use
it, it turns out not to work.
Now, when Wi-Fi Assist switches
you from Wi-Fi to cellular,
those Wi-Fi bars will disappear
but by then it's too late, your
connection has already happened.
So, don't make the user guess.
Don't just make connections and
hope for the best.
Let me show you how this
application actually works.
It makes its connections
constrained to not allow
cellular access.
And starting in iOS 13, it can
actually use the
allowsExpensiveNetworkAccess
control to let the system decide
which is an expensive network.
It also sets
waitsForConnectivity equals
true.
That means the application
doesn't have to retry
repeatedly.
The system will just wait
patiently for as long as it
takes for that connection to
succeed.
When the application tries to
connect, if there is no Wi-Fi,
its taskIsWaitingForConnectivity
delegate gets called and that's
when it can display UI giving
the user the choice either move
to somewhere with Wi-Fi or you
can press the button if you want
to go ahead and use cellular
data.
Some news about deprecations.
If any of you are still using
PAC files using the file or FTP
URL schemes, those are no longer
supported.
If any of you are still using
SPDY, SPDY was a great
experimental protocol, that has
now been replaced by HTTP 2,
that's what Apple supports and
that's where everything should
be moving towards.
And Secure Transport does not
support TLS 1.3 and it will
never support TLS 1.3 so another
reason to move to URLSession or
Network.framework.
So to wrap up, this morning we
talked about wide-area Bonjour
discovery and how to advertise a
tic-tac-toe game.
Some of you may have wondered if
that service type underscore
tic-tac-toe was registered with
Ayana.
The answer is yes it is, you can
check on the website [laughter].
Tommy talked about building
framing protocols and collecting
metrics that make it easier for
you to write your applications
and make it easy for you to
measure performance.
And this morning, we talked
about low data mode that lets
you respect your user's wishes
about when to conserve data.
We talked about combining
URLSession which is a great way
to chain asynchronous operations
together.
And we talked about WebSocket.
If you have web-based
applications that use WebSocket
to talk to the server, you can
now use that same server with
your native iOS apps.
And Christoph Paasch told us all
about mobility improvements with
multipath TCP and Wi-Fi Assist.
And on that note, many of you
will know that ACM SIGCOMM is
the world's leading academic
conference for network research.
And every year they have the
Networking Systems Award that
recognizes the work that's had
the biggest impact in the area
of networking.
And this year, today, they
announced that this year's award
goes to Christoph Paasch and the
rest of the team for multipath
TCP.
[ Applause ]
We would love to see you all
tomorrow in the networking lab.
And if any of you are currently
writing network kernel
extensions, definitely go to
tomorrow's session about network
extensions for modern macOS.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]