[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Hey, everyone.
My name is Lauren.
>> And I'm Doug.
>> And we're on the Design
Evangelism Team.
On Monday night, we hosted the
Apple Design Awards and we
honored some of the best apps
and games that we saw this year.
>> Each year we're really
inspired by the work the
developer community does on our
platforms.
And we're excited to show you
the apps and games tonight.
So we almost called this
session, How to Win an Apple
Design Award, because we get
asked about it a lot.
>> Yeah, and we totally
understand why people would ask
this question, right?
>> Totally makes sense to wonder
what goes into the selection of
just a few apps and games.
>> So are there any criteria
behind the apps and games that
we selected?
>> Sure. Are we going to talk
about those criteria today?
>> Well, we're actually going to
talk about something that is
much more compelling and useful
to you.
>> So we're going to talk about
the values that are behind these
apps and games.
>> Each app and game really
delivers elements of all of
these.
But we're going to take you on a
journey behind the scenes of the
award-winning apps and games.
>> And we're going to tell you
short stories about the design
processes and methods that went
into each one.
In each story we're going to
tease out some lessons.
>> So let's dive right in.
>> Innovation.
>> It's sort of an obvious place
to start maybe, but there were
some really innovative apps and
games this year.
So each of these apps that we're
going to talk about brings out a
different dimension of
innovation.
>> All right, so let's start
with Asphalt 9.
Asphalt 9 is a racing game with
an innovative new control scheme
and to best explain it, I just
think we should check it out.
Three, two, one.
In Asphalt 9, you focus on item
and path selection with swipes,
just like this.
And you tap and hold that gives
you nitro and boost action.
Now drifts and nitro are the
main actions of acceleration and
braking in this game.
Now this is not a
driving-assisted.
It's an entirely new way to
play.
And this new control scheme is
called TouchDrive.
But what makes TouchDrive so
innovative?
Because it subverts our
expectations of racing game
controls.
To do this, the developer
questioned basic assumptions
that we all have taken for
granted.
They questioned the assumption
that driving controls required
acceleration, braking and
turning.
So they started completely from
scratch.
This led to an exciting idea.
After being challenged to figure
out a simplified and more
accessible control scheme for
iOS, the developer tried this
crazy idea that moves the main
controls away from acceleration
and braking to nitro and drift
actions.
They quickly realized there was
something special there because
it helped players get into the
fun so much faster.
But they were not done shaking
things up yet.
Asphalt 9 knew that traditional
turning as a player control was
very prone to player error.
So after rounds of testing and
feedback, they replaced
traditional path -- excuse me,
they replaced turning with path
and item selection through swipe
gestures.
And this made people less
frustrated, because it helped
people focus on learning the
very elaborate tracks and play
more strategically.
So TouchDrive has now become the
default control scheme for
strategic racing, fine-tuning
and level recon.
Now full manual controls are a
matter of surgical precision and
are still available.
But what I love is that this
developer took an informed risk.
After iterating, testing and
getting feedback, the design
decision to diverge from
traditional driving controls has
allowed for an entirely new
experience to emerge.
And the innovation of TouchDrive
has revealed an entirely new way
to play the game.
So during your app design or
game design process, question
assumptions from the start.
Ask questions.
Ask, "Why are we doing it this
way?"
Is it because we've just always
done it this way?
And convert problems into ideas,
just like the problem of
error-prone turning led to new
path selection in Asphalt 9.
Because when you do, you can
create something that has never
been done before.
This game is so much fun.
And that is truly innovative.
>> Okay. Let's stay on the theme
of crazy car stunts.
No, actually, let's stay on the
theme of simplification, making
things easier.
>> What could be simpler than
jumping over the Golden Gate
Bridge with a single swipe?
>> Oh my God, wait till I show
you this.
>> All right.
>> So I want to talk about
HomeCourt.
HomeCourt is an app that uses
your iPhone camera and ML models
to help you become a better
basketball player.
The app works so naturally and
so effortlessly because the
HomeCourt team focused on
removing obstacles to getting
started with each of your drills
and workouts.
And I want to show you how they
did it.
So here's the HomeCourt app.
Like I said, it uses the camera
and machine learning to chart my
shots on a basketball court.
Before this app came along,
people just didn't have access
to this information.
You really needed someone to
manually chart it, each make and
miss.
You could also install an entire
system in your gym to do it, but
you couldn't really do it as
easily as HomeCourt makes it.
So how do you get this
information just by using your
iPhone?
When I tried it, it feels like
magic.
And I wanted to know how they
got there.
So I asked them to tell me where
they started and where this all
came from.
And the founder actually started
out by saying, "When we first
launched, the experience was
actually not magical."
So to get information from
HomeCourt you had to go through
a series of steps.
The first one was to put your
phone in a tripod.
I don't know how many basketball
players are here, but if you
play basketball, I'm guessing
you don't go to play basketball
with a tripod in your gym bag.
So you know, it's clear that
bringing the tripod is an
obstacle, right?
It's something you had to
remember to bring and set up.
And that wasn't the only
obstacle.
You needed equipment and you
needed to do manual work to set
up the app.
Two of the requirements early on
related to lighting.
The app worked best when the sun
was directly overhead on a super
sunny day.
You know, but other than that.
So the HomeCourt team went to
work and they tried to automate
as much as possible using the
camera and machine learning
models.
The first thing they did was
find a way to detect the hoop.
And then they were able to
detect the three-point line.
So this line is in different
places in different kinds of
courts, so this allowed them to
better detect courts in
different countries.
So more and more people were
able to use it at this point.
And this also allowed them to
begin to locate the shot a
little more precisely.
So they've removed some of the
manual work.
You didn't have to tap on the
screen to identify the hoop
anymore and you didn't have to
draw a rectangle around the
lane.
Next, they found a way to detect
legs.
This allowed people to use the
app in almost any lighting
conditions.
So you could use HomeCourt on a
cloudy day.
Soon after that, they kind of
upgraded to full pose
estimation.
So this is detecting all the key
body joints, and this helped
them even more accurately map
where the shot originated.
So they're making progress,
right?
They're simplifying it, but you
still had to bring the tripod.
Until they created a mode that
allowed you to set the phone on
the ground.
So this removed the final
obstacles, and I want to show
you how that last part happens.
So now you can start tracking
your shots just by propping your
phone up against a water bottle,
walking to the free throw line.
And shooting a free throw.
Aw.
>> Aw.
>> Never could get one.
[ Laughter ]
So it might not have been
magical at first, but when you
do it now, it feels like magic.
And there's tons of machine
learning at work, but you don't
see it.
You're not -- it's not right in
your face.
It doesn't feel that way.
And with HomeCourt you get
access to information you've
never had before.
And the app feels like an
extension of what you already
do.
But it's been taken to another
level.
So it fits in the flow of your
shooting practice, but gives you
more.
So the innovation here is
probably obvious.
It's a matter of simplifying
down to what people want to do,
fitting into the natural flow of
their real life.
And providing value without
getting in the way.
>> That's so awesome, Doug.
I actually want to go play some
basketball later.
>> Let's go do some shooting.
So these apps and games really
pushed the boundaries.
>> And the best kind of
innovation is the kind that you
don't even notice, right?
>> Exactly, when they just make
the experience simple and
better.
>> And truly, anything that
helps a person feel more
confident in using it is great.
>> Speaking of confidence, let's
go on to the next one, Trust.
And I want to talk about how an
app or a game can establish
trust with the people who use
it.
And I'm going to use Pixelmator
Photo as an example of this.
So this is a photo editor
designed specifically for iPad
and it also uses machine
learning, but it's doing it
trained on millions, literally
millions of professional photos
to make photo editing awesome
and easy.
And I want to show you how they
do it.
So I want to start by saying
machine learning is popping up
everywhere, but user experiences
that are informed by machine
learning can sometimes feel a
bit like black boxes.
You might often wonder, you
might sometimes wonder, maybe
often, "Why am I seeing this
content?
What forces are at work?
Why is the app showing me this?"
And there are also controls that
claim to do magic things, but
these can feel unpredictable and
random.
And so when things are hard to
understand or hard to predict,
it can be hard to trust them.
So I want to show you Pixelmator
Photo and how they handle it.
I'm going to take a walk on the
beach here.
So on the surface, the UI is
pretty conventional.
There are tools in the
navigation bar and there are
base photo adjustments in the
inspector and presets along the
bottom.
The core of any kind of power
tool is the inspector, and in
Pixelmator Photo this is where
the base adjustments live.
So these will be familiar to
photo geeks and experts, but
most people don't really know
what any of those do, and they
can frankly be a little
intimidating.
But the magic of Pixelmator
Photo is a single button, and it
allows you to apply the
expertise of thousands of
professional photographers to
your photo with one button.
There, I did it.
You'll see it again.
So when you tap that button,
Pixelmator Photo is actually
adjusting your photo with a
model that's been trained on 20
million professional photos.
So the work behind the button is
astounding and the results are
pretty incredible.
In the UI, they're using a
familiar control you might have
seen before, the Magic Wand.
And Magic Wands in UIs typically
mean don't worry about it, we
know what we're doing.
It's going to be awesome.
But from a user point of view,
you're not exactly sure what's
happening when you tap that
button.
So when I ask the developers
about this, about their choice
of icon here, they kind of
agreed that Magic Wands were
often underwhelming, right?
The results felt simplistic or
cookie-cutter.
So in order for this control to
work and to be trusted by
people, they wanted to make sure
that the adjustments in the
photo were clearly reflected in
the UI.
So what's happening kind of
behind the scenes is that their
models are identifying segments
of content inside the frame.
Water, sand and sky are detected
and treated independently, and
skin tone is as well.
But what makes this experience
so much different in my opinion
is how clearly the parameters
animate when the control is
activated, and the ease with
which I can go in and
independently adjust any of
them.
So check out how it's increased
the exposure of the landscape
while leaving the skin tone
alone.
And I can flip the switch to
deactivate them and then when I
reactivate it, my adjustments
are still there.
So it seems simple but it's
pretty remarkable when you use
it and you feel the sense of
confidence as you begin to
adjust and edit the photo.
So being able to see this as I
do it provides a sense of
comfort.
I can see what's happening when
I tap the Magic Wand and I can
go in and make my own
adjustments.
So there's a fancy word kind of
for this in user experience
terms and it's attribution.
I can see cause and effect.
I can visually connect the
effect of tapping the Magic Wand
to the series of independent
adjustments that's happening as
a result of it.
And this is empowering, right?
Pixelmator Photo is revealing
its intelligence to me and also
offering levers to adjust it
myself.
So you can trust an app when the
way that it works feels
transparent and when you can
establish a simple understanding
of what's happening.
So if I can understand or even
better visualize what's
happening, I'm much more likely
to trust it and to take
ownership over those results.
So you want to reveal what's
behind a recommendation and
offer ways to adjust it.
So that pretty much wraps up
trust.
>> Okay. Sounds good.
On to refinement.
Now refinement is more than just
working out problems.
Refining something means that
you're going to fine-tune it,
hone it and make it more
precise.
Refining something means you're
going to make it better.
The Gardens Between is a game
with dream-like levels, soothing
art style and a heartwarming
story.
You have the power to go
forwards and backwards in time,
and you relive these experiences
of these two main characters
while solving puzzles.
I am blown away by the artistry
and cleverness in this game.
And I've always just been really
curious in how the developers
arrived at this truly unique
concept.
So I asked the developers and I
hoped that they would be willing
to share a few design artifacts
that they created along the way
while making The Gardens
Between.
And I expected to see a few
familiar things that reminded me
of the game.
But I didn't.
I was shocked to see that the
design artifacts didn't look
like the game at all.
These images reveal that The
Gardens Between started in a
very different place, in a place
of fairy tales with moments
showing Snow White about to eat
the poisoned apple.
Or Sleeping Beauty right as
she's about to fall into a curse
of deep sleep.
Other design artifacts showed
lost characters and some very
different appearances of the two
main characters named Arina and
Frendt.
And various iterations on
concepts for blocked paths and
experiments with onscreen
controls.
As I flipped through all of
these design artifacts, it
became really clear to me the
creative exploration that these
developers put into making the
game that we love today.
There are tons of different
styles and tones and directions
and perspectives that were all
considered.
Now I know this is a game
example but exploring ideas in
your designs applies to apps
too.
All of these amazing design
artifacts really show the power
of refinement, what can happen
when you take the time to truly
explore your ideas.
To stretch them, to think them
through over time and to distill
them down to their very essence.
Now I love this quote by Carlton
Cuse.
I'm going to paraphrase it a
bit, but it's basically saying
that the creative process is not
like getting struck by
lightning.
Along the way you must allow
yourself room for ideas to
blossom, take root and grow.
So when you take the time to
fully think through your ideas,
you may discover new ones and
then you can validate designs by
refining them and in turn this
gives people a sense of depth.
And that really shines through
the final experience in your app
or game.
Refined designs feel considered
and they also feel thoughtful.
But this all takes time.
You can't rush this.
And iteration is really helpful
and also it's helpful for you to
explore really wild directions
in order to discover your
conclusion.
Now I really love that these
developers were so open to
sharing this incredible
transformation of this beautiful
game between two friends.
And you can feel all of the time
and effort that they put into
honing this experience.
And this experience is what we
feel in the end result.
Award-winning apps and games
rarely start with the same
designs they finish with.
And that's because great designs
are refined over time.
And through this process the
very best ideas are surfaced.
So take your time; explore and
sit with your ideas because you
may discover new ones through
the process of doing your own
work.
And by refining your designs,
you're going to be able to
justify every design decision in
your app or game, and as soon as
you can justify those decisions,
you know that you're much closer
to the final result that you've
been working towards the entire
time.
So all great apps and games go
through the process of
refinement.
>> You know, Lauren, we actually
have another great example of
refinement.
I want to talk about Butterfly
iQ.
Butterfly iQ is actually more
than an app.
It's portable ultrasound system,
and the system itself is super
innovative.
A handheld ultrasound device and
an app that runs on iPhone,
that's what makes it up.
So traditional ultrasound
devices are gigantic.
Really big.
They're big.
They have to be wheeled around
on a cart and plugged in.
They have dozens of knobs and
dials and buttons on them.
So you can really see in
Butterfly iQ how the portability
of their system can create a
whole new way for doctors to use
them.
And I want to show you how the
Butterfly iQ team refined their
ideas to get to something that
really works for doctors.
So when a doctor is using the
system, their attention is
actually split.
In one hand they have the device
that they're orienting on the
patient, and at the same time
they're referring to the phone
screen.
So they need to be able to
operate both one-handed.
The app serves as kind of a
visual stethoscope.
And the doctor needs to be able
to quickly refer to and adjust
the imagery and then to also
access contextual tools to make
measurements and notes.
In their early demos, they
created controls that mirrored
the controls from the ultrasound
cart with the idea that this
would feel familiar to doctors.
So the two values on the right
tell you how deep you're
looking.
That's the depth.
And the amount of contrast
you're applying, that's the
gain.
And they borrowed the behavior
of these buttons from the knobs
on the cart when doctors would
interact with them.
So in the early version, the
doctor would spin these controls
like the dial in a cart and the
dials in the phone in doing this
kind of matched the behavior
that the Butterfly iQ team
thought would be very familiar
and very comfortable.
So in UI terms, they're kind of
implementing a metaphorical
dial.
And metaphors like this can be
super useful when you want to
help the person using the device
create a connection with a
real-world object.
And metaphors are all over the
place in UI's, right?
This is a metaphorical
calculator with metaphorical
buttons.
And our expectations of using
that calculator come from the
behavior that we've built up in
the real world using real-world
buttons like these.
But as the Butterfly iQ team
tested that demo, that 2016
demo, they found that a direct
translation of the dial didn't
feel right at all to doctors
because those values were taking
up valuable real estate.
So they refined it on this
theme.
They started by looking at other
apps and solved the problem --
how other apps had solved the
problem of viewing and editing
imagery.
And they drew inspiration from
the iOS Camera app.
So they considered the ways that
people expect to interact with
objects in the camera view and
the ways that controls can be
accessed via gestures.
The way that those controls
animate in and then the way that
they recede when they're not in
use.
So now in the Butterfly iQ app,
panning left and right changes
the contrast and swiping up and
down changes the depth.
So they moved the information
out of the UI and allowed it to
be accessed via gestures.
And you can notice the ruler
down the right-hand side.
So as the doctor swipes down,
that ruler extends and allows
them to have a little bit more
out-of-the-way persistent look
at the depth.
So transferring the persistent
dials from the ultrasound cart
to the app seemed like it would
establish trust and comfort.
But instead it turned out that
that information and those dials
were occupying valuable real
estate and doctors didn't need
that persistence in order to
feel confident.
So creating those metaphorical
connections can be helpful, but
there's no copy and paste when
nailing a behavior.
You have to be willing to throw
out ideas that might have seemed
like a slam dunk -- that's a
HomeCourt reference, by the way.
And you need to keep refining.
So the process of refinement
never ends.
You want to draw inspiration
from the real world, but make
sure it doesn't conflict with
the expectations that people
have in a digital UI.
And don't be afraid to throw
stuff out.
>> That's really inspiring.
>> So inspiring.
[ Laughter ]
>> But it really shows how
difficult it can be to, you
know, make something that makes
sense to people.
>> It's true.
Moving the information off the
image I think really helped
people see the image more.
>> That's awesome.
>> So having the information you
need just a quick touch away is
beautiful.
>> That's a really good segue,
Doug.
You want to switch sides?
>> Let's switch sides.
>> Okay, perfect.
Awesome. So let's talk about
beauty.
Beauty in aesthetics reflects an
attitude, a perspective and
those are apparent immediately
when you see it.
>> So we're going to talk about
three aesthetically amazing apps
and games.
Actually, these are games.
Yeah, only games.
>> Right. So style,
practicality, immersion and
cohesion in design all work to
support an app's or game's
aesthetics.
>> And even if you're an app
developer, there's definitely
something to learn from each
one.
>> Cool, so let's get started
and right away with Thumper.
Now this game is inspired by
Pinball and a little bit of
psychedelic rock.
It immerses you into this retro
game world with modern game
mechanics.
As we walk through this example,
I want you to pay special
attention to the overall
simplicity of the game UI.
And that is what's going to give
Thumper its immersive aesthetic.
[ Music ]
So right from first launch, you
are greeted with this epic title
sequence.
And it's reminiscent of classic
arcade games.
Now classic arcade title
sequences were designed to get
and keep your attention, to draw
you right in and draw you in and
not pay attention to the other
arcade screens that might be
distracting right next door.
And I want to quote the
developers for a moment.
They said, "The best ones tended
to be simple, powerful and set
the tone for the rest of the
experience."
So into the game.
Nothing competes with these
graphics and nothing should
because they're absolutely
beautiful and captivating.
Now check out the upper
right-hand corner.
I absolutely love how the pause
button fades away into a slash
that communicates the
affordance, and then it just
completely gets out of the way.
Now to learn this game, you jump
right in and start playing.
And the first thing you see is
Swipe Up to Jump.
And the game answers the
question when with the 3, 2, 1
animation before you even have
time to ask.
And to reinforce that gesture, a
subtle arrow swipes up in the
direction only when the player
should actually swipe.
And also the sound design
informs you when to swipe too.
So let's listen.
[ Game sounds ]
Awesome. All of this together
makes for a really great
onboarding experience that's
effective, unobtrusive and
immersive.
So let's turn it down and focus
on the visuals again.
Now to keep you in this deeply
engaging experience, scores and
metadata are only shown at
checkpoints.
If you're planning to create an
immersive app or game, avoid
having too much text onscreen or
different buttons that could
clutter the interface.
The goal with the immersive
experience is to help people
stay concentrated and present in
the current moment.
Now I love that these developers
kept it really simple and they
created this beautifully
immersive experience.
In Thumper, vitality is not in a
HUD.
Instead, it's on the actual
beetle itself which shows full
wings at full health, no wings
at half health, and that's it.
Now you feel the consequences so
much more deeply with this
effect.
And this design decision also
helps you stay focused on the
beetle in the track, which is a
part of the game.
This game also has a great feel,
and that's because the
developers designed the controls
from the ground up for iOS.
It's approachable for beginners
but it's also challenging enough
for the most dedicated mobile
gamer.
Just watch for a few seconds.
[ Game sounds ]
Okay. Wow.
So what is the benefit to
immersion?
Well, the benefit is that you
don't have to second-guess your
swipe, tap or hold.
You know if you make a mistake,
well, it's on you.
Thumper Pocket Edition captures
your attention.
It captivates your senses and it
lures you in through its unique
aesthetic to create an
absolutely beautiful and
immersive experience.
>> So aesthetics can be
captivating and immersive, but I
want to highlight the practical
benefits that they can have as
well.
And I want to show you a game
called ELOH.
ELOH uses unique visual style in
a couple of really practical
ways.
So it's a casual puzzle game and
it combines some familiar game
elements like the bouncing balls
and the movable obstacles.
And this looks and feels very
complete, so I want to show you
where they started and how they
got here.
So this is an alpha version of
ELOH.
So you can see that the puzzle
elements are there.
The essential mechanic is there,
the sounds, and it's even got
kind of a notion of the style
with the anthropomorphic face on
the obstacle.
And this is an example of a
higher level in that alpha.
Neither of these really resemble
the first screen that I showed
you.
But it's clear that they've got
kind of the mechanic nailed in
these early versions.
So I want to walk you through
the journey that they took from
here to arrive at the game
that's on the App Store.
So the first step that the game
designer took was to hire an
illustrator.
And the illustrator explored a
color system and a graphic style
and just in looking at those
three examples, you could see
how different the game could
have been given the different
tones and styles that he
explored.
So an app or game can be
functional without being
beautiful, but the beauty that
ELOH's designer brought into the
game does more than make it look
good.
It enhances the gameplay and
brings visibility and life to
the interactive elements.
There aren't many interactive
elements in the game, so they
took care with each one, like
this button that appears when
you solve a puzzle.
And the visual detail allowed
the characters to really come
alive.
These little guys have so much
personality.
When you drag an obstacle from
place to place or when a ball
hits it, it responds.
And those small moments were
really carefully considered.
You could just tell that the
animators were thinking about
what the face should look like
when the ball hits it or when a
finger pushes down on it.
Pretty amazing.
And the team brought in a sound
designer.
The sounds feel natural.
When you succeed, the sounds are
rhythmic, and the sound adapts
to build drama and suspense
within each level and between
levels.
So ELOH's aesthetics also deepen
the experience.
They connect emotionally with
people while also reinforcing
the intent of the game.
So I want to make one more
subtle point on this.
The people that came together to
create ELOH put so much work
into the game, and I want to
talk about a subtle thing that
they did to give people a chance
to enjoy the gameplay and the
game's beauty.
So they mentioned something
interesting when I asked where
the game came from.
They said that modern puzzle
games often fail to create
long-lasting excitement because
the only thing that happens is
that the puzzles just get harder
and harder.
What's fun about that?
Every puzzle game gets
annoyingly difficult at some
point and it's easy to just want
to quit.
But in ELOH, every once in a
while when you finish an
especially hard level, you find
out that the next one is much
simpler.
And the aesthetics rise to the
surface again and you can notice
the craft of the characters and
appreciate the rhythm of the
soundtrack.
Or turning the page.
Ah.
>> So nice.
>> Simpler.
So that's what I mean by the
aesthetics having a practical
benefit.
The design matches the intent of
the game, and the casual fun
resurfaces every so often as you
progress through 99 levels.
So we expect aesthetics to be
embodied in every element of the
app, and I want to show you one
more quick thing that I think is
awesome.
The HomeCourt team really
sweated the details with their
app icon.
The shapes in the icon clearly
draw inspiration from the
elements of a basketball court.
So a great app icon allows
people to quickly scan their
home screen and map what they
want to do to the intent of the
app.
The H and the C of HomeCourt
emerge from the boundary lines
of the basketball court.
And the background is a clear
call-out to the orange of a
basketball.
>> That's pretty cool, Doug.
>> Right?
>> Yeah. But I don't remember
HomeCourt being in our agenda to
be talking about aesthetics.
>> Yeah.
>> We were supposed to be
talking about Thumper, ELOH and
Ordia.
>> What more is there to say?
[Laughs]
>> Well, I just want to make
sure we have time to talk about
how aesthetics can create
something that feels really
cohesive.
And that aesthetics can give an
app a perception of quality
through a really clear and
consistent design language.
Now Ordia is a game that tells a
story about the struggles of
early primordial life.
And I just love the organic
blobbiness of everything in
Ordia, from the menus to the
transitions, levels, characters.
I mean, this blobby theme is
carried through everything in
the entire game experience.
There's also clever sound design
and haptics to create a really
rich atmosphere to enhance this
incredibly sticky world.
And every screen sticks
together.
They family really well.
Ordia's design language is
meaningful.
It helps communicate to people
what's interactive, what isn't,
and also the colors help people
know what's friendly when it's
in the game.
So to quote the developer, they
wanted to have the player always
feel like they were in the same
environment.
The same environment.
I think that's a great goal for
your app or game.
To create cohesion and
consistency between every aspect
of your design.
So your app or game also needs
to feel connected to the
platform to be truly cohesive.
So you can tell that Ordia was
designed for iOS just by taking
a look at the Share icon.
This seemingly simple design
decision makes a really big
difference in helping people
understand your app and also
making it feel at home in the
platform it runs on.
Now I know it's really hard work
to create designs that stick
together, especially when it
feels like creating an app or
game can be an endless upwards
climb.
But by creating a cohesive
design, it raises the overall
quality of your experience.
So to make your app or game
cohesive, create a consistent
design language.
Lay out every single screen
side-by-side and ask yourself,
does anything feel out of place?
And if it does, replace it with
something that families better.
And finally, cohesiveness
applies to how your app or game
runs on the platform.
And just to tie this all back to
aesthetics, in Thumper aesthetic
beauty helped create immersion.
>> ELOH shows how these
aesthetics support the intended
behavior or experience.
And aesthetics are embodied in
every element of the app, down
to its icon.
>> Nice.
And creating consistent
experience is really important
with a cohesive design language.
>> Okay.
>> And that's aesthetics.
>> Yeah. So let's go on to the
next subtle theme running
through all great apps, and
that's that they're inclusive.
So when we talk about inclusion
in design, we mean that
interfaces are usable by
everyone.
So let's go back to Pixelmator
Photo for just a moment and look
at one of the benefits of using
native components to ensure as
many people as possible can use
your app.
I want to focus on one element:
the native UI switch.
Here it works nicely as a way of
activating or deactivating
parameters.
It clearly communicates the
state of each parameter and
provides a way to remove it and
add it again without losing
work.
When I asked the Pixelmator team
about this, they said originally
they were going to bring over
the controls from their Mac app.
And while the appearance is
similar, the checkboxes don't
pop or communicate as clearly as
the switch.
And not only is the switch a
familiar iOS element, it's also
accessible.
In the Accessibility section of
the Settings app, people can
turn on labels that allow these
switches to be even more
legible.
So using standard components
creates consistency,
predictability and legibility
across apps and devices.
So Lauren, I know you have an
awesome example of inclusion as
well.
>> Yeah, totally.
I want to go back to Ordia.
Now in Ordia, every creature has
a color that communicates to the
player whether it's good, bad or
meant to aid in navigation.
The developer didn't want to
exclude anyone from being able
to understand the game, so they
support a colorblind mode for
people with partial
colorblindness.
To create this, the developers
took screenshots of the game,
applied filters to stimulate
different types of
colorblindness and then worked
on rebalancing those colors to
make them more distinct.
And they made every single
design element distinctive to
include people with full
colorblindness.
So they also tested the game in
pure monochrome.
With over 300 million people
worldwide with some form of
colorblindness, Ordia is
wonderfully inclusive.
So to get started, design for
everyone and investigate if your
app or game is inclusive and
accessible.
>> More and more Apple
frameworks and elements are made
accessible with each release, so
the more you use native
frameworks, the more people will
be able to use your app.
>> All right, we're in the home
stretch.
Hang tight.
We're going to move on to
attention to detail.
>> Attention to detail is a core
value at Apple.
It's something we strive to do
in everything that we do.
>> Meticulous and deliberately
designed apps and games are the
outcome of hard work, the desire
for perfection, and it's also a
telltale sign that the people
that created the app or game
cared about every single aspect
of the experience down to the
last pixel.
So let's talk about Flow by
Moleskine.
This is a drawing app that has a
continual horizontal canvas with
a fully customizable set of
tools.
This app has one goal and it's
to help you stay in a state of
creative flow.
Now we're just going to focus in
on one element of this app that
showcases a tremendous amount of
attention to detail.
Flow's tool and color selector
is one of the most comprehensive
and easy to use that we have
ever seen.
Now you can tell how much the
developer cared about every
aspect of this experience,
because the number of colors
feel endless.
And the interaction from
changing the hue, brightness and
saturation provides immediate
feedback.
To create this experience, the
developer spent countless hours
prototyping.
Now here's an example of a
prototype that was designed to
check the interaction
fundamentals first.
They used pure text buttons so
they wouldn't get distracted by
high-fidelity designs.
That way they could focus on the
detail of perfecting each
interaction of the tool editor.
Only after the interactions felt
good did the developers at Flow
move on to visual design.
Then they iterated to perfect
the details of each individual
tool over time.
And they simplified how unique
properties of the tool were
displayed from the nibs, colors
and labels.
And finally, I just want to call
out how animation brings this
entire experience together.
In the real world, things
transition smoothly from one
state to another.
And it's reflected beautifully
in the Tool Editor here.
Animation is so much more than a
series of screens connected by
transitions.
Really good animation reminds
people how to use your UI.
And it provides feedback and
also draws your attention
onscreen.
But that's not all.
There are over 1,400 unique
color names in this app.
And when I asked the developer
how long it took, they said, "A
while."
In addition to collecting and
sourcing these color names, the
developer sweated the details to
determine what the rules were
for each color and how it mapped
to each color value.
The tool palette with an
expansive color selection
enables creative expression.
And that stays true to the app's
goal of helping you stay in a
creative mindset.
The developer absolutely nailed
the purpose, expanse and joy of
this experience all through the
details that come together.
Now attention to detail helps
your app or game stand out.
It's all about taking the time
and being comfortable staying in
the process of designing.
And you don't want to settle for
your first idea or your first
design.
It's about being methodical.
Solve the really big problems
first, just like Flow did with
interaction in that prototype we
saw, before you move on to
adding further detail like
visual design animation.
And I love this statement from a
really good friend of mine.
At the end of the day, when
someone experiences your app or
game, they should be able to see
the developer's sweat.
>> That is kind of gross.
>> Oh come on, it's not that
gross.
>> But I think I know what you
mean.
>> Yeah, I think what they mean
is it shows that the developer
totally cared about every aspect
of the experience down to the
very last pixel.
>> So we talked about immersion,
trust -- sorry -- innovation,
trust, refinement, aesthetics,
inclusion and attention to
detail with a single example
with each award-winning app and
game.
>> But all of these apps and
games embody these qualities of
great design.
>> These developers sweated the
details and created memorable
experiences.
>> Those experiences are totally
immersive and fun.
>> And everyone, by taking risks
and staying true to a vision,
they provided access to things
that people didn't have before.
>> And all of these apps and
games are original.
There's no copy and paste in the
world of great design.
>> These innovations extended
the reach of care to millions of
people around the world.
So we want to thank the
developers who shared their
stories with us.
>> It was an honor to get a peek
behind the curtain at how you
designed your award-winning apps
and games.
>> [Together] Thank you so much
and have a great WWDC.
[ Applause ]
>> All right.