[ Music ]
>> Welcome to what's
new in tvOS.
[ Applause ]
I'm Hans, and I'm an
engineer on the tvOS team.
We're really thrilled
this year to welcome you
to the very first WWDC for tvOS.
[ Applause ]
So I'd like to begin
this afternoon
with a brief overview of tvOS.
And we'll walk you through some
of the new features of tvOS 10.
And then we'll take a few of
them and dive into more details.
And we even have
a very good demo.
So let's begin.
Just nine months ago we
launched the new Apple TV
and with it the tvOS.
tvOS is a modern
operating system designed
for modern hardware,
which is 64-bit only
with no 32-bit runtime.
So it would save you
nontrivial amount of time
that you'd spent testing
for 32-bit compatibility
or configuring for
32-bit slices.
And unlike your iPhone,
iPad, or even Mac,
the Apple TV is always connected
to a high speed network.
And this makes tvOS
an ideal platform
where you can offload some tasks
like managing your app's assets,
user data, or even your
app's content to technologies
such as CloudKit and
on-demand resources.
CloudKit is your interface
to an almost infinite
amount of storage in iCloud.
It offers a structure
storage for your assets.
It also provides a public and
private database for user data.
So as you've heard in
the previous session,
it can be accessed from
across iOS, Mac OS, and tvOS
and can also be shared.
And thanks to iCloud
authentication, you don't have
to ask your customers for
a separate login anymore.
And this is still true even if
your app happens to also run
on other platforms that
do not have CloudKit.
And by using CloudKit JS and its
web service API's you don't have
to roll your own solution
and still take advantage
of the security and efficiency.
Now, traditionally customers
had to download an entire app
to be able to launch
and start using it.
And as app grows in size,
this becomes a pain point.
Because we don't wait 800
megabytes to download for fun.
And this is not only
frustrating for the users,
but also a challenge
for us developers
because customers
may lose an interest
in our apps before they
even get to try them.
On-demand resources
takes advantage
of Apple TV's constant
connection
and provides a mechanism
by which your app can
launch even before all
of its content is downloaded.
This means for your customers,
they can use the app sooner.
And while the app
is being downloaded,
the system can continue
to download more content
so they're ready
when they're needed,
minimizing further wait time.
And also, applications can
be very large, in fact,
much larger than was
traditionally agreeable.
Let's take a look at this.
Every app has a main app bundle
of executable and
base resources.
And when using ODR, your
main app bundle can be
up to 200 megabytes.
To this you can add a first
set of content to be downloaded
with the app bundle so they're
ready when the app installs.
For example, this could be the
first three levels of your game.
This first set is called
the initial install tags,
and this can be up
to two gigabytes.
What if you have more contents?
Well, you can specific
additional sets of assets packs
to be downloaded
immediately after the install.
And this is called
prefetch tags.
And prefetch tags are
intended for content
that you know you'll need
soon but not soon enough
to justify blocking your
app's initial launch,
thereby preventing your
users from using the app.
So, for example, if your user is
playing level one of your game,
the system will start
downloading levels four,
five, and six.
And by the time the user is
completed with level three,
the next levels are
already downloaded
and waiting for the user.
So the wait has been shifted
from the user to the system.
And the system doesn't mind
waiting, but the users do.
Prefetch tags can be
up to four gigabytes,
using the rest of the allowance.
So, for example, if
you spent 500 megabytes
for initial install tags,
then you have 3.5
gigabytes for prefetch tags.
If you've spent all
two gigabytes
of your initial install tags,
then naturally you
have two gigabytes
for your prefetch tags.
What if you had no
initial install tags?
Well, math says it's
four gigabytes
for your prefetch tags.
But you might want to
move some of that content
into initial install tags
so they can be used early.
In similar way as the
app is further used,
more assets packs
can be downloaded.
And the total downloadable
content can be
up to 20 gigabytes, making the
combined size of app bundle
and downloadable content at
a whopping 20.2 gigabytes.
[ Applause ]
And this is not just a big
number, but a big number
that does not feel to the
customers heavy or tedious
because they can get started
sooner and they can continue
to use the app without
much interruption.
Transistor is a great game and
a great example of using ODR.
It has 160 megabytes of app
bundle and 500 megabytes
of initial install tags, so it
downloads and installs quickly.
But thanks to 900
megabytes of prefetch tags,
gamers are continuously
challenged with new,
gorgeous game levels without
virtually any interruption.
But ODR is not just for games.
One of my favorite
apps is Earthlapse TV.
Earthlapse TV presents
time lapse videos taken
from International Space Station
and creates a virtual window
to the space right
in your living room.
It has over one gigabyte of
super high-quality content.
And yet, it downloads
and launches quickly
and there's virtually any wait
jumping from content to content.
So that's ODR.
And that, by the way, is Canada
seen from the Cupola module.
[ Applause ]
Now, let's take a look at
how we interact with the TV.
We use our phone every day and
we're quite accustomed to it.
But it's unique in
that both our attention
and our action are
right there in front
of us on the touch surface.
When you're looking
at a TV, however,
our attention is 10 feet away
on the other side of the room
and our action is on the
remote right in our hand.
There's no direct
connection between the two.
tvOS provides a unique
opportunity
to make this experience
more direct and connected.
First is the Siri Remote.
Through its touch surface
Siri Remote enables a new
focused-based interaction
designed specifically
for this kind of environment.
By pressing buttons and using
gestures on the touch surface,
users can move focus from
one element to another,
stop on a specific one, and
click to trigger an action.
To complement this
focused interaction,
tvOS also introduces
a new parallax effect.
The parallax effect gives you
a sense of where your focus is
and also the feeling that you
are connected with the screen.
And the best way
to take advantage
of the parallax effect is
by using layered image.
A layered image is an image
type designed for tvOS,
and it increases
depth and dynamism
when an element is in focus.
It can have up to five layers
and is actually required
for the app icon.
And to create a new
layered image,
you can use Xcode's
asset catalog,
the Parallax Previewer
app for Mac OS,
and the Parallax Exporter
plug-in for Photoshop.
And of course, all of these
are available for download
at developer.apple.com.
Now, let's take a step back and
take a look at the Home screen.
The Home screen is where
this 10-foot experience is
best illustrated.
Above the first row of app icons
is an area called Top Shelf,
and apps placed on the first
row can participate in it.
Your apps can present the most
relevant features or contents
as shortcuts to the
content deep inside your app
so your customers can
jump straight to it.
And this could be, for example,
a poster for your movies,
album art for music,
banners, or really anything
that makes sense for your app.
Top Shelf is a great conduit
for bringing customers back
into your app, so
we highly recommend
that you take advantage
of it beyond providing
a placeholder image.
Now let's come back to
the Home screen again.
The Home screen is a collection
of apps you care about.
And as you've heard
in the keynote,
we believe the future
of TV is apps.
And all of this is
enabled by the App Store.
The App Store, just like on
iOS, is where you go to browse,
discover, and download apps.
And because it exists
on both iOS and tvOS,
it supports universal purchase.
So if your customer has
downloaded the app on iOS,
they can enjoy the app on tvOS
with just one button
press and for free.
And thanks to Apple TV's
constant connection,
in tvOS 10 we're
introducing auto download.
So apps downloaded on iOS will
be automatically downloaded
to the TV just like that.
So it's even easier
for your customers
to get a hold of your apps.
But how are you going
build them?
tvOS offers the same
developer tools and languages
as iOS, Mac OS, and watchOS.
And many of the same frameworks
you that already know,
such as UIKit, Foundation,
Core Animation, AVFoundation,
Core Audio, and so on and so
on are all available on tvOS.
And by the way, in tvOS 9.2
we've also brought MapKit to TV.
But this is still a partial list
of a whole lot more you
can pick and choose from.
For example, if you're
developing a game,
you'd be excited to learn
that all the game technologies
that you love are all
available on tvOS: Game Center,
Game Controller, GameplayKit,
Model I/O, MetalKit,
Performance Traders, SpriteKit,
SceneKit and many more,
these are all available
at your disposal.
And finally, tvOS introduces a
brand new high-level framework
called TVMLKit.
TVMLKit makes it
really easy for you
to build content-centric
apps by taking care
of the heavy lifting,
such as layout
and focus management, for you.
And it does so with
predefined templates for layout
and JavaScript for
application logic.
It is really great for rapidly
iteration and deployment.
And, of course, it's tuned
for great performance.
In fact, several of Apple's own
apps are built using TVML --
the Movies app.
And that's right, the App Store
itself is built using TVMLKit.
And all of the developer tools
on iOS that helped you fine-tune
and optimize your apps, such
as Unit Testing, App Analytics
and TestFlight are also
available for tvOS.
This year tvOS continues to
offer new and exciting features.
As you've heard in the keynote,
we're bringing HomeKit to the TV
so you can control
HomeKit-compatible accessories
from your TV.
We're also bringing PhotoKit
so your app can leverage your
customers' iCloud photo library.
Using SpriteKit is even easier
thanks to native support
from the focus engine.
Your movement and navigation
will feel more natural
and fully integrated with
the rest of the OS for free.
Speaking of movement and
navigation, an integral part
of gameplay is how
you control them.
You can hold the Siri
Remote vertically
as a lightweight game controller
and use gestures like swipes
and clicks for jumping, for
example, to control a game.
If your title requires
slightly more complex input,
you can hold it landscape as a
micro game pad with basic D-pads
and two-button controls.
Well, if your game title
requires even more complex
input, you can use the
extended game controllers
and as you heard in the State of
the Union, up to four of them.
You now have an option
to require the use
of MFI-based game controllers,
and the app store will
prompt the user accordingly
if it's necessary.
We're also bringing
ReplayKit to the TV.
Using ReplayKit, players can
record their gameplays locally
on device and share it
with friends via AirDrop.
But that's not all; game
players can now broadcast their
gameplays live on
services like Mobcrush.
In tvOS 10 we're also
bringing a brand new
UserNotification.framework
with iOS 10
and also
ExternalAccessory.framework
for Bluetooth accessories
from iOS.
We're also shipping a brand
new Apple TV remote app.
And finally, users can set
their system appearance
to light or dark.
And when you're actually
building apps,
you have many options.
You might want to use UIKit as
your baseline and take advantage
of all the available frameworks.
If you're already comfortable
with full native frameworks
or if you have an
existing iOS app,
we have some great sessions
this week for to you check out,
including mastering
UIKit on tvOS
where you can take your
UIKit app to the next level.
And in Focus Interaction
on tvOS,
we review the Focus system,
discuss some of the new features
on tvOS 10, and of
course, SpriteKit.
We also recommend that
you check out TVMLKit.
TVMLKit is an incredibly
rich framework.
And if your skillset already
includes JavaScript and XML,
it's really easy to use
TVMLKit to rapidly develop
and deploy content-centric apps.
And because TVMLKit is built on
top of UIKit, you can even mix
in UIKit for further
customization.
And these sessions focus on
getting the most out of TVMLKit,
and we highly encourage you
to come -- go check out.
And if you are a game
developer, of course,
all the game technologies
packaged
as GameKit might
well be your choice.
Next I'd like to switch gears
and take a deep dive into some
of the new features in tvOS 10.
And for that, I'd
like to hand it
over to my colleague,
Marshall Huss.
[ Applause ]
>> Good afternoon.
My name is Marshall.
I'm a tvOS engineer.
And today we're going to dive
into how you can implement some
of the new features
with tvOS 10.
We heard in the keynote
that there's a new
Apple TV Remote app.
We'll take a look at how
you can use notifications
to notify users when you
have new content available.
And finally, we're going to look
at how you can implement
the light/dark appearance
in your app.
So the new Apple TV Remote app
works just like the Siri Remote,
so there's no changes
that are required
for your app to make it work.
It also includes a new
Game Controller layout
so users can use
it to play games.
Now, if the user is using the
app and your app is linked
against the game controller
framework, then they're going
to get a new icon in
their navigation bar
that looks like this.
When that user taps that
icon, they'll get presented
with a Game Controller
layout that they can use
by rotating the phone.
To learn more how
to make the most use
of Game Controller framework,
we have a session coming
up later this week.
Also, as you heard, the
seed is available today.
So go download it
and try it out.
Next we're going to take
a look at notifications
and how you can use
those to notify users
when you have new
content available.
A great way of doing
this you might be used
to is badging your
application icon.
And we've added this
support for tvOS 10.
Now, like iOS you're required
to request permissions
from the user in order to
badge the application icon.
But on tvOS this looks
a little bit different.
They're going to get a
full-screen modal alert.
So make sure that you
that request permission
at an appropriate time, or this
may be the first experience the
user has with your app.
We've also added support
for remote notifications
so you can use Apple's
Push Notification service
to send remote notifications.
We support two notification
types.
Those are Badge, which we just
saw and also content-available.
Now, if your app is
in the background,
then these content-available
applications will not wake
up your app like you
might be used to in iOS.
Let's take a look
at what that means.
So say your user has
new content available.
A great way to notify them would
be to send a Push Notification
with content-available
and a Badge of 1.
If the application's
not open, tvOS will hold
onto this notification and
update the user's Badge.
Now, the user gets
more content-available,
so you can send another
Push Notification
that updates the Badge icon.
tvOS will hold onto the
latest notification and wait
for the app to come back.
And finally, you get
more content-available
and you can update
the Badge again.
When the user is ready
to go back to the app
and see what they have is
new, they can open the app.
And then we deliver that last
notification so you can go
to your servers and get
maybe any new content
that's available.
In order to support
this you have
to use the new user
notification framework.
If you've implemented
notifications in iOS before,
you might be used to
using the UIKit API's.
Well, those have been
prohibited up until now on tvOS,
and they're going to
remain prohibited.
So in order to fully
support local
and [inaudible] notifications,
you're going to need
to use the new user
notification framework.
We have a few sessions
coming up later this week
on how you can learn to fully
implement those in your app.
And finally today, we're going
it take a look at the new light
and dark appearance on tvOS.
We see that that this is a
system-wide setting to the user.
The user will determine
when they want the change
between light or dark.
Now, something to consider is
that users might have their
rooms in different environments.
It could be in a movie
room, which is dark;
it could be in a living room,
which has a lot of windows.
Or the user may change
it based on time of day.
So it's important in order
to respect your user's choice
to offer them the
best user experience.
In order to fully support
this we've added new API
on the UITraitCollection,
and you must actually opt-in
for the dark appearance.
If you don't opt-in for the dark
appearance, your app will remain
in the light just
like it did in tvOS 9.
So let's take a look at
what it takes for your app
to adopt the new light and
dark system appearance.
The first step is to add a
new key to your Info.plist;
we've added one called
UIUserInterfaceStyle.
If you set a value of Light, it
will always resolve to light.
If you set a value to Dark,
your app will always stay dark.
Or if you use what we recommend,
Automatic, it respects the user
and the system setting and will
propagate that through your app.
If you create new projects
in Xcode 8 for tvOS,
this will actually
default to Automatic.
I mentioned that there is
new API and TraitCollection.
We've added a new property
called .UserInterfaceStyle.
This could have a
value of unspecified,
which might the case if your
view has not been inserted
in the view hierarchy yet, or if
could be light or dark depending
on what the system setting is
and what your app supports.
In order to support
developers adopting this,
we've added developer
tool support
to Interface Builder
and the simulator.
If you use standard
UIKit controls,
these will actually
automatically change for you.
If you're used to using
the appearance proxy,
with a little bit
of refactoring,
you can then specify colors
depend on TraitCollection.
And if you want the
most control,
you can implement
TraitCollectionDidChange
in your views or
view controllers.
Now in Interface Builder
you can specify colors right
in the inspector
for light and dark.
We added a light and dark
preview to storyboards
so you can rapidly develop
and design your app.
We've also added a shortcut
to the simulator to be able
to quick toggle between
these system appearances.
I mentioned UIKit controls
will automatically update them.
And we use these a lot
in our own system apps.
We see that certain views like
this keyboard or text field
or [inaudible] control
automatically update their style
to look best against
the TV wallpaper.
If you use a table view like
we do in our settings app,
it will automatically adjust
its background colors,
its text color, and
everything to look good.
And if you're using the
system built-in keyboards,
than those adapt as well.
If you're looking to customize
your text, we've added support
to UILabel and UITextView,
so those will automatically
change their color as well.
Text color will be set to
black for the light appearance;
it will be set to white
for the dark appearance.
But one caveat is if you
ever set the text color,
then you're responsible
for updating that color
for both those modes
on your own.
We've also added two new
blur styles to the API.
You can now use
UIBlurEffectStyleRegular
or UIBlurEffectStyleProminent.
And we call these
automatic styles.
And they'll actually adjust
the effective blur effect style
based on what the
system setting is.
So if you use
UIBlurEffectStyleRegular
and the system's in light,
it will use
UIBlurEffectStyle.light.
If you use regular and
dark, you'll use dark.
If you use prominent, it will
use .extraLight and .extraDark.
.extraDark will be
coming in a later seed.
Now, you might customize your
app with the appearance proxy.
So you might have code like this
that sets the title
color of a button to red.
With a little bit
of refactorring,
we can vend a TraitCollection
for both light and dark.
And using the appearance
proxy API's we can set a color
for each of those
specific TraitCollections.
Now in this case our button will
use red in the light appearance
and blue in the dark appearance.
And finally, if you want the
most control over these changes,
you can respond to
them directly.
You can do this using
TraitCollectionDidChange
in your views or
view controllers.
Let's take a look at
what an implementation
of this would look like.
First we override
TraitCollectionDidChange
in our view controller.
Then we check to make sure
that UITraitCollection responds
to the new user interface
style property.
This allows us to build this
feature for our users on tvOS 10
but still support users
who might be on tvOS 9.
Next we check to see that the
user interface style actually
changed; otherwise we might be
doing more work than we need.
And finally, we can check
the user interface style
and update our controls
accordingly.
Now, one more advanced use
of this is if you wanted
to override TraitCollections.
And this might be the case
that if you want your app
to support the automatic style
but may have certain views
or view controllers in
your app that you want
to specify the style itself.
We use this in our system apps,
our product pages and our movies
and TV shows actually
use the artwork to base
on what the elements look like.
In this case we have light
artwork, so we use black text
in button styles that
make the colors pop out.
We also have dark pages where we
use white text on darker styles
and the buttons also
update accordingly.
In order to override
these TraitCollections,
we use API that was
added in iOS 8.
And this is
setOverrideTraitCollection
for ChildViewController.
In order to use this we can
use a small wrapper class.
Let's see what an example
of this might look like.
First we create a new class,
AppearanceViewController,
and we inherit from
UIViewController.
We can add a property that has
the style that we might want
to set in our
ChildViewControllers.
And then we can another property
where we actually set the view
controller in which we want
to set that style for.
Then we use a
setOverrideTraitCollection
for ChildViewController using
the style that we specified.
And finally, we use standard
ChildViewController containment.
Now, if you wanted
to use this class,
we could vend our
AppearanceViewController,
specify the style
that we want for based
on whatever attributes we want,
we can set the ViewController,
and then we can present
it to the user.
Next, I'd like to invite Brandon
up to show you what it takes
to update your app for tvOS 10.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Marshall.
Hi, everyone.
My name's Brandon,
and I'm really excited
to show you the tvOS app
that we've been working on.
It's called Fireplaces
of the World.
And fireplace enthusiasts
have been loving it so far.
Let's take a look.
This app allows to you
bring fireplace styles
from around the world
straight to your living room.
Let's see what a fireplace
from Vermont looks like.
Ahh, doesn't it feel
cozy in here?
I think this is great.
Now, even though the simulator
appearance will set to dark,
our app is using the light
appearance by default
because we haven't
specified a preference.
I'm excited to adopt
the new dark appearance,
so let's go update our app now.
The first thing we need to do is
add the new User Interface Style
key to our Info.plist.
We'll set the value to
automatic and rerun our app.
We chose automatic because
we want our app's appearance
to match the user's
appearance setting.
Okay. This is looking
pretty good so far.
So all of our standard
UIKit views have been
updated automatically.
So in this case the tab bar
and the wallpaper now
have a dark appearance.
For some of you this
might be all you need
to do to update your apps.
However, our designers
have decided
that they want a different logo
color for the dark appearance.
And the background color on the
collection view styles sticks
out a little bit too much.
So let's go make those changes.
So let's go to our
main.storyboard.
And the first thing
we need to do
because this is an
existing project,
we need to enable the trait
variations feature in Xcode 8.
So to do that, we'll go to
the File Inspector and click
on this Use Trait
Variations checkbox.
When we do that, we're
going to get a warning
that trait variations
is only compatible
with Xcode 8 or later.
And that's fine,
so we'll continue.
So now we'll click on our logo,
go to the Attributes Inspector.
And there's these
new plus buttons next
to some of the properties.
So we'll click on that and add a
darkinterface for our logo image
and we'll specify yellow.
Now, one cool feature of Xcode 8
is that you can actually switch
between the light and
dark appearances directly
within Interface Builder.
To do that we'll go to the
bottom of our storyboard
and click on this View As:
Apple TV (Light Style).
And we have two options here.
We have light and dark.
When we click dark everything
updates automatically.
So our logo changed color
and also the tab bar
and wallpaper have
changed color as well.
So that looks pretty good.
So let's go update
our background colors.
In our AppDelegate we're
setting the background color
of our CollectionViewCell
using the appearance proxy.
Now, we want the
background color
to change based on
specific traits.
So we need to use a
trait-specific appearance proxy.
So first we'll start out by
creating a UITraitCollection.
So let light equals
UITraitCollection
with a UserInterfaceStyle
of light.
Then we'll replace our
generic appearance proxy
with a trait-specific
appearance proxy.
So for TraitCollection,
and we'll pass
in the TraitCollection
we just created.
We'll do the same for dark
and specify a different
background color.
Now, because we can't view this
in Interface Builder,
we'll rerun our app.
We've added a keyboard
shortcut, so you can switch --
quickly switch between the light
and dark appearances
within the simulator.
To do that, we'll
hit Command Shift D
to switch the light appearance
and then Command Shift D
to switch back to
the dark appearance.
So that's looking
pretty good so far.
But I've noticed that the
icon is hard to see now
that we've changed
our background color.
So let's go update that as well.
So we'll go to our to custom
collection ViewCell subclass
and before we were
setting the tint color
in our awakeFromNib function.
Since we want the
tint color to change
when our TraitCollection change,
we'll override the
TraitCollectionDidChange
function.
We'll use the same
color as before
for our light interface style,
and for our dark we'll
actually use a light gray.
Now, TraitCollectionDidChange
is called each time your view is
added to a view hierarchy.
So we remove our
initialization code here.
But for backwards
compatibility reasons,
we'll just leave it in there.
Let's run our app,
see how it looks now.
Okay. That looks much better.
So let's switch to
light appearance,
make sure nothing has changed.
And that still looks good.
And we'll switch back
to the dark appearance,
and that looks great.
So we've just updated our app
to adopt a new dark appearance,
and we're ready to
ship with tvOS 10.
Now I'd like to invite
Hans back up on stage.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Brandon.
That was a very cool
demo and warm.
So as you've seen,
adopting light
and dark appearance
is really easy.
So we hope all of you can adopt
it in your apps very soon.
This afternoon we
have seen just a few
of the many features in tvOS.
tvOS offers the same tools,
services, and frameworks
that you already know so it's
really easy to get started.
And focus-based interaction,
layered images
with parallax effect and Top
Shelf, they all work together
to create a direct and
connected 10-foot experience.
And with Universal
Purchase and Auto Download,
your customers are ever-closer
to enjoying your apps.
We're also shipping a brand
new Apple TV Remote app.
And it's available as a
seed, so please download
and test your app with it.
And with ReplayKit and
SpriteKit support directly
from Focus Engine, game
experiences are even better.
And finally, users can set
their system appearance
to their liking.
We hope you're excited
by what you've seen
and you can learn even more
throughout the great many
sessions this week.
And the Apple TV
Tech Talk videos
from earlier this
year are very useful
in guiding you through
the basics.
And they're available at
developer.apple.com as well.
And of course, all this
information is available
on the session link.
Finally, we can't wait
to see the great things you
create for the future of TV.
Thank you so much for coming,
and enjoy the rest
of the conference.
[ Applause ]