[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Good afternoon and welcome.
My name is Nurinder Manj and
I'm the Engineering Manager
of TVMLKit team.
I'm here with Parry
Panesar to talk about how
to build great apps
using TVMLKit.
Now most of you here have built
one or more native apps and gone
through the hard work
of performance tuning
and optimizing user interface.
Often that means sacrificing
features or delayed shipping.
Some of you have built web
apps which offer flexibility,
dynamic updates, but the user
experience is not so great.
TVMLKit, which is a brand new
framework introduced for tvOS,
bridges the gap between these
two development choices.
When you build your apps using
TVMLKit, they are going to look,
feel, and perform
like Apple apps.
Let's get started.
Today, first I'm going to talk
about what the framework
offers you.
Next, we have sample app
built for you that is going
to demonstrate a
fully-featured TVMLKit app.
But before that, I will cover
the overview of the framework.
The latter half of the talk is
dedicated to talking about some
of the exciting new
features we are going
to introduce for tvOS 10.
Let me walk you through some
of the user interface examples.
This is an app store
app built into Apple TV,
a gorgeous iTunes movies app,
an example from Search app.
Another example is Apple Music.
In fact, all of these
apps that ship
with Apple TV are
built using TVMLKit.
And if you take a step back
to consider what are
all these apps about,
they have a common goal.
They let people browse, interact
with, and consume catalogues
of content in a simple,
consistent but unique way.
So what does the
framework offer?
The framework offers
template-based native user
interface, which is
performance tuned and optimized,
saving you both development
cost and time.
That rich and complex
user interface
that you just saw is defined
using a simple markup API
and JavaScript drives
the application.
Templates are very flexible.
You can change their appearance
and behavior using styles.
Now the framework
is not constrained
to the templates
that we provide.
You can enhance existing
Apple templates
by adding your own views
and view controllers to them
or even create brand
new templates.
You can also extend
JavaScript functionality
that is specific to your app.
And let me assure you
this is not a web browser.
It an optimized native user
experience built for tvOS.
Let's build an app.
There are three main components
that I'm going to talk
about that we are going to
need built our sample app.
First is Xcode to create and
configure the client project.
Next, I will talk about
the Markup and the styles
to configure the templates.
And last, I will talk
about the JavaScript API,
how it will drive
the application.
Now before we dig into details,
let me show you what this looks
like from an architectural
perspective.
A typical TVMLKit app is based
on a client server
architecture model,
where your client app is
a UIKit-based app running
on a tvOS device and your
server hosts the media content
and JavaScript files.
The framework offers an
application controller API
that will download the main
JavaScript file and set
up a JavaScript environment
and hand
over the control to JavaScript.
Once the control is handed
over, JavaScript is responsible
for downloading any
additional content that it needs
to present the templates
to the user.
And JavaScript is
also responsible
for handling any user events and
reacting to them appropriately.
Now the first step to
build an app is Xcode.
Xcode provides TVML application
template which will act
as a starting point
for your app.
This is the partial code that
gets generated by the template.
The first step here is to modify
the JavaScript URL to point
to your main JavaScript file.
Next step is to create an
application controller context,
associate the javaScriptURL,
and you can optionally also
specify the launch options
that will be passed on to the
JavaScript when it is launched.
And the last step is to create
an application controller
instance with the
context and window,
and that will download your main
JavaScript file, evaluate it,
and hand over the
control to JavaScript.
You can also optionally
specify the delegate
to monitor the state of your
controller, for instance
if it launched successfully
or failed.
Next let's talk about templates.
Now TVML is a Markup
specification
to define Apple-TV-specific
templates.
The Markup when presented
on the navigation stack
from JavaScript translates
into user interface.
Now once it is presented, you
can keep modifying your XML,
and those changes
will be propagated
to user interface in
a performance way.
Templates out of the
box just look right.
You don't have to do
any explicit styling.
Just fill in your content
and you are good to go.
However, you can
change the appearance
and behavior using styles
to suit your [inaudible].
In terms of Markup,
document is the entity
that wraps the templates.
This is the XML structure
representing a document.
There are two child elements.
The first is head,
which has a style,
which encapsulates all the
custom styles defined by you.
The second element is the
templateName and its content.
Each template has a unique
name and functionality.
Let's take a look at
one of these templates.
This is the Top Movies page
from iTunes Movies app.
This template allows
you to scroll
through stacks of content.
In Markup, it is called
as a stackTemplate.
In this particular example,
this template is
represented using this XML.
At the root of the template
is a collectionList element
which encapsulates various
collection types, like carousel,
shelves, grids, and
other supported types.
Now the top row here
is a carousel control
which allows horizontal
navigation of content
with the focused
one in the middle.
This control when in idle state
will auto scroll the content,
and the Markup to create
this control is simply this,
where you have a
section defined and list
of lockups with imagines.
There is no any additional
configuration required.
The row next to the
carousel is a shelf
which also allows horizontal
scrolling of content.
And the Markup to represent that
is very similar to carousel,
but shelf allows you
to specify a header
and can have one
or more sections.
Each section further
can also have a header
and must have one
or more lockups.
So what is a lockup?
A lockup is a UI control
that encapsulates image
and text elements.
This is a [inaudible],
by the way.
And going back to our example,
if you notice, only the lockup
that is focused has its
text element visible.
This is not the default
framework behavior.
This is an example of how you
can customize using styles.
Let me show you how to do this.
Here we are defining a new class
which has a highlight style
property set to the value
to marquee and show
when highlighted
and then you set this class not
the appropriate text elements
of the lockup and that
gives you this behavior.
However, this is a fairly
simple example of customization.
Let me show you a
couple of more examples.
This is a stackTemplate again.
Here we have a banner which has
a background image specified
and banner is a sibling
to collectionList.
There's a background color
specified on the template,
and the template seamlessly
blends the background color
into the banner image
giving this nice effect.
The layout for the banner title
and the button is
custom-configured using styles.
Another familiar example
is a movie bundles page.
This is also a stackTemplate.
The background image on
this template is created
by the framework by
just specifying an image
as a hero image element.
And again, the layout
for the title, the shelf,
and the buttons is
custom configured.
Now there are numerous templates
available for you to pick from.
And using styles, you can
create unique experiences
that suit your brand.
TVML Catalogue is a
great resource to browse
and interact with templates.
Please check it out.
Now as I mentioned before,
TVMLKit bridges the gap
between native and
web development.
You just saw how easy
it is to create rich
and complex user interface
by simply using Markup.
Let me show you how
the JavaScript drives
the application.
The JavaScript engine that
is provided is powered
by JavaScriptCore framework and
the built-ins in Web Inspector
to debug and performance
tune are provided.
And starting tvOS 10,
JavaScriptCore is ES6
compliant as well.
[ Applause ]
TVMLKit adds platform-specific
APIs
to help drive the application.
Now the standard web APIs like
XMLHttpRequest to transfer data
between client and server;
DOM, to parse and [inaudible],
listen for user events,
local storage,
session storage are all
provided by the framework.
In addition to that, TVMLKit
also provides platform-specific
APIs, for instance to
manage the navigation stack,
access system info,
play [inaudible] slideshow
photos, and many more.
In addition to that,
the framework also
provides very simple API
to handle media playback.
Now one important thing I
would want to point out is
that there is a single
JavaScript context per
application controller, and you
manage all of your documents
within that single context.
Let me go into details for
some of the key classes.
The first is app object.
App object provides callbacks
that you must register
and the first and
foremost is onLaunch.
This is the starting point for
your JavaScript application.
Another API I would
want to point out is
to handle errors,
which is onError.
You must provide this
callback as well,
to handle those unexpected
failure cases.
Now once the control is
handed over to JavaScript,
the first thing you will want
to do is probably
present a document.
To do so, NavigationDocument is
the class you would want to work
with here and it's equivalent
to a UINavigationController
in TVMLKit.
There is a global
instance already provided
and you can now create
new instances.
Now you're only responsible
to push the documents,
[inaudible] them as a result
of Menu gesture is
handled by the framework.
There are three main APIs that
you will be using the most.
The first two here
which is pushDocument
and replaceDocument
go hand in hand.
Let me show you a recommended
way on how to use these.
Here is a code snippet to
create a loading template.
Typically when you are
handling a user event
or launching the app, you
would want to present a Spinner
so that the users know
something is happening.
And once you have created
this loading document,
you would use pushDocument
to push it on the stack.
Now while you are waiting for
your remote data to be fetched
and prepared, later
on you would want
to replace your loading document
with your intended document.
And to do that, you would
use replaceDocument.
This is a very common
pattern, and we encourage you
to show the Spinner right away
while you are fetching the data
from the network.
And the last API is presentModal
to present alerts or errors
or actually any other
templates modally.
Now the key to TV watching
experience is video playback
and we have made
it really simple.
Let me show you how to do that.
With less than 10 lines of code,
you can configure a
fully-featured video
playback experience.
Let me walk you through
this code.
First, create a MediaItem
with the type of video
and the URL to the video stream.
You should also specify title,
artwork, URL description
so that it can be made
available in the info panel
of the video playback
experience.
Next, create a playlist and add
one or more media items to it.
And the last step is to
create a new player instance,
associate the playlist,
and present the player.
And that gives you a
fully-featured video
playback experience.
In addition to that,
all the features
like to handle interstitials,
protected content,
chapter groups, time
[inaudible] and a bunch
of other APIs are also provided
from within JavaScript
environment.
Now similar to video playback,
we have also extended the
audio playback capabilities
and doing so is very similar.
The only thing changed
here is tied to audio
and the URL to an audio stream.
And that gives you
this beautiful
and functional Audio
Now Playing experience,
which is the same
as Apple Music.
Now if you're building a music
app, there is one more step
that you should do which
is to configure your app
so that it can continue
playing back audio while it is
in the suspended state and
doing so is very similar
to how you have done it
on iOS, which is to set
up a playback category
on the AV session
and add the background
modes to the info.plist
and the rest is handled
by the framework.
And with that, I would like
to invite Jeff on stage
to demo Building a
TVMLKit application.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Nurinder.
Hello, everyone.
My name is Jeff.
I'm here to show you a TVML
application that highlights some
of the things that we've
talked about so far.
You'll also get a
sense of how easy it is
to build a native application
for the Apple TV using TVMLKit.
So for this demo, we'll be
showing you a simple version
of the WWDC app.
In terms of the user interface,
we'll have multiple shelves
of content where each shelf
will contain session videos
for a single track
in the conference.
So just imagine having a
shelf for developer tools,
app frameworks, design,
and so forth.
So let's get started.
So this is the Xcode project
that we had prepared earlier.
Let's start with the
AppDelegate first,
which is our app's entry point.
In the application
didFinishLaunchingWithOptions,
as you can see in just
a few lines of code,
we have bootstrapped
this application
as a TVML application.
We also specified the
JavaScriptApplicationURL here,
which happens to
point to a server
that is running on this Mac.
So if you look at this
directory over here,
this is where I've configured
the server to serve files from.
And as you can see, there is a
file here called application.js
which is the JavaScript file
that drives the TVML
application.
There is also a JSON file here
which will contain all the data
that we need for this demo.
So let's work through
the application.js file.
So at the top of this file here,
we have declared some variables
to hold our model data.
Next in the App.onLaunch
function is the function
that gets called when TVML
application starts up.
So the main thing that
we want to do on here is
to fetch our JSON file and then
create a user interface using
the data.
Now before we go
ahead and do that,
we should really be showing a
loading indicator on the screen.
This is always recommended
for better user experience
while something is fetched
over the network.
So let me add a few
lines of code here.
So the way to do
this in TVMLKit is
to create a loading
template document.
And this is done
in this function
called createLoadingDocument.
Let's jump into this
function and you will see
that we are basically
creating the Markup
for a loading template and then
creating a DOM document object
using the DOMParser.
Now returning to
the launch function,
after creating the
loading document,
we will now use the
navigationDocument object
to push the document onscreen.
So this is like using
UINavigationController in UIKit.
So now that we have a loading
Spinner visible on the screen,
we will now call a function that
I created called request JSON,
which will use the built-in
XMLHttpRequest object
to fetch our JSON file and
then returning a response
in a callback.
Next, we will convert the
JSON text that we get back
into our JavaScript
data structures.
Now as our UI calls
for a stack of shelves,
we will be creating a
stackTemplate document.
So let me paste some
coding here and jump
into our createStackDocument
function.
Now as you can see, similar to
the way we created the Markup
for the loading template
earlier,
we are creating the Markup
for a stackTemplate here.
So within the stackTemplate
Markup,
we've added a top
banner image here.
And within the body
of collectionList,
we are actually looking through
each track in the conference
and creating a shelf
element for each of them.
And this is done using the
createShelfElement function
that I have here.
So let's jump into
this function.
And again, we are creating the
Markup for a single shelf here.
And within its body, we are
creating a lockup element
for each session video.
So let's now jump into the
createLockupElement function
and you will see that we
are creating the Markup
for a single lockup that
describes the session.
And in this case, we are
capturing the sessionId
as a custom attribute.
We are also adding an
image with the width
and the height and a title.
So just a recap, we have now
created a stackTemplate document
that contains multiple
shelf elements,
and within each shelf element,
we have multiple
lockup elements.
So now let's return to
the launch function.
So after creating
the stackDocument,
we will now use the
navigationDocument object
to replace the loading document
that we have currently visible
with our stackDocument.
And with that, we are
now ready to run this.
Let's switch to Apple TV.
So there you go.
We now have a beautiful
UI of a stack of shelves,
[ Applause ]
where each shelf contains image
lockups or session videos.
So as you can see, with
just a small amount of code,
we were able to create an
application that looks great
and feels right at
home on the Apple TV.
So the next thing that we
want to do is to be able
to play a video when we
click on a lockup here.
At the moment it
just does nothing.
So let's head back into Xcode
and add this functionality.
So back into our
launch function,
I will now add these
two lines of code.
So this will register for
the select and play events.
The select event is when
you press on the trackpad
of the Siri Remote and the
play event is triggered
when you press on
the Play button.
And in both cases,
my playSelectedLockup
function will be called.
So let's jump into this
function and implement this.
So the first step is to
retrieve the lockup element
from the event.
From there, we can retrieve
the session using the sessionId
custom attribute.
Next, we will create a new
mediaItem object, whoops,
of the type video and
initializing it with a URL
of the video, as shown here.
We will also populate other
information about the session
such as the title,
description, track, and artwork.
Next, we will create
a playlist object
and push our mediaItem
object into it.
And finally, we will
create a new player object,
set the playlist, and
then simply call play
to play the video
in full-screen mode.
So just a recap, we have
now created a player object
with a playlist that
contains a single video item.
So with that, let's
see this in action.
So back on a UI, we will now
use the Siri Remote and click
on the lockup and the video
should now start playing
in full-screen mode.
[ Music and Applause ]
Thank you.
And you can press
the Menu button
to exit the video as well.
So that was video
playback for TVMLKit.
Thank you for your time.
Back to you, Nurinder.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Jeff,
for the amazing demo.
But just little amount of code,
you could build a
fully-featured app
which is performance
tuned and polished.
The spacing between the lockups,
rows, shadow treatments,
text treatments all
just looks right.
Before we continue, let me
recap what you just saw.
Using the TVML application
template in Xcode,
create and configure
your client project.
You learned how to create
a simple loading document
and a complex stack
document from JSON.
And you learned how to use
NavigationDocument to push
or replace documents
on the stack.
JavaScript is responsible
for handling user events.
And in this case, we handle
select and play events
and configured video to playback
corresponding to that lockup.
Now when we introduced TVMLKit,
you could already
create great apps
and a lot of you already did.
So thank you.
You have provided some
great feedback and we wanted
to make it even better.
We have been hard at work
and are adding some exciting new
features that are easy to adopt
and would help take your
app to the next level.
To talk all about them, I would
like to invite Parry
on stage now.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> Good afternoon.
My name is Parry and I'm
going to walk you through some
of the new features
we've introduced
in TVMLKit in tvOS 10.
Now TVMLKit provides you
with highly desirable app-level
features through a simple
yet flexible interface.
And the new features we've added
in tvOS 10 are no different.
For example, simply by
adding one attribute
in the search results
in a search document,
you can make the results
animate in and out
as the user is typing.
This provides an engaged
experience to the user
as they are trying to
narrow down the results.
Or if you have a music app,
simply by adding one menu item
to the top-level Menu bar, you
can enable the presentation
of Now Playing audio experience
there, all managed by TVMLKit.
So it comes in and goes out as
the playback starts and stops.
This gives your users a
convenient way to return back
to the playlist and
continue listening to music.
Now all of these features
are really powerful,
but they're also very
easy to implement.
And to show you that, I'm
going to take three of these,
talk about them, and at
the end, implement them
in the demo you just saw.
So let's start with the first
feature I want to talk about,
light and dark appearance.
In tvOS 10, there's a new dark
appearance that's implemented
systemwide and all
apps should adopt it.
Your TVMLKit app is
going to opt into this
by configuring the
applications info.plist.
It's the same thing you would
do is you were writing an
application using UIKit.
So you'll specify the appearance
you want for your app.
You can say either
light, dark, or automatic,
in which case it picks
the system preference.
But no matter which
option you pick,
your standard TVMLKit app
is going to work right
out of the box, without
any further modifications.
All of our templates are
configured with styles
for both appearances,
light and dark.
And TVMLKit switches between
them as and when required,
so you get it for free.
However, if you have explicit
styles in your document,
then you will have to
specify those styles
for both appearances as well.
Let's take an example.
So here's a template that has
a title and its color is set
to black using an
explicit style class foo.
This may not work
in dark appearance.
And for it to work,
you would have
to define the class foo specific
for an appearance like this.
So in order to do
that in tvOS 10,
we've added a new media
feature called tv-template
that has a feature
called tv-theme using
which you can create
a media query
that is specific
to an appearance.
So simply combine
all your styles
up for both the appearances,
group them in their
respective media queries,
put them in the document,
and TVMLKit will pick
the right styles for you.
So with little configuration
in the style and zero lines
of code, your apps are
ready for dark appearance.
Now let's move on
to something else
that also enhances
your user experience
but in a different way.
Let's talk about
embedded videos.
It's fair to say that
videos are a major part
of TV watching experience.
And if you have a catalogue
of rich video content,
then you want your users
to experience that as soon
as they launch your app.
And embedding videos in your
app creates a big impact.
Now just to show you what
a difference it can make
to your app, we created
a small sneak peek
of the demo you just saw but
with embedded videos in it.
Have a look.
[ Music ]
It's seamless.
Not only it's not obtrusive
to the browsing experience
but it compliments it.
It makes it more immersive.
And as expected, TVMLKit does
most of the heavy lifting
for you and gives you this
nice high-level interface
to work with it.
So let's have a look at that.
So in a nutshell with TVMLKit,
you get to embed a player
and a playback area
inside your documents.
Most likely it's going
to be inside a lockup.
TVMLKit handles the playback
for you and all you have
to do is specify when
do you want it to begin.
So you can say that
it should begin either
when the containing lockup
gets focused or as soon
as it appears on the screen.
You have full control
over transitioning the
embedded video to full screen.
And if you have advanced use
cases, encryption using FairPlay
for instance, then you have
access to the embedded player
in JavaScript with all of its
APIs so you can implement that.
Now you can embed videos using
TVMLKit in three easy steps.
First, you configure
the template.
Second, you configure the player
with the media item
you want to embed.
And third, you want to handle
triggering the transitioning
to full screen.
Let's have a look at these
in a little bit more details.
So we've made configuring the
template for you very intuitive.
We've added a new element
in TVML called mediaContent
that you can use the wrap
the image of the lockup
in which you want
to embed the video.
This gives the lockup
the same behavior
and look before the
playback begins.
And the image inside the
lockup provides the bounds
in which the video will play.
You can specify the
playback mode as an attribute
on the mediaContent as
well, so it will be as soon
as the lockup gets focused
or it appears on the screen.
Here's an example.
So here's a lockup
that has a mediaContent
which wraps the image
of the lockup.
And the width and height on
the image provides the bounds
in which the video will play.
Second step, configure
the player.
Now each one of these
mediaContent elements comes
with its own player,
and you can access
that player in JavaScript.
Simply query for
the player feature
from the mediaContent's
DOMElement
and configure the playlist
with the media item
you want to embed.
Here's a small code for that.
Now if you notice
carefully, the configuration
of the player is
not that different
from what you saw in the demo.
You create a playlist,
you add the media item,
and you set it on the player.
But there are two differences.
One, you don't have to
create a new player.
You just use the
embedded player.
And two, instead of doing it
when the user selects
the lockup,
you do it well in advance.
In fact, you do it even
before you push the document,
which brings me to
an important point.
For better user experience,
you must configure the player
before you push the document.
Once the document is loaded,
you can change the playlist
at any time you want.
And finally the last step,
transitioning to full screen.
Now it's worth noting the
TVMLKit will not trigger the
transition for you.
It's one of those flexibilities
that we want you to have.
So you'll add an event
listener for select and play
for the lockup and use
the embedded player
to trigger the transitioning
to full screen.
Here's a small example.
So here, I have added
an event listener
on select event on the document.
I'm grabbing the
mediaContentElement
from the subtree
of event target.
Now this would be the lockup
because all events get
dispatched on the lockup.
And finally calling present
on the embedded player
to trigger the transitioning.
Now you have full control
over when you want to do this,
but transitioning back
to embedded mode happens
automatically on a Menu gesture.
So that's it.
With these three easy steps you
can make your user interface
inside your apps so
much more immersive.
But what happens next?
What happens when the users
are already in full screen?
They're watching your content.
How can you make
that more engaging?
Well that brings me to the
third feature I want to talk
about today that lets
you do exactly that.
Interactive video overlays.
Now in a sense, it's a
counterpart to embedded videos
in that it lets you
enhance your content
by putting a user
interface on top
and you can do so much with it.
For example, you can suggest
more options to the users
so that they can pick from
it and continue watching.
You can let them skip
past teasers and credits
and implement a perfect
binge-watching experience
for them.
Or you could implement
in-app purchase right on top
of your content while the users
are immersed in that experience.
Even if you do it with
something as simple
as interactive metadata, like
Cast, you make your content
so much more engaging
and interactive.
And as you've seen
with other features,
implementation is really simple.
You basically create a document,
use any template for it,
and set it on the player,
and TVMLKit will present
that document when the
video goes full screen.
Here's the code for that.
We've added a new
property on the player
in tvOS 10 called
modalOverlayDocument.
So when you set the
document on this property,
we will present it for you
on top of full-screen video.
If the player is already
playing in full screen,
your documents will get
presented immediately,
but if the player is not
playing or if it's playing
in the embedded mode,
they'll get presented
when the video goes full screen.
So it's really convenient
for you
to just set it at
any time you want.
And with that, let's
have a demo.
Let's implement these features
in the demo you saw earlier
in the presentation,
and to do that,
let's welcome back
Jeff on stage.
Jeff.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Parry.
Hello again.
Let me show you the new stuff.
So back on the Apple TV.
So this was the demo that
we showed you earlier.
Now let's go Home and hit
into the Settings app.
Let's navigate down to the
new Appearance setting here.
We will now toggle the
appearance to dark.
So let's go Home again.
Now because we created the
demo app using Xcode 8,
we will have the
entry in info.plist
to support automatic
user interface dock.
So what this means is
our demo app is going
to support dock appearance
automatically.
So let's see how this looks.
Boom. There you go [applause].
Look how beautiful our UI is
in dock appearance as well.
And again, zero code
to support this.
Now let's talk about
embedded videos.
For our demo, we
will like the video
to start playing automatically
inside the lockup right there.
As Parry mentioned earlier,
there are three main
steps to achieve this.
Step one is to use the
mediaContentElement tag.
Step two is to configure
the embedded player.
And step three is to
handle full-screen playback.
Let's get back into Xcode.
So let's get into the
createLockup function.
Now instead of creating a
standard image lockup right
here, I will now add the
new mediaContent element tag
and have it wrap our image.
That is it.
So that is step one.
Pretty easy.
Now onto step two.
Now as Parry also
mentioned earlier,
each mediaContent element
is going to come built
in with an embedded player.
So what we will need to do is to
configure these embedded players
with a corresponding playlist
before we present the document.
So let's head back into
the launch function.
Now before we present
the document,
I will now call a function
that I created called
configureMediaLockupElements.
And inside this function,
we are first retrieving
all mediaContent elements
from this document.
And for each
mediaContentElement,
similar to the previous demo,
we will be creating a
new mediaItem object,
a new playlist object that
holds our mediaItem object,
but instead of creating
a new player right here,
we will use the getFeature
function
to retrieve the embedded player
and then we just set
the playlist on it.
So that was step two.
The final step is to
handle full-screen playback.
So let's head into the
playSelectedLockup function,
which as you recall is triggered
from the select and play events.
We won't be needing
all of this code here,
so let's replace
this code with this.
First we are retrieving the
lockup element from the event,
then retrieving the mediaContent
element from the lockup element,
and again using the getFeature
function to get access
to the embedded player, and then
we simply call present on it
to take it full screen.
So let's see how this looks.
So as you can see, [Background
Music] the video will now start
playing automatically inside
the lockup right there.
And when I clicked on the
lockup, you will now transition
to the video into
full-screen mode.
>> Welcome to 2015
Apple Design Awards
and welcome your host
for this evening --
>> Pretty cool stuff.
You can also press the Menu
to exit the full-screen mode.
So that was embedded videos.
The next new feature we wanted
to show you is interactive
video overlays.
So this new feature is going
to allow you to place a UI
over the video while
it is playing.
So for our demo, let's say we
want to show a single shelf
of related videos
on top of the video.
So let's head back into Xcode.
Now in my playSelectedLockup
function,
I will now call a
function that I created
that creates my overlay called
createInteractiveVideoOverlay.
And inside this function,
as you can see, we are basically
creating another stackTemplate
with a single shelf,
and within the shelf,
we have multiple
lockup elements.
Also, we are changing the
style of this stackTemplate.
We are adding a blurred
background
and we are also adding
some padding at the top
so that our shelf
stays positioned
at the bottom of the player.
So let's head back into
playSelectedLockup function.
Now after we create our overlay
document, we will now set it
to the new modal overlay
document property of player
and the player object
will just show it.
In fact, the player will show
any TVMLKit document using
this property.
Now we can also show
this overlay
at any time while the video
is in full-screen mode.
For example, we might want
to show the overlay 30 seconds
before the end of this video,
but for the purpose
of this demo,
we will just show
the overlay as soon
as the video goes full screen,
which is why we called it here.
So let's run this.
Again, the video is going
to start playing
automatically inside the lockup
[Background Music].
And when I now take
the video full screen,
you will now see the
overlay on screen.
[ Applause ]
And the overlay is also
interactive so you can pan
around within the
lockup in the shelf here.
So that was interactive
video overlays.
We hope the demo has
been useful to everyone.
Thank you for your time.
Back to you, Parry.
>> Thank you, Jeff.
That was an amazing demo.
Let's quickly recap what
we saw in that demo.
You saw how light and dark
appearance just works right
out of the box for TVMLKit apps.
You saw how easy it is to embed
videos in three simple steps.
And finally, you saw an example
of a binge-watching
experience implemented
through interactive
video overlays.
Now with that, I would like
to summarize what we've
learned today.
So there's one thing I
want you to take away
from this presentation
and it's this.
TVMLKit is an easy
way to make apps on TV
that gives you native
experience which looks
and performs like Apple apps.
It's based off of web
technologies like Markup
and JavaScript that lets you
develop your apps rapidly
and reduce the time to market.
And with the new features
and how you saw how TVMLKit
takes the onus off of you
for writing the user interface,
you can spend your time, money,
and intellectual energy on
the features and content
that make your app
unique and great.
I highly encourage you to go to
the developer website and check
out documentation and
download sample code.
There's a wealth of
information there for you all.
I'd also like to suggest some
related sessions including
What's New in tvOS, and one
in particular that going
to happen tomorrow,
which is TVMLKit, Part 2,
and we talk about how can
you mix your own views,
view controllers, and even
JavaScript APIs in TVMLKit.
And finally, I would like to
thank you all for being here
and I wish you have a very nice
rest of your WWDC16 experience.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]