[ Music ]
>> Good morning.
My name is Steve Breen.
>> And my name is Peter Hajas,
and we're both engineers
on the UIKit Frameworks Team.
>> We're really excited to share
with what we're working
on in CollectionView.
So let's get right into it.
We've got three big topics
to talk about this morning.
Our first topic is going
to be smooth scrolling.
Now, every iOS app expects
to have great scrolling
performance,
and we got some great
additions to CollectionView
to help your apps scroll better
than ever, and the best part
about this is many of these
additions require little
to no work in your applications.
Next, we're going to talk
about improvements
to self-sizing cells.
Now this API was
introduced in iOS 8,
and we're bringing some great
improvements to it in iOS X
to make it easier to adopt.
And, finally, we're going to
go over interactive reordering.
This API was introduced
last year in iOS 9,
and we've got some
great enhancements
that we're going to
go over for iOS X.
>> Let's start off
with smooth scrolling.
A hallmark of the iOS device
experience is responding
immediately to the user's
touch, and a big part
of this responsive user
experience is making sure
that as I scroll my
finger across the screen,
the objects onscreen move
as if they're moving
in the real world.
This is really important
to keep your users immersed
in their applications.
We're going to talk
through smooth scrolling
and some enhancements we've
made to UI CollectionView
by talking through a demo app.
As you'll see, this application
starts off not scrolling
that great.
We wanted to scroll like
butter, but right now,
it's scrolling a lot more
like chunky peanut butter.
So let's go to the iPad.
I'm going to switch
over to the iPad.
Just to clarify, blue squares
are usually pretty cheap,
but we've intentionally
made these slow.
So imagine they're
more complicated.
For example, maybe they
have two colors in them.
Anyways, we've got this
CollectionView, and we can see
that scrolling already
loaded content is nice
and fast, but check this out.
Steve, watch closely.
When I scroll a little bit more.
>> Ooh, ouch.
One star, do not buy.
>> I wouldn't buy it either.
This type of user experience
is something we really want
to avoid.
So what's going on here?
Well, we said before that these
are some really expensive blue
squares to simulate to really
expensive complicated cell
in your app, and that's running
up against CollectionView
and the fact that it loads cells
exactly when they're required.
Let me show you what I mean.
We'll reload our data
here, and I'm going to turn
on a view that's going to show
all the cells that are loaded
in the CollectionView.
So you can see those bottom
cells are just peaking
up beyond the visible bounds.
Now watch what happens
when I scroll.
We're bringing in an
entire row of cells at once.
This is what's leading to that
stuttery scrolling performance.
In performance terminology,
we would say
that the app is dropping frames.
Let's switch back to slides
to hear a little bit more.
>> So what exactly do
we mean when we talk
about dropping frames.
Now, in your applications,
the users expect a smooth
scrolling performance,
which means your app wants
to hit that magical number
of 60 frames per second.
Now if we do the math,
that means that for every time
we refresh the display we need
to hit that window
in 16 milliseconds.
OK. So let's look
at a couple frames.
Here we have a diagram that
shows three distinct frames.
In our first frame, we got
very little work to do.
Now as Peter mentioned before,
we're moving existing content
up and down the display.
It's a highly optimized
situation on iOS.
So it's superfast.
Not much work to hit, and
we've got this great five-star
scrolling performance.
That's a good frame.
However, in the demo, it
wasn't always so great.
Occasionally, we'd
have this situation
where we have a lot
of work to do.
Not only do we fill
up our current frame,
we went into the next frame.
This is our ad frame.
We drop a frame, one star.
Let's look at this in a
little bit different light.
Now on this graph, we can see
we've got two distinct regions.
We have the region on the top,
which we're going to
call the red zone.
This is the area where we miss
a frame, and we're up above
that magical 16 millisecond
line.
Let's check out the labels
that we have on the axes.
So on our y-axis, we're
going to graph the CPU time
on the main thread,
and on the x,
this is the display fresh events
as the scrolling's occurring.
OK. So let's look at a graph.
Alright. So in this graph,
this shows what Peter was
demonstrating a second ago
where we have these visits
up into that red zone
where we're dropping
frames, but most importantly,
look at these quiet times
where the CollectionView's
doing very little work,
but then we have
this other visit
to the red zone at the end.
So what if we could change this
behavior a little bit and smooth
out the amount of work we're
doing as the user's scrolling.
OK, cool. Look at this.
So now instead of these
visits up into that red zone
and those periods of quiescence,
we've got a nice even amount
of work, and we're spreading
the work out across time.
>> To help talk through
how we're going
to flatten these peaks
and bring up this valley
to create this nice, consistent
line of work, I'd like to talk
through the life cycle of a
cell as it existed on iOS 9.
We're going to go through the
whole circle of life of a cell.
It's beautiful.
Let's bring our CollectionView
cells,
and we're scrolling along,
and let's say we need
to bring in a new cell.
We'll take it out
of the reuse queue,
and we'll call prepareForReuse
on it.
This gives the cell an
opportunity to reset itself
to its default state, ready to
receive new data from your app.
Next, we'll continue calling the
rest of cellForItemAtIndexPath.
This is where you should
be doing the majority
of your work populating
the cell.
You'll access your data
models, set them on the cell,
and return them back
to the system.
Now, right before that
cell's about to go on screen,
we'll call willDisplayCell.
This will give your app a chance
to do any other last-minute
work it needs to do before
that cell goes on screen.
And for any outgoing cells,
we'll call didEndDisplayingCell.
>> OK. So that's the life
cycle of the cell before iOS X.
Now let's check out what
this looks like in iOS X.
So here we have the
same type of layout
that Peter just talked about.
The single column.
It's simple for demonstration
purposes.
So now as the user scrolls up,
notice here that well
before this cell is needed
to be displayed on screen,
we're going to bring it
in from the reuse queue.
And then following that familiar
pattern Peter was talking about,
we're going to send
it a prepareForReuse,
and then construct the rest
of the content in your cell
with cellForItemAtIndexPath.
Now as the user continues to
scroll, here's what's different.
Now we didn't call
willDisplayCell right
when we created this cell.
We have a hesitant, hesitation,
and then right when it displays,
we're going to call
willDisplayCell.
OK. So now the user
continues to scroll.
We're going to fade away
those other cells to focus
on the lifetime of this
cell, and now the cell is
about to exit the visible
bounds from the CollectionView.
So we'll send it the
expected didEndDisplayingCell.
Now what Peter was talking
about iOS 9, at this point,
the cell entered the reuse
queue, and we'd be done with it.
To display the data in
this particular cell again,
we'd have to go through the
beginning of the life cycle
to cell and call
cellForItemAtIndexPath.
But in iOS X, we're
going to hold
onto that cell just
a little bit longer.
So if the user scrolls
up a little bit,
and then says, "Oh,
wait a minute.
That was a picture of
my sister's new kid.
I'm going to scroll back
down," we're going to hang
onto that cell, and send
it a willDisplayCell again.
Now the content will
continue on in the cell.
[ Applause ]
>> So notice as Steve's showing
you here, this also applies
to multicolumn layouts.
We're going to be bringing in
the cells one at a time instead
of all at once to get better
scrolling performance.
>> That's right,
Peter, and notice here,
these cells aren't actually
displayed on screen quite yet.
They're still off the screen.
And now that we sent the
second cell that we DQ'd,
the cellForItemIndexPath,
and scroll up both cells,
now we're going to send
the willDisplayCellMessage
to both right before
they appear on screen.
>> While this may seem
like a subtle change,
it's actually a lot
bigger than that.
By adopting this new
life cycle in iOS X,
we get automatic faster
scrolling performance.
Let's go back to iPad.
So I'm going to switch back
to the iPad, and here you see
that same CollectionView we
were just looking at in iOS 9.
Remember, scrolling existing
content is nice and fast,
but when we have to
bring in more cells,
that's when things get choppy.
Now, while preparing
this CollectionView,
we also prepared one in the
oven cooking under iOS X.
So I'm going to switch
over to that,
and here we've got the
exact same CollectionView
with those same really expensive
blue squares running on iOS X.
We can see that scrolling
existing content is still nice,
fast, and fluid, but
watch closely, Steve.
>> Alright.
>> When I scroll
a little bit more.
>> Oh, that's great.
Five stars.
>> That's exactly right.
[ Applause ]
This is because we're using
this new cell life cycle.
The application hasn't
changed at all.
I'm going to turn on that
same view, which is going
to show you all the cells
that CollectionView's loaded
to help highlight
this difference.
So let me turn that on.
So here you can see
that bottom row
of cells is just peaking above,
but watch what happens
when I scroll faster.
Instead of bringing in a
row of cells at a time,
we're now spreading that
work out during the scroll.
This is what leads to that much
smoother scrolling performance.
Isn't that great?
To learn more about this,
let's go back to slides.
>> So this is pretty great.
So today we're very pleased
to announce UI CollectionView
Cell Pre-Fetching.
Now this is enabled by default
when you compile
your apps on iOS X.
There's no step one.
Now for any reason you need
to use the old life
cycle behavior pre-iOS X,
opting out is easy.
Just set the new property
on UICollectionView
to isPrefetchingEnabled
defaults.
Now we've got some
best practices
for adopting this
new technology.
The first thing we want
to talk about is we want
to do all the heavy lifting
in cellForItemAtIndexPath.
All the, all the content
creation for your cell.
Everything should be centered
in cellForItemAtIndexPath.
Additionally, we want to
make sure we do minimal work
willDisplayCell in
didEndDisplayCell.
And, finally, it's
important to note
that cellForItemaAtIndexPath
may prepare a cell that's never
actually displayed.
The user may scroll away before
the cell has an opportunity
to be displayed.
>> So this is great.
By just recompiling in iOS X
and doing what you're likely
already doing with the majority
of your work in
cellForItemAtIndexPath,
you automatically get better
scrolling performance for free.
But we wanted to
go a step further.
We understand that there's
a class of application
which has a simple question for
preparing their CollectionViews.
What do I do about my
expensive data models?
The fact of the matter is
that many CollectionView cells
require expensive data model
access to create.
I'm talking about things
like decoding images,
talking to your database,
or loading things
out of your core data store.
And we understand that for
this class of application,
we don't want to show things
like template cells while we do
an asynchronous network request.
To help solve this problem,
we're introducing new API
in iOS X to help inform how
your data model loads content.
Since its introduction,
UI CollectionView has always
had two companion objects:
The data source and
the delegate.
And new in iOS X we have
this third companion object.
It's optional, and it's
called the prefetchDataSource.
There's just one
required method.
It's really easy to implement.
ColletionView prefetchItemsAt
indexPaths.
This will be called on
your prefetch data source
when it's time for
you to preload content
from your asynchronous model.
That argument index paths is
an ordered array of index paths
so earlier items in that
array are coming up sooner.
You can use this to influence
your asynchronous model reads.
There's a second optional
method in this protocol.
CollectionView
cancelPrefetcingForItemsAt
indexPaths.
This will be called on
your prefetch data source
when we determine that we're no
longer scrolling towards a set
of index paths.
You can use this to cancel
or lower the priority
of any pending loads.
Now there's something really
important about this API
that I want to highlight.
This is not a replacement
for the data model
that you've already written.
Instead, it works alongside your
existing asynchronous solution
that you've built for
loading data in your app.
What you'll do is use this as
an additional hint for when
to load content in
your CollectionView.
>> So let's tie all this
together with a demo
that shows all of the concepts
we've talked about so far,
and we're going to introduce
a little science, too.
>> Check this out.
Steve's about to
do some real magic.
>> Science, man.
Alright. We're going to
switch back to our demo app,
which we showed before.
OK. So here's the demo app
we've been looking at so far,
but we've hidden this really
great feature we call the
science panel.
Alright, so I'm going
to turn that on now.
OK. So we have these two
distinct regions, right.
We've got that red zone.
That's the one star bad
zone, and then we've got
that nice fat green
zone at the bottom
where we get the super
smooth scrolling performance.
So what I'm going to do
now is I'm going to run
through with the iOS 9 version
of the app, and I'm going
to play back a scrolling
session that I recorded earlier
to show you what this looks
like and do the science.
OK. So here we go.
Scrolling along,
doing our science.
Chop, chop.
OK. What do we have here?
So check out this graph.
We got eight visits
up into that red zone.
Eight dropped frames.
But also we can see that
we've got these long periods
of quiescence like we
talked about earlier.
So the area on the graph
is this big spiky thing,
and then going back
down to the valley.
Let's see what this
looks like in iOS X.
OK. I'm going to switch
back to that iOS X mode
that Peter was talking about
earlier, and now I'm going
to playback that same scrolling
session with [inaudible].
Check it out, Peter.
>> It's a lot smoother, Steve.
>> Yeah, that definitely
looks better.
See what we get.
Hey, look at that.
No missed frames.
Pretty great.
Now check out what we've
got under the curve
on this particular graph.
Instead of those peaks way up in
the air and the quiet periods,
we've blended those together,
and now we have this
smooth amount of work
that makes your app much more
responsive on the main thread.
OK. You ready for this, Peter?
>> I'm set.
>> Let's do it.
OK. So now we're going to
look at the iOS X version,
but we're going to have
the API, pre-fetch API's
that Peter talked about earlier.
We're going to adopt
those in this application.
Alright. So I'm all
set in the demo app.
I'm going to play back that
same scrolling session.
Whoa, Peter, look at that.
>> Now that's butter, Steve.
>> That's looking pretty good.
Five stars.
And the science agrees.
[ Applause ]
OK. So, but, Peter, something's
different here, right.
The area on the curve between
this main queue activity
and the prior version
don't match.
This is a lot lower.
What's going on here?
>> So if we're adopting the
pre-fetch API correctly,
we're probably moving
that data model read
onto a background queue
to free up the main queue.
>> That's exactly right.
That's what's going on.
So now we've moved all that
work onto a background queue,
and we no longer have to
clutter up the main thread.
Let's switch back the slides.
So next I'd like to
talk a little bit
about some pre-fetching API tips
to make your apps adopt this API
in the best possible way.
The first, when you
get the pre-fetch call,
you want to make sure
you do all the work
on the background
[inaudible] right away.
Now we've got two great
technologies for this:
GCD and NSOperationQueue.
Now it's also important
to remember
that pre-fetch is an
adaptive technology.
Now what do I mean by
adaptive technology?
Well, remember when we talked
about those quiet periods
and how pre-fetch takes
advantage of those
by doing additional work.
There are times in
an application
where the user's
scrolling so fast
that there's no quiet times.
During these times when we have
to update the display
very often,
we will not do pre-fetching.
[Inaudible] And, finally,
use the cancelPrefetchingAPI
to adapt to your
user's shifting focus.
Now it's possible that
the user is moving
up in their CollectionView,
and they're scrolling along
with the content, but then
they change their mind
and move in another direction.
We will notify you of this
event with a cancel message
so you can deprioritize
those prior ones and focus
on the new content that
the views are scrolling to.
>> So this is really
great for CollectionView.
By doing no work at all, you get
better scrolling performance,
and by doing just a
little bit of work
and using the classes
you've already written,
you get even better
scrolling performance.
And if you're using
UITableView, don't worry.
You're not chopped liver.
We've brought the exact
same API to TableView, too.
[ Applause ]
It's got a very similar optional
pre-fetch data source companion
object with a similar
required method, just one.
TableView prefetchRowsAt
indexPaths.
Again, index paths is an array
ordered by their proximity
to the table's visible area.
So earlier index paths
are coming up sooner.
Just like with the
CollectionView API,
you can use this to inform your
asynchronous data model reads.
And it's got that same second
optional delegate method.
TableView
cancelPrefetchingForRowsAt
indexPaths.
As Steve just mentioned to
you earlier, you can use this
to cancel or deprioritize
any pending data model loads.
And this is what's really great.
Just like with the
CollectionView API,
this works alongside your
existing asynchronous
model solution.
You don't have to
throw anything away.
Instead, use this to inform the
loads that you're already doing.
So that's it for cell
pre-fetching in iOS X.
[ Applause ]
>> So we're really excited about
bringing this technology, guys.
I mean, we can't wait
to see the actual build
with the smoother
scrolling experience.
So next up, we're going
to talk a little bit
about improvements we've made
this year to self-sizing cells.
This API was introduced in iOS 8
and we're bringing some
additional enhancements this
year to make it easier
to adopt in your apps.
Now, before we get
into this, I want to go
over the existing API,
chat a little bit about it.
So we shift a concrete
layout class
in CollectionView called
UICollectionViewFlowLayout,
and we have full support
for self-sizing cells
with this class.
To enable this, we just need
to set estimated item size
to some non-zero CG size,
and this tells Collection
that you want to, you want to
calculate the layout dynamically
as content is displayed.
Now as far as getting the
actual sizes of your cells,
there's three different
methods for doing this.
The first method is
using auto layout.
If you can fully constrain the
content view of your hierarchy
to the content view of
the CollectionView cell,
we'll ask the auto
layout system how large
that cell should be
and use that value.
Now if you don't
use auto layout,
or you need more manual control,
you can override sizeThatFits.
And, finally, for
the ultimate control,
you can override
preferredLayoutAttributes
FittingAttributes, and provide
not only the size information
but also you can
tweak the attributes
like alpha and transform.
>> So specifying the
cell size using one
of these three mechanisms,
it's pretty easy.
Most apps will use auto layout,
but for those that don't,
they can take on
more manual control
with the second two
mechanisms there.
But we found that
for types of layouts,
picking a good estimated
item size turns
out to be really challenging
because sometimes it's
just hard to guess.
I mean, sometimes
what do you use?
50 by 50, 100 by 100, even more.
It's hard to say.
For these types of layouts,
what would be really cool is
if flow layout could adapt
its estimate and do the math
on your behalf and instead
compute that estimated size
from actual sizes of
content that we've sized.
So in iOS X, we've got new
API on flow layout to do that.
All you have to do is set your
flow layout.EstimatedItemSize
to a new constant,
UICollectionViewFlowLayout
AutomaticSize.
By setting your estimated
item size to automatic size,
you'll indicate to the
CollectionViewFlowLayout
that it should do
the math for you.
It'll keep a running
tally of all the cells
that it's already sized, and use
that to influence its
future sizing estimates.
As we'll see in a minute,
this makes the flow layout much
more accurate while it's sizing
your CollectionView cells
leading to better performance
and a more accurate
layout while we're sizing.
So we're going to do a demo
to show you the benefits
of UICollectionViewFlowLayout
automatic size.
So I'm going to switch
back to the iPad.
Now here we've got a
CollectionView using a
flow layout.
Each cell represents a
word in a run of text.
Just to clarify,
we're not recommending
that you build a text viewer or
editor using UICollectionView,
but this does make
a really good demo.
I'm going to put
the app into a mode
where we can watch
the flow layout
as it sizes each
individual cell.
No user would ever see
this, but it's really great
for visualizing the
advantages of this new API.
Let's start out with
fixed estimates
like we'd use on iOS 9.
So I'm going to turn
on the simulation.
Here, you can see that
we've seeded each cell
with that initial estimated
item size where we just guessed.
And I'm going to size the first
word in this run of text, Lorem,
and watch what happens.
So we size Lorem, and now
it's the correct size,
but notice the CollectionView
is really no closer
to what its destination
layout size will be.
We didn't use that estimate
to influence anything else,
and everything else is still
this large initial estimate
that we passed in.
Now this continues as we
size each cell individually
in this CollectionView.
Notice how we're not actually
adopting, adapting any
of the other cell sizes
to account for the sizes
that we've already computed.
This is especially obvious
when we size the last word
in this run of text, Fusce,
and as we go to size this word,
you'll notice that we slide
up all the other cells,
invalidating their y-positions,
and we haven't used the
information from that first line
of text to influence the sizes
of any of the other cells.
So now I'm going
to turn the device
into iOS X mode using
UICollectionViewFlowLayout
automatic size.
So let's switch over.
OK, great.
So we've seeded this with
the same initial size
to help you visualize
the difference.
I'm going to size the
first word, Lorem,
and watch what happens.
Wow. So we size that first
cell, and use that cell size
as a running estimate for all
the other CollectionView cells.
Now the layout's not
totally accurate yet,
but notice how it's a lot closer
to what it will eventually be.
In fact, the heights
in y-positions are
pretty much spot on.
And notice that as I size this
run of text, we're adapting
that estimated size, making
it more and more accurate
for your CollectionView
cells holistically.
And notice when we size the
last word in this run of text,
we're no longer invalidating
the y-positions
of all the other cells.
This is really great
and can help out a lot
when you're doing things like
scrollToItemAt indexPath.
Now due to the nature of this
API, you'll get the most bang
for your buck using
automatic size
if your cells have
similar widths or heights.
So that's it for self-sizing
improvements in iOS X.
Let's go back to slides.
[ Applause ]
So that wraps up our
self-sizing cell segment,
and now we're going
to talk a little bit
about an API we introduced last
year, interactive reordering.
Now, this is a familiar
user experience
to users of TableView cells.
They like to, users might grab
a piece of content and move it
and rearrange it
vertically in your TableView.
So we brought this technology
to CollectionView last year
with a new interactive
reordering API.
Let's run back over to the iPad
and see what this might
look like in the demo.
Switch back over to the iPad.
>> Alright.
>> Here we are.
OK. So we've got this really
pretty looking custom layout.
Oh, man, look at
that scroll, Peter.
>> We probably adapted
pre-fetching,
which is really easy.
>> That's probably it.
OK. So check it out.
So let's say the user
loves this content,
but they want to rearrange it.
Might drag their finger around
and move the content smoothly
around the CollectionView,
and notice how it
reflows automatically.
And not only that, if
we change to an item
that has a different
size, let's you be able
to do the right thing.
Now when the user's done
reordering, they might let go.
Smoothly animates into
place, and that's it.
Let's switch back to slides, and
let Peter go through that API.
>> So that's interactive
reordering as it existed
on iOS 9, and this
API is really simple.
To start an interactive
movement, you're going
to call CollectionViews
beginInteractive
MovementForItemat indexPath
where index path represents
the index path of the cell
that we'd like to move around.
If you're doing this in
response to a gesture,
you can hit test the
CollectionView using index path
for item at location.
Next, each time the gesture
updates, we're going to want
to update the cell's position
in response to our finger.
For this, we're going to call
updateInteractiveMovement
TargetPosition.
Passing in the location
of the gesture
in the CollectionView's
coordinate space.
Next, when we'd like to end
the interactive movement
and confirm the reorder,
we're going to call
endInteractiveMovement
on the CollectionView.
CollectionView will
put the cell down,
handling all the layout
attributes correctly,
and then message back to
your app's data source
so that you could do the
actual rearrange in your model.
Now, if the gesture cancels,
or if you'd like to not allow
reordering at this time,
you can call CollectionView's
cancelInteractiveMovement.
Here, we'll put everything
back to where it was before,
and we won't call
your data source.
Now for those of you using
UICollectionViewController,
this is even easier
for you to use.
You just have to set the
install standard gesture
for interactive movement
property to true,
and CollectionViewController
will add a gesture
that will call these
methods on your behalf.
All you have to do is
implement the data source parts.
>> So that's the API that we
shipped last year in iOS 9.
This year we're very proud
to announce we're going
to add paging support to this.
Now there's no new API, which
is the best kind of API,
and since CollectionView is
derived from UIScrollView,
all you need to do is set
the isPagingEnabled property
of the ScrollView's
inheritive property to true,
and that'll enable the support.
Let's switch back to the iPad
and check this out in a demo.
>> And here, we've
got a horizontal
scrolling CollectionView.
This is currently
not using paging.
It's just continuous, and look
at that smooth scrolling
performance.
>> Hey, hey.
>> So in reordering when
we're scrolling continuously,
we pick up the CollectionView
cell and move it to the edge
of the screen, and then we
get this really nice auto
scrolling behavior.
This is familiar to users
of many CollectionView
based applications.
Now I'm going to turn on
paging support, and we'll see
that CollectionView now advances
in page size increments.
This is really natural for
some types of CollectionViews.
Now here's what's new.
We're calling the
same reordering API,
but new in iOS X,
that reordering works
alongside paging.
So as I move my cell to
the edge of the screen,
we're going to automatically
scroll in page size increments.
This can give your app a
really home screen style
reordering experience.
I'm going to let
go, and that's it.
[ Applause ]
Let's go back to slides.
>> So they're a little
[inaudible].
So while we were developing
iOS X in the early phases,
Pete would often come to my
office very enthusiastic.
"Steve, I'm working
on this great feature.
Developers are going to flip."
He's like that.
And I agree, it's
a great feature.
I can't wait to show it
to developers everywhere.
So during the run up to WWDC,
now he's looking for a place
to land this particular
slide so we can talk about it
and share it to people.
So even a couple days ago,
he made the pitch again,
"We've got to do it."
So I said, "OK, fine."
Two slides, ninety
seconds, Peter.
Can you get it done?
>> Thanks, Steve.
It'll just take a minute.
Another feature that I'm
really excited about that's new
in CollectionView in iOS
X is UIRefreshControl!
That's right!
UIRefreshControl is now
directly supported inside
of CollectionView.
But not only that, it's also
directly supported inside
of UITableView without
using UITableViewController!
And not only that, it's also
supported inside of UIScrollView
because RefreshControl is now
just a ScrollView property!
It's really easy to use, too.
All you have to use, do is
create the RefreshControl,
add yourself as a target
to it with an action,
and set it on your
CollectionView,
and you'll be pulling
to refresh in no time.
Thanks a lot, Steve.
It means a lot to me.
>> Hey, great job.
Great job.
It's like the summarizer
we talked about today.
We went over the brand
new UICollectionView cell
pre-fetching stuff,
and we can't wait
to see what you guys are going
to do in your apps with this.
And then we covered the new
pre-fetch data source API
for Collection and TableView.
Next, we covered
the improvements
to self-sizing cells with the
new automatic size constant.
And then we chatted a little bit
about the iOS 9 introduced
API interactive reordering
and the new paging
support we have in iOS X.
You want to check out the
sample code and other resources
for this app, for this session,
we can see the address there
on the developer website.
We got some great
related sessions
with these technologies
[inaudible].
We want to thank you
very much for coming out.
Have a great --
>> Thank you so much.