[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Hello everyone.
Welcome to Session 230.
I'm Sirisha, an engineer
on CallKit and I'm joined
by my colleagues,
Stewart and Nick.
And we are excited to introduce
a brand new framework today,
CallKit.
A lot of you here have
created VoIP apps before.
You have changed the
face of telephony
and have made the world smaller.
And you want your app to be
the primary way your users make
and receive calls on
iOS and we want to help.
CallKit is a framework
that's going
to elevate your third
party VoIP apps
to a first party experience.
[ Applause ]
Thank you.
So while a lot of you
have created VoIP apps,
for the next 40 minutes
let's assume that you
and I have created a brand
new app called Speakerbox.
So Speakerbox is a
simple app that can make
and receive voice calls on
iOS as iOS exists today.
So before we take a look, let
me setup the stage for you.
So Jane has been
traveling around Europe
and her concerned parents
are trying to reach her
to make sure she's doing okay.
But because she's international
they're using Speakerbox
to make calls to her.
So let's see how an incoming
call to Jane looks like today.
So this is Jane's locked screen.
And at first, she gets
an iMessage from Dad.
And before she could
even respond,
she gets an incoming
call from mom.
Jane can't discern
the difference
between this incoming
iMessage notification
and the incoming phone
call notification
because that's just what
VoIP calls are today.
Just a notification.
And if Jane wants to
actually answer this call,
she has to slide on
Speakerbox, type in password,
and then that gets
her taken to the app
and then she can begin speaking.
And this is Jane's
unlocked screen
and the experience
is just as bad.
She gets an incoming
call from Mom.
Did you miss that
notification by any chance?
That's right.
It was just a banner
from the top.
So wouldn't it be nice if
instead the incoming call
to Jane looked more like this?
This is Jane's locked
screen still.
And she gets an incoming
call from Mom.
Notice the full screen
Native UI.
[ Applause ]
And Jane can just
slide to answer
and start talking to her mom.
And from the unlock
screen, it's the same, rich,
Native UI with answer
and decline buttons
and your custom ringtone
playing.
[ Applause ]
And wouldn't it be nice if
VoIP calls could interplay
with other calls on the systems?
Perhaps at the telephony
call or a FaceTime audio call
or maybe another VoIP call?
And even have VoIP calls get
started from recents, favorites,
and even get assigned
to contacts.
And get started from
Siri, Bluetooth,
and even get do not disturb
and blocked functionality.
That is CallKit.
[ Applause ]
All right.
So today we're going to go over
the architecture of CallKit
and incoming call flow, and
outgoing call flow, and then end
with some more details
about the API.
So let's get started.
All right.
So over here, we have all our
system services like Bluetooth,
Siri, CarPlay, and
then our Native UI.
And over here, we have all
our VoIP apps like Speakerbox.
These are two separate
entities right now.
Calls made on Speakerbox
are non known to our system
and then our services.
In iOS 10, we have
adopted CallKit
in all our system services.
So now calls made on
Bluetooth are known
to our system UI via CallKit.
So if Speakerbox wants
a similar experience,
it needs to adopt CallKit.
So now calls made on
Speakerbox will get known
to our system via CallKit
and then system can
publish these calls
to the rest of our services.
So let's talk a little
bit more about Speakerbox.
So here we have Speakerbox
and all of its code.
It talks to its network
and has its own app UI
and we're going to link CallKit.
So there are two primary classes
in CallKit that we care about.
The first is the CXProvider.
So the provider is the class
that Speakerbox will use
to let the system about any
out of band notifications
that have happened.
The second class is
the CXCallController.
The CXCallController is the
class that Speakerbox will use
to let the system know
about local user actions.
So let's take a deeper look
at these two classes
starting with the provider.
So the provider, like I
said earlier, is the class
that we use to let the
system know about out
of band notifications.
That is these are
not user actions
but actually external
events like, for example,
an incoming call
coming to Speakerbox.
Contrasts this with
the CXCallController.
The CXCallController is the
class that Speakerbox will use
to let the system
know about requests
from within the app itself.
That is these are
actually user actions
and like internal events,
like a start call action.
By using the CallController,
Speakerbox gets to interplay
with other calls on the system.
Say, for example, there's
already an active telephony call
and the user wants to
start a Speakerbox call
from Speakerbox's UI.
By using the controller,
the system gets to know
about the start call action
and then the system can
tell the telephony provider
to hold its call so as to let
the Speakerbox start its call.
So let's take a look at
some examples of this.
So the provider is
used to report
out of band notifications.
Like, for example, an incoming
call coming to Speakerbox
or maybe an outgoing
call getting connected.
Or that outgoing call
ending on the remote side.
Whereas the controller is
used to request actions
from the system like
the user wanting
to start an outgoing call or the
user wanting to answer the call
from Speakerbox or maybe ending
the call from within Speakerbox.
So when the provider
wants to communicate
to the system it uses
the CSXCallUpdate class.
And when the system
wants to let Speakerbox
about any user interactions,
it uses the CXAction classes
to let Speakerbox know.
And the controller communicates
to the system user actions
bundled up into a CSTransaction
to let the system to know
about these user actions.
So that was a lot
of information.
So let's take a look all of
that in an incoming call flow.
So here we have Speakerbox
and Jane gets
that incoming call from Mom.
The incoming call
comes to Speakerbox
and then Speakerbox
creates a CXCallUpdate
and using the provider
sends that to the system.
And then the system can then
publish that incoming call
to all our services
including our UI.
And if Jane wants to answer
the call from within our UI,
the answer action
comes to our system.
Our system can then tell
Speakerbox, we have the provider
to the CXAnswerCallAction
and then Speakerbox can answer
the call however it needs.
And if Jane now wants
to end that call
from within the app's own UI,
the end action comes
to the controller.
The controller bundles it
up into a CXTransaction
and that comes to the system
and if everything looks okay,
the system sends that back up to
the Speakerbox via the provider
and then Speakerbox can
end the call as necessary.
All right.
Now let's take a look all of
that in a demo with Stewart.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Sirisha.
So now that you've heard
about the benefits of CallKit,
I'd like to show
you how to adopt it
in an existing VoIP
application, the Speakerbox app
which Sirisha mentioned.
I'll first show you how to adopt
it to handle an incoming call.
So I'll first open up the
Speakerbox Xscript Project.
Now before I dive into
adopting CallKit in this app,
let me just show
you a little bit
about how the app is structured
so you have a frame
of reference.
So we have two main classes
in the app right now.
The SpeakerboxCallManager class
which maintains a list of calls
in the app and has
certain operations
such as starting a
call and ending a call.
And our other primary
class is SpeakerboxCall.
This is our model class which
represents a single call
in the app and has
metadata about it as well
as some call back blocks
so we can be notified
about the life cycle events
of the call as it progresses.
So like Sirisha mentioned,
the first we need to do
when adopting CallKit is
to create a CXProvider
and set its delegate.
So I'll do that by
creating a new file
called ProviderDelegate.
So into this new file,
I'll bring in some code
that we've already
written but let me walk you
through what this is doing.
So in our initializer
we pass in a reference
to the SpeakerboxCallManager
class.
This allows the ProviderDelegate
to access the app's list
of calls and references them
by UUID which we'll show later.
Next, we have -- we create
a CXProvider instance
and we pass it -- something
called a provider configuration
which we see here.
The provider configuration
is something we'll go
into more detail later in the
session but this allows our app
to configure to the
system a few options
about how it should behave.
Now back in our initializer, we
set this class as the delegate
of our provider and
then if necessary,
we request authorization
to use the provider.
So great. So now we have our
provider and our delegate set
but we need to create
this in our app delegate.
So I'll declare a property
for our provider delegate
and I'll instantiate that in
the application did finishing
launching with options method.
Cool. So now we have
a provider in our app.
How does the app respond
to an incoming call?
So if I scroll down, we can see
that the app currently
uses PushKit to learn
about an incoming call
via push notification.
And if we look at what
this code is doing,
we can see that it looks
at the dictionaryPayload
from our push notification
and gets some metadata
about the incoming call
such as UUID and handle
which is an identifier
representing who's calling.
And then we call the
display incoming call method
and we can see here that this is
where the app hosts the
local notification for --
to show the user
that incoming call.
But when using CallKit
we no longer have to rely
on a local notification
to show this.
We can, instead, use the
system's full screen native
incoming call UI and we want
to do instead because it's
so much richer of an experience.
So to do that, I'll go back
to the ProviderDelegate
and I'm going to
create the helper method
which will allow us to call
the API on our provider.
I'll call that report
IncomingCall and in this method,
I'll start by creating
a CXCallUpdate
which contains metadata to
represent that incoming call.
And then we'll call the
report NewIncomingCall method
on our provider and this is the
step that notifies the system
about that incoming call.
Now, in the completion block,
we'll check if there is an error
and if there wasn't, we create
a SpeakerboxCall instance
and configure it and we add that
call to our app's list of calls.
We'll go into more detail
later in the session
about why there could be an
error here but suffice it
to say, there's certain
conditions
in which the device
will not be prepared
to accept an incoming call.
Okay. So now that we
have this helper method
on our ProviderDelegate, I'll
go back to my app delegate
and just replace this code that
posted the local notification
with a call to our helper.
So great. So now
we're using CallKit
to report an incoming
call that we learned
about from a push
notification to the system
and the system is showing the
full screen Native incoming
call UI.
Well what happens when the
user presses that green button
and answers the incoming call?
When that happens,
our ProviderDelegate will
receive another method
that we need to implement.
And that is the
ProviderPerformAnswerCallAction
method.
Let me walk through
what this is doing.
So we start by getting
an instance
of our Speakerbox call class
corresponding to the UUID
of the call that
we're answering.
Next, we call the answer
Speakerbox call method
and this is some code that
was elsewhere app prior to now
and this talks to our
network to tell it
to actually answer that call.
And now we do it here in our
ProviderDelegate call back.
And last, we call
fulfill on our action.
In CallKit, every action
must either be fulfilled
if it was successful or
failed it there was an error
in processing in that.
And we can actually see
a few lines above here,
if we were unable to find a
Speakerbox call for this UUID,
we call the failed
method on our action
to indicate that to the system.
So this method handles
answering the call but what
about when the user
wants to end the call?
For that, we have a similar
delegate method called
ProviderPerformEndCallAction.
And this is very similar.
It looks up a call
based on the UUID.
It talks to our network using
endSpeakerBoxCall method.
It signals that that
was successful
to the system by
calling fulfill.
And it removes the call from
the app's list of calls.
So we're almost done
handling the incoming call
but there's one other
thing we need to consider
when handling that
incoming call.
And that is our call's audio.
So when using CallKit, you will
no longer activate your app's
audio session directly.
Instead you will only
configure the audio session
and the system will actually
activate your app's audio
session for you at
an elevated priority.
So let me show you
how that works.
Back in our
PerformAnswerCallAction method,
I'll insert a call to
this function configure
audio session.
And this does like it says,
it configures the
app's audio session
but does not activate it.
Instead our audio session will
be activated by the system
and after that happens,
we'll receive a delegate
call back called Provider
didActivate audioSession.
And this is the point where
we begin processing our
call's audio.
Now the last step is to stop
processing our call's audio
in the PerformEndCallAction
method.
Okay. So that's all
the code we need
to handle an incoming
call using CallKit.
And now I've got on my device
setup to mirror to the screen
and let's build and run
the app on the device.
So for the purpose of this demo,
I'll just simulate an
incoming call using this button
at the bottom.
And now when I press this,
we'll see our call using
Speakerbox presented using the
full screen Native
incoming call UI.
And I can just accept that call
and our ProviderDelegate
receives the
PerformAnswerCallAction method.
It fulfills that and then
finally, when I'm done talking
to Jane I can just end the call
and our app, ProviderDelegate,
fulfills that as well.
So that's a demo of handling
an incoming call using CallKit.
And I'll now pass
it back to Sirisha.
Thanks.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Stewart.
So let's take a look at
what Stewart just showed us.
So first, we reported
incoming calls
to the system via the report
new incoming call API.
Then we handled an
answer call action
by implementing the delegate
method perform action answer
call action.
Then once we've actually
answered the call, we fulfilled
that action by calling
the fulfill API.
So CallKit can do more
than just answer calls.
Here a list of all our other
actions that we support.
As you can see, there's holds,
group, play DTMF, and many more.
So now let's spend a few seconds
talking about multiple calls.
So say Speakerbox can
handle more than one call.
Right here, in this example,
there's already an active
Speakerbox call going on
and then there's an
incoming call waiting call.
Now if the user wants
to end the active call
and the answer incoming waiting
call from within the Native UI,
the system will send
Speakerbox a CXTransaction.
A CXTransaction is nothing
more than just a list
of one or more actions.
In this case, it's a list
of end and answer actions.
And once Speakerbox has handled
each of these and performed each
of these actions, it
needs to fulfill each
of them individually so
that the system knows
to transition the UI.
All right.
Now I'll hand this
off to Nick to take us
through an outgoing call flow.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Sirisha.
So let's check back
in with Jane.
She talked to her mom yesterday
but today she's feeling a little
homesick and would like to check
in with the home front.
So let's see what it takes
to make an outgoing call.
So the first thing that happens
when Jane goes into recents
and taps to call her mom back is
our app is going to get launched
with a start call intent.
Now some of you may have already
seen the introducing SiriKit
session where we introduced
intents but if you'd
like to find out
more information,
you can always watch
the video online.
In a nutshell though,
an intent is an object
that represents a
desired user action,
is wrapped up in
an NSUser activity,
and then passed back to our app.
So our app has received
the start call intent
and now we've constructed
a start call action based
on the information
on that intent.
We'll take that action
and request it via
the CallController.
The CallController will
then pass that action
through to the system and if
it's accepted, it will come back
to our app via the
ProviderDelegate.
Then finally our app
can take that action
and use the necessary
commands on our network
to make that outgoing call.
So now let's take a
look at the life cycle
of the outgoing call
from this point.
So we've just begun performing
the start call action.
So the call is in
a starting state.
From here, we'll finish
executing the action
and fulfill the action to move
the call to a started state.
Then when the remote
side answers the call,
we'll notify the provider that
the call has started connecting.
And then finally,
we'll tell the provider
that the call has connected
to inform the system
that the two parties can
begin talking to each other.
So now I'd like to
bring Stewart back us --
back up to give us another demo.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Nick.
So now I'd like to give
you part two of our demo
of adopting CallKit
and Speakerbox.
This time how to use it to
handle an outgoing call.
I'll open up the Speakerbox
Xscript project again.
Now back in our app
delegate class,
we can see that Speakerbox
already handles being launched
with a URL to start a new call.
But when using CallKit,
the process of dialing an
outgoing call is similar
but when the user starts a call
from places like the phone apps,
recents tab, or a
contact card or from Siri,
the app will be launched with
an intent and that will be given
to us via an NSUser activity.
So the first step in
using CallKit here is
to implement the application
continue user activity method.
And taking a look at
what this is doing,
we look at our NSUser
activity and we get the value
of the startCallHandle property.
This is some code we've
already written to look
at the NSUser activity, get the
intent, and return the handle
which is a string
which represents the
person we want to call.
Now once we have our handle,
the process of starting
a new call is identical
to the URL handler above.
We just call the start call
method on our call manager.
So now let's look at what
this method is doing.
So we can see in the
SpeakerboxCallManager class
that we start a call by
creating a new instance
of our model class,
Speakerbox call,
and then we call the
startSpeakerBoxCall method
which talks to our network
and actually starts that call.
And finally we add this
call to our list of calls.
But now this is not yet using
CallKit to notify the system
about our intention
to start a new call.
And we need to do that.
So I'm going to remove this
code for now and I'm going
to add parts of it back later.
The first step of adopting
CallKit in this class is
to import the framework.
And then I need that second
class which Sirisha mentioned,
the CXCallController class.
And now that I have that,
in our start call method,
I need to create a
startCallAction and configure it
with the handle that
we want to dial.
Then I create a CXTransaction
containing that action
and finally I call
request transaction
on our callController to
request that from the system.
Now just to reiterate a point
that Sirisha mentioned earlier,
you maybe wondering why we need
to request this transaction
from the system when it seems
like everything that's
happening here is happening
within our own app.
And the reason for that
is that when you attempt
to begin an outgoing call,
there may already be a call
elsewhere on the system.
For instance, if the user is
in a phone or a FaceTime call,
or even a call from
another VoIP app.
If that happens, the
system needs to hold
that call before
your call can begin.
So that's why we need to
request action from the system
to let it know about
those intentions.
So now, once the system receives
and improves our start call
action, it's going to send
that back to our app via
our ProviderDelegate.
So I need to implement
another method
on our ProviderDelegate class.
This time it's the provider
perform StartCallAction method.
And let's fill this
out together.
So we start same
as we did before
of creating a Speakerbox
call model instance
and configuring it
with the handle
which we're going to dial.
Then we configure our audio
session just like we did
when answering a call
previously and next,
we need to configure a few
properties on our call.
And there's a lot
going on in this one
so let's walk through it.
We set two call back
blocks on our call.
The
hasStartedConnectingDidChange
and hasConnctedDidChange.
These are asynchronous call back
blocks which will be invoked
when the call progresses
to connected and finally
to connecting and
then to connected.
And in these call back blocks,
we report to the system
the progress of the call.
And it allows the system
to be aware of that
and reflect it in the UI.
So with that set, we can now
call the startSpeakerboxCall
method on our call.
And this again, talks
to our network
and it starts it outgoing.
We fulfill the action to
indicate success to the system
and add the call to
the callManager's list.
Okay. So this handles starting
the outgoing call but what
about when the user wants to
end that call and this time
from within our own --
or the app's own UI?
So for that, we need to go back
to our Speakerbox
callManager class
and look at the end method.
And we can see here that just
like the start call
method before,
this is not yet using CallKit.
So I need to replace
it with code that does.
I'll just drag this in and we
can see that this creates an end
to call action and it
wraps it in a transaction
and then requests
that transaction
from the callController.
But this time, we don't need
to do anything further back
in our ProviderDelegate
because as you can see,
we already implemented
this earlier in the demo.
So that's all the code that we
need to handle an outgoing call
and I'll now build and
run the app on the device.
And give you another demo.
So I've built and updated
the app on the device
but to show you an
outgoing call, I'd actually
like to go back to the phone
app under a contact card.
And we can now see the
Speakerbox app listed right
on the contact card and I just
can tap this to launch our app.
And when we do, our
app will be launched.
It will receive that intent
and it will start a call
using the callController.
It will request a transaction
which will be approved
by the system and fed
to our ProviderDelegate
which will then fulfill
that action.
And here we go.
We just saw that happen.
The call is now active.
So now once the call is
active, if I home out,
we can see something new.
For the first time, the green
double height status bar is
shown for our app.
Previously this was
reserved for the native phone
and FaceTime calls
only but if I tap this,
we'll be sent right
back to Speakerbox.
[ Applause ]
Thank you.
Then when I'm done
talking, I can end the call
and this will request an end
call action from the system
which our ProviderDelegate
will fulfill.
So that's all demo for handling
an outgoing call using CallKit.
I'll pass it back to
Nick to recap and go
over a few other API details.
Thanks.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Stewart.
So first let's take a quick
look at what we just saw.
The first thing that happened is
Speakerbox received a start call
intent, created a start call
action based on that intent,
and then requested
that start call action.
Then the start call
action was received via the
ProviderDelegate,
executed, and then fulfilled.
And then finally, Speakerbox
reported that the call moved
to connecting and then
finally connected.
So, now that we've seen a few
basic flows let's dive into some
of the details of the
API to really round
out our usage of CallKit.
And in particular, we'll take a
look the provider authorization
and configuration to
help customize our app
in the native UI.
We'll take a look at how
to handle action errors
and system restrictions and
then finally, we'll take a look
at how CallKit plays a role in
our call's audio on our app.
So as with other APIs like
contacts and core location,
CallKit requires permission
from the user to use.
And because of this,
one of the first things
that your app should do when it
launches is check its current
authorization status.
This may have changed since the
last time your app was launched.
If the user went into settings
and maybe enabled or
disabled your app.
Then from here, if you discover
that your app's authorization
status has not
yet been determined, you
should request authorization
for your app.
And what this does is it tells
the system to display an alert
to the user to request
permission.
And this is done on behalf of
your app and because it's done
on behalf of your app,
you should always be sure
to include an informative usage
string in your app's info.plist.
And lastly while
your app is launched,
you should always be sure
to observe and listen
to any authorization status
changes that may happen
so that you can always show the
most up-to-date UI to your user.
So now let's talk about
the provider configuration.
So the provider configuration
is a way for your app
to customize its in
call experience directly
in the Native and Call UI.
Some of the things that can
be customized are your app's
localized name to
display for your calls.
This also includes
certain capabilities
such as whether your app
supports video calling.
And this even includes things
like specifying your own masked
image icon to show directly
in one of the buttons
of the end call UI.
And when tapped, this will take
the user directly to your app.
Just a note though
that this support
for this app icon
will be available
in a future seed [phonetic].
So we've taken a look at what
happens when things go smoothly
when executing actions
but what happens
when we run into a problem?
Well take a look at the
outgoing example from before.
We've just started performing
the start call action.
Let's say that in the process
of performing that,
we run into an error.
Maybe we don't have
good connectivity
with our network server,
so we can't actually
make the outgoing call.
Well in this case, we should
fail the start call action.
And the reason this is important
is because it informs a system
that something went wrong.
And then the system
can, in turn,
inform the user via things
like call failure UI.
And along with these action
errors are action time outs.
So each action on the
system has a particular time
out associated with it.
And these time outs are
important because they assure
that actions initiated
by the user are performed
in a performance and
responsive manner.
So because of this, your
app should always be sure
to perform those actions
in a timely manner.
However, if an action
does time out,
your app will be notified via
an appropriate provider delegate
method at which point it
can react appropriately.
So based on the current
state of the device,
certain system restrictions
may be in place.
And we'll take a look at an
incoming call as an example.
One of the reasons
why your calls --
your app's incoming call
might be denied is, perhaps,
the user has disabled your app
and it's no longer authorized.
Or maybe the remote caller
for the incoming call is
in the user's blocked list.
Or perhaps the user has enabled
do not disturb and doesn't want
to see any incoming calls
at the current time.
Well for all of these cases,
you app will be notified via
completion handlers on the API.
For example,
the reportNewIncomingCall
API passes back an error
in its completion handler.
And as you can see here,
our app checks the error
that's returned.
Sees that the error code is
filtered by do not disturb
and then handles
that appropriately.
So now let's take a look
at audio with CallKit.
So with CallKit your app
gets a lot of great benefits
with its call's audio.
And one of the biggest
benefits it gets is
that its audio session will
be at a boosted priority
on the system on par with
phone and FaceTime calls.
And what this means
is other apps
on the system will not be able
to interrupt your
app's call audio.
And in addition to
this, CallKit is aware
of certain audio routing
hints on this system
which means it can decide where
to route audio based on things
like the user's current
accessibility settings
or currently connected
Bluetooth devices.
Let's take a look at an incoming
call flow as an example.
We know that, at some point,
during an incoming call our
app will receive an answer call
action and then fulfill
that answer call action.
Well after receiving the answer
call action is a great time
to configure our audio session.
And that's because we know
that the call will
soon move to connected.
Then when we fulfill
the answer call action,
the system will automatically
start an audio session
for our app at a
boosted priority
and then let our app know
that this has happened via
the did activate audio session
provider delegate call back.
And this is an indication
to our app that it is time
to start media for the call.
So that was just a quick look at
some of the details of the API
to help us complete our
adoption of CallKit.
So now we invite
you to adopt CallKit
in your existing VoIP apps
or to build a new VoIP app
from the ground up
using CallKit.
With CallKit you'll
integrate directly
into the system's
calling infrastructure
and once you've adopted CallKit
you'll maintain feature parity
with native calling services.
But most importantly,
with CallKit your app will
increase its visibility
across the system whether
it's with full screen,
incoming alerts on the locked
screen, appearances in recents,
favorites, and contacts,
or integration with Siri,
CarPlay, and Bluetooth.
For more information you can
check out our session's webpage
at developer.apple.com
where we'll also have the
Speakerbox sample code
that we've been referencing
throughout this presentation.
We've got a lot of great
related sessions for you.
So be sure to check out more
information about Siri, intents,
networking, and audio.
Thank you all so
much for joining us
and we'll see you in the labs.
[ Applause ]