[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Good morning.
And thanks for checking
out our session.
My name is, Dave Browning.
And here with me today
is, Nihar Sharma.
And we're going to be,
we're both engineers
on the CloudKit team.
And we're going to be
talking to you today
about some best practices
when building your
applications with CloudKit.
So, what are we going
to cover specifically?
Well, first I'm going to
walk through how we here
at Apple use CloudKit.
We'll talk about the work
flow and the API's that we use
in order to provide a seamless
experience for our customers.
And by that I mean, allowing
them to access the same data
in their applications
across all of their devices.
Next, Nihar is going to come
up and talk about some details
when using the CKOperation API.
And the configurability
and flexibility you can
get when you use it.
Then he's going to
talk about some things
to consider when data modeling.
What you're going to
store in CloudKit.
How you're going to store it.
How you're going to
build your scheme up.
And then he'll talk
about error handling,
which we've always
said is very important
in CloudKit applications.
He's going to cover the
different types of errors
that you'll encounter
potentially when using the API
and how to consider
responding to those depending
on your application's use case.
So, a quick reminder, we here
at Apple have built CloudKit,
or built many applications
on top of CloudKit.
And so you can be confident
that yours will scale,
because we've scaled it to
hundreds of millions of users.
I also want to do
a quick refresher
about the conceptual model.
So, the highest level, we have
what's called a container.
This is usually a one to one
mapping to an application.
So, the photos application
has a container in CloudKit,
the notes application,
your application.
Inside of the container
you have a public database.
This is where you can store
data that all users can see.
So, an example of
this is the WWDC app,
or the news app in iOS.
They're built on CloudKit.
They use a public database
for storing articles, news,
that kind of stuff
that everyone can see.
Next there's the
private database.
This is where you store data
specific to a single user.
That user can see their data
across all of their devices,
but no other users can see it.
And then new this year
is the shared database.
If you want to learn more about
this makes sure to go back
and check out the video
for yesterday's session
on What's New in CloudKit.
And they do a deep dive
on the sharing stuff.
Inside of the database
you then have a zone.
And there's a default zone, and
a public, and private database,
where if you throw records
in there by default,
that's where they'll end up.
But, you can choose in
the private database
to create 1 or more
custom zones.
And you can store
stuff in those zones.
And then when content is shared
to a user from another user,
that shows up as a shared
zone in their share database,
which you can think of
as basically a proxy
to the custom zone and the
private database of the owner.
And then of course if multiple
users share stuff with you
in multiple custom zones
you're going to end
up potentially seeing
a lot of shared zones
in the shared database.
And now what I'm going to focus
on with this work flow is mostly
in a custom and shared zones
that we're talking
about right here.
Finally at the lowest
level you have records.
This is your key value structure
data where you store everything.
And a record always
exists in a specific zone.
So, a quick reminder on the
benefits of using CloudKit
at the high level, you focus
on building your application
and not worried about
building back in services.
We do that for you.
Your users get what we like to
call automatic authentication.
That means, if they're signed
into iCloud on a device,
you do not need to prompt them
for signing up, or logging in,
or any of the stuff that can
usually then be a barrier
to using your application.
If they're signed into
iCloud with CloudKit,
you immediately have a uniquely
identifier for that user.
And you can start storing
data on their behalf.
And then finally, what the
focus is today is you can get
that same data, your users can
get the same data across all
of their devices when
you store it in CloudKit.
All right.
So, let's talk about the
common use case that we see
when we're building our
apps on top of CloudKit.
And so what happens is, you have
a user who runs an application,
in this example let's
talk about Notes.
So, Notes is built on CloudKit.
They create a note on
their iPhone, let's say,
that's stored over to the cloud.
And then when they open up
Notes for the first time,
maybe on a second
device, their iPad,
it feels like that data was
sort of magically pushed.
And it's already
there in their iPad.
And if they make
edits in the iPad,
it feels like it's just
magically pushed the other way.
So, that's sort of the use
case that we're looking
at providing for our users.
So, the way to think
about this is, iCloud,
the servers are the
source of truth,
your devices have a local
cache of that truth data.
And then CloudKit, the API is
the glue in between the two.
All right.
So, how does this actually work?
Well, basically when
your app launches,
the work flow we recommend is
that you fetch changes
from the server.
Especially the first
time your app launches,
because you don't know if
something already exists
that the user wrote
from another device.
All right.
So, you talked to the server.
You fetched down any data
that you don't have yet.
And then you insure that you're
subscribed to future changes.
By subscribing to future
changes, it tells CloudKit,
the server, to send
push notifications
to your applications
on their other devices.
And then of course
when you get a push,
you'll want to fetch
changes again to pull
down the new changes
that happened
from the users other device.
All right.
So, let's dig into these
in a bit more detail,
so subscribing to changes.
The way this work is, when
your application is launched
for the first time, and we'll
talk about why in just a second,
but when it's launched
for the first time,
you create a subscription
telling the server,
here is the set of data I
care about subscribing to.
And then when that data
changes, it will let you know.
When your application
launches for the first time
on another device the
subscription might already exist
for the user on the server.
But, your app doesn't know that,
because it's launching
for the first time.
So, you need to make
sure it exists.
So, you'll do the same thing
that you did before
on the other device.
Now that you're subscribing
to changes
and CloudKit is sending
you push notifications,
you want to listen for
those push notifications.
So, let's walk through
an example.
The user writes a new note.
The application stores
that down to the server.
The servers says, ah ha, there's
a subscription for this user.
They wanted to know
when new data showed up.
It says it came from the iPhone.
So, I don't need
to bug the iPhone.
But, the user also had an iPad.
So, it looks up the proper Apple
push notification service token.
Talks to APNS on your
behalf, and tells them
to send a push to the iPad.
So, you don't have to deal
with sending pushes
yourself in the back end.
So, then finally your
iPad gets the push.
What does it do next?
Well, as we said, now it goes
and fetches the new
changes from the server.
So, it talks to CloudKit,
pulls down the new data,
updates its local cache, and
then when user opens up notes,
bam, they see the same stuff
they just wrote on their iPhone.
All right.
So, let's look at
actually building this.
Let's walk through the code,
the specific API that we use
to make all of this happen.
So, first we'll talk about
subscribing to changes.
So, remember what I said before.
This is one of those
things that you only need
to do the first time
your app launches.
So, you'll notice we have
a check here at the top
of our code that says, have we
locally cached on this device?
The fact that we've already
created this subscription,
because if we've already
created it, we don't need
to keep doing it
every time we launch.
You save yourself
network requests.
You save the user
some network stuff.
All right.
So, if we haven't
done this before,
let's look in the
code to set it up.
So, new this year in iOS 10,
there's an API called
CKDatabaseSubscription.
This allows you to
subscribe to any change
across an entire
database, and it works
in a private database,
in a shared database.
So, in this example let's focus
on the new shared database.
So, you can give a
subscription an ID,
which allows you
to check it later.
And we'll talk about
that it just a minute.
But, in this case
because we're dealing
with a shared database let's
call it, shared changes.
Next you need tell CloudKit what
type of push you want it to send
when this subscription triggers.
And so let's dig into the
different types you can do.
So, the first one that we
actually use a lot and recommend
in most cases is a
silent push notification.
And the way to do that in our
API is on a subscription object.
You can set the notification
using a CKNotification
info object.
And if you set the property,
shouldSendContentAavailable
to true, and only that property,
you'll get a silent push,
the back end will send a
silent push on your behalf
for this subscription.
And the key to this is
that you do not need
to prompt the user
for acceptance.
So, we've had people
ask in the past, hey,
we have this subscription,
but it's popping up here.
You guys have seen it, allow
push notifications for this app.
And a lot of people
hit no to that.
You don't get pushed and
then you rely on pulling.
If you do it this
way, you're not going
to be alerting the
user in any way.
So, you don't need to
ask for acceptance.
And then finally you can listen
for these notifications
in your app delegate.
RegisterForRemoteNotifications.
So, if you do want to send a UI
push, you actually want a badge,
or banner, or make a sound,
then you can set any one
of these 3 properties.
And that will tell CloudKit to
send a UI push to your user,
because you will be alerting
them you do need to ask
for user acceptance
in this case.
And then of course you
register for remote notification
in the same way as before.
So, a little bit of fine print.
If you read the APNS
documentation, they tell you
that pushes can be
coalesced depending
on the conditions of the device.
So, that means if a subscription
triggers and a push is sent
to your user's device, there
are many cases low battery,
bad network, etcetera where
they may not get that push.
But the coalescing piece
means they promise to deliver
at least one of those.
So, what that means is, you
should not think of push
as a way to tell your
apps what changed,
because if 5 pushes were sent
but you missed 4 of them,
you're going to miss
4 of those what's.
Instead, think of push
as a way to tell you
that something changed.
One or more things.
And that's why we need
to go talk to the server,
to figure out what those were.
And the good news is the
CloudKit API provides you a way
to ask for only what
has changed.
So, you don't have to pull down
all the stuff you already have.
All right.
Let's jump back into our code.
Remember we're creating
a subscription.
And in this case we've set
up a silent push notification
by doing
shouldSendContentAvailable
to true.
Now, we need to take
this subscription
and ask the CloudKit client
to save if off to the server.
And you're probably
familiar with this
if you've used CloudKit.
But, the way you do
everything is with operations.
And in this example, we do a
CKModifySubscriptionsOperation.
And we tell it about the
subscription we've just created.
And this is the one
we want to save.
With CloudKit because the
client is going to be talking
to the server over the network,
and that might take a bit
of time, everything
is asynchronous.
So, that means all of
your operations have
completion blocks.
They get called once
a response comes back.
And so in this case, we
have a modify subscriptions
completion block.
And the first thing
you want to do in all
of your completion blocks,
I know we say this all the
time, is check for errors.
And Nihar is going
to talk to you
in a bit more detail about this.
But, in this case, let's just
say if there not an error,
then we know that the
subscription was saved.
Now we can locally cache the
fact that we've done this,
so that we don't
do it next time,
because of that check
up at the top.
Quick note, and Nihar is
going to talk about this to.
CKOperations inherit from
NSOperation, or Operation
in Swift 3, and so
you have the ability
to set this quality
of service property.
And the default is utility.
And he'll talk about some
of the things to keep
in mind when setting this.
And then finally, the way
to actually finally take this
operation and ask the client
to send it back, is to add it
to a database's operation queue.
And again because we're doing
a shared database subscription
in this case, we add it
to the shared database's
operation queue.
And the client will now go off
and send that to the server.
Okay. So, we're subscribed
to changes now.
So, now the next step
is to listen for pushes,
since CloudKit will
send them to us
when data is changed
on another device.
So, you want to make sure
that in Xcode you've
turned on background modes.
And you want to check the
box for remote notifications.
And potentially background
fetch if you want
to do this while your
app is in the background.
Once you've done that, there's
a method in the app delegate
that you might be familiar with,
which is applicationDidReceive
RemoteNotification,
fetchCompletionHandler.
This method gets passed
a user info dictionary.
And CloudKit provides
you a handy way to see
if you can get a CKNotification
out of that dictionary.
So, if you can, remember
there might be pushes
for other reasons.
But if it's coming from
a CloudKit subscription,
you'll be able to
get a CKNotification.
And now we can check
the subscription ID.
So, the reason this is important
is because likely you're going
to end up having a
database subscription
for the private database,
and the shared database
and maybe for other things.
So, this is how you
differentiate
which subscription
triggered this push.
So, in this case let's say
it was our shared changes.
Now we can go off and
fetch that shared data.
And we'll talk about
that in just a second.
And when that's done, we
call it CompletionHandler
that was passed into
this method.
Okay. So, now we are
listening for pushes.
And let's say some time later
your application gets a push.
So, what do we do?
Remember what we said.
You need to fetch new changes.
And so let's look at
a graphical example
of sort of how this works.
So, we got to push
into our device.
And we said, okay, that's
for the shared database.
There are sort of 2
steps you need to take.
The first one is, you
go and ask the server
for which zones changed
in the shared database.
Remember we talked about
zones before, right,
because there may be
new zones that showed
up that you don't
even know about,
because someone shared
something with you.
And you pass along a
server change token
that tells the server
where in history you are.
And we'll dig into
that in just a minute.
Step 2 is, now with the no
zones, you go back to the server
and say, okay, please
tell me what records
where changed inside of
those specific zones.
And again you have change
tokens for each zone marking
where in history your
local device cache is.
All right.
So, let's talk about
that change token thing
in a bit more detail.
So, imagine your
user has a device,
the iPhone we were
talking about before,
they're using your application,
and they send some
changes down to the server.
Those changes are accepted,
and the server wants to mark
that point in history.
It does that with the
server change token.
And in this case for simplicity
sake, let's save the letter A.
That device sends down
another set of changes
that are accepted, goes to
B, etcetera, it goes to C.
Sometime later user runs
your app on a second device.
Let's say that iPad we
were talking about before.
And the first thing
that iPad needs to do,
remember on app launch
is go and ask
for any changes that
it doesn't have.
So, it goes and says, I would
like to fetch the
changes from the server.
The server says,
okay, here you go.
Here's what exists.
And at the end of that it says,
you are now at server
change token C.
So device 2 has now marked
where in history it is.
Now let's say device 2 then
later writes some data.
Somewhere along the way
device 1 gets a push.
Device 1 fetches
down the new changes.
And at the end of that
the server says, okay,
you're now at change token E.
All right.
Device 2 makes another
set of changes.
Device 1 gets a push,
pulls that stuff down,
it's now at change token I.
Now you'll notice that device
2 is still at change token C.
And that's because when you're
writing data you're not getting
change tokens back.
You don't get those until
you actually fetch it.
So, let's say device
2, the app restarts,
or they restart their
iPad or something.
Your app launches up.
You go and fetch changes.
The server will send you
the stuff that you wrote
from that device, because
it doesn't know if you had
that locally cached or
not, for various reasons.
All right.
So, don't be surprised if
you see some of the same.
This allows you to confirm
that you have this stuff.
And now at the end of
that, the server will send
out a change token, I.
And you notice that both devices
are now at the same state.
They have same server
change token.
So, that's sort of an
example of how that works.
Okay. So, let's look at
actually writing the code
for fetching these changes.
So, in this case we're going
to talk about database.
So, a new API, iOS 10 is
CKFetchDatabaseChangesOperation.
And again you pass in
the server change token
that we just talked about.
And the first time you ever
do that, that will be nil,
and it will tell the server
that you have nothing.
And it will give you everything
that exists on the server.
Next, in previous
versions of the API,
at the end of this operation
you had to actually check a flag
to see if the server said that
there was more data coming.
Now, we'll talk about
it in just a second.
But, if that was set to
true, it was your job
on the client's side to
re-trigger this operation.
But, what we've done is,
we've added a new property
on these operations
called fetchAllChanges.
And it defaults to true.
And what it does is, it tells
the CloudKit client to do
that on your behalf so that
you don't have to fool with it.
So, if after running
one of these operations,
if the client sees that
the server has more data,
it will automatically enqueue
your operation again for you.
And of course call your
callbacks along the way
so that you don't have to
worry about that anymore.
Next, you want to implement
this completion block,
recordZoneWithIDChangeBlock.
And this is where you will
be told about the zones
that changed in the
shared database.
So, you'll want to collect
these zone ID's, and we'll talk
about what to do with
them in a second.
Next, there is,
recordZoneWithIDWasDeletedBlock.
This tells you about the zones
that no longer exist
on the server.
And allows you to clean up
any local cache data that was
in those zones from before.
And you'll see this
in cases potentially
where something was
unshared with your user,
because that zone no longer
exists in their shared database.
And then new is, a
changedTokenUpdatedBlock.
So, let's dig into this.
So, remember before we had
device 1 had written some data
down in the server.
We had device 2 had
written some data down.
And then sometime way later,
device 3 for this
user comes along.
And remember the first
thing it needs to do is,
go talk to the server
and fetch any changes.
And because fetchAllChanges
was true,
it's asking for everything.
But, there might be a lot of
data there, like in this case.
Right. And the server might
decide, it doesn't make sense
to send all of this back
in a single response.
So, we're to chunk it up.
So, it's going to send
you back a chunk of it.
The CloudKit client will see
that there's more
coming from the server.
So, it needs to go back
and issue another
operation on your behalf.
But, before it does that, it's
going to call changeTokenUpdated
and tell you that you're
now at change token C.
And this allows you to sort
of move along with the client
as it's making its operations.
So, you update your local change
token and don't repeat some
of the stuff you've
already done.
So, let's say this client,
on your behalf, says,
there's more stuff
coming from the server.
Let's go back and get it.
See some new data.
At the end of that calls
changeTokenUpdated,
see if there's new data, goes
back to the server again.
But, this time there's an error.
In your error handling, it's
likely that you're going to end
up calling fetchChanges again.
But, instead of starting
all the way back at A,
because you have a
changeTokenUpdatedBlock,
your local change
token is now at E.
So, when you call your next
one, the server says, okay,
you only need F through I.
You don't need the old stuff
that you've already processed.
So, that's why it's important
to implement the
changeTokenUpdatedBlock.
And you just cache the
server change token just
like you normally do.
And then finally we have
our completion block,
which in this case is,
fetchDatabaseChanges
CompletionBlock.
Again, the first thing
you do, error handling.
Again, Nihar will
walk about this.
And then you'll get
a final change token,
which in that last example
had we not received an error,
would have been the
I at the end.
Cache that just like
you normally do.
And so now we've
collected a set of zones
that changed in that database.
Now we need to go fetch
the records that changed.
That was step 2 in
that diagram before.
And we do that via new API,
CKFetchRecordZone
ChangesOperation.
And it allows you to pass
in a set of zone ID's.
So, you don't have to worry
about calling all these
for all the different
zones that changed.
You call one, pass in all
the zones that changed.
And we won't dig into the code,
but it looks very
much like this.
You're going to have
some completion blocks
where you're dealing with
records instead of zones.
And you'll be getting
change tokens along the way.
All right.
So, quick recap on
what we talked about.
So, you subscribed to changes
to tell CloudKit that you want
to receive pushes when
a user changes the data
on another device.
You've listened to those
push notifications.
And when you receive one, you've
gone and talked to the server,
and fetched exactly
what changed.
And by doing this, your
application now provides
that seamless experience
for your users
across all of their devices.
All right.
So, now Nihar's going
to come up and dig
into some more specific
best practices.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Dave.
Good morning, everyone.
Thanks for coming out today.
My name is, Nihar Sharma.
And I'm an engineer
on the CloudKit team.
And today I'm very
excited to share
with you some CloudKit
best practices
that we've learned here at
Apple over the past few years
that you can take advantage
of in your apps today.
Let's take a look at what
we're going to cover.
First, I'd like to talk about
automatic authentication.
Dave touched on this briefly.
I'd like to go into a little bit
more detail about what it is.
How you can take
advantage of it.
Next, I'd like to talk
about the CKOperation API,
which is the workhorse of our
native talk at frameworks.
Then we'll dig into a couple of
tips that you can keep in mind
when designing the
schema for your apps,
that will help you
take advantage
of the CloudKit API
more effectively.
And finally, we've told you
before just how critical great
error handling is to
writing a CloudKit app.
And I'd like to reiterate
that today.
And talk to you about a few
different class of errors,
and how your application
should handle them.
So, let's get started.
First up, automatic
authentication.
Now, you might be familiar
with a UI like this,
where on first launch
an app requests a lot
of private information
from a user,
even before the user has
started using their apps.
Well, we think in CloudKit
we have a great way for you
to increase the chances of
engaging with your users
without requiring any
private information upfront.
The way we do this is via
the CloudKit user record.
As a reminder, this user
record is automatically created
for every user that when
they first use your apps
that is logged into
an iCloud account.
In this manner it is unique
per CloudKit container.
And it offers you a stable
identifier for that user
that is stable across
app re-launchers,
OS upgrades, etcetera.
So, you can save this
identifier to your servers
and start building a profile
for that user right away.
And when you notice
that they're engaged
with your apps a lot more, then
go ahead and request information
to enrich their profiles.
The way you access
the user record ID
for the current user is
via the fetchUserRecordID
CompletionHandler
API on CKContainer.
So, that was automatic
authentication with CloudKit.
Now, let's talk about
CKOperations.
As a recap, there
are 2 main ways
in which the CloudKit framework
exposes operations to your apps.
One is via convenience
API calls,
which work on one
item at a time.
And the other is via those
CKOperation counterparts.
So, in this manner, every
convenience API call
that we expose, that
works on one item,
has a CKOperation counterpart.
And that works on a
batch of those items.
So, for example, we have
the fetchWithRecordID API
on CKDatabase to fetch
1 record at a time.
And we have its corresponding
CKFetchRecordsOperation
that takes an array
of record ID's
and fetches them in a batch.
Now, there's certain advantages
to using this CKOperation API
that you get over
convenience API call.
I'd like to walk through
a lot of those today.
So, first and foremost,
CKOperation is a
subclass of NSOperation.
What this means is that,
you get the full power
of the NSOperation API
available to you for free.
You can do things like,
set up dependencies
between your CKOperations.
You can assign the
quality of service to them,
to let the system know how
important that operation is
to you, or even manage queue
priorities when scheduling them
on your own NSOperation queues.
And you even get
cancellation for CKOperations
that have already
started executing.
So, I'd like you
to go up, go back,
and read up the documentation
on NSOperations
to take full advantage
of the CKOperation API.
A great reference for this is
our advanced NSOperations talk
that we gave at WWDC last year.
So, now since we're talking
about CloudKit operations,
there are a few more things
that come along with the ride.
And I'd like to touch upon 3
of those main things today.
First, is the configurability
that CKOperation gives you.
Next is, how it lets you
optimize resources both
for the system, and
you as a developer.
And last, I'd like to talk
about lifetime management,
which is something new
that we've enabled you
to be able to do in iOS 9.3.
So, first up, a quick recap
on just what you can
configure on a CKOperation.
Operations let you have
fine grain access to whether
or not you wish network
activity for that operation
to go out over cellular.
You can also specify keys for
operations that fetch items
from the server if you want
to download just partial records
instead of the entire record,
which the community's
API does not let you do.
You can even limit
the number of results
that a particular
operation returns to you.
And finally, long running
operations also give you
progress updates
that you can use
to drive certain UI elements.
Now, let's talk about
resource optimization.
The number 1 resource
used by your operations
on the system are
network requests.
Now, every convenience
API call turns
into at least 1 network
request on the system.
So, when you use the CKOperation
batch API, you allow the system
to minimize the number of
requests needed to be able
to send your changes
to the server.
So, for instance, if you want
to save a batch of records
and you use a
CKModifiedRecordsOperation,
the system will take
that batch and be able
to optimize a request needed
to send that to the server.
So, now in this manner
it is not only good
for the system resources,
but it also helps you optimize
your network request quota
as developers.
Additionally, by default
CKOperation lets you opt your
network activity into
discretionary behavior.
What we mean by this is that,
you let the system
decide an opportune time
for your request
to be scheduled.
For more information I
encourage you to check
out the discretionary property
on NSURL session Configuration.
The way we expose this to you on
CKOperation is via the quality
of service properties.
So, by default, CKOperations
have a quality
of service utility.
Any QOS, which is utility
or below will opt-in
to this discretionary behavior.
So, if you notice that your
CKOperations are taking a much
longer time to execute than
you expect, that might be
because the system does not
think that it's a good time
for your request to go out yet.
Now, additionally there
are a few other behaviors
that you should keep in mind.
When opting into
discretionary behavior,
network failures will be
automatically retried for you.
And along with that, by default
you get a 7-day resource timeout
for every single request
that your operation executes.
So, that was resource
optimization.
Now, let's talk about
CKOperation lifeline management.
On our platforms, there are
various reasons why your
application may exit.
For instance, you might be
suspended in the background
and be evicted, or a user
might force quit your app.
Now, you might have certain
updates running while this
happened, which were
either user-initiated
and you really want to just
save them to the server.
Regardless of whether
your app may have exited,
or you might have a
longer running update
at a lower priority that
you wish to finish whether
or not your app sticks around.
So, to serve this purpose in iOS
9.3 we introduced the concept
of CloudKit long-lived
operations.
What these operations
let you do is,
once you mark them long-lived,
the system will execute
that operation on your
apps behalf whether
or not your app sticks around.
We will cache any
server responses we get
for that operation, and
will provide you with an API
to be able to replay those
responses once your app returns.
So, let's take a look at
the API that we have exposed
to be able to do this.
Well, on CKOperation it's
pretty straightforward.
You have an isLongLived flag.
So, you create a
CKOperation like normal.
Once you've set this
flag, you've turned it
into a long-lived operation.
Along with that you
have an operation ID,
which is a system
assigned string
that uniquely identifies
every CKOperation.
And we will take a look
at why that's important
in just a second.
So, here's the general
architecture
of how you run a
long-lived operation.
You initialize an operation
like you would normally.
You just set the
isLongLived flag on it,
along with your arguments
and callbacks,
and you run the operation.
Now, when you wish to
resume it, you will fetch
that long-lived operation
from the CKContainer class
via the operation ID.
You will set the callbacks
if you're interested
in hearing about.
And you would run that
operation once more.
Let's take a look at an example.
Let's say we wish
to run a long-lived
fetchRecordsOperation.
So, we set up the operation
like we did normally
with our arguments.
But, we remember to set
the isLongLived flag.
And we save the operation ID
property to our local cache
so that we'd remember what
this operation represented.
We set up the callbacks, and
then queue the operation.
Now, when you wish to resume it,
you can use the
fetchLongLivedOperation
with ID API available
on CKContainer
to fetch that operation.
And since you know what
that operation represents
and from your cache,
you can safely cast it
and set the appropriate
callbacks on it.
You do not need to set the
arguments again, or tweak any
of the other operation
properties
that you might have previously,
and you've resumed
that operation.
Now, CloudKit will then replay
all the cache responses we have
back for that operation.
And either catch you
up to the progress
that the operation has made
why your app was not around,
or give you the entirety of
the results of that operation.
And what this also means is that
these operations are cleaned up.
That's important sign.
And normally this happens
when the completion block
of that operation is called.
You must note that your apps
will have at least 24 hours
to resume any long-lived
operations
that they might have enqueued.
So, that was all
about CKOperation API.
Now, let's switch gears and
talk about data modeling.
There's 3 main tips that
I'd like to give you today.
The first one is around
schema redundancies.
How you can use them and how
they help you leverage the
CloudKit API more effectively.
The second one is
how to use references
to avoid a certain class of
errors that you might encounter
in your CloudKit apps.
And lastly I'd like to talk
about parent references,
which are a new type of
reference that we've added
in this release to
support CloudKit sharing.
So, let's talk about
schema redundancies.
Let's take an example of
developing a photo sharing app.
Now, the first thing
that you might have
on a server this app is
a record type for photo,
where you store a user's
high resolution photograph
that they've taken on one of
our iOS devices as a CK asset.
Now, let's say when the
user first launches the app,
while you're fetching changes
like Dave recommended before,
you wish to display
just a thumbnail view
of all the user's
most recent photos.
Something like this,
which the photos app does.
Then it seems like an awful
waste of network bandwidth
to be able to download
that entire high resolution
asset every single time you have
to load this page.
So, what can you do here?
Well, it's pretty
straightforward.
You can think about adding a
redundant field on that record,
which represents the
downscaled asset.
And what this allows you to
do is, coupled with the usage
of CKOperation and the
desired keys property
that we talked about,
that enables you
to fetch partial records.
You can now fetch just the key
that you need to drive the UI
that your user's interested in.
You can even set the
results limit property
to limit just the
number of results
that you're showing
on a single page.
So, in this manner, you can
enqueue an optimized download
to be able to present a
dynamic UI to your users.
You fetch only what is
needed, when it is needed.
And the desired keys
property is also available
on the new CKFetchRecordZone
ChangesOperation,
as well as
CKFetchRecordsOperation,
both of which fetch items
from the Cloud for you.
Now, as a reminder, these
API's are also available to you
on the web via CloudKit JS.
So, by using them,
you enable your users
to have a more dynamic
experience in your apps,
because they're not waiting
for you to finish operations
that are downloading data
that they're not going to use.
Next, let's talk
about CKReferences.
As a quick reminder,
what are these?
Well, they're CloudKit's
way for you
to point records
to other records.
So, for instance, if
we have 2 records here.
Record A and record B, we
store reference on record A,
initializing it with record B.
We've created a CKReference.
Now, let's say we wish to add
albums to our photo sharing app,
which can contain
multiple photographs.
So, how would we go
about modeling this
one-to-many relationship?
Well, in a simple manner,
and either you might think
that this might be a good
day to model for this.
Storing the record ID's, the
references to the photo records
that are part of
that album right
on the album record
itself as an array.
This is what that
will look like.
Now, let's take a look at what
happens when multiple devices
for your user try to add albums,
try to add photographs
to that same album.
So, let's say we have an
album record up on the Cloud
that does not have
any photos yet.
Now, remember that
your users are going
to have multiple devices.
They all fetch this
album record.
See that it has no photos.
They're happy with it.
Now they have photos.
They each have photos that they
wish to add to the same album.
So, now they in-queue that
update on that record.
Let's say our iPhone
gets there first.
And now the server knows
about one of the photographs,
the references to one
of those photographs.
But, now when the other
new devices come in and try
to make their updates, they're
no longer updating the latest
version of the server record.
So, in this case, both of those
devices will see the error,
CK error serverRecordChanged.
Now, I invite you to take a look
at our advanced CloudKit talk
from WWDC '14 for more details
on how you can handle
this error.
But, let's see if we
can figure out a way
where we can avoid it entirely.
Well, in this case we know
that our album record is going
to have frequent rights on it.
So, instead if we model our
one-to-many relationship using a
back pointer by storing the
reference on the photo record
that is part of that album,
we completely eliminate
the right contention
that we had on our album record.
So, in this case whenever a
new photo needs to be added,
you just set a reference
on it to the album record
that it's a part of and
save the photo record.
But, by doing this you've
completely eliminated your
contention that you
had previously.
And now you might wonder, well,
how do I fetch all those photos,
which is part of my
problem to begin with?
Well, you can use
queries for this purpose.
Here's a query that
you need to be able
to fetch all photo records
that are part of this album.
It's pretty straight forward.
All you need to do is equate
it to the album reference field
that you have on
your photo records.
Next let's talk about
parent references.
On CKRecord this year,
we've added a new type
of reference called
a parent reference
that will help you
model your data in a way
that better supports
CloudKit sharing.
What we'd like to
recommend is that,
if your app supports sharing,
you use the parent references
to set up a hierarchical
data model.
Recognize the unit of
sharing in your apps and set
up the parent references
accordingly.
Let's take a look at an
example of what I mean by that.
Our photo and album
records are a great example
of using a parent reference.
An album is clearly a
parent of a photo record.
So, all we need to do is
set the parent property
on the photo record to
our album record ID,
and save that photo record.
Now, let's say that we've used
this model throughout our app,
and we end up with a
hierarchy that looks like this.
And now a user comes
along that wishes
to share this entire album.
Well, all you would need
to do in this case is,
create a CKShare with that album
record as the group record.
And in one fail swoop you will
share the entire hierarchy
that you set up using
parent references.
Now, CloudKit also supports
partially shared hierarchies.
So, in this case, if a
user might have only wanted
to share photo C, for example.
You could have created a
share just with photo C.
And in this case, only the photo
C and all its descendents set
up via parent references
will be part of that share.
And that was data modeling.
Let's talk about error handling.
Now, there are a few
different types of errors
and your application
should handle these
in a few main different ways.
And let's take a
look at each of them.
So, let's say we
have a simple example
where your device comes along
and you chose a
CKModifyRecordsOperation
and tries to talk to the server.
There are 2 main things that
the server might respond with.
It could either say that, I
didn't like that request at all,
please don't try it
again, or it could say
that everything was
fine with your request,
but right now is
not a good time.
Come back a little
later and try it again.
Now, we need your apps to
handle these 2 types of errors
in very different ways.
And let's take a
look at what that is.
The first kind of error,
which is a fatal error,
you really can't do much.
There are a couple
of error codes
which indicate a fatal error.
For example, internalError,
serverRejectedRequest,
invalidArguments, or
permissionFailure.
In this case, we want you
to show an appropriate UI
to your user in your
apps and let them know
that something went wrong,
which cannot be retried.
However, the other
type of error,
where the server wants you
to come back at a later point
and time, we will tell
you the amount of time
that the server wishes
for you to wait.
Here are a couple of error
codes that will have that value
of time embedded in them.
ZoneBusy, serviceUnavailable,
and requestRateLimited.
When you receive any of these
error codes, you should check
for the CKError RetryAfterKey
in the errors users
info dictionary.
You should wait for
that period of time
and reinitialize
the same CKOperation
with the same arguments,
and retry that operation.
Here's all the code you need for
a simple example of how to wait
for that period of
time represented
by the CKErrorRetryAfterValue.
And reinitialize the
same CKOperation.
Now, what happens in some cases
when your operations
might be failing
on the device before even
talking to the server?
There are 2 main cases that
I'd like to discuss today
where CloudKit may be
completely unavailable to you.
The first one is when
the device is off line.
Well, in this case,
what we recommend is
that you monitor network
reach-ability just
like you would for any
other network based app.
If you're using a quality
of service of user initiated
or above, such that a
network failures are not being
automatically retried for you,
you will see this error code
CKErrorNetworkUnavailable.
So, once you're monitoring
network reachability,
which you can do via the
SCNetworkReachability API,
for example, in system
configuration framework,
you can then let the
user know that, hey,
these changes are not going
to make it to the server yet.
But, we recommend that you let
your users keep interacting
with your app while
the device is offline.
You should save these changes
to where your local cache.
And when your reachability API
tells you the device is back
online, then you enqueue
your CloudKit operations
to save those records
to the server.
The other main state
is when you're trying
to use the private
database for a user
and the user is not logged
into an iCloud account.
In this case we will
return the error
code CKErrorNotAuthenticatedTo.
And what we recommend
is, for all of your apps,
on first launch always
register to listen
to the CKAccount
change notification.
When it fires use
the account status
with CompletionHandler API
to research the account
status for the current user.
And let them know that
certain operations may fail,
because they don't have an
iCloud account signed in.
So, in summary, let's take a
look at what we've seen today.
We saw how to subscribe
and fetch changes
to efficiently stay up
to date with the server.
We saw the advantages of using
the batch CKOperation API,
which we recommend all
of your apps adopt.
We saw a couple of tips on
how to design your schema
to completely avoid a
certain class of errors,
or to use the CloudKit
API more effectively.
And finally, we saw how to
handle certain types of errors.
And how to differentiate
between them.
And what the server
means when it comes back
with certain error code
as opposed to others.
Now, we had a related
session yesterday.
If you could not check it
out, I invite you to go back
and look at it online.
More information
is available here.
Thank you and have a great day.
[ Applause ]