[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Good morning.
>> Thank you.
I'd like to welcome the
physicians who came here today
who also code and the developers
who are working with researchers
to create great research apps.
And of course, that includes
our students who are here today
who I know are already
using ResearchKit.
Welcome to all of you.
Would you like to see a
great ResearchKit app?
>> Yes.
>> Good, I'm glad there are at
least a couple of people awake
after last night's party.
Autism & Beyond from
Duke Medicine.
Yes and we do have the Duke
developers here, so thank you.
Autism & Beyond from Duke
Medicine is a study that seeks
to identify and understand the
risks for child development.
In this ResearchKit app a
young child views a video
and the forward facing camera
records their reaction.
Let's take a look.
>> The itsy bitsy spider
went up the water spout.
>> The app analyzes the video of
the child for emotional reaction
and extracts facial expression.
One day a video like this might
be used to screen a young child
in her own home for autism
and other mental health
challenges like anxiety.
If the research is
successful, Duke will be able
to use science-based tools
to help parents understand
and support their
child's development.
I think this app is pretty
amazing and it's just one
of the many apps that
have been created
over the past year
using ResearchKit.
Today, my colleague, Yuan Zhu,
and I hope that we
can inspire you
to create other great
ResearchKit apps like this.
Today, we will go over the
new features in ResearchKit,
we'll talk a little bit
about the contributions
from the open source community
and how you can contribute.
But first, I'd like to start
with a recap of ResearchKit.
We introduced ResearchKit over
a year ago and the aim was
to take the basic components
of clinical research
and to move them over
to the mobile world.
And those basic components
are informed consent,
survey tasks and active tasks.
It's pretty staggering to think
about the number of iPhones
that are in the world
and how users like you
and I can contribute
to research.
But there's some
significant differences
between clinical research
and the mobile world,
specifically in clinical
research.
The participant is right there
where the researcher can
see them and show them what
to do and be with them.
So when you move to the mobile
space there are some things
to consider.
I'd like to go over
each of these components
and show you how
ResearchKit does them.
Informed consent is
requirement for all studies
that use human subjects.
Researchers are required to tell
participants what the study's
about, what data they're going
to collect, how they're going
to use the data, how they're
going to ensure privacy,
how the person can withdraw from
the study, and many more things.
So typically what
happens is that a person
like in the Autism & Beyond
study will be given a form
like this to read.
It's rather long because
if you were to put it end
to end it would be
taller than I am.
So it's a lot of text the
person needs to go through.
So translating this
to ResearchKit we developed
an informed consent module
and what we do is we
split this large form
into a series of screens.
On each screen it describes
that particular section,
gives an overview,
provides a learn more link
where the participant can drill
down and get more information
if they want to, as they're
doing here with withdrawing.
And then at the end everything
is put back together again
for one final review and
then the person can decide
to participate in
the study or not.
If they decide to participate in
the study, then they'll be asked
to give their name and sign an
electronic consent form just
as our most famous user, Johnny
Appleseed, is doing here.
Now what I want to point
out is if you're a developer
and you're doing your first
ResearchKit app you can't just
cut and paste this
text here that Duke has
or any other study has.
Informed consent
text is approved
by an institutional review board
or ethics committee and you need
to use the text that
they give them.
And you also have to like resist
the urge to be a creative writer
and to like, you know, I look
at these things and think wow,
I can simply this, I can make
this really exciting to read.
But you don't want to
do that, you just want
to take what the researcher
gives you and make sure
that it has been approved.
So that's informed consent.
In clinical research researchers
typically have a participant do
at least one survey if only
to ask for demographic data.
But it's also quite
common for researchers
to use standard surveys
like this,
the patient health
questionnaire or PHQ-9.
Now it's pretty easy to
translate a paper survey
into a mobile survey
and ResearchKit tries
to make this a little
bit more pleasant
by in most cases putting
one question per page.
And of course, we can support
anything that paper has in terms
of fill in the blank,
multiple-choice.
But because it is mobile
ResearchKit can do even more.
You can do your multiple-choice,
it can have a truly
sliding-scale where you have
to slide your finger, you can
give location as an answer
or date and time or images.
There are many, many
rich answer formats
in ResearchKit that
can be there.
Good, the date looks
right for me now.
So that was our survey tasks.
Now active tasks, in a clinical
setting a participant might be
asked to do something like walk,
so the researcher can
observe their gait or maybe
to solve a puzzle
or tell a story
for psychological research.
Or they might even
be asked to do things
like that require fine
motor coordination.
And again, in the clinic
you have somebody there
to show you how to do it
and to make sure you're
doing it correctly.
So I'm going to show
you two tasks
so that you can get an idea
of how ResearchKit
handles active tasks.
The first is a voice task and
here the participant is asked
to say "ah" into the microphone
and then the app collects the
audio and analyzes it in any way
that is fit for that
particular research.
So this task has all the
components that can be
in an active task, so
let's go through them.
There is a page that
describes what the task is,
that gives instructions to the
user on how to perform the task,
and a lot of active tasks
have a countdown timer.
And then some feedback
to the user
and in this case it's
saying that she's too loud,
so you can make sure that
you do the task correctly.
All the screens you
see, the animation,
the screen to screen navigation
are all provided by ResearchKit.
To get this task you
only need to use one call
in ResearchKit, it's that easy.
Here's another task.
This is a tapping speed task
where a user needs to tap back
and forth as fast as she
can during a given time.
But there are many, many
other tasks in ResearchKit,
including a walking task,
spatial memory task,
and there are others.
So those are active tasks.
From the first day
that ResearchKit was released it
was integrated with HealthKit.
It's very easy in Xcode to
add the HealthKit entitlement
to your app and it doesn't take
too many more lines of code
to get a screen like this
where you can ask the user
to have access to the
data in HealthKit.
When you do that you need to
specify the data that you want
to read from and write
to the health app.
The user has the option to give
you permission for everything
that you ask for or she can
just give you permission
for specific pieces.
So I suggest that when you are
going to ask for access to data
that you ask only for the data
that you're absolutely going
to use in your research.
So don't ask for everything
and you'll have a better chance
of success of getting that
permission from the user.
One of the big questions
that we got asked
over the past year is what does
ResearchKit do with the data,
where does it store it.
And that's really
easy for me to answer
because ResearchKit doesn't
do anything with data.
If you were here for last year's
presentation on ResearchKit
where John Earl explained
the architecture
of ResearchKit he also talked
a lot about result objects.
And the short story is
that ResearchKit has
a results property
on the Task View controller
and it will hand you the
results in that property.
But it's up to your app to
persist the data locally
and also for a research study
you want to send that data
to secure server where you
can aggregate and analyze it.
If you haven't watched
John Earl's presentation
from last year I suggest
that you do so because
in it he also shows how
to code informed consent,
survey tasks and active tasks.
But rather than have me
go over that coding today
because you can watch that
video I would like to bring
up my colleague, Yuan Zhu, who
can go over the new features
of ResearchKit and explain
to you how to code with them.
Yuan.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you Bunny.
The open source community
discovers
that mobile research
needs more features
than research can provide it.
And we have been
collaborating with the community
to add more features
to ResearchKit.
So today, I'm really excited
to show you three of them.
First, branching task.
It can be confusing
on the paper,
but on mobile devices this
is really themed to the user.
Second, app access.
It protects user's privacy
and data, which is critical
to most of the research apps.
Last, charts.
Present the data in a
visual way to your user,
then your user can
understand the data better.
First, I will talk about the
first one, branching task.
Whether your app is
giving instructions,
presenting a survey or running
an active task everything
in ResearchKit is a
collection of steps,
which together form a task
and the task can be
presented to the user.
With this model it's
quite straightforward
to create a linear task,
but branching task is not
that obvious how to create.
Let me show you an example.
What you see here is a
survey with three questions.
And apparently it only makes
sense to ask the second question
to the user who has
responded yes
to the first question,
do you own a car.
And the last question,
do you own a bicycle
should always be asked
at the end regardless the answer
to the first two questions.
Then you may wonder how
could I create this survey
in ResearchKit.
To help you do that I
introduce you a new class,
ORKNavigableOrderTask.
Since it's a task, so it has
a collection of steps as well.
But besides that it also holds a
collection of navigation rules.
The navigation rules defines
the branching logic in the task.
Next, I'm going to show you
how to use this new class
to present a survey
and just show to you
and it's really easy to use.
In the code first I need to
create those question steps.
Once I have the questions steps
I can create the navigable order
tasks with those steps.
As you can see, it's as easy
as create a linear task.
But after that I need to create
the navigation rule for it.
The navigation rule I'm
trying to create here is
to display own a
bicycle question right
after the own car question to
the people who don't have a car.
And I want to let you know
the navigation rule has
three elements.
First, a trigger step, which
it triggers the navigation rule
to be evaluated.
Second, expected answer, so
expected answer here is no
to the first question,
do we own a car.
Last, it requires
a designation step.
Now you have learned the three
elements in the navigation rule.
Let me show you the code now.
In the code first I
use the resultSelector
to locate where is the result.
And then I create the predicate
with the expected answer.
After I have the predicate I
can create the navigation rule
with the destination step.
Last, I'll add the first
question, do you own a car,
to be the trigger step.
As you can see, it's
quite easy just one, two,
three I create this
navigation rule.
And also the task is ready
to be presented to the user.
Now you have learned how
to use branching task.
Next, let me show
you the app access.
User account is a
very important aspect
of managing the user
in your app.
App access provide this
necessary functionality.
Two basic operations to
support account in your app,
account registration
and account login.
Account registration allows
your user to log in to register
with your app is
password and username.
And a registered user
can use account login
to continue participating in
your app even on a new device.
So that's account.
And you may know, user's privacy
and data security
are very important
for most of the research apps.
To help you do that we recommend
your app to allow the user
to set up a passcode [inaudible]
and use it later
to unlock your app.
Same here there are two
basic operations in passcode.
First, passcode creation.
It lets user to select
a desired passcode.
Once the passcode is created,
then the app can assist the user
to enter the correct
passcode to enter the app
to use passcode authentication.
Now you have learned app
access has two parts,
account and passcode.
Let me show you the
account part first.
You see here it's a screenshot
of account registration.
It lets a user register
with your app
by providing an email address
and enter the possible
twice to avoid typos.
Next, I will show
you this in code.
All I need is to create one
step ORKRegistrationStep
with identifier, title and text.
And the last parameter
options can be used
to provide additional
input fields
like gender or date of birth.
Once I have this step I can put
it into a task and present it.
After the step is completed I
need to retrieve the username
and password from
the result object.
It's easy to do.
I just need to use the
predefined identifier
to get them.
Once I have the username
and password I can securely
send them to a remote server
to create the account
for the user.
So that's account registration.
Next, account login.
For the user who
already registered want
to continue participating
in your app.
You see here it's a
screenshot of the account login.
It allows a user to log in
with username and password.
Additionally, if a user forgot
his password there's a button
available for them
at the bottom.
We only need a few lines code
to create this in your app.
Same here, we need
a step ORKLoginStep.
I create this step with
identifier, title, and text.
And you may notice the
last parameter I need
to provide a
ViewControllerClass.
Why? Because I need to
subclass the view controller
from the ResearchKit to
provide my own custom handler
to the action forgot password in
case something forgot password
and click that button.
After I have done this,
then this login step is
ready to be presented.
Now I'm showing you account
registration and account login.
Next, let me show you how to
let your user create an account,
create a passcode and use
it to unlock your app later.
In the process of passcode
creation the user will be asked
to enter the passcode first,
then confirm it and optionally,
if the device has Touch ID
enabled the user can opt
in to use Touch ID to
unlock your app later.
You can see here a few steps,
but in the code it's
really easy to do.
Same I need one step,
ORKPasscodeStep
and after I create
it I recommend you
to provide a decryption text to
your user to explain the purpose
of setting up a passcode.
That's all I need to do.
Some of you may want to ask
where the passcode is being
stored, that's a good question.
Let me show you that.
From this diagram you can see
the passcode is being stored
in the iOS Keychain,
so it's secure
and also telling you
the passcode writing
and passcode reading are both
managed by the ResearchKit,
so you don't need to
worry about it all.
Isn't that cool?
>> Yeah.
>> Thank you.
After you learn this let me show
you the passcode authentication.
The passcode authentication
allow the user
to enter the correct passcode
before accessing the app.
Let me show you the code.
All I need is a view controller.
I can create this
view controller easily
and also I need to
remember assign a delegate
to it at the end.
I will show you next how
to implement this delegate.
The passcode authentication view
controller's delegate provides
opportunities to the developers
to handle the different result
of the possible authentication.
For example, if the passcode
authentication succeed I can
present that function
to the users.
But if the passcode
authentication failed I need
to show alert or the passcode
authentication is canceled I can
show the default welcome
screen to the user instead.
So that's this delegate and also
this new controller is ready
to be displayed to the user.
Now I have showed you all
the parts in the app access,
I hope you find it useful.
I can show you the charts.
With charts you can present
your data to your user.
There are three types of charts
in ResearchKit, as you can see
from those screenshots.
There are pie charts, line
graph, and discrete graph.
Let's zoom into the
first one, pie chart.
A pie chart is [inaudible] ring
and which is divided
into segments.
Each of them represent a
proportion of the whole
and each segment has its
own value, color and title.
Once you have learned the basics
of this pie chart I can show
you the code behind this.
To code it I need to create
this pieChartView first,
then I'll assign a data
source object to it
because the data source object
provide all the information
to be displayed in the chart.
Now I need to implement
this data source,
but before I'm jumping
onto those functions I need
to take some time to set
up the data object first.
In order to do that I first
define a base structure
to carry the basic information
for each segment in the chart.
You can see from here I
defined the base structure
with title, value, and color.
All the basic information
that is needed.
Once I have done that I
can create the data objects
with those structures.
Next, I will return
them in the functions.
Since I already have these
objects ready I can create those
functions easily.
First, I return the
total number of segments,
then I return the value of
each segment and the value
that will be used to calculate
the proportion in the ring.
After that is a color
and the title.
After I have done that,
then this pie chart is
ready to be displayed.
Now you have learned how to
use pie chart with ResearchKit.
And line graph and discrete
graph are quite similar to use.
You can simply go
to GitHub site,
download our simple
project to learn from it
and you can see the
URL on the screen.
Branching task, app access,
and charts are the three
new features I introduced
to you today.
With them I'm sure you will find
doing a research app will be
more easier.
Now I'm giving it back
to my colleague, Bunny,
to talk about contributing
to ResearchKit.
[ Applause ]
>> The reason why
ResearchKit has
so many great new features is
because of our open
source community.
Many of our contributors
are here today
and I'd like to thank them.
But any of you out
there can work with us
to make ResearchKit even
better, so let me tell you how.
Contributing to ResearchKit
is like contributing
to any other open
source project.
Go to our GitHub repo,
pick or open an issue
and please drop us a line
and let us know what
you're working on.
Then submit a pull request.
At that time Apple
engineers and active members
of the ResearchKit community
will take a look at your code
and no doubt they're
going to have some advice
for you on how to improve it.
So we want you to work
with the review team
until everyone's happy.
Then your changes will get
merged into the master branch.
Sometimes later we'll
branch for convergence.
At that time you code
will have been localized
into all the languages
that iOS supports,
updated for accessibility,
and tested on a wide variety
of devices and scenarios.
We'll also look at your code
with an eye towards
privacy and security.
Now this open source process
might seem a little Apple
centric to you, but
we want to make sure
that your code can be used all
over the world and by users
who have a variety of
different abilities
and on a variety of
different devices.
So now that you know
how to contribute some
of you might have ideas of
what to contribute and others
of you maybe you don't,
so I'd like to give you
a little inspiration.
But before I do that we do tag a
new stable version at some point
and our last stable version is
Win.3 that we tagged in January.
Okay, so what can
you contribute?
Of course, you can
contribute active tasks,
I've already showed you a few.
This year we've had a 9-hole
peg test contributed and I'd
like to thank Julian
Therrier [assumed spelling]
for contributing that.
This task is supposed
to be a digital version
of a test that's
done in the clinic
for rehabilitation medicine
to test upper extremity
functioning.
Now right now this task
is undergoing validation
in a research study because
we don't really know whether
or not this digital
version is equivalent
to the one in the clinic.
So validation is
really important.
When you develop a new task
researchers want to know
that what you say it's measuring
that the task is
really measuring that.
So you might have to get
involved in a little bit
of validation study to do that.
The Tower of Hanoi is a
puzzle that's commonly used
in psychological research and
I'd like to thank James Cox
for this contribution.
I'm sure there are many
other tasks out there.
In fact, researchers often write
to me and say that they would
like things like maybe the
Stroop, which is the color test
or psychomotor vigilance task.
So there are many
things out there
that if you ask researchers
I'm sure
that you can develop
these tasks.
There are many other
answer formats than what's
in ResearchKit I'm sure and
I'd like to thank Quintiles
for giving us the
location answer format.
As you probably gathered
from Yuan, the basic thing
in ResearchKit is a step and
there are always many more steps
that could be contributed.
I'd like to thank
Quintiles once again
for contributing a wait step.
This step turns out
to be really important
when you're doing a very
lengthy calculation and you want
to get the results to the
user before they proceed
on with other steps in the task.
Modules are encapsulated
pieces of functionality
that help researchers.
Yuan just told you
about the charts module,
this is a great contribution
and I'd
like to thank Ricardo Sanchez
[inaudible] and James Cox
for contributing this.
Just about every new ResearchKit
app is using this module
and it turns out that users love
to see charts about their data,
their progress in the study,
and things about the study.
The genetic basis of
condition is of interest
to many researchers and right
now there are two ResearchKit
apps out there looking
at genetics.
PPD Act is looking
at the genetic basis
of postpartum depression
in women.
And MyHeart Counts recently
added a genetic component
so that they could
look at genetics
in cardiovascular health.
It turns out if you want
to collect genetic material
from someone, there is an
informed consent process that's
above and beyond what's
required in your app.
So I'd like to thank
23andMe for coming
up with the ResearchKit module
that shows how to do the --
that has informed consent in it.
And right now they're hosting
this on their own website,
so if you want to use 23andMe
to collect genetic data you
could go to their website
and get this ResearchKit module.
And the great thing is that
they have complete documentation
of how to add this to your
app and the modifications
that you need to make
in your app to make sure
that this works really well.
I'm sure there are other modules
that you could contribute.
Now as I mentioned before,
ResearchKit doesn't do anything
with your data, so you need to
connect it to a data service.
If you're someone who provides
data services I suggest
that you download our sample,
ORKSample and you modify it
to use your data service,
then host that modified app
on a GitHub repo, so people
can come there and see how
to connect their ResearchKit
app to your data service.
It would be a great help to
researchers who are struggling
with trying to get that
data over to a server.
So after you've made all these
code contributions maybe you
want to do more.
I can see some of you.
If you've gone
to ResearchKit.org
recently you'll see
that we feature a number
of tutorials written
by the open source community.
Specifically, I'd like to thank
the [inaudible] Blog in France
and Raywenderlich.com.
We love to see developers
teaching other developers how
to code.
And if you're one of those rare
people who know how to code
and write, please find
a topic in ResearchKit
that you think needs
explaining and write a tutorial.
Then let us know about it
and we'll help you
to get out the word.
Now while the ResearchKit
community has been busy writing,
so has Apple.
We've updated the
ResearchKit programming guide
and reference documentation
earlier this year
and we also added a chapter
to the iOS Human Interface
Guidelines to give you guidance
on how to write a
great ResearchKit app.
If you haven't read that,
please go out and do
so at your earliest convenience.
I have some homework for you.
This is your call to action.
If you haven't already
downloaded ResearchKit
framework, please do so today.
You'll get access all
the great new features
that Yuan talked about.
Inside the framework you'll
see a sample folder and in
that is the ORKSample app,
we added that this year.
I suggest that you build and
run it, it's a great app.
It's in Swift, it uses best
practices not only for Swift
and ResearchKit, but
for iOS in general.
It has a great architecture
for a ResearchKit app.
You can even start with that app
and you'll have a great
start on your own research.
Also build and run
the ORKCatalog app.
As its name suggests,
it's a catalog
of ResearchKit functionality.
When you run it you'll see
what each active task does,
you'll get a look at
all the answer formats,
you can even see what
an eligibility survey is
like and more.
And finally, please
make a contribution.
ResearchKit is open source
and it will become
only what you make it.
Everything you need to get
started with ResearchKit is
on this page,
developer.apple.com/WWDC16/234.
There's links to
the GitHub repo,
to the tutorials I talked about,
to own documentation,
so please look at it.
This afternoon I'd
like you to join us
at the Getting Started
with CareKit session.
CareKit is a new open source
framework that we introduced
in March and that will help you
to build great apps for people
to manage their own care.
So with that, thank you and
have a great rest of WWDC.