[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you.
Good afternoon everyone.
Welcome to the session
Getting Started with CareKit.
I'm Umer. I'm an engineer
on the CareKit Team.
Our agenda will consist of
exploring the story of CareKit
and how it came about.
Taking a look at an app
that utilizes CareKit
to enhance the patient-provider
experience.
Working through the CareKit
architecture in order
to create an app here.
Then a demo of an app that uses
a customization in CareKit.
And then lastly what's
next, how Apple
and the developer
community can work together
to take it to the next level.
So before I talk
about what CareKit is,
let's see where it came from.
Many of you might be
familiar with ResearchKit.
It's a framework that
we released last year
that enables providers
and medical researchers
to create a study
that they can conduct
on a large-scale using iPhones.
So if you're interested, I
would recommend taking a look
at the session from
earlier today.
What's New in ResearchKit,
hosted by Bunny Laden
and Yuen Xiou [phonetic].
And the ResearchKit
session from last year,
hosted by John Roll [phonetic],
Building Apps with ResearchKit.
In the past year with
ResearchKit, we received a lot
of requests on study
participants,
to be able to see the data
that they were providing
for medical research.
This led us to brainstorm
patient-centric modules.
While brainstorming these
modules, these are the use case
for care, expanding beyond the
boundaries of medical research.
And therefore from ResearchKit
evolved our new framework,
CareKit.
So CareKit is an open source
framework that enables providers
to build apps that
can empower patients
to take an active
role in their care.
Now CareKit is great for
chronic and acute use cases.
So a great example for a chronic
use case is mental health.
Where medication
tracking is critical.
Also doing assessments like
depression and anxiety surveys
to see your progress and
performing activities
that actually improve
your mental health.
Just stuff that you need
to do outside of a group --
a support group or
therapy session.
And then another good
example is surgery where one
of the most critical parts
is the recovery phase,
post-surgery.
So let's focus on this use case,
and walk through the current
scenario of the patient
and provider experience.
So currently, if you leave the
hospital or a doctor's office,
you're given a sheet of
paper that looks like this.
This has everything you need
to do for a healthy recovery.
This sheet of paper has some
very specific instructions,
with many that change over time.
The compliance to these
types of plans is horrible.
And they typically
lead to user confusion.
These plans are not dynamic,
and therefore they don't change
based on the user's improvement.
And ultimately the
patient returns
to the hospital to be retreated.
Our goal with CareKit
was to solve this problem
and take something like
this sheet of paper,
and turn it into what
we call a Care Card.
Now this is a Care Card
that allows the patient
to see their entire
treatment plan.
One that is interactive,
updated dynamically,
and it provides a great sense
of progress for the patient.
So in the development of
this module we discovered
that there's so much
more we can do
because now we're on an iPhone.
And that let us create
three other modules to help
with the patient
care experience.
The Symptom and Measurement
Tracker,
which records subjective
and objective measurements.
The insides dashboard, that
displays the data in the app
in a way that enables
a patient to see trends
and gaps in their care.
And the connect module
that enables communicating
and sharing the data with a
family member or your care team.
So let's see how
these come together
to enhance the patient-provider
experience.
Texas Medical Center was one of
our initial partners of CareKit.
They've taken these modules
to create a unique
patient-provider experience.
So let's take a look at
these modules in action.
At first, you are greeted with
a walk-in screen that allows you
to create an account or log in.
Our patient, John Appleseed,
has already registered
and is set up to use the app.
So John wakes up and
receives a notification
that he needs to weigh himself.
He enters the app
with a secure passcode
and then he weighs
himself on a smart scale
and the value is
transferred into HealthKit.
And the CareKit app will
autopopulate the data
using HealthKit.
This is very easy
to do with CareKit,
because CareKit provides
seamless integration
with HealthKit.
After recording his weight,
John goes to his Care Card
to see what he needs
to do on his --
what's on his to-do list today.
So the Care Card and the Symptom
and Measurement Tracker
we're looking at,
is populating its
content directly
from the ERM Health System
at Texas Medical Center.
So John doesn't recall
the specifics for one
of his activities,
the short walk.
So he can tap into that cell,
and he can read the
instructions for this activity.
And then John completes
his activity,
and takes his first
dose of medication.
He now taps into
the Assessments Tab
to see what assessments he
needs to complete today.
In his Symptom and Measurement
Tracker, he wants to indicate
that he has some surgical
side pain, and some signs
of what could be an infection.
So first he records
his pain score,
using the scale assessment.
And then he decides to take
a photo of the infected area,
and upload it to the app.
And he can do that
directly from the Symptom
and Measurement Tracker,
and this data is
transmitted to his provider.
Lastly, he performs a
get-up-and-go activity.
As he is walking around
to complete this activity,
the sensors on the iPhone are
being used to record his steps.
And once he has completed
the entire activity,
the data is transmitted
directly to his provider.
So John decides to take a look
at the Insights Dashboard now
to see his data for
the last couple weeks.
He can see the tips and
charts for the current week.
This provides a way for him to
understand his data in a visual
and user-friendly way.
And then he also navigates
to the previous week,
to be able to compare his
current week's performance.
Meanwhile, he is still worried
about the possible infection
that he reported earlier
in the assessments.
So he decides to send a
message to his care team member.
He taps to compose a
message, and he decides
to email his provider,
Dr. Paul Cashman.
In his message, he does not need
to upload the infection
photo anymore
because it's already been
transmitted to Dr. Cashman
through the infection
assessment.
So then later in the day,
he receives a reply message
from his care team
member, Dr. Paul Cashman.
And he can go back into
his app and see the message
that the provider
has provided to him.
And that's how Texas Medical
Center has taken the CareKit
module, and created an app that
can completely close the loop
with the patient-provider
experience.
[ Applause ]
Thanks. Let's take a
look at the process
of creating an app
just like them.
Here are the four
front-end modules
that we've already looked at.
Accompanied by two back-end
modules: The Care Plan Store
and the Document Exporter.
Now we'll go into each one of
these, but let's first focus
on the Care Plan Store.
The Care Plan Store consists
of activities and events.
So let's begin by defining
what activities and events are,
then creating an activity
and adding it to the store,
exploring the relationship
between activities and events,
and then bringing
these up to the UI.
So if you look at
this Care Card here,
we can visualize what an
activity and an event is.
Let's focus on the ibuprofen.
Where Ibuprofen 200
mg is the activity.
And the circles underneath
are the events.
And then activities and
events come together
to create the Care Plan Store.
So here's an activity.
Let's go ahead and
create an ibuprofen one.
You'll first give an identifier,
which we've used
ibuprofen medication here.
This helps uniquely
identify this activity
in the Care Plan Store.
Then a group identifier to
be able to create groups
of certain activities that you
can query the backend store
later on.
The title is Ibuprofen.
The text is 200 mg.
Now these properties
surface to the user.
So be sure they properly
define what the activity is.
The tint color, which can be
any UI color, so we chose blue.
Apart from the tint
color on each activity,
there are many other
customization properties
that are available in CareKit
and we'll discuss
them in a little bit.
Now the two properties
I really want to focus
on are type and schedule.
So the type determines
which front-end module
this activity belongs to.
So for example, we
have an intervention,
which belong on the Care Card.
And we have assessments,
which are shown in the Symptom
and Measurement Tracker.
So because we're creating
a medication activity,
it belongs in the Care Card.
Therefore, the activity
type is intervention.
Next, I want to focus
on schedule.
The schedule determines
how many times,
and when this activity
should happen.
So there are three
different ways
to specify the days
for the schedule.
You can use a daily
schedule, a weekly schedule,
or you can create your
own custom schedule.
And then you can
specify the frequency,
to indicate how many times per
day this activity should occur.
Now this sounds a
little bit complicated,
but it's really not.
So let's simplify it.
Let's go ahead and define a
schedule for our activity.
Well here's a weekly schedule.
And we'll say we want the
patient to take this medication
on Monday, Wednesday,
and Friday.
And then we can use a frequency
to specify four times on Monday,
twice on Wednesday, and
four times on Friday.
And then combined together
it creates a schedule object
for this activity.
And now we have a complete
activity ready to be added
to the Care Plan Store.
So before we look
at the code on how
to create the Care Plan Store
and add this activity in there,
let's just discuss what an
event is really quickly.
So an event is an object
that a developer never
directly initializes.
In fact, it's created
automatically
by the Care Plan Store.
So to understand how these
are created, let's go back
to the schedule object
we just had.
A schedule object
generates events based
on the frequency you specify.
So for example, here, we
have four events on Monday.
Therefore, we've got four
events for June 20th.
And then we have two
events on Wednesday,
so you've got two for June 22nd.
And then it'll keep
on generating them.
So the way you can stop the
generation of these events,
is by specifying an end date.
Once you specify an end
date for an activity,
the Care Plan Store will
stop generating these events.
So even though a developer
doesn't create an event,
it provides a lot of
useful information.
From an event object you can
retrieve the date of the event.
You can see what state it is
in, such as an initial state,
which means the user
hasn't invoked it.
It could be completed
or not completed.
The results object contains
the completion status of it.
As things such as
when it was completed,
and any other information you
want to store along with that.
And then there's also a
pointer back to the activity
that this event came out of.
So activities generate
events in the Care Plan Store
and combined together they
create what we call here,
a Care Plan Store.
So let's take a look
at the code for this.
So now to create
a Care Plan Store,
it's very straight forward.
You just define a variable,
which I have here
myCarePlanStore
of type OCKCarePlanStore.
Then you have to define a
persistent directory URL.
Which in this case
I've used application
to documents directory.
And then you just initialize
the [inaudible] URL,
and you have a Care
Plan Store ready to use.
So now, let's go ahead and
add the ibuprofen activity
that we just created.
First you will create
a schedule object.
So you have a start
date just specified
as the beginning of this year.
And then using a weekly
schedule, I can use the array
for occurrences on each day to
specify how many times per day.
So for example, our
array starts on Sunday.
So zero on Sunday, four on
Monday, and zero on Tuesday.
And then so on and so forth.
So once you have that
object, you go ahead
and initialize the
care plan activity.
You give it the identifier,
the group identifier.
All the other parameters
will be defined.
There's two here that we
have not discussed yet,
which is instructions
and image URL.
So these are shown
on the detailed [inaudible]
for that activities.
For example, when John
Appleseed clicked on short walk,
he could see additional
instructions for it.
So we'll have additional
instructions for ibuprofen along
with an image, and we'll
take a look at how this looks
when we look at the Care Card.
And then to add this activity
to the Care Plan Store,
we just call the add method
passing the activity you've
created, and then use
a completion handler
for any error checking
you would like to do.
That's how you create
a Care Plan Store
and that's how you
add an activity to it.
Let's see how we can use
the data in here to show it
onto the Care Card now.
Creating the Care Plan Store
and adding an activity
is the tougher part.
Showing it on the Care Card
is actually very simple
and straightforward.
I'm going to show you the
activity we just added.
Emphasize the type property
here, that it's intervention.
So because you set intervention,
the Care PlanS tore
already knows
to show it on the Care Card.
And then to actually
create the Care Card,
you just initialize the
CareCardViewController
with a carePlanStore object.
You embed it inside a
NavigationController.
The reason this is necessary is
because we provide some
bar button items to assist
with calendar navigation as
well as details that we push
onto the navigation stack.
And then you just present
it, or we can embed it
into a tab bar controller.
And with these three
lines of code,
you get what we have
here is a Care Card.
[ Applause ]
So as you can see here, we have
the ibuprofen activity along
with some other ones
that I've added.
And then let's look at the
different components of this UI
to understand what
we're looking at.
So the header view shows you
a glance of the current week.
You can slide left and right
to navigate between weeks.
You can select a specific date
to see the details for that day.
The heart completion here
is automatically calculated
and updated based
on the information
in the Care Plan Store.
So the heart and the fill
color here are customizable.
You can specify a
different image
that might suit your
use case better.
And then the fill
color can be changed
to match the custom image.
And we'll see an
example of a Care Card
that has this customization
later on.
Now below the header
is the treatment plan.
This shows all the interventions
that the user needs
to complete for that day.
So any time you add
or remove an activity
from the Care Plan Store, this
UI gets updated automatically,
with no additional work
necessary from the developer.
So here's ibuprofen
intervention we just added.
And if you tap on the
cell, it will take you
into the detail view which
has the detail instructions,
as well as an image
of the medication
so that the user does not
confuse them with other pills
that they might be taking.
Now let's take a look at
a different intervention.
So this one here asks the user
to stand and move a little.
So while this is something
the user can self-report
by just tapping into the cell,
it can also be updated
automatically using sensors
on the Apple Watch.
So that brings me
to the next point,
is how can we update
these events?
Well there's different ways.
One of which, like we
said, is self-reported
such as medication tracking
where they can report they've
taken their medication.
They can be marked completed
after the user has
completed a task.
Such as an active
task from ResearchKit.
Or it can be updated
passively using the data
from device sensors
such as the Apple Watch
and the iPhone using HealthKit.
So that's the Care Card.
It's an interactive
treatment plan
that uses the Care Plan Store to
schedule activities and events,
and provide the user
with a focused experience
on their day-to-day health.
So just like the Care
Card, the Symptom
and Measurement Tracker also
uses the Care Plan Store
to record a subjective and
objective measurements.
So the process of adding an
assessment is very similar
to how we did in the
ibuprofen intervention.
So let's say that we have
a pain survey that you want
to create for your lower back.
The code here is nearly
identical to create this,
so we'll assume that
it's already been added
to the Care Plan Store.
Now let's take a look at how
you can create a Symptom Tracker
to actually show
this assessment.
Just like the Care Card, you
initialize the Symptom Tracker
with your controller with
a Care Plan Store object.
There's a delegate
that you can implement,
but I'll get to that shortly.
And then embed it into
a navigation controller.
And then again, just present it
to see something like this here.
So if we dissect this UI,
the header view contains
the similar navigation model
as the Care Card where
we can slide left
and right to change weeks.
We select specific days to
see details for that day.
As you're working on the
assessment for that day,
the ring -- there will be a ring
that shows you your progress.
And once you've completed them,
it'll turn into a checkmark
to know that you have no more
assessments for that day.
The color for the ring and the
checkmark can be customized
to suit your app.
Underneath here, you will have
a list of assessments that need
to be completed for the day.
Now there can be a
variety of assessments
so let's take a look
at some of them.
Here we have a pain survey.
For this you can use the
survey module in a ResearchKit
to present a beautifully
designed survey.
They can be an active task.
So you could launch
like a tapping test,
or create a custom active
task using ResearchKit,
such as the range of motion one.
It can be self-reported.
So you can present a view
controller, just like we did
in the Texas Medical Center
app, where you can ask the user
to take a photo of the
infection and report it back.
And then it could be any data
from a HealthKit or
Bluetooth device.
So in the Texas Medical
Center app,
John jumped onto
his smart scale,
and it automatically updated
the data and CareKit app.
So that's where the
delegate comes in.
In order to present the
appropriate assessment,
you have to implement the
Symptom Tracker delegate
which provides a callback
for the developer whenever the
user taps on an assessment cell.
In this call back, you're
given the assessment event
that they want to launch.
And then you can determine
which view controller
to present appropriately
at that point.
Once you've presented
the view controller,
let's say a pain survey,
you have to go ahead
and use the data from that
and calculate a pain score,
then you create a result object,
which takes in a value strength,
an optional unit strength, and
then a user info dictionary
for all the -- any additional
information you would need.
And then you just update the
Care Plan Store with this event,
the result object, the state
that it's entering into,
and then use the completion
block for any error handling.
And all that combined gives you
what you see here, the Symptom
and Measurement Tracker.
[ Applause ]
The Insights Dashboard can use
data from the Care Plan Store
to generate messages and charts.
And this allows the user to
better understand the data
that they're actually
looking at.
So for us to make this easy
for developers to create,
we've created what we
call insight items.
You can plug and play those
into the Insight's Dashboard.
And these also can include
messages such as tips or alerts.
And they can also be charts
such as the grouped bar chart
that we introduced in CareKit,
as well as any custom charts.
So for example the charts
from ResearchKit can
easily be subclassed
into our chart object.
So let's take a look at the
insight items in this dashboard.
This is a medication
adherence message item.
Message items help motivate
users to complete their care
by surfacing valuable
information about their health.
This message item is using
data from the Care Plan Store
to calculate the adherence for
ibuprofen for the past week.
These messages can also be
generated from a remote server,
and then passed into
the Insights Dashboard.
So let's look at the code on how
you can query the backend store.
Here you can specify start
date and an end date.
So I've used the beginning
of last week, Sunday,
and the end of last
week, Saturday,
as a start and end date.
Then we can call the
enumerateEvents method
on the Care Plan Store,
provide the activity we want
to enumerate on, the dates
that we want to enumerate from
and to, and then in the handler
we're given back all the events
in the store for that activity.
And then we can enumerate
through these events
to check their state
to determine
if they've been completed or
not, to calculate adherence.
So let's say we calculated
the adherence now,
and we want to go ahead
and create a message item.
Here you will want to take the
adherence you've calculated,
and turn it into a
user friendly message.
So that it's easier
for the user to read,
and actually gain
insights from it.
And then you just create --
initialize a message item with
a title, he message you would
like to show, a color,
nd then the message type.
For example, this one's a tip.
Next we have a group bar
chart that allows you
to present multi-series
data in a single chart.
For example, in this
chart we have pain
and ibuprofen mapped together
so the user can see their data
in a way that allows
them to visualize trends
and gaps in their care.
So here I've defined a
variable called barChartItem.
It's of type OCK insight ttem.
A barChartItem consists
of series.
In the one we just saw
there was a pain series
and an ibuprofen series.
So in order to create
this chart,
we will define a pain series
by initializing a bar
series with a title.
And an array of numeric
values, and then an array
of string values,
and the tint colors.
Now the number of items
in the array are not
limited by any means.
So your chart can show
weekly data, monthly data,
or any number of data points.
The array of numeric values is
what determines a bar length
on the chart.
And the array of string values
shows up right next to each bar.
Oftentimes these
are not the same.
For example, in the
ibuprofen series,
the numeric values determine
the length of the bar,
but they don't represent
the data itself.
For example, the 1-5-4 and so on
and so forth can
easily be misunderstood
to mean one tablet, five
tablets, or four tablets.
Therefore, the value
labels help the user know
that their medication is
adherence; 10 percent,
50 percent, and 40 percent.
So now that we have the
series that we need to show,
we're going to go ahead and
initialize a bar chart item.
Give it a title, a
text, a tint color.
And we've got two arrays for
axis titles and axis subtitles
that show up to the
left of each bar group.
And then you can specify
all the data skews you would
like to show.
This could be one, two, or ten.
Now there are two
optional parameters here
which is the scale.
The minimum scale range and
the maximum scale range.
If you don't specify these, we
automatically generate it based
on the data you've given us.
But if you do, then be mindful
of what you specify here
so that the data
doesn't seem skewed.
For example, if you have data
points that are going from one
to ten, and you specify a
scale that's from five to ten,
then all the points that are
below five will now be visible
to the user.
And it will make the
data seem out of context.
So we have a message
item we've created.
And we have a chart item.
Let's go ahead and create
the Insights Dashboard.
You initialize the
InsightsViewController
with an array of
these two items.
Give it an optional
header and a subtitle.
A title and a subtitle.
And then you just present it,
and you get something like this.
[ Applause ]
And that's how you
create an Insights Module.
So the next one is Connect.
Connect allows you to
communicate and share your data
with your care team and
your friends and family.
So to make this easy as well,
we've created what we
call CareKit contacts.
And there are two types here.
We've got a care team contact,
which is a physician or a nurse,
or any other care team member.
And then we have a
personal contact,
which could be a close
friend or a family member.
So if we look at
the Connect Module,
these show up grouped
by their type.
Here we have the care
team members up top.
And then down below we have
the friends and family.
So let's look at the code
on how we can create this.
To create a physician
contact, you define a variable.
PhysicianContact of
type, OCKContact.
And then you just initialize the
contact object with the type,
which is careTeam, the name,
the relation of the patient
to this contact, the tint color,
and then we have phone number
and message number, which
are CNPhoneNumber objects
for formatting purposes.
The email address is just a
string, and then a monogram
to be shown if there's
no image, or the image
to specify what the physician
or the care team
contact looks like.
Once you've created
all your contacts,
you just initialize the connect
view controller with an array
of all the contacts, and
then you just present it.
But there's also a delegate
here that you need to implement,
which we'll get to
in a little bit.
And before we can present
this, you have to embed it
in a navigation controller,
because we have master
and detail views for
the Connect Module.
So you will get a Connect
Module that looks like this
with the Connect
View Controller.
Now if we focus in on the
contact we just created,
Dr. Paul Cashman.
If we tap into the cell, it will
take you into the detail view
where you get a contact
card for him.
In this contact card, you see
all his contact information
up top here, which shows you
how you call him, text him.
Text message him, or
send him an email.
And then down below is
the ability to share
and send your reports with him.
Now this is where the
delegate comes into play.
The connect delegate
enables sharing the data
with this contact.
So for example, when the
user taps the share button,
this method is called.
And then you are given
the contact object
from which you can determine
what kind of a report
to generate and then you can
go ahead and share that report.
Now this part is
actually quite tedious.
To create the report
and to share it.
So let's see what we can
do to make this easier.
So to make the connect
module work hand --
to make it easy to share
data with the connect module,
we've created the
document exporter,
which works hand-in-hand
with it.
The document exporter
allows you to take the data
from the Care Plan Store.
And even other sources to create
a rich PDF that can be shared.
And just like everything
else we've done in CareKit
to make this easy, we've created
CareKit Document Elements.
You've got headers and footers.
We've got texts and paragraphs,
images, charts, and tables.
And then combining
all of these together,
you can create a rich
PDF that looks like this.
[ Applause ]
So as we can see in this
PDF we've got an image
of the patient, a user friendly
summary of their progress,
and now the same chart
that they were looking
at in their Insights
Dashboard can be seen here
by their provider, so that
they can all see the trends
and gaps in their care.
I know there's a
table that neatly lays
out all the subjective
and objective measurements
for these patients
on the previous week.
So let's take a look at
the code to create this.
We have a
DocumentElementPparagraph,
which is just text content.
This text content can also come
from the Care Plan Store
or a remote source.
Then we have a document
element chart
which basically accepts the same
chart object that you created
in the Insights Dashboard.
So there's no need
to do any new code,
or new chart generation here.
Then we have a table here which
gives you an array of headers.
And an array of arrays, in
which each array is a row
of the data you want to show.
For example, a weekly
data of the pain scores,
or a weekly data of
tapping tests results.
Then once you have all the
different elements you want
to use in the document, you
initialize a document object.
Give it a title.
And then give it an array
of all the elements.
And then turning
this document element
into a PDF is really
straightforward.
You just call the
createPDFData method.
Use the NSData that's returned
to you in the completion block,
and write it to a file URL.
So now when the user taps the
share button, we can go ahead
and generate the PDF using
the document exporter we just
created, present it
to the user to preview
so they know what they're about
to share, and then they can tap
on the share button and then
bring up the share sheet
to share this PDF with others
in the way they want to.
And that's how the Document
Exporter works hand-in-hand
with the Connect Module
to allow for data sharing.
[ Applause ]
So all these modules
come together
and form the CareKit framework.
So Patient PAL recently
transformed their entire patient
care experience using CareKit.
And I want to show you how
they've used customization
to match their user experience
and they've created
interventions and assessments
to help their patients
improve their health.
So their Care Card
replaces a heart
with a custom image
of an exercise buddy.
Their app is focused on
getting their patients
to perform certain
exercises throughout the day.
For example, if you focus on
the hip extension exercise,
the pink one down
below, we will tap
on the remaining
circle to complete it.
But before it can be
marked as completed,
we have to perform
this exercise.
In this exercise task,
there's a nice description
of the exercise along with a
video that the patient can watch
to make sure they're performing
the exercise correctly.
What's even nicer is
that they provide a way
to record yourself while
you're performing the exercise
so that the care provider
can see it as well.
When you tap the
Watch Video button,
it shows it embedded
within the task.
And once you feel like you've
understood the exercise,
you can tap Get Started
to start performing it.
And then there's an
active task that walks you
through each set and each rep.
Once you've completed
the exercise,
you can see under Care
Completion Progress updated
to reflect the change.
And now you've got a completion
for that little circle
down there.
So by default, we
don't provide --
we provide detailed views for
each activity on the Care Card
but you can implement
the delegate
to provide your own as well.
So one other thing that
they've customized here is
that when the user taps on
one of the detail views here,
for example the hamstring
stretch, it will go ahead
and bring up a view controller
that lets you send
reminders for these exercises.
So there's the two
that I've already done.
And then the third one,
I want to say that --
go ahead and let's
do it at 8:00 pm.
And now the app will go ahead
and me a push notification
to come back in and perform this
exercise to complete my care.
So CareKit provides a lot of
flexibility with this module,
so that you can tailor
them to suite your needs.
And these are some of the ones.
So that brings me
to the last section,
or slides What's
next for CareKit?
Currently, CareKit allows you
to build patient centric apps.
Next, we want to focus
on building the hooks
between these apps and
the provider clouds
and then also transmitting
that information from the cloud
to the care team app or portal.
This sort of infrastructure
can be seen
in the Texas Medical Center app
as well as the Patient PAL app.
What we would like is, as you're
building your CareKit apps
and linking them to your cloud,
you build these hooks in a way
that you can contribute
it back to the community.
And other people who are using
similar cloud solutions can also
benefit from it.
CareKit is open source.
It will become what
you make of it.
[ Applause ]
So please contribute.
You can find the
project on GitHub.
It's
on github.com/carekit-apple/
carekit.
So here's how you can help
us make CareKit even better.
Your role involves checking
out the issues section
on GitHub page.
You can create a new issue or
you can choose an existing one,
then develop the feature.
Feel free to reach out
to us or the community
with any questions you have
during the development.
And then work with us through
the code review process.
And this usually involves
you, the community,
and the Apple engineers.
And that's kind of where
our role also begins.
Once you have facilitated with
the development and review
of the feature, we'll
take it over
and enhance the feature even
more by providing accessibility.
We'll localize it for all the
languages we support in CareKit.
And then we'll do QA testing
for all the supported platforms.
We might ask for your help
during this process as well.
And then once the feature's
ready, we'll go ahead
and merge it into the framework.
With CareKit we are
excited to see how all
of us can work together
to create this new
patient-provider experience.
You can find more
information behind this URL.
It includes links to our website
and the GitHub repository,
as well as information on
how to get in touch with us
if you have any technical
questions,
or if you have a
great CareKit app idea
that you would like to share.
Be sure to check out
these related sessions
that can help you
build your CareKit app.
And thanks for coming
to this talk.
[ Applause ]