[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Hello, everybody.
Thank you for coming out
and spending your
Friday afternoon with us.
Hopefully you had a
great week at WWDC.
And I'm excited for our talk
now because I think we're going
to discuss something
that all of you want.
Fundamentally, everybody is here
because you love
building great apps,
and you probably want those
great apps to have more users.
Now, the good news is, we want
to figure out opportunities
to offer your app at the
right time to our customers,
so that you get more engagement.
And we're going to spend the
entirety of this talk discussing
about different ways
that you can do that.
We promote apps in
various forms,
throughout the operating system
today in many different places.
Siri app suggestions are
available to our customers
when they swipe left from home,
as well as when they
invoke search.
Even after entering a
query, you may get results
from inside other
third party apps.
Handoff is another way we
advertise third party apps,
your apps, as well.
As you start an activity from
one device and more to the next,
we try to anticipate what
you're about to do and offer
that app's icon in the bottom
left hand corner of the screen.
In certain situations, where
we think what you really want
to do is play a form of media,
we'll promote your app's content
to the lock screen
of the device.
So say after you plug in a
headphone or Bluetooth pair
to your car or your
speakers, if there's an app
that you usually use
in that circumstance,
the system will learn that, and
then offer not only that app,
but that app's content.
And we're going to talk today
about how you can build a great
experience for that environment.
As you're using the
operating system,
say reading a news article,
you can create reminders
that are contextual to the
content you're staring at.
So for example, if
you're reading an article
and you decide that you want to
take another look at it at home
or you want to read it at home
because you're in the middle
of watching a WWDC presentation,
you can invoke Siri.
And Siri will understand
what you mean when you say,
"Remind me about this."
It will have the context of
what's currently on screen.
And this will work in any app
that adopts some of the APIs
that we're going to
discuss later today.
This is particularly exciting
to you because this means
that when customers
open the Reminders app,
they'll be de-blinked right
back into your content.
New in iOS 10 is the promotion
of locations throughout
the system
when we think the customer has
a particular intent to want
to go somewhere, to
want to use a location
that they've been
recently looking at.
We'll be talking later today
about how you can get your app's
data flowing through the system.
Multitasking as well
is another interface
where we will promote locations
we think the customer is
interested in.
You can get your app, your
icon, suggested right there
at the prime real estate
in the Multitasking UI.
New in iOS 10 as
well is our promotion
of your app's contact
information
within the native contact app.
So you notice here, there's
a handle that's been found
in WhatsApp.
And we'll talk later today
about how you can get your
app's content in that interface.
So, to learn when to promote
you, the operating system needs
to learn about your
data and your app.
Now, the good news is that a few
simple APIs will give you much
of the value that I
just described and more.
In addition to having your
app promoted at various times,
you'll also get deeper Siri
integration like I described
with the contextual reminders.
So what we're going to do
today, is we're going to talk
about these APIs and
we're going to walk you
through proper adoption of
them so that all of you end
up getting more engagement
from users due
to promotion throughout the OS.
First, we're going to talk about
NSUserActivity and schema.org.
NSUserActivity is the kind
of the API that is the eyes
of the operating system.
It helps us understand what the
customer is currently staring
at on screen.
And schema.org is somewhat
of an equivalent for the web.
Next, we're going to talk
about some new enhancements
and new APIs around apps
that handle locations.
So if you're an app like
Yelp that's a directory
that offers many different
locations, or conversely,
if you're an app like Uber
that consumes locations,
this will be very
relevant to you.
Then we'll talk about
building a great experience
around media apps suggestions.
I showed you earlier an example
of the type of content promotion
that will happen, say
after a customer plugs
in their headphones,
and we'll talk
about how you can get
your content front
and center in that interface.
And then, we'll try to overview
about all the different things
we hopefully learn today.
To kick things off with
NSUserActivity and schema.org,
I'd love to invite
Sofiane onto the stage.
Sofiane?
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Daniel.
Good afternoon everyone.
My name is Sofiane.
And I'm really excited to
be here today to talk to you
about some of the features
that we've been up to lately.
Now, we just heard Daniel
talk about great ways
to promote the content in your
apps, throughout the system.
Now let's talk about
some of the APIs
that you can adopt
to make this happen.
Throughout this presentation,
we'll talk about features.
Some that you may be already
familiar with, like Handoff
or Spotlight Search, and some
new features we're introducing
in iOS 10, like location
suggestions for instance.
Now all of the features
that you're looking at here,
have something in common.
And it's a single API
called NSUserActivity.
First, some background.
NSUserActivity was introduced
in iOS 8, support Handoff,
which is the amazing
feature that allows you
to start an activity on a
device and pick it up right
where you left off on another.
Last year in iOS
9, we added support
to promote content directly
from NSUserActivity inside
Spotlight Search results.
Now, this year in iOS 10, we
further enhance NSUserActivities
so it can capture locations
viewed inside your app
and promote them in many
places throughout the system.
Even inside other apps.
NSUserActivity now also
provides context to Siri,
so Siri can now help you get
directions, or make a call
to the place you're
looking at inside an app.
Also new in iOS 10,
NSUserActivity enables
your communication app
to be promoted straight
from a contact card,
as an alternate communication
method.
Now, I know what you
guys are thinking.
"That's cool," hopefully.
"But how does this work?"
Well, let me tell you,
it's really straightforward
and we have a lot of great
content to talk about.
So let's dive right in.
We're going to talk about
NSUserActivity and schema.org.
These APIs allow you
to seamlessly integrate
with the system.
NSUserActivity for native apps,
and schema.org for the web.
We'll focus on the
NSUserActivity first.
NSUserActivity is a
lightweight interface
to capture application state
as users move through your app,
in a way that can
be restored later.
So for instance, here we're
looking at the Yelp app
which is a local search app,
and as the user browses the app,
we created an NSUserActivity
capturing the information
that we need to recreate
the state later.
So for instance, when I trigger
a search for a restaurant,
we follow the same pattern
of creating activities.
And again, when I actually
view result from that list.
Now, in this particular case,
we're looking at a location.
In iOS 10, NSUserActivity
is now more aware
about certain concepts
such as locations
or communication interactions.
We'll talk about this in a
minute, but before I wanted
to take a closer
look at this screen.
So here we create an activity
and describe it with information
to recreate the state later,
as well as submitted data.
For instance, the
location's name or address.
Then we inform the system
that this represents
the current user state,
and we decide whether it will
be advertised for Handoff,
available temporarily
throughout the system
for location suggestions.
Or added to the on
device index --
or added to the Spotlight on
device index, so that it appears
in Spotlight Search results.
Now there are a few related
sessions on this topic,
specifically on adoption
of NSUserActivities
for Handoff and App Search.
Really recommend that you
guys go check them out.
They provide a lot
of great content.
Alright, now let's dig
into the code, shall we?
So, I'm going to show you how
you create these activities.
So here we're extenuating an
instance of NSUserActivity.
And providing it with
an activity type.
That's the string
that you provide.
It's the same string that you
specify in your info plist.
Now we recommend to use a
reverse the NS style notation
here to keep the strings unique.
Next, our activity needs
a title, and we're going
to use a title that describes
the content we're looking
at here.
So here we're looking
at a restaurant.
And something to keep in mind
is that this is the public face
of your user activities.
This is how, for instance,
they're represented
in Spotlight Search results.
So you want to make
sure you use a title
that is descriptive
and meaningful.
Next, we're enabling Handoff,
App Search, and public indexing,
since the content we're
viewing here is public.
And then we're setting
a dictionary
on the userInfo property,
capturing the information
that we need to recreate
the state
when the activity is restored.
Now in that case,
we use the unique ID
of that location we were
working with, and typically,
when the activity is being
restored, for instance,
when it's handed off to another
device, you can fetch back
that ID from the server
and restore the location
as the user would expect.
Now to fully describe
your activity
and for richer search results,
you can use this
class we introduced
in iOS 9 called CSSearchableItem
AttributeSet.
It provides a common language
between your app and the system
to describe your content better.
Now, if you have a website
that mirrors the content
that you're looking
at inside your app,
can provide the web URL so
that if your activity is being
for instance, handed
off to a device
where your app is not installed,
it will be appropriately
launched
in Safari instead,
following that link.
And finally, we call
becomeCurrent on the activity,
indicating to the system
that this represents
the current user state.
This is what the user is
seeing on their screen.
Now, what happens when your
app is actually being launched?
When your activity is being
restored, for instance?
Or handed off to another device?
Your application is
launched, which is good,
and a UIApplication
delegate method is called,
called continueUserActivity
restorationHandler.
The first thing we need to do
here is check the activity type
and make sure that it
matches one that we expect.
That case matches the one
that we were just
working with earlier.
And then we can use the
User Input Dictionary
to start restoring the state.
Earlier, we had put the
unique ID of that location.
So typically here, we would
be able to fetch it back
from the server and
then restore it back
and display the right controller
as the user would expect it.
So with minimal code here,
we were able to benefit
from three great features;
Handoff, Spotlight Search,
and contextual Siri reminders.
Now, we'll talk about some of
the other features listed below.
Before, let me ask you this.
Have you ever been in a
situation where you're hungry
and you're trying to find
a good restaurant to eat?
So you start in Yelp and
you find the perfect place.
Then you want to
text your friends
so that they can meet you there.
So you switch to
messages, start writing,
"Hey guys, I found this place."
But then you realize you don't
actually have the address
of that place, so you
switch back to Yelp,
you copy the address, then
you switch back to messages.
You paste it in there, and
then you're done finally.
Except you're not,
because at some point,
you're also going to
need to get there.
So you're going to
switch through maps,
and there's probably more
back and forth in there.
And you get the idea.
It's not a great experience.
So in iOS 10, we're trying
to make this experience
much easier.
You still start at a same point.
You're looking at a location,
say a restaurant,
inside your app.
And by adopting NSUserActivity,
your app can promote
that same location in many
different places throughout
the system.
When you switch away
from the app,
the multitasking UI
makes it very easy
and offers this nice proactive
suggesting at the bottom,
offering to get directions
using your favorite routing app
to the place you
were just looking at.
If you go to Messages,
no more back and forth.
You can start writing
something like, "Let's meet at--
" and the QuickType UI
will automatically promote
that location directly into
QuickType from the content
that you're providing.
Same thing with Maps.
Maps promotes these locations
directly in the Maps app.
Not only in the Maps app,
but also in the new
Today View maps widget,
as well as in CarPlay which is
my favorite feature actually.
Imagine that.
Look at your app, get in
your car, tap on your screen,
that's it, you're done.
You can be on your way.
These locations can even be
promoted inside other apps.
So what we're looking at here
is a location provided by Yelp
through NSUserActivity
displayed inside the Uber app,
as the user engages with
a destination text field.
Again, it also provides
context to Siri,
so you can now be looking
at your app and ask Siri
to get you directions
or make a call
to the place you're looking at.
So all of these features with
the adoption of NSUserActivity.
And all of these features
have something in common,
is that they all indicate
where the suggestion is
originally coming from,
in that case from Yelp.
Now imagine if this
were your app.
Wouldn't that be great?
Well, this is possible now.
NSUserActivity now allows you
to do so by capturing locations
that are viewed inside
your apps.
We're introducing new
simple APIs in both MapKit
and CoreSpotlight, allowing
you to do that, and integrate
with all of these places
that I just talked about.
In terms of code, we're going
to create an NSUserActivity
and we're going to
reuse the same activity
that we had defined earlier,
and just add on top of it.
We don't have to create
separate activities.
So, for apps using
MapKit, it's as easy
as setting your MKMapItem to
this new MapItem property,
defined as NSUserActivity.
And that's pretty much it.
This also has the
great side effect
of populating the
content attribute sets
for you automatically
so you don't --
so if you want to adopt App
Search, all you have to do is
to specify that you
want opt into App Search
and these locations
will also be indexed.
Now there's another way which is
by adopting App Search actually,
and for those of you who are
already familiar with that,
you can use CSSearchableItem
AttributeSet
and describe the location.
Now, let's break this
down a little bit.
First thing we're doing
here is setting the name
of the location, which
matches what we're looking at.
And that's required for all
of the UIs we just
talked about earlier.
Next, we're specifying the text
representation of the address,
and that's required for
all of the text based UIs,
such as the keyboard,
for instance.
Next, we're specifying the
latitude and longitudes.
That's optional,
but that insures
that your users are
accurately routed
to the place you
intend to route them to.
Latitude and longitude is the
most precise representation
that you can use if you
have this information.
Next, we're setting the phone
number, and that allows us
to get access to Siri
so that we can say,
"Call this place," for instance.
And finally, we're indicating
that this content supports
both navigation and phone call.
This way, the results will be
presented in the spotlight UI.
In Spotlight Search results UI,
with the right quick action
icons to make a phone call
or get directions, for instance.
That's how you get
location suggestions.
It's that easy.
Now, your app is going
to be promoted in all
of these different places.
We think this is going
to provide a much richer
experience, both inside
but also outside your app.
Now, your brand can be further
promoted throughout the system.
Not within the confinement
of your apps only.
Let's move on to
contact interactions.
IOS 10 DP integrates
communication apps directly
from a contact card.
So what we're looking at
here is a contact card
where the WhatsApp handle was
learned and displayed there.
When I go ahead and tap on the
Quick Action button at the top
to send a message, I'm
asked to select what method
of contact I'd like to use.
And if I do so, this choice can
even be remembered and persisted
as a default mean
of communication.
So your app can be promoted
there as a default channel
for messaging for
that specific contact.
That's also supported by
NSUserActivity together
with a new intense framework,
which is the same
framework you use
to get deep Siri integration.
There were two great talks about
this topic earlier this week.
I really recommend that
you guys go check them out.
So here we're looking
at this WhatsApp app,
sending a text message,
and we're going
to work on how this works.
So the first thing we do is
create an INInteraction object
which is a new object we're
defining in the intense API.
This contains information
about the intent.
For instance, which
represents the user action.
So for instance, sending a text
message or making a video call,
as well as some other
information about the recipient,
the sender, and some
metadata in creating things
like whether the communication
was successful, for instance.
Next, you call the Donate
Method on your interaction.
This way the system will
learn about this interaction
and promote your app directly
inside a contact card.
Now, when users interact
with your app
through the contact card,
we follow the same pattern.
Create an INInteraction
representing what the user is
trying to do.
And wrap it up inside
an NSUserActivity
which your app is
then launched with.
Now let's see how this
translates into code.
The first thing here,
we're creating the
sender and recipients.
And something to note is
that if your app has access
to the user's address book,
you can specify what contact
identifier you're working
with here.
And this way the system will
be able to better figure
out the right contact
to be augmented.
Next, we're creating intent.
And here we're using
the INSendMessageIntent
since we're sending
a text message.
Now there are three
communication intents available
to you for sending
text messages,
making audio, and video calls.
Now it's important
to note that you want
to also make sure you specify
what intents your app is capable
of handling in your info plist
to that pretty much the same
thing as with activity types,
what we talked about earlier.
Next, we'll provide the
service name we're using.
And here we're using WhatsApp.
And this is particularly
useful if your app deals
with multiple protocols.
So for instance, if you
have multi-client chat app,
which deals with both
Jabber and ICQ for instance,
you'll want to make sure you
use the right service name here.
Next, we create an INInteraction
object which captures all
of the information
we created before.
And some metadata
including things
like directionality
of the communication.
Now since here we're
sending a text message,
we're using the outgoing
direction,
and that's the only
supported direction
for donations of interactions.
And finally, we donate this
interaction to the system.
This way it will be --
the system will be able
to augment the contacts you're
were communicating with.
Now again, like I said, when
users interact with your app
from a contact card, we
follow the same pattern
and use the same UI
application delegate method
to launch your app.
The first thing we're doing
here is check the intent
and interaction from
the NSUserActivity,
and then we can start
communication
with the intended recipients.
And that's how you get
contact interactions.
Now, your app can be promoted
straight from a contact card,
which is the most natural
way of communicating.
So we did it.
We checked everything
in that list.
But we're not done.
We have some more to talk about.
So let's talk about some
best practices to keep
in mind while working
with NSUserActivity.
The first thing is to be lazy.
Okay, now we're talking.
So, imagine you're working in a
Mail client, and you're trying
to adopt Handoff so
that your users are able
to start writing an email on
their Mac and pick it up right
where they left off on
their iPhone, when they're
on the go for instance.
So here what we're doing
is we have a method
that is called every
single time a key is pressed
on the keyboard.
And every single
time, we recompute
and update the userinfo
dictionary.
Now that can be costly
and inefficient.
So instead what you should do is
to use the needsSave property,
indicating to the system
that this activity is dirty.
And then this way, the system
will be able to call you
at an opportune time to update
your userinfo dictionary.
For instance, right before the
activity is being handed off
to another device.
Now here, this is
what we're doing,
and we're implementing the
updateUserActivityState delegate
method, and this
is our opportunity
to update the userinfo
dictionary.
This way we can do it only once
and we're way more
efficient like that.
Next, make sure you
keep a strong reference
to the current activity.
So what we're doing here is
extenuating NSUserActivity,
doing a bunch of things to it,
calling becomeCurrent to it.
So that's good.
Except after that, we're not
keeping a strong reference
and exiting the function.
And therefore, the
activity is released
because it goes out of scope.
An activity release
cannot be current
because it doesn't exist.
So instead what you should
do is keep a strong reference
to the current activity.
If you're dealing with
UIViewControllers or anything
that conforms to a UI responder,
can also use the User
Activity Define --
User Activity Property,
defined on UI responder.
And this has the great effect
of having UIKit manage the
activity currentness for you.
So you don't have to call
becomeCurrent of invalidate it.
UIKit does it for you
as your view controller
for instance are linked
to the view hierarchy.
Next, transfer a small payload.
So make sure that you keep
only just enough information
in your userinfo dictionary,
to recreate the states,
but not much more.
And remember that these user
info and activities are sent
over the air, by Bluetooth, so
that's why they need to be kept
as lightweight as possible.
So for instance, imagine you're
working on an app that deals
with large photos
downloaded from the internet.
So what we're doing here is
downloading these photos,
serializing them as
data, and putting them
in the userinfo dictionary,
which could be very
easily several megabytes,
which is not efficient.
Instead what you can do is try
to keep a unique item to fire
to that content you're working
with, for instance, the web URL,
this way when you're
restoring the activity,
you can maybe fetch
it back from a server
or obtain it through
other means.
Now if you really have to
deal with large payloads,
you can use continuation
streams,
and these are specifically
designed for that.
There's a ton of
information on this
in the developer documentation.
Okay, one more.
Make sure you keep your activity
types unique and descriptive.
And that's to avoid collisions.
But it's also important
that they represent the
current user activity,
or the current user actions.
So instead of having a
single activity type here,
that I reuse everywhere
inside my app,
it's good to have multiple
activity types describing the
different parts of my app.
So for instance, one when
I'm viewing a location,
one when I'm searching
for locations,
and what you'll notice
here as well is
that I'm using a reverse DNS
style notation which makes sure
that there's no collision
with other activity types
that might have been
defined inside other apps.
Alright, time for a demo now.
So we're going to use
our Proactive Toolbox app
which is a sample we're
making available to you
on the Developer Library.
And we'll see how we
can adopt NSUserActivity
to promote locations.
We'll also briefly touch on
Handoff as well as App Search.
Let's get writing.
Alright, so I'm going to launch
the Proactive Toolbox app here
and I have my device
running iOS 10 on the left,
and Xcode here right behind.
So I'm going to give you a
quick tour of the app first
to get an idea of what it does.
So here we have a
list of pizza places.
This is an app that
searches for pizza locally,
and uses core location to get
my current location as well
as MapKit to fetch places
that match the pizza criteria.
So I'm going to look
at the first one here,
and I get a richer page
with more details about it,
like the name, phone
number, address, website,
as well as a map of this place.
Now we're going to work
on how we can go ahead
and implement location
suggestions
so that this same
location is promoted
in many different places.
But before this, let's do that.
I'm going to time myself.
How about that?
See how long it takes to do so.
Now, I'll start the
timer and let's go.
Alright, so I'm going
to go in Xcode now.
And this is my location view
controller which is the control
that I use to display the
right, richer search --
the richer results
for the pizza place.
And this is the method
that I call every time a map
item is updated inside my app.
So I'm going to go ahead and
drag and drop this right there.
And this is where I'm
creating in NSUserActivity.
So as you can see, I am creating
an activity, providing it
with an activity type that is
meaningfully representing what
I'm doing.
In this case, I'm also using
a reverse DNS style notation
which makes sure that my
activity types are unique.
And I already defined
this activity type
in my info plist earlier.
Next, we're setting the
title and the keywords.
And again, here I'm
using a meaningful title
because that's what's going
to be the public face
of my user activity.
Next, I'm setting Handoff, App
Search, and Public Indexing,
because the content we're
looking at is public here.
And the more important
part here is this,
which is where I'm setting my
mapItem inside my activity.
Now again, this has
the side effect
of populating the
contentAttributeSets for us.
So that's what I'm
doing right there.
I'm just completing
that by indicating
that this content supports
navigation and phone call.
This way it will have
the right nice icons
in the Spotlight Search results.
Okay now, remember
about being lazy?
That's what I'm doing here.
So, setting needsSave to
True and the delegate method.
This way, the userActivity
delegate will be called
when I need to update
my userinfo dictionary.
And finally, I'm using the
userActivity property defined
by UR Responder in
my UIViewController,
and setting the activity to it
so that I keep a
strong reference
and that UIKit manages
it automatically for me.
Next, I'm going to
implement this UI --
this User Activity
Delegate Method,
updateUser ActivityState.
And this is where I'm going to
update my userinfo dictionary
with the content that I
define in this method below,
which returns the
dictionary of the information,
the relevant information,
that I need to recreate
this state later.
Okay, let's go ahead,
build and run.
Okay, so safe to say
the same place here.
Okay, I didn't break
anything for a change.
So I'm going to go ahead
and double-tap Home,
and now as you can see,
we're seeing this nice banner
at the bottom to get
directions to the place
that I was just looking at.
It's very easy.
Super handy.
Same thing when I go to Maps.
I see that same location
directly here,
even showing my application
icon.
[Applause] thank you.
[ Applause ]
Alright, let's zoom back out.
Same thing when I go to
Messages, and say something
like "Let's meet at-- ."
You see that I have the same
location right there being
suggested directly inside the
QuickType UI provided by my app,
so I can just tap on it and
both the name of the place
and the address get inserted.
[ Applause ]
But, it even works
with incoming messages.
So here I'm getting a text
message asking me what their
phone number is, and it's
pulling the information right
from my NSUserActivity so
that I can just tap on it
and insert the phone
number as well.
That's really cool.
[ Applause ]
Now let's go check on timing.
Three minutes, forty.
So that's not bad.
All of these location
suggestions features,
provided by my app
with a single API.
Well, I cheated a little bit.
I had some sample codes
but you get the idea.
It's not a tremendous
investment.
So messages, QuickType,
Siri, Maps, multitasking,
all of that, a single API.
Alright, so we had worked
on App Search as well,
indexing this content.
So I'm going to go
back to the app first
and restore it in
its initial state.
Then I'm going to go ahead
and search for pizza.
Pizza. And sure enough, I
see that place right there.
But when I go ahead and tap
on it, my app is launched,
but my app doesn't
do the right thing.
It doesn't restore
the context back
to the user as they
would expect.
It doesn't show the rich
UI of the pizza place.
I'm going to go back
to my code here,
and this is because I
did not implement the
UIApplicationDelegate methods.
So I'm going to go to my
app delegates, drag and drop
that part, and what
I'm doing here is,
I'm implementing the continue
userActivity restorationHandler
UIApplicationDelegate, checking
the activity type first.
This is the one that we
were just working with.
And then calling this method
that I defined right below,
which looks at the userInfo
and restores the state
as the user would expect.
I'm going to build
and run again,
and see that one more time.
So, I'll go back to
Spotlight, tap on this result,
and now we're doing the right
thing and restoring the content
as the user would expect.
So that's a quick tour of how
you can adopt NSUserActivity
for location suggestions,
App Search, and Handoff.
Alright, let's switch back.
[ Applause ]
So again, this sample
is available to you
on the Developer Library.
It actually does a couple
more things over there.
And it helps you test your
integration with NSUserActivity.
So it's a great tool to keep by
your side while you're working,
on the Location Suggestions
feature.
Okay, so we just saw how easy
it was to adopt NSUserActivity,
and promote your content in many
different parts of the system.
And we'll take a look at how
schema.org can provide some
of these benefits, specifically
for location suggestions.
Now when we design these
feature these location
suggestion features.
We wanted them to
work just as well
with websites you
view in Safari.
And so for this, for instance,
when you're looking at yelp.com
which mirrors the same content
we were looking at earlier
in the Yelp app, when you
switch away from Safari,
you get the same,
nice, handy suggestions
to get directions to this place.
And that's because
yelp.com adopts schema.org
which is the technology
we use for this.
A little bit of background,
schema.org is open web markup
standard that allows you
to semantically annotate
your content
with rich, structured, metadata.
So there are many
schemas providing a bunch
of representations
for various concepts.
And schema.org is also intended
to provide a rich search
experience to your users,
both inside iOS, but also
with all major search engines.
So these schemas
are all organized
in a tree-like structure.
So for instance,
more specific Schemas
like restaurants inherits
from more generic ones
like local business.
Let's take a look at
restaurant as an example.
So, it inherits from multiple
schemas and therefore,
inherits from all
of their properties,
defining each of these.
And for instance, the name
property which is defined
in the Thing schema would
capture things like the name
of the restaurant in that case.
Same with the address
which is defined
in the Local Business schema.
And things that are more
specific to restaurants,
such as whether it accepts
reservations are defined
directly inside the
Restaurant schema.
So here's an example of
schema.org in action.
On the left, we're seeing the
same websites we were looking
at earlier.
And on the right, content
that's semantically describes it
in a way that can be
understood by Safari.
Creating things like
the phone number,
the name of the restaurant,
address,
rating, website, and more.
It can even do more.
Let's look at a simple example.
Here is a very simple
HTML document,
describing content
about a restaurant.
Now, let's look at how
this page could look like,
with the addition of
JSON-LD schema.org markups.
As you can see, we
haven't changed anything
to the actual content
or the actual structure
of the document.
We've just provided
metadata alongside,
describing the content in a
more machine friendly format.
It includes simple
properties like the telephone,
but also more complex structured
properties, like the address,
which is itself another
schema of type PostalAddress.
If you prefer, you can
also annotate your content
in line with microdata.
So that's what we're doing here.
We're changing the
actual structure
of our initial document
and augmenting it
with inline microdata markups.
So Safari in iOS 10, it strikes
these location related schemas,
and promotes them much
like a native app would
promote NSUserActivity.
That also gives you some of
these benefits that we talked
about earlier for
location suggestions.
So these are some of the
schemas that safari extracts.
Anything with a PostalAddress,
GeoCoordinate,
or a telephone property, and the
Restaurant schema for instance
that we were working with
earlier, is a perfect example.
You have all of these
properties and you can combine
or specify the ones that you
have available at the time.
Alright, so we talked about
NSUserActivity and schema.org.
Use NSUserActivity,
to promote locations
that users view inside
your app in many places,
throughout the system,
effortlessly.
Also for communication apps.
And also of course for all
cases of Handoff and App Search.
Use schema.org for your website,
to get some of these benefits
for location suggestion,
much like you would get
through NSUserActivity.
Alright, now let's move
on to how your apps can
actually consume these location
suggestions like we
just saw earlier.
So here we're going to talk
about two different
ways to do that.
One through the keyboard, and
one specific to routing apps.
Let's start with Number 1.
So, if your app deals with
addresses and text format,
you can benefit from location
suggestions inside your app
through the QuickType UI.
Now here we're looking
at the Uber app,
which is ride sharing app for
those of you who don't know.
And as the user enters a text
field, which is annotated
as a location text field, we're
promoting content in that place
from Yelp, directly inside Uber.
Now this includes locations
that have been recently promoted
in NSUserActivities by
other apps, or schema.org.
Upcoming locations
based on your calendar.
Locations that you may have
copied in your pasteboard.
So if you receive text message
with an address for instance.
And even, recent places
that you may have interacted
with using Siri.
So for instance, if
you ask to get --
if you ask Siri to show
you restaurants nearby,
and then interact with a
result, you can expect to see it
in there as part of
location suggestions.
So, we're introducing
a new API in UIKit.
So your app can inform the
system what content type your
text fields are expecting.
And in this case, we were
working with locations.
Now based on this hint,
the keyboard will be able
to make the right
proactive suggestions,
if there's any available
at this time in context.
But if there's no proactive
suggestions available,
it still provides a
much richer experience
in terms of auto correction.
Because autocorrect
can now be able to --
is now able to know what
content your app is expecting.
So, we added a new property
in UITextInputTraits
called text content type,
which allows you
to specify this.
So here, we're working with
a UITextField which conforms
to UITextInputTraits, and
therefore, gets this property.
And we're indicating that
this text field expects a full
street address.
There's a bunch of text content
types that you can work with,
ranging from describing
people to locations
and a bunch of others.
There's a full list
that's available to you
in the Developer Library.
But let's take a closer
look at two in particular.
So these two are both
related to locations,
but they have different
levels of granularity.
So you want to use the one
that represents your
use case the best
with the right level
of granularity.
So for instance, a navigation
app would typically expect a
full street address so that it
can accurately route the user
to their destination, whereas a
weather app may only typically
care about the state and city
because that might just be
enough for a weather use case.
And as you can see here, based
on the different content type
that we specified, we're getting
different content promoted
inside the QuickType bar.
In one case, the full street
address, and in the other case,
just San Francisco, California.
And that's how easy
it is for you
to get suggestions
inside the keyboard.
Now let's look at how your
routing apps can benefit
from these nice direction
banners at the bottom.
Like Daniel said
earlier, routing apps,
third party routing apps
can also be elevated here,
accelerating users
directly into your apps
when we think there is an intent
for the user to get directions.
So we're leveraging an existing
API called MKDirectionsRequest
which was introduced in iOS 6,
and lets your routing
app register as such
and then handle all
directions request.
iOS will learn over time what a
user's preferred routing app is
based on various factors, such
as engagement for instance.
And then suggest it
in the Multitasking
UI when appropriate.
So, to do so, you want to make
sure you configure your app
to receive directions requests.
And that's easily
done inside Xcode
through the capabilities panel.
In iOS 10, we're
introducing a new routing mode
which is specifically
for ride sharing apps.
Next, you want to
declare the map regions
where your app is
actually relevant.
So if your app is a local
metro app for instance,
you can specify that your app
is only relevant in this area.
And finally, you
want to make sure
that you take the appropriate
action when your app is launched
within MKDirectionsRequest.
And that is that your app should
automatically start directions,
or populate the UI in a
way that makes it easy
for the user to get directions.
In terms of code,
this is an example
of how you can adopt
MKDirectionsRequest.
MKDirectionsRequest
uses a URL theme.
So when your app is launched,
it's launched with a URL.
First thing we're
doing is checking
that the URL we're
getting is actually a
valid MKDirectionsRequest.
An MKDirectionsRequest offers
there is directions request
to your URL for that.
Next, we're extenuating an
instance of MKDirectionsRequest
from the contents of that URL
which will contain information
about the origin
and the destination
that the user is
trying to go to.
And next and new in iOS 10,
something really important,
especially for those of you
who already adopt
MKDirectionsRequest,
is that you can now be
launched with map items
that don't have geo-coordinates.
And in this case,
you'd want to geocode
that address dictionary you
were getting, using CLGeocoders,
geocode AddressDictionary, which
will give you back a place mark
with the right latitude
and longitude,
which will help you
then start directions
to the intended location.
And that's pretty much it.
That's how your routing app
can be promoted right there
in this prime real estate
of the Multitasking UI.
Now with that, I'd like to
hand it back to Daniel to talk
about media app suggestions.
Thank you.
>> That was awesome.
Alright. Now, let's talk
about media app suggestions.
So, if you're an app that
handles any form of media
like a podcast app or a
Spotify-like app, or even an app
that plays video, you'll
want to stay tuned for this.
iOS today, promotes the app
that we think you're likely
to use based on your behavior.
And we promote that app in
a bunch of different UIs
that I showed you earlier.
We in particular, offer those
suggestions in Spotlight
and in the Today View.
If the act of the suggestion
follows a particular trigger,
like for example when you plug
in headphones or Bluetooth pair,
or even arriving at a certain
location, and it's a media app,
we may further elevate that.
So, let's see what
this looks like.
This is what the promotion
in Spotlight looks like.
If say, I always or
frequently listen to podcasts
after plugging in headphones.
Notice, in the upper
left hand side,
the podcast app a suggestion.
In certain situations
though, the promotion
of that will be elevated
to the Lock Screen itself.
And so what you're seeing is,
the UI we'll traditionally use
for Handoff, is now being
used to promote an app
that we think I'm likely to
use because it followed one
of those triggers I mentioned.
Now, this is a pretty good
experience, but it's not as good
as it could be because at the
end of the day, what you have
to do now is you have to
unlock your device and swipe
in the right direction in
order to get to the content
that we're predicting, we
think you want to consume.
With a pretty simple API,
you can build a far better
experience for your users.
This is what it looks
like before.
This is what I just showed you.
And this is what it
looks like after.
We're getting it?
This is what it looks
like before.
like after.
Far, far better.
Not only can the customer engage
on the content without having
to unlock their device, but you
also get your album art front
and center, in front
of the user.
Now, this might be quite
obvious in hindsight,
but this particular interface
offers also far better
conversion if you look
at the actual numbers.
And so, if you're interested
in getting your users
actually playing your content,
which presumably you are,
this is an API for you.
So how do we do this?
I'm going to walk
you through it.
The adoption is pretty simple.
It all boils down to a class
called MPPlayableContentManager.
So let's imagine you've got
a dictionary with a bunch
of different properties.
You know, a title, an artist,
an album, and what you want
to do is you want to get this
elevated to the Lock Screen
of the device when the system
thinks the customer's likely
to engage with it.
Well, you're going
to want to start off
by doing is importing Media
Player and declaring yourself
as conformant as to a
delegate in that class.
And then you're going to want
to implement a method called
playableContentManager.
It's pretty simple.
First, you want to
grab the media item
through whatever means you have.
Now, you'll obviously
want to be prepared,
especially if you're
fetching remote assets
for it not working.
In which case, you're
going to call
that call back handler
you see below as such
and the system will understand,
not to necessarily promote you.
Next, you're going to want to
populate the NowPlayingInfo
on the Lock Screen
of the device.
This is a method that I
implemented, so I'm going
to show you what's behind it.
The first thing that you
want to do is grab a hold
onto the infoCenter object,
and then if you do
have a particular image
that this media item
has, you can promote
that to the Lock
Screen of the device.
If you have a default image that
you use, this is an opportunity
for you to get your
brand elevated as well.
Then you're going to
translate your representation
to the nowPlayingInfo
representation,
and most importantly, you're
going to set the nowPlayingInfo
on the infoCenter,
before the callback
that I showed you
earlier, completes.
So you want to do this
before your method closes.
If for whatever reason you don't
feel like or your app has a bug
in preparing playback.
Again, if the phone's
on Airplane Mode.
This is another opportunity
for you to error out early.
Now note, you don't
actually want
to start playback at this point.
You plugged in your
headphones, you want to wait
for the customer to
hit the Play button.
But you want to get
prepared for it,
load into Stream, and so forth.
And that's it.
So again, today, iOS promotes
apps based on your behavior.
If they follow a particular
trigger and they're a media app,
we elevate them to
the Lock Screen.
Through pretty simple adoption
that I just showed you,
you can get a much better
experience and an opportunity
to promote your brand
and whatever gorgeous
album art you have.
Alright, so let's summarize
what we walked through today.
We spoke about a few simple APIs
that helped you deeply
integrate your app
into the operating system.
We spoke about NSUserActivity,
the kind of eyes
of the operating system.
It helps us understand
semantically what the customer
is currently staring at.
Then we spoke about schema.org,
which is in many ways,
similar to NSUserActivities
for the web.
We spoke about a new use
case in an existing APIs well
as a brand new UIKit API, to
help us as the system understand
when to elevate locations.
Then we spoke about MPContent,
MPPlayableContent Manager.
Which is particularly
relevant if you're a media app.
And hopefully it's been
clear to all of you today
that these APIs are easy
to adopt and easy to test.
There's some more
information available online,
as well as some great
related sessions
that you should check out,
if you haven't already.
There's a lot of related
work with SiriKit.
A lot of related work around our
search APIs that you saw today,
as well as some previous
sessions from the past two years
around Handoff and
aforementioned search APIs.
Lastly, I wanted to close by
saying that this is an area
that we are going to continue
to invest in as a company.
And what we need from you,
developers, is to inform us
about the capabilities
of your app
in the most detailed
way possible.
Because fundamentally the
more we know about your app,
the more we'll understand
when it's best to promote it.
And so, you saw today, a
lot of different situation
where there was varying levels
of kind of semantic detail
that you could annotate an
activity or a text field in.
I'd encourage you as much
as possible to try to be
as explicit as you
can when you do so,
not only to support the features
that we're discussing today,
but also to put your application
in a good place,
towards the future.
Thank you all for coming today.
I hope you had a great
WWDC and a great Friday.
Bye, bye.
[ Applause ]