[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Hi, good afternoon.
Good afternoon, and welcome to
What's New in iTunes Connect.
I'm Dave Van Tassell,
Engineering Manager
here at iTunes Connect.
I'm excited to spend some times
this afternoon talking to you
about what we've been up
to and where we're headed.
Now iTunes Connect covers the
whole lifespan of your app,
from uploading the metadata,
submitting to App Review,
releasing your app onto the
App Store, and even tracking
to see how well you're
doing on the App Store.
And so, today we're
going to touch on a few
of these different
pieces of iTunes Connect.
We're going to start with
all the changes we're making
to in-app purchases and
also talk a little bit
about iTunes Connect for iOS,
our mobile companion
app to iTunes Connect.
We're also going to
talk about App Analytics
and what's new with
App Analytics.
And then something
completely different and new,
which is screenshot
simplification,
and this is about the
rules and requirements
about uploading images and
app previews for your app.
We want to talk a little
bit about iMessage apps,
what you have to do in iTunes
Connect in order to set up
and submit your iMessage apps.
And then we're going to finish
off with the updated guidelines.
So let's get started.
We're going to talk
about in-app purchases,
and the first area we're going
to talk about are subscriptions.
Now when we talk
about subscriptions,
what we're talking about are
autorenewable in-app purchases,
and the biggest change we made
there is we're opening them
up to all categories.
[ Applause ]
So no longer is it
only a few categories
that can use autorenewables.
Everybody's eligible
to use them.
Now we're also introducing
a new feature
so that you can price your
subscriptions differently
in each territory.
Instead of selecting one price
tier for all the territories,
you can select individual
price tiers for each territory.
And to go along with that, we're
actually increasing the number
of available price
tiers for autorenewables
to over 200 different
price tiers,
and this should really let
you pick the right price
in the right country
for your subscriptions
and your subscribers.
Another new feature we're adding
to the subscriptions is
called price preservation.
Now this is for your
existing subscribers.
When you raise the price of a
subscription, you can choose
if you want them to also
pay this new, higher price,
or you can let them keep
their existing price
so when they renew,
they will continue
to pay their existing price.
And the last change we're making
is for subscribers who have been
with you for over a year.
When they renew,
they'll get 85 percent
of the proceeds, and
this is live now.
So you no longer have to
wait 12 months until works.
Anyone who's already
been subscribing
to your in-app purchase for
more than year, when they renew
with their next subscription
period,
you will receive 85
percent of those proceeds.
[ Applause ]
This is a good one.
Now there's actually so much
to talk about with the changes
to subscriptions we've
created two sessions
that are dedicated just to this.
The first is a more
technical deep dive and how
to actually program a
StoreKit, work with it in Swift,
check your receipt,
and validation.
It's a great session.
The second one is more about
what subscriptions actually are
and how to set up all this new
information in iTunes Connect.
To change the price in
different territories
and preserve your price, so
these are both on Tuesday.
If you didn't get a
chance to see them,
then I highly recommend
you check it out.
And those are the changes
we have for subscriptions.
Now this next change
is applicable
to all in-app purchases,
and this is in-app
purchase promo codes.
[ Applause ]
In-app purchase promo
codes are going to live
in iTunes Connect right next to
where you get the promo codes
for your app versions.
So you go to the features
tab for your app, and up top,
you have where you can
select your promo codes
for your app version.
And then down below,
we're going to let you set
up in-app purchase promo codes.
The first thing you
do is you select
which in-app purchase you
want to get a promo code for.
I'm going to do Dream
Trips to Europe.
I just need the one right now.
And so we go through
the next step.
It's how many promo
codes do you want?
So we can select in here.
I think right now I need 25.
That ought to do it.
And that's it.
Now I'm ready to
generate my promo codes.
I can download them as a text
file and distribute those,
and people can download my
in-app purchase via promo code.
Now this feature, as well
as the rest of the changes
to subscriptions, will be
available later this fall.
And those are our changes
to in-app purchase.
Now the next thing
I want to talk
about is iTunes Connect for iOS.
And to do that, I'm
going to introduce Mike
on state to tell you more.
Mike?
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Dave.
Good afternoon, everyone.
My name is Mike Amirault, and I
am very excited to be here today
to talk to you about
iTunes Connect for iOS.
Before I begin, how many of you
out there have downloaded
and used our app?
All right.
Quite a few.
We'll try to get the rest of you
to download it before
this session's over.
For those of you who
haven't downloaded it,
let me give you a brief
description about what it does.
iTunes Connect for iOS is
our mobile companion app
to the iTunes Connect website.
It allows you on-the-go access
to your sales and trends,
ratings and reviews
for all your apps,
the ability to reject a
binary or at least your app
for the store, and
push notifications,
so you can be immediately
notified
of any changes to your apps.
It is available for
free in the App Store.
Let's talk about what's new.
In the past year, we
released many new features
for the mobile app, but
there's three that I would
like to highlight for you today.
First, new push notifications,
second, multiprovider support,
and third, full access
to Resolution Center
within the mobile app.
Let's look at each of these.
New push notifications,
we added three new types
of push notifications
in the past year.
First, if your app contracts
are about to expire, second,
if you get a message
from our App Review team,
you can now get a push
notification so you can deal
with the issue immediately.
And lastly, and this has been
a developer favorite so far,
you can get a push notification
when your app has finished
input processing for the store.
[ Applause ]
I know. It's the little things.
So let's talk about
multiprovider support.
What does that mean?
Some of you work on apps
for more than one provider.
In the past, this was
not the easiest thing
in the world to do.
You would have to have
a separate user account,
and you would have to
log out and log back in,
in order to see all your apps.
With multiprovider support,
you can one account,
and you can have it associated
with all the providers
that you work for.
I'd like to show you how
that works in the mobile app.
When you log in, we'll
automatically set the provider
to the last one that
you logged in with.
If you want to change it,
simply tap on the settings icon
in the bottom right, and then
tap on the providers line.
This will show you all
the providers associated
with your account.
Simply pick the one you want,
and now you're seeing content
for just that provider.
Now push notifications
are unique per provider.
So you can turn them on
for some of your providers
or turn them off for others.
It's completely up to you
how you want to set it up.
So that's multiprovider support,
and I hope that helps those
of you that work with
more than one provider.
Resolution Center, this was the
biggest new feature we've added
in the past year, full
access to resolution center
within the mobile app.
Let me show you what
that looks like.
Anywhere within the mobile
app where we display a list
of your apps, either in recents,
favorites, or search results,
any of your apps that have
active Resolution Center issues
will be displayed
with a red badge.
Let's tap into one of those.
So you can see at the top
of the view it gives you a
brief description of the number
of active issues you have and
which platform they're on.
Let's tap on that header.
Here you can see the
full text of the issue,
and you can get a
complete history
of all the replies
associated with it.
If you tap on the reply
icon in the top right,
you have the option here
to forward this issue
on through email to another
member of your team to look at,
or you can reply directly
within the mobile app
to the App Review team.
When App Review responds, you
can get a push notification
so you can deal with
the issue immediately.
So that's the Resolution
Center feature.
It's just one of the three --
So that's the Resolution
Center feature.
Now let's talk about
what's coming next.
Now there's one feature
that's been at or near the top
of this list for most
developers, sales and proceeds,
the ability to see exactly
how much money you're making
in gross sales and proceeds
directly within the mobile app.
I am happy to say that
this feature will be coming
in our next release, and I would
like to show it to you now.
So this is the Sales and
Trends module as it looks
when you sign in today.
On the left side, you'll
see the number of downloads
for each line item, and on
the right side in the red
and green rectangles,
you see the delta change
between the current
period you're looking at
and the previous period.
Much like the stocks app,
if you tap on one of the red
and green rectangles, you
can change the display.
So let's tap on it, and now
we're looking at proceeds
for each of these line items.
If we tap on it again, now we're
seeing the gross sales figures.
As we tap through
the various displays,
the graph at the bottom
of the page will change
to represent the dimension
that you're looking at.
Let's look at top products.
Here we're showing the
gross sales numbers
for your top products.
This will allow you to easily
see exactly how much money your
most popular apps are
generating for you, and again,
you can tap the red or
green rectangles to change
between sales, proceeds,
and units.
Let's look at a specific app.
When you're looking
at a specific app,
you can get the daily
sales breakdowns.
Here we're showing the
number of downloads.
If we tap on the view line,
we can switch between units,
proceeds, sales, and updates.
Let's look at sales.
Then we hit back.
So now we're displaying
the gross sales numbers
on a per day basis.
So that's our new sales
and proceeds feature.
It will be available
in our next release,
and we know you've been
waiting for it for a while,
so it'll be available today.
[ Applause ]
Now since we're going to be
releasing this feature today,
I'd like to take this
opportunity to demonstrate
for you my favorite
feature of our mobile app,
and that's the ability
to release your app
for the App Store.
So what I'm going to do
is I'm going to show you
on the current version
of iTunes Connect for iOS
to release the new version
of iTunes Connect for iOS.
So we're going to do that now.
First off, you want
to find your app.
Mine's very easy to find because
naturally it's in my favorites.
And you can see we
have two versions.
One is currently
live on the store.
We don't want to be
downloading that one right now.
And our second one is
pending developer release.
So let's look at
our new version.
And you can see we
have two options here.
We can either release this
version, or reject the binary.
We don't want to reject
the binary right now.
So we're going to tap
on release this version,
and it will give us
a confirmation panel
because we don't want you
to accidentally reject
or release your binary.
And we're going to
tap on release.
And there it is.
The app is now ready for sale.
[ Applause ]
So the app is now
live in the App Store,
and it'll be available
for download shortly,
and I'm now going to hand
you back over to Dave.
>> All right.
Thanks, Mike.
That's what's coming up
in iTunes Connect for iOS,
with enhanced notification
support,
Resolution Center built
right into the app,
as well as the just released
sales and proceeds updates.
So I'm going to talk about
App Analytics, and it's hard
to believe that it's
been just over a year
since this has become
such a great tool
in iTunes Connect Toolbox.
And to talk more about what
is new with App Analytics,
I'm going to invite
David on stage.
David?
[ Applause ]
>> All right.
Thanks, Dave.
I'm David Hopkins, and I'm going
to talk to you a little bit
about what's new
in App Analytics.
For those of you who
haven't used App Analytics,
it's available as a
part of iTunes Connect.
It's free.
There's no integration
required, no SDK,
and it has customer
privacy built in.
So let's talk about
why App Analytics.
Why are analytics important?
First, analytics
provides answers.
Are customers finding my app?
Are customers downloading
my app?
Are they using my app?
How stable is my app?
These are some of the questions
that App Analytics
can help you answer.
Next, App Analytics reveals
missed opportunities.
Perhaps you have a large
customer base in Japan,
and you didn't realize
that customers were
using your app in Japan.
Well, that's an opportunity
for you to go
and localize your
app to Japanese.
And App Analytics can help you
find opportunities like this.
Next, App Analytics helps
you build a better app.
There's been a lot of great
sessions this week helping you
design and build great apps.
But we believe that building
great apps doesn't just stop
when you release
the first version.
It's important to continue
to iterate on your app,
and App Analytics can
provide you the information
to make great decisions
moving forward.
So let's talk about the types of
analytics data that we provide.
First, we provide
App Store data.
This is data about how many
times your app is being viewed
on the App Store, how many
customers are purchasing
your app.
Next, we provide sales data.
This is data about how much
money customers are spending
in your app, how many users
are spending money in your app,
and how much -- and how many
in-app purchases are occurring
in your app.
And finally, there's usage data.
This is data about how
frequently customers are using
your app, what your
customer retention is like,
and how stable your app is.
So with this data, we're able
to provide you data all the way
from the time that
you're acquiring customers
with App Store data
down to engaging
with customers with usage data.
But today, we're primarily
going to be focused
on updates to App Store data.
And App Store data starts
with product page views.
Every time a customer views your
App Store page on the App Store,
this registers a
product page view.
So, for example, we have
our app, Trip Guide,
and this is our product page.
Customer views this.
This would count as
a product page view.
If a customer goes on to
purchase our app, it's $3.99.
They purchase our app.
This would count as an app unit.
So app units help you track
the number of new users
that you have in any
given time period.
So this helps you understand
your App Store presence.
You're able to see
the number of times
that your product
page was viewed.
You're able to see the
number of new users you have.
But it doesn't tell the whole
story of your App Store presence
because it doesn't tell
you all the other places
in the App Store that
customers can view your app.
And so, to help you
understand that,
we're introducing a new
measure called impressions.
[ Applause ]
So impressions are going to
show you the number of times
that customers have viewed
your app on the App Store.
So we talked about one way
that customers view your apps.
That's your product page.
But let's talk about other ways
that customers view your
app on the App Store.
First, there's search.
A customer searches for
guides, for example,
and our app Trip Guide shows
up in the search results.
This will count as an
impression as well.
If you're taking advantage
of the new search ads
and your app shows up in
search results this way,
this will also count
as an impression.
If your app shows up
in the category section
or in our top charts or
featured, these are all ways
that will register
impressions in App Analytics.
So this is the new
feature impressions.
Let's take a look at what this
looks like in the product.
This is the App List.
This the entry point to
the App Analytics product.
From here, you can see a
snapshot across all of your iOS
and Apple TV apps
across five key measures,
starting with your impressions
to see how many customers
are viewing your app
on the App Store, app units
to tell you how many
new users you have,
sales to tell you how much
money customers are spending in
or on your app, sessions to tell
you how many times customers
have opened your app, and
crashes to give you an idea
of how stable your app is.
We show you the value for
the current period as well
as the percentage change
from the previous period
to help you understand whether
this number is good or bad.
So we can see our
app, Trip Guide.
It's in the first row here.
And we can see that
in the last 30 days,
we had around 300,000
impressions.
This is a 17 percent increase
from the previous period.
If we want to find out more
information about this number,
you can click into that number,
and it'll take you
to the metrics view.
So the metrics view allows
you to see a little bit
of more information about
any of these numbers.
You can see this data
charted over time,
and you can also slice this
by various dimensions to see
if you want to see something --
drill down to something
more specific,
perhaps how many impression you
have just in the United States.
In addition to providing
a count of impressions,
we're also providing unique
devices on impressions.
So if you select
that, you'll filter
down to just the unique
devices for impressions.
So if I were to view
my app Trip Guide
on the App Store three times
in one day on the same device,
that would count as
three impressions,
but one unique impression.
So if I select that, now I'm
viewing just the unique devices
for impressions.
This helps us better understand
the total number of customers
who are viewing our
app on the App Store
at any given time period.
With this, we can start
to compare that number
to the number of new users we
have, and then we can start
to understand our App
Store conversion rate,
how well our App Store presence
is converting to new users.
So I'll walk you through that.
You can select compare to
and compare to app units.
Now you're viewing app units
compared to impressions
on the same graph, but
it'd be a little easier
to view this data as a ratio.
So if you change from single
access and select ratio,
now you can view this as
a ratio trended over time,
and we can see that
our app has about --
it takes about ten
impressions for one app unit.
And so, we can start to --
as we update our screenshots
and our description to our
App Store page, we can start
to see what effect that has on
our App Store conversion rate.
So that's the impression feature
and how you can start to use it
to look at your App
Store conversion rate.
And we're excited to announce
that all this is available
now in App Analytics.
[ Applause ]
So let's talk about what's
next in App Analytics.
We've given you impressions to
help you understand the number
of customers that are viewing
your app on the App Store,
but the next question we want
to help you answer is how
are customers finding my app?
And we do this today
with sources.
And so, let's talk about what
types of sources there are
for customers to find
your app on the App Store.
The first source is
browsing the App Store.
So we talked about
one example earlier
with searching on the App Store.
We've searched for guides.
That's one way that
customers discover your app.
Similarly, if we were to find
our app browsing the App Store
in the top charts, in featured,
in the categories section,
these are all ways that
customers are finding your app
by browsing the App Store.
So that's one source for
customers to find your app.
But we recognize that
there are other ways
that customers are finding your
apps outside of the App Store.
And so, the first source
that we're going to talk
about outside of the
App Store are websites.
So websites are tracked any
time a customer taps on a link
from a website in Mobile
Safari, and that takes you
to the App Store page.
This counts as a
source type of websites.
So we have our app Trip Guide
here, and we've included a link
on our website,
TripGuide.Apple.com.
This would be a situation
where the source is website,
and the website is
TripGuide.Apple.com.
So that's one source
where customers can find your
app outside of the App Store.
The other source that
we're going to talk
about for customers to
find your app outside
of the App Store are other apps.
So for example, we tweeted
about our app Trip Guide here,
and we included a link
to our App Store page.
We're trying to promote our
app socially on Twitter.
Someone follows that link.
That would be an
example of a case
where the source was another
app, and the app was Twitter.
Similarly, if customers are
sharing your app using mail,
if you're taking advantage
of the new messages features
in iOS 10 and customers are
sharing your app on messages,
these are other examples
of where the source
would be another app
for customers to find your app.
And the apps here would
be mail and messages.
Okay. So those are the
three sources types
for how customers
are find your apps.
Let's take a look at how we plan
to visualize this
in the product.
First, if you've been
using the product today,
you're probably familiar
with this view.
This is the list of
your top websites.
From here, you're able to see
which websites are driving
the most traffic to your app,
and not only are you able to
see the number of impressions
that came from these websites,
but you're also able to see
that across your app units
to understand how many new
users came from each website.
You're able to see the sales
to understand how much money
these customers are spending
who came from each website.
And you're able to see sessions
so you can understand the usage
from customers who
came from each website.
So we talked about the Twitter
mobile app as an example.
Well, if a customer also is
viewing your app and came
from Twitter.com in
Safari, this would show
up under your top websites.
All right.
So that's the list
of your top websites.
Let's talk about how we plan
to visualize the list
of your top apps.
This is the App List.
From here, you're able to view
the top apps that contributed
to traffic for customers
finding your app.
So we talked -- again,
we talked about Twitter,
the Twitter mobile app.
It'll show up here.
Messages, if that's a source
for customers finding your app,
this will show up here as well.
So as you start to
promote your app
across many different
channels, you'll be able to view
which channels are the
most effective and be able
to compare them not just across
impressions, but across all
of the measures that
you have available
on App Analytics today.
[ Applause ]
So that's the new app sources
feature with the new top apps.
Next we're going to
talk about how we plan
to visualize the three sources
that I talked to
you about before.
And the first way is
with the Source Overview.
With the Source Overview, we're
planning to give you visibility
into each of these three sources
so that you can understand
which of these three
sources is contributing
to the most customers
discovering your app.
So you can see customers
who found your app
from browsing the App
Store, customers who came
from an app refer,
and customers who came
from a web refer,
all in one place.
And you can see a percentage
from each of those sources.
Right now, we're
looking at impressions,
but you can also look at
any of the other measures.
So again, you can
look at your sales.
You can look at your sessions
and understand how
customers are using your app
that came from each source.
And so, we talked before about
the App Store conversion rate
and how you're able to look at
your App Store conversion rate.
Well, you could also look at
your App Store conversion rate
across each of these sources.
So let's do that.
When we left off in the
metrics view, we were here
in the App Store
conversion rate.
If we want to view this rate
across each of our sources,
we can select view by.
And you can see in there we have
all of our sources available.
We could look at territory
to understand how our App
Store conversion rate is
on each territory.
But for right now, we're
going to select source type.
And so, if we select
source type, now we're able
to see our App Store
conversion rate for each
of the three sources
that we talked about
and better understand
which source is converting
the best on the App Store.
So that's the new sources
feature and how we plan
to visualize it in the product.
We're excited to say that this
will be coming later this year.
[ Applause ]
That's what's new
in App Analytics
and a little bit
of what's coming.
I'm going to hand it
back over to Dave.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> All right.
Thanks, David.
That's what's new
in App Analytics.
So let's talk about
screenshot simplification.
And to talk about this,
the best way to do it is
to take a step back and think
about what are our screenshots?
So you can have up to
five screenshots for each
of your devices that give
customers a real quick snapshot
into what's going on in your app
when they're browsing
the App Store.
And since we give
you five screenshots
for each device size, when
you're developing for iPhone,
that's going to give
you 20 screenshots.
As you start to include
iPad into your app,
that number increases to 30,
and this is before you've even
done any kind of localization.
And we support up to
28 different languages
on iTunes Connect and the
App Store, bringing you
up to 840 different
screenshots that you can upload.
And we haven't even
included the Apple Watch.
With Apple Watch, that
number increases to up
to 980 screenshots,
and this is great.
There's a lot of power in this
because you can actually
get the right screenshot
for the right device and
the correct localization.
But you don't always
need this much power,
and that's what screenshot
simplification is about
and how we can simplify
this into just one set
of screenshots per
device family.
[ Applause ]
Yeah, we can clap for this one.
So let's see what this is going
to look like in iTunes Connect.
So we're going to start
on the version page,
and the first thing
you'll notice is that there
at the top we just have the
two sections, iPhone, iPad.
And now the [inaudible] will
support our larger sized iPhone
screenshots, the 5-1/2 inch.
So we drag those on in.
They fill in.
We have our app preview first,
followed by our five
screenshots.
And if we want to see our other
sizes, that's just down below.
We can open it up,
and we can see
that automatically we've begun
to share those screenshots I
uploaded from my 5-1/2 inch
down to these smaller sizes.
In fact, if we zoom in,
we can tell we've written
on the screenshot where
these images came from.
And if we want to change
this, what screenshots we have
for these other sizes,
then we have a new area
of iTunes Connect
called the Media Manager.
Now let's look into this.
This Media Manager is going
to hold all of our information
about all those screenshots
and app previews that we upload
across different languages
on all of our devices.
So you can see at the top we
have our 5-1/2 inch screenshots,
and they've been shared down
below with the smaller sizes.
In fact, if we change
our screenshot order
for the 5-1/2 inch, it's
also going to change those
that have been shared.
But not every app looks
and behaves the same
on the 5-1/2 inch iPhone as
it does on the smaller sizes.
So you may want to
upload screenshots
that are more specific
for your device size.
In order to do that,
there's a checkbox right here
for our 4.7 inch.
We're going to stop sharing
by unchecking that box,
and that's going to clear
out these shared screenshots.
We simply drag in the
new 4.7 inch screenshots,
and now these screenshots
are actually sharing
with those that are smaller.
We're going to find the
next closest larger size
from which we can
share screenshots.
Now if we want to localize our
app on our app screenshots,
we can do the same thing
in other languages.
So let's pick German.
When we look at our German
images inside of Media Manager,
we're going to see that the
5-1/2 inch German screenshots
came from my default
localization,
in this case my US English.
And the 4.7 are copied from
the 4.7 default localization.
If I want to upload
German-specific screenshots,
I can come here to my
checkbox, uncheck this sharing,
and this is actually
going to clear out all
of my screenshots for German.
We're going to favor your
localized screenshots
over all else.
So now we can drag in my
5-1/2 inch German screenshots,
and they're going to fill in
not only this larger size,
but everything down below.
And since my German app
also behaves differently
on these different
sizes, I can come in here,
uncheck the sharing
for this 4.7 inch.
They get cleared out, and I
drag in my new screenshots.
And that's it.
And that's how we use
screenshot simplification.
There's two different
kinds of media management.
We start with iPhone and iPad
where they're going to share
across all the different
localizations as well
as the different
size that you have.
But there are some device types
that don't have multiple sizes,
Apple Watch, Apple
TV, and the Mac.
You can still use
screenshot simplification,
but in this case, all
you're going to share
across are the localizations.
What if you do want to still
upload all 980 screenshots?
Well, the best way to do that
is for the Transporter XML Feed.
This is a command line
automation tool that we provide
that lets you upload
all screenshot sizes,
all your app previews, as well
as any other localized metadata.
You can set your
pricing for your app.
You can include metadata
for your in-app purchases,
your leaderboards, and
achievements in Game Center.
And if you want more
information about this,
you can go to the Resources and
Help section of iTunes Connect,
or last year we had a great
session on getting the most
out of iTunes Connect, where
we went over a little bit more
to Transporter XML Feed.
So what is screenshot
simplification?
Quite simply, create only
the required screenshots
that you need and share those
across localizations and sizes.
And this will be
available later this summer.
Now I want to talk
about iMessage apps.
This is a great new
feature that we're providing
so you can really interact
with the people using
your app in new ways.
And we wanted to touch
on what do you have to do
on iTunes Connect to get these
apps ready for the App Store?
We tried to make it as simple
as possible and as relatable
to what you're already doing.
So the first thing is,
is if you're creating a
Stickers iMessage app,
then we have a new category
for you, a Stickers category,
with some more subcategories,
all about Stickers.
And the second thing is we
have device screenshots just
for your iMessage apps.
So you can show what it'll be
like to use your app inside
of messages, and
we can show those
on the App Store
for iMessage apps.
Now how does this work
with the Media Management?
iMessage apps behave
just like iPhone and iPad
in that we have different
sizes we take
so you can show how it works
on all of your devices as well
as across localizations.
And this works the same way
with screenshot simplification.
Now if you want to know more
information about iMessage apps,
we have two great
sessions on that.
If you didn't get a
chance to see those, again,
I encourage you to
check those out.
And that's what it
takes in order
to use your iMessage
apps on iTunes Connect.
Now the last thing
we want to talk
about today are the
guideline changes.
And those of you who
are frequent viewers
of "What's New on
iTunes Connect?"
know that often we take this
time to talk with App Review
about do they have any
suggestions for you on ways
to maybe get your app through
App Review more efficiently
or perhaps some common stumbling
blocks that developers run into.
And this year, we're going to
do it a little bit differently
for a couple of reasons.
The first is that App Review
times have gone way down,
and we've worked really
hard to make that faster.
[ Applause ]
And the second is that
we've updated our guidelines
to hopefully make it easier
for you to get these answers
to the questions, and you
can get this information
much faster.
So the biggest change in
our guidelines is the way
in which they're worded.
You could call it
more human readable.
Instead of a list of things,
don't do this, or don't do that,
we've really tried to give you
advice on what makes a good app
and what are the best ways
to get your app ready
for the App Store.
In fact, we've also
included information in here
for when you're ready to submit
your app, sort of a checklist
on things you can be thinking
of, such as is my server ready
to go when I submit to App
Review, not just when it's ready
to go on the App Store?
Does your app require a
login in order to work?
If that's the case,
go ahead and put
that on iTunes Connect before
you submit to App Review.
These guidelines are
really meant to be read
so you can understand them,
just sort of sit down.
In fact, how many people
have already read the new
App Guidelines?
So that's not enough.
Those at home can't see this.
It takes about 20 to
30 minutes to sit down
and read the guidelines and
get a feel for what they are.
The great thing about
them being human readable
in English is it's much
easier to translate them
to be human readable in Spanish
or human readable in Chinese.
And so, we've localized in
these App Guidelines in up
to ten different languages.
We've also combined our macOS
guidelines with iOS guidelines.
You only have one place
to go to get an answer
to what is appropriate
for my app.
And lastly, I want to talk
about the organization
of these guidelines.
We want to try to make
it easier, like I said,
to find answers to questions
that you have about your app
and getting it through App
Review, sort of changing it
from more of a feature-based
system to more contextual.
And so, we broke this
into five different areas.
And in fact, it kind
of shows some
of the changes with
the guidelines.
We've created a comic book and
broke these five different areas
into five different
parts of that book.
So let's talk about
this different areas.
The first is safety, and
this is really the safety
of the people using your app,
the content, if it's appropriate
for kids, if it's safe for kids.
And also, are the
people that are going
to be using your
app doing some harm
to themselves or to the device?
It's that kind of safety.
The next area is performance.
What kind of hardware
does your app need?
How is it running?
Then we can talk about business.
Is your app appropriate
for these in-app purchases?
How does it work
well with Apple Pay?
Do you have a alternate
business model?
You want to understand what kind
of business models are
appropriate for the App Store.
You can check with the
business area of the guidelines.
Let me talk with design
and what makes a great app
for the App Store?
Simple, refined,
innovative, and easy to use.
And last, everybody's
favorite, legal.
A couple of people
thought that was funny.
This is where we can talk
about the rules around privacy,
intellectual property,
and gambling apps.
If you want to know when do I
need to have a privacy policy
and more information about
that, you can check these out.
And these are our different
areas for the guideline changes.
Again, instead of reading
the guidelines and finding
out that you need a privacy
policy for a kid's category
or you need a privacy
policy for an autorenewable,
why don't you instead
go to one place to find
out what are the rules
around privacy policies?
In order to help
you find the answers
to the questions
you have better.
And those are our
changes to the guidelines.
So what's new in iTunes Connect?
Well, we've got the
changes to in-app purchases
with subscriptions
and promo codes.
We have updates to
iTunes Connect for iOS
with a Resolution
Center built into the app
and just released changes
to sales and proceeds.
We also talked about the
new impressions coming
to App Analytics
and other sources.
Screenshot simplification
allows you
to create just the screenshots
that you need and the languages
and sizes that work for you.
We talked about what
do you need to do
to get your iMessage apps
ready for the App Store
through iTunes Connects and the
changes to the App Guidelines.
If you have any more questions,
you can get more information
from our sessions URL here
at the Developers Conference.
We talked about these
other related sessions.
I'm putting them here so
you can take a look at them.
And with that, I hope you've
had a great conference
and a great week, and
we'll see you next year.
Thanks a lot.
[ Applause ]