[ Music ]
>> Hi, good morning.
Thanks.
[ Applause ]
Welcome to What's
New in Xcode Signing.
Signing your apps
can be complicated.
We understand this.
And what you need to know is,
in Xcode 8 we've made it really
easy and fast to manage signing.
In fact, it's automatic.
And on the other hand,
if you want 100% control
over what Xcode does and
when it signs your apps,
you now have that as an option.
And Xcode won't modify
or create profiles.
[ Applause ]
Signing identifies you to users.
And they know that when they
get your app, it came from you
and it hasn't been
tampered with.
Signing also prevents
spoofing your apps.
When you register your bundle
ID with the developer website,
another developer team can't
come along and use that one.
Signing also allows
access to system services
like iCloud internet payments.
We're going to go over
four things today.
We're going to start
out by talking
about the fundamentals
of signing.
What do you need in
order to sign your apps?
After that, we'll talk
about some exciting changes
that we've made involving
setting up new machines
with signing certificates.
Today, you have to do things
like sync private keys.
Or revoke and recreate
certificates.
And that's a thing of the past.
Yeah [applause] you're
going to love that.
And after that, we're
going to introduce you
to some new workflows that makes
managing signing really easy.
And we'll finish by talking
about some best practices
with setting up your projects.
Let's talk about
the fundamentals.
Now when Xcode builds
and signs your app,
behind the scenes it uses
a tool called codesign.
Now if you're new, you don't
need to think about this.
Xcode does this for
you automatically.
And if you're experienced, you
might be wondering, signing.
How does it work?
Well, we use this codesign tool.
And what codesign does is,
it takes your app's bundle
and applies a code seal.
And this allows the
system to detect changes
that have been made after
the app has been signed.
So if someone messes with your
app, it won't install or launch.
Codesign also applies a code
signature to the application.
So it can be identified.
And people know where
the app came from.
There are three things that you
need in order to sign your apps.
The first thing is a
signing certificate.
Signing certificates establish
your identity as a developer.
Provisioning profiles
are all about your apps,
and they grant permissions.
And entitlements declare
support for capabilities.
Like iCloud or Wallet.
So certificates.
These are issued by Apple.
And this is important because
the device needs a trust chain
back to Apple so it
can install the app.
And certificates
come in two forms.
You have development
certificates,
which are for build and run.
And you have distribution
certificates.
Which are used
for authentication
with iTunes Connect.
Or, if these are
enterprise certificates,
it's for distribution to users.
And all signing certificates
require a private key.
This private key has
to be in the keychain
if you want to sign your apps.
And the private key for
a certificate is created
when the certificate
gets generated.
And so it's very important
to have this private key.
And it's worth noting here
that Apple never has a
copy of your private keys.
You can't go to the developer
website and download them.
Now the good news
is, in Xcode 8,
for your development
certificates, you don't need
to worry about this anymore.
And we'll talk more
about that in a second.
Provisioning profiles
are also issued by Apple.
And in contrast to
certificates which are all
about your identity
as a developer,
the profiles are
all about your apps.
Profiles allow access to
things like running on devices.
There's a list of
identifiers in a profile.
And at install time, the
device runs down those list
of identifiers to check
if yours is included.
And if it is, you
can install the app.
Profiles also allow
access to entitlements.
There's a white list of
entitlements in a profile.
And if you want to
use an entitlement,
it has to be in that list.
Now once again, if you're new,
you don't need to
think about this.
Xcode handles this for you.
And if you're experienced,
you might be wondering
why you need a new profile
when you add an entitlement
to your app.
It's because of that white list.
Speaking of entitlements,
entitlements declare
support for capabilities.
And fundamentally an
entitlement is just a string
with an associated value.
Like a string or a bowl.
And these are defined
per target.
So if your app uses one
set of capabilities,
and your app extension uses
another set, that's fine.
And Xcode has a dedicated editor
for working with capabilities,
called the Capabilities tab.
And the Capabilities tab will
manage your entitlements PLIST
in the configuration details.
So you don't have to visit
the developer website.
You can do it all
from within Xcode.
So those are the things you
need in order to sign your apps.
Now what happens when Xcode
goes to sign your app?
It needs to know which
certificate to use,
and which provision and profile.
The way that works is,
Xcode will build your app.
And then it looks at the list
of certificates on your machine.
And it picks the newest one that
matches your development team.
Xcode then looks at
the list of profiles.
And it picks the newest one
that matches your bundle ID.
And these two things
are brought together.
The profile is embedded
in the app.
And the certificate
is used with Code Sign
to apply the code seal.
So that's a quick
run through of some
of the fundamentals
of signing your apps.
Let's talk now about the
changes we've made for setting
up new machines with
signing certificates.
So who's seen this before?
Yeah. Your account
already has a certificate,
and Xcode offers to reset it.
So what happens when
you click that button?
Yeah, so what happens
is it gets rid
of your current cert
and makes a new one.
And why is this?
Well, your development
account has a limit
of one signing certificate.
And if you have a single
machine, this works great.
The cert is created.
You have a private key that's
generated, and it stays
in your keychain
and it just works.
Now what happens if
you have a second Mac?
Well, to build and sign
on that second Mac,
you need a signing
cert and a private key.
And you can either sync that
over using keychain access
or Xcode and import the
private key on the second Mac.
Or you can create a new
signing certificate.
But that first requires
getting rid of the old one.
And now you can build on the
second Mac, but you can't build
on your first Mac anymore.
And it's easy to repeat this
process, and go back and forth
between being able to build on
one machine, and not being able
to build on another one.
And this is really
frustrating and cumbersome.
Well, the good news
is in Xcode 8,
you can now have multiple
development certificates.
So -- yeah [applause].
Each of your machines can have
their own dedicated certificate
and private key.
So you never have to sync
private keys for development,
and you don't have
to see this again.
These changes apply just for
development certificates.
Your distribution certs
still have a limit of one
that you need to manage.
These are created both through
Xcode or the developer websites.
And these are created
in Xcode 8 and later.
And if you have an old copy
of Xcode on your machine,
and you create one of these new
signing certificates, it works.
They're 100% backwards
compatible.
So that's what we've changed
about signing certificates
in Xcode 8.
I'd like to turn the stage
over to my colleague, Itai,
who's going to tell you
about the new workflows
in Xcode 8 [applause].
>> Good morning everyone.
So Joshua's walked us
through the fundamental pieces
that are involved in
signing your applications.
You need a signing certificate
and a provisioning profile
that matches your device
and your app's entitlements.
But many of you also
have app extensions.
Watch apps.
Or embedded frameworks
in your app.
And each of those brings its
own signing requirements.
All this can add up to
a complicated picture,
where signing becomes
a bit of a puzzle.
And fitting all the pieces
together can be pretty
difficult sometimes.
So Xcode for many releases
has provided assistance
to help make this easier.
In Xcode 7, the Fix Issue button
would appear whenever Xcode
detected that something was
wrong with your signing setup.
Now sometimes clicking on Fix
Issue would fix the problem,
and you can return to
developing your app.
But a lot of the times it
wouldn't fix the problem.
Or you had to click
it multiple times.
And in all cases, Xcode
wasn't very communicative
about what the issue was.
What it did when you
clicked Fix Issue, and why.
And really, if Xcode knew
how to solve the problem,
why did it need to interrupt
your development workflow
and make you click a button?
Interacting with signing
in Xcode 7 often felt
like you were talking
to a black box.
You couldn't see inside, but you
could mash the red panic button
whenever you got frustrated.
So that didn't work
out very well.
And in Xcode 8 we've gotten
rid of the Fix Issue button.
But we've also done a lot more.
[ Applause ]
We fully redesigned how
signing works in Xcode 8.
There's a brand new
signing infrastructure
which is much faster and
more reliable than before.
On top of that, we
built new workflows,
and a new user interface
in the General tab.
So you can see and manage
your signing settings all
in one place.
Then we took a look at
how Xcode communicates
with you about signing issues.
A lot of the error messages
were not very actionable
or communicative.
And so we've revised
them all in Xcode8.
So that you see much
more helpful
and actionable information
when something goes wrong.
And for those of you
who are very curious
about what Xcode
does on your behalf
when it fixes a signing problem.
We've added new status
reporting.
So you can always see exactly
what Xcode did and why.
So as Joshua mentioned
at the beginning,
there are two new ways of
working with signing in Xcode 8.
The first one is
automatic signing.
Now automatic signing has
been fully redesigned,
and it takes care of all of
your signing needs for you.
You'll never need to create a
profile, or update your app ID.
And Xcode will do it
all in the background.
So while you're developing
your application,
Xcode will keep your
signing up to date.
For those of you who
want full control
over how your application
is signed,
you can enable customized
signing.
In this mode, Xcode will
never create or modify one
of your provisioning profiles.
And it will never change
your signing settings.
So let's take a look
at how these work
in a little bit more detail.
Starting with automatic signing.
When you create a new project,
automatic signing
will be on by default.
But if you're an
experienced developer,
or you're opening an existing
project, you can enable it
in the General tab in
this new signing UI.
All you have to do
is check the box.
And then tell Xcode
your development team.
From that point on, Xcode will
take care of creating profiles
and signing certificates
for you.
And it will even show you
the profile and certificate
that will be used when
you build your app.
So what sorts of things will
automatic signing do for you?
Well, it will create your
signing certificates.
So if you're developing
an iOS app,
it'll create an iOS
development certificate for you.
It will also create and update
your app ID's and profiles.
And it does this
in the background while you're
working on your application.
So you can stay focused
on developments.
But there are still
some instances
where Xcode 8 will prompt you.
In particular, when you connect
a new device to your Mac.
One that's not already
registered
on your development team.
Xcode will ask you
before it registers it.
Because we know device limits
are finite, and you want
to have full control over
how those are allocated.
And finally, if you're
curious about what Xcode does
on your behalf in
the background,
you can view the signing report
to see exactly what
Xcode did, and why.
So let me show you how this
all works on the demo machine.
So I'm going to show you
automatic signing on Xcode 8,
using a brand new iOS app.
I'll hit Next.
And I'll give this a name.
I'm not a great cook,
so I like easy recipes.
Now the first thing I'd
like to call your attention
to in the new project assistant
is the new popup labeled "Team".
When you create your project,
you can immediately choose the
development team that you'd
like to use for signing.
And from that point on,
your project will
already be configured
for automatic signing
with the right team.
So I'll just hit Next.
And I'll create this
on my desktop.
So what did Xcode just do?
It created a brand new project,
and automatic signing
is turned on by default.
When I created the project,
it immediately generated
the signing certificate
and a provisioning
profile for me.
I can zoom in on here
so it's easier to see.
If I'd like to change
my development team,
I can also do that there.
So that's how easy it is to
set up a brand new project.
I can immediately build
and run on a device.
I never had to click "Fix Issue"
or configure any
profiles myself.
All I did was create a new
project, and tell Xcode my team.
But let's make this a
little more interesting.
As Joshua mentioned earlier,
you can use the Capabilities tab
to enable platform
features that you'd
like to use, like Cloud Kit.
So let's do that in
this application.
We'll go to the Capabilities
tab.
And here I see all
the capabilities
that my app can support.
And all I have to do is flip
this switch to turn one on.
I'd like to use Cloud Kit
here, and Push Notifications.
So when I did that, Xcode made
a few changes to my project.
It linked frameworks.
It modified my Entitlement's
file.
But it also communicated
with the developer portal
to download a new profile.
And now I can build
and run my app.
And I can immediately
start using these features.
Again, I never had to
click a Fix Issue button,
or type in any entitlements
myself.
Now, I happen to know that
Xcode downloaded a new profile,
because I'm an Xcode engineer.
But most of you probably aren't.
So if you're curious about what
Xcode did, you can always click
over to the Reports Navigator.
Where you'll see a brand new
report called Update Signing.
Whenever Xcode resolves a
signing problem for you,
one of these reports
will be created.
Let's take a look at
the most recent one
to see what it contains.
And I'll zoom in to
make that easier to see.
So here we can see Xcode
diagnosed a problem.
And I can see more information
about that problem by selecting
that row and expanding it.
So Xcode's telling me my
existing profile doesn't
support iCloud.
And immediately below that,
I can see that it created
a new profile for my app.
So that's how easy it is to
see exactly what Xcode does
on my behalf whenever
it fixes a problem.
[ Applause ]
Now there are a few more
things you should know
about automatic signing.
The first one is that it
does development signing.
Distribution is handled
through a different workflow;
which Joshua will describe
a little bit later.
And it's limited to Xcode
created provisioning profile.
These of course are profiles
Xcode makes on your behalf,
and it keeps them up-to-date
as you're working
on your application.
And as a result of these,
you can use automatic signing
without ever having to worry
about your distribution signing
assets being touched by Xcode.
So your distribution certificate
and provisioning profile
will never be modified
by automatic signing.
So automatic signing.
It's been completely
redesigned in Xcode 8.
It stays out of your way,
and it manages signing.
So you can focus on
what's really important,
which is developing your app.
Now let's take a look at
the other side of the fence.
Customized signing.
As you'll recall, this is a
mode where you have full control
over how your app is signed.
You can enable customized
signing
by unchecking the checkbox
in the General tab.
And once you've done that,
Xcode will let you choose
different provisioning profiles
for each of your
build configurations.
This is really handy if you have
a continuous integration system.
Or you need different
profiles for free
and paid versions of your app.
Now you have the
power to do that.
And you can configure this
all within the General tab.
You don't have to visit the
Build Settings Editor anymore.
So this is a really
powerful new UI
for configuring your
signing settings.
But we wanted to take
this one step further.
Those of you who have manually
chosen profiles in the past,
have probably run into
some weird installation
or runtime issues usually
having to do with entitlements.
And we wanted Xcode to give
you more helpful information
about that before you
run into those issues.
So we've added new
error reporting right
within the General tab.
And you can see this right
alongside your settings.
So it's easier to
choose the right profile.
Here I can see that my profile
doesn't support the capabilities
that my app is using.
So I know exactly what
I need to do in order
to resolve the problem.
In addition, I can
see more information
about my provisioning profile
by clicking the profile
info button.
And here I can see
a lot of details.
Like when my profile
was created.
Which capabilities it supports.
And again, it's easy to
tell when there's a problem,
exactly what I need
to do to resolve it.
Now customized signing
is limited
to manually created profiles.
These are profiles
that you or someone
on your team has created
using the developer website.
And Xcode will never
modify these.
And you can choose
any type of profile.
So as I mentioned, if you want
to use development profiles
for some build configurations,
and distribution profiles
for others, you're
free to do that.
Now this is a really cool thing.
Especially for those of
you experienced developers
who have manually chosen
profiles in the past.
There's a new build setting
in Xcode 8 called
Provisioning Profile Specifier.
And what this does is it
references your profiles
by name.
Now the reason this is a
big deal is because prior
to Xcode 8, Xcode would
reference your profiles
by their unique ID.
Whenever a new developer
joined your team,
or you added a new device,
you'd need to generate a
new version of your profile.
And when you did that,
you'd get a new unique ID.
So then you'd need to
update your project.
Well, now in Xcode 8, since
we reference profiles by name,
all you need to do is
generate a new profile,
and Xcode will automatically
pick it up.
You don't need to update your
project [applause] thank you.
[ Applause ]
So let's take a look
at how customized signing
works on the demo machine.
Okay. I'm going to show you
another app I've been working
on called, Scrapbook.
And let me zoom in on that.
So Scrapbook is set up
for customized signing.
I've chosen different
profiles for the free
and paid versions of my app.
And it's really easy
to configure
that in the General tab.
This is all I had to do.
Just select different
profiles from those pop ups.
And since I don't see
any error messages here,
I already know I can
build and run on a device,
and everything will work.
But as in the earlier demo,
let's make this a
little more interesting.
I'd like to use the Capabilities
tab so I can use iCloud
and Push Notifications
in this app as well.
Now if you've used the
Capabilities tab in the past
with a manually specified
provisioning profile,
you might've noticed that it
sometimes would change your
signing settings.
Or make changes that
you didn't really want.
In Xcode 8, the Capabilities
tab is now safe to use
in customized signing mode.
It'll make the local changes
that are safe to make,
such as updating your
entitlements PLIST.
But it won't touch
your profiles.
It'll just tell you what steps
you need to take manually
in order to resolve
those problems.
So let's take a look at that.
I'll click on Capabilities,
and then turn on iCloud
and Push Notifications.
Now Xcode is showing me
checkmarks next to the steps
that it was able to complete.
And little error icons next
to the steps that I still need
to complete on the
developer website.
I can see more information
about this in the General tab.
I'll zoom in on that.
And if you look at
that error message,
you can see Xcode's telling
me my selected profile doesn't
support iCloud and
Push Notifications.
That's kind of obvious
since I just enabled those.
But it's really clear.
I can tell exactly what I need
to do to fix this problem.
Whereas in the past, if I
had tried to build and run,
my app either wouldn't install
or wouldn't run correctly.
And finally, if I want
to see more information,
I can click the Profile
Info button.
And Xcode will show me more
detail about my profile.
Like the capabilities that it
supports and those it doesn't.
So again, it's easy to
see exactly what I need
to do to fix a problem.
So let's go fix this one.
As I mentioned earlier, in
customized signing mode,
Xcode won't modify
profiles for me.
I need to visit the developer
website to do it myself.
So I'll open up the
developer website and click
on Certificates,
Identifiers, and Profiles.
The first thing I need to
do is update my app ID.
So I'll select App IDs.
And I'll choose the app ID I've
already created for this app.
This shows me all the
capabilities that are available.
I'll hit, Edit.
Scroll down and turn on iCloud.
Now this alert message that
I'm seeing is reminding me
that after I update my app ID,
I also need to download
a new version
of my provisioning profile.
So I'll just hit, Okay.
And then I'd like to enable
the newer version of iCloud.
So I'll turn that on.
And again I'm reminded
that I need a new profile.
So I'll click, Okay.
Scroll down and turn
on Push Notifications.
And now I'm done.
The next step is
updating my profile.
So I'm going to click
on Development.
And you'll see the two scrapbook
profiles are now marked
as invalid.
That's because I've made
changes to my app ID.
But I haven't regenerated
the profiles yet.
So they're out of date.
Let's update the
Scrapbook Free profile.
I'll select it and click, Edit.
And I can scroll down
through all of this.
I'm not making changes
to certs or to devices.
And I'll click on Generate.
And then download
the new profile.
Now the very last step is I
need to install this profile
so that Xcode can use it.
I can do that just by clicking
it in the Downloads folder.
So what just happened there?
I'll zoom in on that.
When I clicked on the
profile, Xcode installed it,
and immediately updated
to start using it.
So we can see the errors in
the free build configuration
of my app have disappeared.
You might also have noticed
that I didn't make any
project changes here.
This is provisioning profile
specifier working behind
the scenes.
Once I installed the new
version of the profile,
Xcode just started
using it automatically.
Now I can build and run
the free version of my app,
and everything will work.
I can use iCloud and Push.
But it looks like I still need
to update the premium
version of my app.
Does everybody want to see me do
that on the developer website?
Or we get the idea?
Okay. It's a little bit tedious.
If you were paying
attention to the earlier demo,
you might have noticed
this is actually --
all those steps I just performed
are the exact same steps
that Xcode performed for
me in automatic signing.
So that's customized signing.
A brand new mode in Xcode 8,
where you have full control
over how your app is signed.
Xcode won't interfere
with your settings,
or modify your profiles.
But I'd like to encourage
you all to try
out automatic signing.
It's been completely
redesigned in Xcode 8,
and it's provides a really
seamless development workflow
that I think you'll
really enjoy.
Now I'd like to invite
Joshua back
up to show you some best
practices [applause].
>> Thanks Itai [applause].
So we just saw the new
workflows in Xcode 8
that makes it really easy
and fast to manage signing.
Now I'd like to talk
about some best practices
for managing signing
in your projects.
The first thing is,
use automatic.
Automatic is designed to make
your life as easy as possible.
And it works great
with individual developers,
or large teams.
So you should add all of the
developers that work on your app
to your development team.
You should use the Capabilities
tab to manage entitlements.
So you can avoid visiting
the developer website
to configure things
like iCloud containers.
If you use customized signing,
don't set code sign identity.
You have a specific
signing certificate
that is linked to your account.
So if you set this to your
particular signing cert
and someone else
pulls your project,
they won't be able to build.
So you should leave that
with the default value.
Instead of visiting the
Build Settings Editor,
you should use the new UI
in the General tab
of the Target Editor.
This allows you to see more
information about the profile.
And it also correctly sets
the profile specifier by name,
so you can avoid churn
in your projects.
You should also use
the Capabilities tab
in Customized Signing Mode to
manage your entitlements PLIST.
And if you use development
signing for all
of your project's configuration,
you should try out automatic.
When you get back to your
Mac, go check that checkbox
in the target editor
and try it out.
When it comes to
distributing your app,
Xcode has a dedicated
workflow for this.
And it's based around
building an archive.
Archives contain a
copy of your app.
And it's important to note
that you should use
development signing.
If you sign your app with
a distribution certificate,
you won't be able to
test the exact bits
that you were trying to develop.
So this should be
development signed.
And when it comes time
to distribute that,
when you use the organizer,
Xcode will resign the app using
your development certificate
and provisioning profiles.
And if you clicked
Upload it will go straight
to iTunes connect.
Or if you clicked Export,
you'll get an IPA file or an app
that has been distribution
signed.
So that's the best practice
for distributing your content.
We've covered a few
things today.
We've talked about the new
changes to signing certificates
that makes it really easy
to set up new machines.
We've talked about the
new automatic workflow,
which takes a lot of the pain
out of developing your apps.
And we talked about the new
customized signing mode.
So you can configure your
projects as you see fit.
If that's what you desire.
If you want to learn
more, check out this link.
If you want to learn more
about security or Xcode,
check out these sessions.
And with that, thank you.
[ Applause ]