[ Music ]
>> Good morning and
welcome to session 406,
Optimizing App Startup Time.
My name is Nick Kledzik,
and today my colleague Louis
and I are going to take
you on a guided tour
of how a process launches.
Now you may be wondering,
is this topic right for me.
So we had our crack developing
marketing team do some research,
and they determined there are
three groups that will benefit
by listening to this talk.
The first, is app
developers that have a app
that launches to slowly.
The second group, is app
developers that don't want to be
in the first group [laughter].
And lastly, is anyone
who's just really curious
about how the OS operates.
So this talk is going to
be divided in two sections,
the first is more theory and
the second more practical,
I'll be doing the
first theory part.
And in it I'll be walking
you through all the steps
that happen, all
the way up to main.
But in order for
you to understand
and appreciate all
the steps I first need
to give you a crash course
on Mach-O and Virtual Memory.
So first some Mach-O
terminology, quickly.
Mach-O is a bunch of file types
for different run
time executables.
So the first executable, that's
the main binary in an app,
it's also the main binary
in an app extension.
A dylib is a dynamic library,
on other platforms meet,
you may know those
as DSOs or DLLs.
Our platform also has another
kind of thing called a bundle.
Now a bundle's a
special kind of dylib
that you cannot link against,
all you can do is load it
at run time by an
dlopen and that's used
on a Mac OS for plug-ins.
Last, is the term image.
Image refers to any
of these three types.
And I'll be using
that term a lot.
And lastly, the term
framework is very overloaded
in our industry, but in this
context, a framework is a dylib
with a special directory
structure around it
to holds files needed
by that dylib.
So let's dive right into
the Mach-O image format.
A Mach-O image is
divided into segments,
by convention all segment names
are, use upper case letters.
Now, each segment is always
a multiple of the page size,
in this example the text
is 3 pages, the DATA
and LINKEDIT are each one page.
Now the page size is determined
by the hardware, for arm64,
the page size is 16K,
everything else it's 4k.
Now another way to look
at the thing is sections.
So sections is something
the compiler omits.
But sections are really just
a subrange of a segment,
they don't have any of the
constraints of being page size,
but they are non-overlapping.
Now, the most common segment
names are TEXT, DATA, LINKEDIT,
in fact almost every binary has
exactly those three segments.
You can add custom ones but it
usually doesn't add any value.
So what are these used for?
Well TEXT is at the
start of the file,
it contains the Mach header,
it contains any machine
instructions as well
as any read only constant
such as c strings.
The DATA segment is rewrite,
the DATA segment contains
all your global variables.
And lastly, is the LINKEDIT.
Now the LINKEDIT doesn't
contain your functions
of global variables, a
LINKEDIT contains information
about your function of variables
such as their name and address.
You may have also heard of
universal files, what are they?
Well suppose you build
an iOS app, for a 64 bit,
and now you have
this Mach-O file,
so what happens the next code
when you say you also want
to build it for 32 bit devices?
When you rebuild, Xcode will
build another separate Mach-O
file, this one built
for 32 bits, RB7.
And then those two files are
merged into a third file,
called the Mach-O
universal file.
And that has a header
at the start,
and all the header has a
list of all the architectures
and what their offsets
are in the file.
And that header is
also one page in size.
Now you may be wondering,
why are the segments
multiple page sizes?
Why is the header a page sizes,
and it's wasting a lot of space.
Well the reason everything
is page based has to do
with our next topic
which is virtual memory.
So what is virtual memory?
Some of you may know the
adage in software engineering
that every problem can be solved
by adding a level
of indirection.
So the problem with, that
virtual memory solves,
is how do you manage
all your physical RAM
when you have all
these processes?
So they added a little
of indirection.
Every process is a logical
address space which gets mapped
to some physical page of RAM.
Now this mapping does not
have to be one to one,
you could have logical addresses
that go to no physical RAM
and you can have multiple
logical addresses that go
to the same physical RAM.
This offered lots of
opportunities here.
So what can you do with VM?
Well first, if you
have a logical address
that does not map to any
physical RAM, when you access
that address in your
process, a page fault happens.
At that point the kernel stops
that thread and tries to figure
out what needs to happen.
The next thing is if
you have two processes,
with different logical
addresses,
mapping to the same
physical page,
those two processes are now
sharing the same bit of RAM.
You now have sharing
between processes.
Another interesting feature
is file backed mapping.
Rather than actually
read an entire file
into RAM you can tell the VM
system through the mmap call,
the I want this slice
of this file mapped
to this address range
in my process.
So why would you do that?
Well rather than having
to read the entire file,
by having that mapping set up,
as you first access those
different addresses,
as if you had read it in memory,
each time you access an address
that hasn't been accessed before
it will cause a page fault,
the kernel will read
just that one page.
And that gives you lazy
reading of your file.
Now we can put all
these features together,
and what I told you about
Mach-O you now realize
that the TEXT segment
of any of that dylib
or image can be mapped
into multiple processes,
it will be read lazily, and
all those pages can be shared
between those processes.
What about the DATA segment?
The DATA segment is read, write,
so for that we have trick
called copy on write,
it's kind of similar to
the, cloning that seen
in the Apple file system.
What copy and write does is it
optimistically shares the DATA
page between all the processes.
What happens when one process,
as long as they're only reading
from the global variables
that sharing works.
But as soon as one process
actually tries to write
to its DATA page, the
copy and write happens.
The copy and write causes
the kernel to make a copy
of that page into
another physical RAM
and redirect the
mapping to go to that.
So that one process now has
its own copy of that page.
Which brings us to clean
versus dirty pages.
So that copy is considered
a dirty page.
A dirty page is something
that contains process
specific information.
A clean page is something
that the kernel could
regenerate later if needed
such as rereading from disc.
So dirty pages are much more
expensive than clean pages.
And the last thing is the
permission boundaries are
on page boundaries.
By that I mean the permissions
are you can mark a page
readable, writable,
or executable,
or any combination of those.
So let's put this all together,
I talked about the
Mach-O format,
something about virtual memory,
let's see how they
play together.
Now I'm going to skip
ahead and talk a little,
how the dyld operates and in a
few moments I'll actually walk
you through this but for now,
I just want to show
you how this maps
between Mach-O and
virtual memory.
So we have a dylib file here,
and rather than reading it
in memory we've mapped
it in memory.
So, in memory this dylib
would have taken eight pages.
The savings, why it's
different is these ZeroFills.
So it turns out most global
variables are zero initially.
So the static [inaudible]
makes an optimization
that moves all the zero
global variables to the end,
and then takes up no disc space.
And instead, we use
the VM feature
to tell the VM the first
time this page is accessed,
fill it with zero's.
So it requires no reading.
So the first thing dyld
has to do is it has to look
at the Mach header, in
memory, in this process.
So it'll be looking at
the top box in memory,
when that happens,
there's nothing there,
there's no mapping to a physical
page so a page fault happens.
At that point the kernel
realizes this is mapped
to a file, so it'll read
the first page of the file,
place it into physical
RAM, set the mapping to it.
Now dyld can actually start
reading through the Mach header.
It reads through the Mach
header, the Mach header says oh,
there's some information
in the LINKEDIT segment
you need to look at.
So again, dyld drops down what's
in the bottom box
in process one.
Which again causes a page fault.
Kernel services it by reading
into another physical
page of RAM, the LINKEDIT.
Now dyld can expect a LINKEDIT.
Now in process, the
LINKEDIT will tell dyld,
you need to make some
fix ups to this DATA page
to make this dylib runable.
So, the same thing happens,
dyld is now, reads some data
from the DATA page, but there's
something different here.
dyld is actually going
to write something back,
it's actually going to
change that DATA page
and at this point, a
copy on write happens.
And this page becomes dirty.
So what would have been
8 pages of dirty RAM
if I just malloced eight pages
and then the read the stuff
into it I would have
eight pages of dirty RAM.
But now I only have one page of
dirty RAM and two clean pages.
So what's going to happen
when the second process
loads the same dylib.
So in the second process dyld
goes through the same steps.
First it looks at
the Mach header,
but this time the kernel says,
ah, I already have that page
in RAM somewhere so it simply
redirects the mapping to reuse
that page no iO was done.
The same think with
LINKEDIT, it's much faster.
Now we get to the DATA page,
at this point the kernel has
to look to see if the DATA page,
the clean copy already still
exists in RAM somewhere,
and if it does it can reuse it,
if not, it has to reread it.
And now in this process,
dyld will dirty the RAM.
Now the last step is the
LINKEDIT is only needed while
dyld is doing its operations.
So it can hint to the
kernel, once it's done,
that it doesn't really need
these LINKEDIT pages anymore,
you can reclaim them when
someone else needs RAM.
So the result is now we have two
processes sharing these dylibs,
each one would have
been eight pages,
or a total of 16 dirty pages,
but now we only have
two dirty pages
and one clean, shared page.
Two other minor things
I want to go over is
that how security effects dyld,
these two big security things
that have impacted dyld.
So one is ASLR, address
space layout randomization,
this is a decade or
two old technology,
where basically you
randomize the load address.
The second is code signing, it
has to, many of you have had
to deal with code signing,
in Xcode, and you think
of code signing as, you
run a cryptographic hash
over the entire file, and then
sign it with your signature.
Well, in order to
validate that run time,
that means the entire file
would have to be re-read.
So instead what actually
happens at build time,
is every single page of your
Mach-O file gets its own
individual cryptographic hash.
And all those hashes are
stored in the LINKEDIT.
This allows each
page to be validated
that it hasn't been
tampered with and was owned
by you at page in time.
Okay, so we finished the
crash course, now I'm going
to walk you from exec to main.
So what is exec?
Exec is a system call.
When you trap into the kernel,
you basically say I want
to replace this process
with this new program.
The kernel wipes the entire
address space and maps
in that executable
you specified.
Now for ASLR it maps it
in at a random address.
The next thing it does is from
that random, back down to zero,
it marks that whole
region inaccessible,
ad by that I mean it's
marked not readable,
not writeable, not executable.
The size of that region is at
least 4KB to 32 bit processes
and at least 4GB for
64 bit processes.
This catches any NULL
pointer references
and also foresees more bits,
it catches any, pointer
truncations.
Now, life was easy for
the first couple decades,
of Unix because all I
do is map a program,
set the PC into it,
and start running it.
And then shared libraries
were invented.
So who loads dylibs?
They quickly realize that they
got really complicated fast
and the kernel people didn't
want the kernel to do it,
so instead a helper
program was created.
In our platform it's
called dyld.
On other Unix's you
may know it as LD.SO.
So when the kernel's done
mapping a process it now maps
another Mach-O called
dyld into that process
at another random address.
Sets the PC into dyld and
let's dyld finish launching
the process.
So now dyld's running in
process and its job is
to load all the dylibs
that you depend on
and get everything
prepared and running.
So let's walk through
those steps.
This is a whole bunch
of steps and it has sort
of a timeline along
the bottom here,
as we walk through these we'll
walk through the timeline.
So first thing, is dyld has to
map all the dependent dylibs.
Well what are the
dependent dylibs?
To find those it first reads the
header of the main executable
that the kernel already mapped
in that header is a list
of all the dependent libraries.
So it's got to parse that out.
Then it has to find each dylib.
And once it's found each dylib
it has to open and run the start
of each file, it needs to make
sure that it is a Mach-O file,
validate it, find
its code signature,
register that code
signature to the kernel.
And then it can actually
call mmap
at each segment in that dylib.
Okay, so that's pretty simple.
Your app knows about
the kernel dyld,
dyld then says oh this app
depends on A and B dylib,
load the two of those,
we're done.
Well, it gets more
complicated, because A.dylib
and B.dylib themselves could
depend upon the dylibs.
So dyld has to do the same
thing over again for each
of those dylibs, and each
of the dylibs may depend
on something that's already
loaded or something new
so it has to determine whether
it's already been loaded or not,
and if not, it needs to load it.
So, this continues on and on.
And eventually it has
everything loaded.
Now if you look at a
process, the average process
in our system, loads anywhere
between 1 to 400 dylibs,
so that's a lot of
dylibs to be loaded.
Luckily most of those are OS
dylibs, and we do a lot of work
when building the
OS to pre-calculate
and pre-cache a lot of
the work that dyld has
to do to load these things.
So OS dylibs load
very, very quickly.
So now we've loaded all the
dylibs, but they're all sitting
in their floating
independent of each other,
and now we actually have
to bind them together.
That's called fix-ups.
But one thing about
fix-ups is we've learned,
because of code signing we can't
actually alter instructions.
So how does one dylib
call into another dylib
if you can't change the
instructions of how it calls?
Well, we call back
our old friend,
and we add a lot
of old indirection.
So our code-gen, is
called dynamic PIC.
It's positioned independent
code,
meaning the code can be loaded
into the address and is dynamic,
meaning things are,
addressed indirectly.
What that means is to call
for one thing to another,
the co-gen actually creates
a pointer in the DATA segment
and that pointer points
to what you want to call.
The code loads that pointer
and jumps to the pointer.
So all dyld is doing is
fixing up pointers and data.
Now there's two main
categories of fix-ups, rebasing
and binding, so what's
the difference?
So rebasing is if you have
a pointer that's pointing
to within your image, and any
adjustments needed by that,
the second is binding.
Binding is if you're pointing
something outside your image.
And they each need to
be fixed up differently,
so I'll go through the steps.
But first, if you're
curious, there's a command,
dyld info with a bunch
of options on it.
You can run this on any binary
and you'll see all the fix-ups
that dyld will have to be doing
for that binary to prepare it.
So rebasing.
Well in the old age you could
specify a preferred load address
for each dylib, and that
preferred load address was the
static linker and dyld work
together such that, if you load,
it to that preferred load
address, all the pointers
and data that was supposed to
code internally, were correct
and dyld wouldn't have
to do any fix-ups.
But these days, with ASLR,
your dylib is loaded
to a random address.
It's slid to some other address,
which means all those pointers
and data are now still
pointed to the old address.
So in order to fix those up,
we need to calculate the slide,
which is how much has
it moved, and for each
of those interior pointers,
to basically add the
slide value to them.
So rebasing means going
through all your data pointers,
that are internal, and basically
adding a slide to them.
So the concept is very
simple, read, add,
write, read, add, write.
But where are those
data pointers?
Where those pointers
are in your segment,
are encoded in the
LINKEDIT segment.
Now, at this point, all we've
had is everything mapped in,
so when we start doing rebasing,
we're actually causing
page faults to page
in all the DATA pages.
And then we causing copy and
writes as we're changing them.
So rebasing can sometimes be
expensive because of all the iO.
But one trick we do is
we do it sequentially
and from the kernel's
point of view,
it sees data faults
happen sequentially.
And when it sees that, the
kernel, is reading ahead for us
which makes the iO less costly.
So next is binding,
binding is for pointers
that point outside your dylib.
They're actually bound by name,
they're actually is the string,
in this case, malloc
stored in the link edit,
that says this data pointer
needs to point to malloc.
So at run time, dyld needs to
actually find the implementation
of that symbol, which
requires a lot of computation,
looking through symbol tables.
Once it's found, that
values that's stored
in that data pointer.
So this is way more
computationally complex
than rebasing is.
But there's very little iO
because rebasing has done
most of the iO already.
Next, so ObjC has a
bunch of DATA structures,
class DATA structure which
is a pointer to its methods
and a pointer to a super
gloss and so forth.
Almost all those are fixed
up, via rebasing or binding.
But there's a few extra things
that ObjC run time requires.
The first is ObjC
is dynamic language
and you can request a class
become substantiated by name.
So that means the ObjC run
time has to maintain a table
of all names of which
class that they map to.
So every time you load
something, it defines a class,
its name needs to be
registered with a global table.
Next, in C++ you may have heard
of the fragile ivar
problem, sorry.
Fragile base class problem.
We don't have that problem
with ObjC because one
of the fix-ups we do is
we change the offsets
of all the ivars
dynamically, at load time.
Next, in ObjC you
can define categories
which change the
methods of another class.
Sometimes those are in classes
that are not in your image
on another dylib, that,
those method fix-ups have
to be applied at this point.
And lastly, ObjC [inaudible] is
based on selectors being unique
so we need unique selectors.
So now the work that we've
done all the DATA fix-ups,
now we can do all
the DATA fix-ups
that can be basically
described statically.
So now's our chance to
do dynamic DATA fix ups.
So in C++, you can
have an initializer,
you can say [inaudible] equals
whatever expression you want.
That arbitrary expression,
at this time needs to be run
and it's run at this point now.
So the C++ compiler
generates, initiliazers
for these arbitrary
DATA initialization.
In ObjC, there's something
called the +load method.
Now the +load method is
deprecated, we recommend
that you don't use it.
We recommend you use
a plus initialize.
But if you have one,
it's run at this point.
So, now I have this big graph,
we have your main executable
top, all the dylibs depend on,
this huge graph, we have
to run initializers.
What order do we want them in?
Well, we run them bottom up.
And the reason is, when an
initialize is run it may need
to call up some dylib
and you want to make sure
that dylibs already
ready to be called.
So by running the initializers
from the bottom all the way
up the app class
you're safe to call
into something you depend on.
So once all initiliazers
are done,
now we actually finally get
to call the main dyld program.
So you survived this theory
part, you now all are experts
on how processes
start, you now know
that dyld is a helper program,
it loads all dependent
libraries,
fixing up all the DATA
pages, runs initializers
and then jumps to main.
So now to put all this
theory you've learned to use,
I'd like to hand
it over to Louis,
who will be giving you
some practical tips.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Nick.
We've all had that experience
where we pull our phone
out of our pocket, press the
home button, and then tap
on an application
we want to run.
And then tap, and tap, and
tap again on some button
because it's not responding.
When that happens to me,
it's really frustrating,
and I want to delete the app.
I'm Louis Gerbarg I
work on dyld and today,
we're going to discuss how to
make your app launch instantly,
so your users are delighted.
So first off, let's discuss
what we're going to go
through in this part
of the talk.
We're going to discuss how fast
you actually need to launch
so that your users are going
to have a good experience.
How to measure that launch time.
Because it can be
very difficult.
The standard ways you measure
your application don't apply
before your code can run.
We're going to go through a list
of the common reasons why your
code, or sorry we're going to go
through a list of, why,
the common reasons your
launch can be slow.
And finally, we're
going to go through,
a way to fix all the slow downs.
So I'm going to give
you a little spoiler
for the rest of my talk.
You need to do less
stuff [laughter].
Now, I don't mean your app
should have less features,
I'm saying that your app has
to do less things
before it's running.
We want you to figure
out how to defer some
of your launch behaviors
in order
to initialize them
just before execution.
So, let's discuss the goals,
how fast we want to launch.
Well, the launch time for
various platforms are different.
But, a good, a good
rule of thumb,
is 400 milliseconds
is a good launch time.
Now, the reason for that is
that we have launch animations
on the phone to give
a sense of continuity
between the home screen
and your application,
when you see it execute.
And those animations take
time, and those animations,
give you a chance to
hide your launch times.
Obviously that may be different,
in different context your app
extensions are also applications
that have to launch, they launch
in different amounts of time.
And a phone and TV, and a
watch are different things,
but 400 milliseconds
is a good target.
You can never take longer
than 20 seconds to launch.
If you take longer
than 20 seconds,
the OS will kill your
app, assuming it's going
through an infinite loop, and
we've all had that experience.
Where you click an app, it
comes up to a home screen,
it doesn't respond, and
then it just goes away,
and that's usually
what's happening here.
Finally, it's very
important to test
on your slowest supported
device.
So those timers are
constant values
across all supported
devices on our platforms.
So, if you hit 400 milliseconds
on a iPhone 6S that you're using
for testing right now, you're
probably just barely hitting it,
you're probably not going
to hit it on a iPhone 5.
So let's do a recap of
Nick's part of the talk.
What do we have to do to
launch, we have to parse images,
map images, rebase
images, bind images,
run image initializers,
and then call main.
If that sounds like
a lot, it is,
I'm exhausted just saying it.
And then after that, we have
to call UIApplicationMain,
you'll see that in
your ObjC apps
or in your Swift apps
handled implicitly.
That does some other things,
including running the
framework initializers
and loading your nibs.
And then finally
you'll get a call back
in your application delegate.
I'm mentioning these last
two because those are counted
in those 400 milliseconds
times that I just mentioned.
But we're not going to
discuss them in this talk.
If you want a better view
of what goes on there,
there's a talk from 2012, iOS
app performance responsiveness.
I highly recommend you go
back and view the video.
But that's the last we're going
to speak of them right now.
So, let's move on, one more
thing I want to talk about,
warm versus cold launches.
So when you launch an app,
we talk about warm
and cold launches.
And a warm launch is an app
where the application is already
in memory, either
because it's been launched
and quit previously, and it's
still sitting in the discache
in the kernel, or because
you just copied it over.
A cold launch is a launch
where it's not in the discache.
And a cold launch is generally
the more important to measure.
The reason a cold launch is more
important to measure is that's
when your user is launching an
app after rebooting the phone,
or for the first
time in a long time,
that's when you really
want it to be instant.
In order to measure
those, you really need
to reboot between measurements.
Having said that,
if you're working
on improving your warm launches,
your cold launches will
tend to improve also.
You can do rapid development
cycles on warm launches,
but then every so often,
test with a cold launch.
So, how do we measure
time before main?
Well, we have a built in
measurement system in dyld,
you can access it through
setting an environment variable.
DYLD Print Statistics.
And it's been available
in shipping OSes actually,
but it prints out a lot
of internal debugging
information that's not
particularly useful, it's
missing some information
that you probably want.
And we're fixing that today.
So it's significantly
improved on the new OSes.
[ Applause ]
It's going to put out, a lot
more relevant information
for you that should
give you actionable ways
to improve your launch times.
And it will be available
in seed 2.
So, one other thing I want
to talk about with this,
is that the debugger
has to pause launch
on every single dylib load
in order to parse the symbols
from your app and load your
break points, over a USB cable
that can be very time consuming.
But dyld knows about that and
it subtracts the debugger time
out from the numbers
it's registering.
So you don't have to worry
about it, but you notice it
because dyld's going to give
you much smaller numbers
than you'll observe by looking
at the clock on the wall.
That's expected and understood,
and it's everything's going
correctly if you see that,
but I just wanted
to make note of it.
So let's move on, to setting an
environment variable in Xcode,
you just go to the
scheme editor,
and you add it like this.
Once you do that you'll get the
new console log into the output,
console output logged.
And what does that look like?
Well this is what the
output looks like,
and we have a time bar
on the bottom representing
the different parts of it.
And let's add one more thing.
Let's add an indicator for
that 400 milliseconds target,
which this app I'm
working on is not hitting.
So, if you look in, this is
in order basically the steps
that Nick discussed in order to
launch an app so let's just go
through them in order.
So dylib loading, the
big thing to understand
about dylib loading and the
slowdown that you'll see
from it, is that embedded
dylibs can be expensive.
So Nick said an average app
can be 100 to 400 dylibs.
But OS dylibs are fast
because when we build the OS,
we have ways of pre-calculating
a lot of that data.
But we don't have every
dylib in every app
when we're building the OS.
We can't pre-calculate them
for the dylibs you embed
with your app, so we have to go
through a much slower
process as we load those.
And the solution for
this is that we just need
to use fewer dylibs
and that can be rough.
And I'm not saying you can't
use any, but there are a couple
of options here you can
merge existing dylibs.
You can use static
archives and link them
into both, into apps that way.
And you have an option to lazy
load, which is to use dlopen,
but dlopen causes some
subtle performance
and correctness issues,
and it actually results
in doing more work later
on, but it is deferred.
So, it's a viable option but
you should think long and hard
about it and, I would discourage
it if at all possible.
So, I have an app here that
currently has 26 dylibs,
And it's taking 240
milliseconds just to load those,
but if I change it and merge
those dylibs into two dylibs,
then it only takes 20
milliseconds to load the dylibs.
So I can still have dylibs, I
can still use them to share,
functionality between my
app and my extension, but,
limiting them will
be very useful.
And I understand this is
a tradeoff you're making
between your development
convenience
and your application
launch time for your users.
Because the more dylibs that you
have the easier it is to build
and re-link your app in and
the faster your development
cycles are.
So you absolutely can and should
use some, but it's good to try
to target a limited number, we
would, I would say off hand,
a good target's about
a half a dozen.
So now that we've fixed up
our dylib count let's move
on to the next place where
we're having a slowdown.
Between 350 milliseconds
in binding and rebasing.
So as Nick mentioned, rebasing
tends to be slower due to iO
and binding tends to be
computationally expensive
but it's already done the iO.
So that iO is for both of
them and they're comingled,
the timing's also comingled.
So if we go in and look at
that, all that is fixing
up pointers in the DATA section.
So what we have to do, is
just fix up fewer pointers.
Nick showed you a
tool you can run
to see what pointers
are being fixed
up in the DATA, section,
dyld info.
And it shows what segments
and sections things are in,
so that will give you a good
idea of what's being fixed up.
For instance, if you see
a symbol to an ObjC class
in ObjC section, that's probably
that you have a bunch
of ObjC classes.
So, one of the things you
can do is you can just
to reduce the number
of ObjC classes object
and ivars that you have.
So there are a number
of coding styles
that are encouraging
very small classes,
that maybe only have
one or two functions.
And, those particular patterns
may result in gradual slowdowns
of your applications as you
add more and more of them.
So you should be
careful about those.
Now having 100 or 1,000
classes isn't a problem,
but we've seen apps with
5, 10, 15, 20,000 classes.
And in those cases that can
add up to 7 or 800 milliseconds
to your launch time for
the kernel to page them in.
Another thing you can do is
you can try to reduce your use
of C++ virtual functions.
So virtual functions create
what we call V tables,
which are the same as ObjC
metadata in that in the sense
that they create structures
in the DATA section
that have to be fixed up.
They're smaller than
ObjC, they're smaller
than ObjC metadata but
they're still significant
for some applications.
You can use Swift structs.
So Swift tends to use less
data that has pointers
for fix-ups of this sort.
And, Swift is more inlinable and
can better co-gen to avoid a lot
of that, so migrating to Swift
is a great way to improve this.
And one other thing,
you should be careful
about machine generated codes,
so we have instances where,
you may describe some
structures in terms of a DSL
or some custom language
and then have a program
that generates other
code from it.
And if those generated programs
have a lot of pointers in them,
they can become very expensive
because when you generate your
code you can generate very,
very large structures.
We've seen cases where,
this causes megabytes
and megabytes of data.
But the upside is you
usually have a lot of control
because you can just
change the code generator
to use something
that's not pointers,
for instance offset
based, structures.
And that will be a big win.
So in this case, let's look
at what's going on here
with my, with my load time.
And I have at least 10,000
classes, I actually have 20,000,
so many it scrolled
off the slide.
And if I cut it down
to 1,000 classes,
I just cut my launch times, my
time in this part of the launch
from 350 to 20 milliseconds.
So, now, everything but the
initializer is actually below
that 400 millisecond mark,
so we're doing pretty good.
So for ObjC set up, well Nick
mentioned everything it had
to do.
It had to do class
registration, it has to deal
with the non-fragile ivars, it
has to do category registration
and it has to do
selector uniquing.
And I'm not going to spend
much time on this one at all,
and the reason I'm not is, we
solved all of those by fixing
up the rebasing and
data, and binding before.
All the reductions
there are going
to be the same thing
you want to do here.
So we just get a little bit of
a free win here, it's small.
It's 8 milliseconds.
But we didn't do
anything explicit for it.
And now finally, we're going
to look at my initializers
which are the big
10 seconds here.
So I'm going to go a little more
in depth on this than Nick did.
There are two types
of initializers,
explicit initializers,
things like +load.
As Nick said we recommend
replacing that with +initialize,
which will cause the ObjC run
time to initialize your code
when the classes were
substantiated instead
of when the file is loaded.
Or, in C/C++ there's an
attribute that can be put
onto functions which will
cause it to, generate those
as initializers, so that's
an explicit initializer,
that we just rather
you didn't use.
We rather you replace them
with call site initializers.
So by call site initializers I
mean things like dispatch once.
Or if you're in cross
platform code, pthread once.
Or if you're in C++
code, std once.
All these functions have
basically the same sort
of functionality
where, any code in one
of these blocks will be
executed the first time its hit
and only that.
Dispatch once is very, very
optimized in our system.
After the first execution of
it, it's basically equivalent
to a no op running past it, so
I highly recommend that instead
of using, explicit initializers.
So let's move on to
implicit initializers.
So inplicit initializers are
what Nick described mostly
from C++ globals with
non-trivial initializers,
with non-trivial constructors.
And one option is
you can replace those
with call site initializers
like we just mentioned.
There's certainly places
where you can place globals
with non-global structures
or pointers to objects
that you will initialize.
Another option is that you don't
have non-trivial initializers.
So in C++ there's initializers
called a POD a plain old data.
And if you're objects are just
plain old datas, the static,
or the static linker will
pre-calculate all the data
for the DATA section, lay it
out as just data seen there,
it doesn't have to be run, it
doesn't have to be fixed up.
Finally, it can be
really hard to find these,
because they're implicit,
but we have a warning
in the compiler
-Wglobal-constructors
and if you do that it will give
you warnings whenever you're
generating one of these.
So it's good to add that to
the flags your compiler uses.
Another option is just
to rewrite them in Swift.
And the reason is, Swift
has global variables
and they'll be initialized,
they're guaranteed
to be initialized
before you use them.
But the way it does it, instead,
is instead of using
an initializer, it,
behind the scenes, uses
dispatch once for you.
It uses one of those
call site initializers.
So moving to Swift will
take care of this for you,
so I highly encourage
it that's an option.
Finally, in your initializers
please don't call dlopen,
that will be a big performance
hit for a bunch of reasons.
When dyld's running it's
before the app has started and,
we can do things like
turn off our locking,
because we're single threaded.
As soon as dlopens
happened, in those situations,
the graph of how our
initializers have
to run changes, we could
have multiple threads,
we have to turn on
locking, it's just going
to be a big performance mess.
You also can have
subtle deadlocking
and undefined behaviors.
Also, please don't start
threads in your initializers,
basically for the same reason.
You can set up a mute
text if you have to
and mute text even have like,
preferred mute texts even have,
predefined static values
that you can set them
up with that run no code.
But actually starting a
thread in your initializer is,
potentially a big performance
and correctness issue.
So here we have some
code, I have a C++ class
with a non-trivial initializer.
>> I'm having trouble
with the connection.
Please try again in a moment.
>> Well, thank you Siri.
I'm having a, I have a
non-trivial initializer.
And I guess I had it in for
debugging all commented out
and okay, I'm down to
50 milliseconds, total.
I have plenty of time
to initialize my nibs
and do everything else,
we're in very good shape.
So now that we've
gone through that,
let's talk about what we
should know if you just,
this was really long
and pretty dense.
The first one is please
use dyld print statistics
to measure your times, add it
to your performance
or aggression suites.
So you can track how your
app is performing over time,
so as you're actively doing
something you don't find it
months later and have
trouble debugging it.
You can improve your app launch
time by, reducing the number
of dylibs you have, reducing the
amount of ObjC classes you have,
and eliminating your
static initializers.
And you can improve in
general by using more Swift
because it just does
the right things.
Finally, dlopen usage
is discouraged,
it causes subtle
performance issues
that are hard to diagnose.
For more information you can
see the URL up on screen.
There are several related
sessions later in the week
and again, there's the app
performance session from 2012
that goes into the other
parts of app launch,
that highly recommend you
watch, if you're interested.
Thank you for coming
everybody, have a great week.
[ Applause ]