[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Hello and welcome to
Understand Swift Performance.
I'm Kyle. Arnold and I are so
excited to be here today to talk
to you guys about Swift.
As developers, Swift
offers us a broad
and powerful design
space to explore.
Swift has a variety
of first class types
and various mechanisms for
code reuse and dynamism.
All of these language
features can be combined
in interesting, emergent ways.
So, how do we go about
narrowing this design space
and picking the right
tool for the job?
Well, first and foremost,
you want to take
into account the
modeling implications
of Swift's different
abstraction mechanisms.
Are value or reference
semantics more appropriate?
How dynamic do you need
this abstraction to be?
Well, Arnold and I also
want to empower you today
to use performance to
narrow the design space.
In my experience, taking
performance implications
into account often helps guide
me to a more idiomatic solution.
So, we're going to be focusing
primarily on performance.
We'll touch a bit on modeling.
But we had some great
talks last year
and we have another great talk
this year on powerful techniques
for modeling your
program in Swift.
If you want to get the
most out of this talk,
I strongly recommend watching
at least one of these talks.
All right.
So, we want to use performance
to narrow the design space.
Well, the best way to understand
the performance implications
of Swift's abstraction
mechanisms is
to understand their
underlying implementation.
So, that's what we're
going to do today.
We're going to begin
by identifying the different
dimensions you want to take
into account when evaluating
your different abstraction
mechanism options.
For each of these,
we're going to trace
through some code using
structs and classes
to deepen our mental model
for the overhead involved.
And then we're going to look
at how we can apply what
we've learned to clean up
and speed up some Swift code.
In the second half of this talk,
we're going to evaluate
the performance
of protocol oriented
programming.
We're going to look
at the implementation
of advanced Swift features
like protocols and generics
to get a better understanding
of their modeling
and performance implications.
Quick disclaimer: We're
going to be looking
at memory representations and
generated code representations
of what Swift compiles and
executes on your behalf.
These are inevitably going to
be simplifications, but Arnold
and I think we've struck
a really good balance
between seeing simplicity
and accuracy.
And this is a really
good mental model
to reason about your code with.
All right.
Let's get started by identifying
the different dimensions
of performance.
So, when you're building
an abstraction
and choosing an abstraction
mechanism,
you should be asking
yourself, "Is my instance going
to be allocated on
the stack or the heap?
When I pass this
instance around,
how much reference counting
overhead am I going to incur?
When I call a method
on this instance,
is it going to be statically
or dynamically dispatched?"
If we want to write fast Swift
code, we're going to need
to avoid paying for
dynamism and runtime
that we're not taking
advantage of.
And we're going to need to
learn when and how we can trade
between these different
dimensions
for better performance.
All right.
We're going to go through
each of these dimensions one
at a time beginning
with allocation.
Swift automatically allocates
and deallocates memory
on your behalf.
Some of that memory it
allocates on the stack.
The stack is a really
simple data structure.
You can push onto
the end of the stack
and you can pop off
the end of the stack.
Because you can only ever add or
remove to the end of the stack,
we can implement the stack --
or implement push and pop just
by keeping a pointer to
the end of the stack.
And this means, when we call
into a function -- or, rather --
that pointer at the end
of the stack is called
the stack pointer.
And when we call into a
function, we can allocate
that memory that we need just
by trivially decrementing the
stack pointer to make space.
And when we've finished
executing our function,
we can trivially
deallocate that memory just
by incrementing the
stack pointer back up to
where it was before we
called this function.
Now, if you're not that familiar
with the stack or stack pointer,
what I want you to take away
from this slide is just how
fast stack allocation is.
It's literally the cost
of assigning an integer.
So, this is in contrast to the
heap, which is more dynamic,
but less efficient
than the stack.
The heap lets you do things the
stack can't like allocate memory
with a dynamic lifetime.
But that requires a more
advanced data structure.
So, if you're going to
allocate memory on the heap,
you actually have to search
the heap data structure
to find an unused block
of the appropriate size.
And then when you're done
with it, to deallocate it,
you have to reinsert
that memory back
into the appropriate position.
So, clearly, there's
more involved here
than just assigning an integer
like we had with the stack.
But these aren't even
necessarily the main costs
involved with heap allocation.
Because multiple threads can be
allocating memory on the heap
at the same time, the heap needs
to protect its integrity
using locking
or other synchronization
mechanisms.
This is a pretty large cost.
If you're not paying attention
today to when and where
in your program you're
allocating memory on the heap,
just by being a little
more deliberate,
you can likely dramatically
improve your performance.
All right.
Let's trace through some code
and see what Swift is
doing on our behalf.
Here we have a point struct
with an x and y stored property.
It also has the draw
method on it.
We're going to construct the
point at (0, 0), assign point1
to point2 making a copy,
and assign a value of five
to point2.x. Then, we're going
to use our point1
and use our point2.
So, let's trace through this.
As we enter this function,
before we even begin executing
any code, we've allocated space
on the stack for
our point1 instance
and our point2 instance.
And because point is a struct,
the x and y properties are
stored in line on the stack.
So, when we go to construct our
point with an x of 0 and a y
of 0, all we're doing
is initializing
that memory we've already
allocated on the stack.
When we assign point1 to
point2, we're just making a copy
of that point and initializing
the point2 memory, again,
that we'd already
allocated on the stack.
Note that point1 and point2
are independent instances.
That means, when we go
and assign a value of five
to point2.x, point2.x is
five, but point1.x is still 0.
This is known as
value semantics.
Then we'll go ahead and
use point1, use point2,
and we're done executing
our function.
So, we can trivially deallocate
that memory for point1
and point2 just by incrementing
that stack pointer back up to
where we were when we
entered our function.
Let's contrast this to the same
exact code, but using a point
which is a class
instead of a struct.
All right.
So, when we enter this
function, just like before,
we're allocating
memory on the stack.
But instead of for the actual
storage of the properties
on point, we're going
to allocate memory
for references to
point1 and point2.
References to memory we're going
to be allocated on the heap.
So, when we construct our
point at (0, 0), Swift is going
to lock the heap and
search that data structure
for an unused block of memory
of the appropriate size.
Then, once we have it, we can
initialize that memory with an x
of 0, a y of 0, and we can
initialize our point1 reference
with the memory address to
that memory on the heap.
Note, when we allocate it on the
heap, Swift actually allocated
for our class point
four words of storage.
This is in contrast to
the two words it allocated
when our point was a struct.
This is because now
the point is a class,
in addition to these
stored for x and y,
we're allocating two more
words that Swift is going
to manage on our behalf.
Those are denoted with these
blue boxes in the heap diagram.
When we assign point1 to
point two, we're not going
to copy the contents of point --
like we did when
point1 was a struct.
Instead, we're going
to copy the reference.
So, point1 and point2
are actually referring
to the same exact instance
of point on the heap.
That means when we go and assign
a value of five to point2.x,
both point1.x and
point2.x have a value five.
This is known as reference
semantics and can lead
to unintended sharing of state.
Then, we're going to
use point1, use point2,
and then Swift is going
to deallocate this memory
on our behalf locking the heap
and retraining that unused block
to the appropriate position.
And then we can pop the stack.
All right.
So, what did we just see?
We saw that classes are
more expensive to construct
than structs because classes
require a heap allocation.
Because classes are
allocated on the heap
and have reference semantics,
classes have some
powerful characteristics
like identity and
indirect storage.
But, if we don't need those
characteristics for abstraction,
we're going to better
-- if we use a struct.
And structs aren't prone
to the unintended sharing
of state like classes are.
So, let's see how we can apply
that to improve the
performance of some Swift code.
Here's an example
from a messaging application
I've been working on.
So, [laughing] basically
this is from the view layer.
And my users send a
text message and behind
that text message I want to
draw a pretty balloon image.
My makeBalloon function is
what generates this image
and it supports a
configuration of different --
or the whole configuration
space of different balloons.
For example, this balloon
we see is blue color
with a right orientation
and a tail.
We also support, for
example, a gray balloon
with a left orientation
and a bubble tail.
Now, the makeBalloon function
needs to be really fast
because I call it frequently
during allocation launch
and during user scrolling.
And so I've added
this caching layer.
So, for any given
configuration, I never have
to generate this balloon
image more than once.
If I've done it once, I can
just get it out of the cache.
The way I've done this is
by serializing my color,
orientation, and tail into
a key, which is a string.
Now, there's a couple
things not to like here.
String isn't particularly
a strong type for this key.
I'm using it to represent
this configuration space,
but I could just as easily put
the name of my dog in that key.
So, not a lot of safety there.
Also, String can
represent so many things
because it actually
stores the contents
of its characters
indirectly on the heap.
So, that means every
time we're calling
into this makeBalloon function,
even if we have a cache hit,
we're incurring a
heap allocation.
Let's see if we can do better.
Well, in Swift we can represent
this configuration space
of color, orientation, and
tail just using a struct.
This is a much safer way
to represent this configuration
space than a String.
And because structs are
first class types in Swift,
they can be used as the
key in our dictionary.
Now, when we call the
makeBalloon function,
if we have a cache hit,
there's no allocation overhead
because constructing a struct
like this attributes one doesn't
require any heap allocation.
It can be allocated
on the stack.
So, this is a lot safer and
it's going to be a lot faster.
Let's move on to
our next dimension
of performance, reference
counting.
So, I glossed over a
detail when we were talking
about heap allocation.
How does Swift know
when it's safe
to deallocate memory it
allocated on the heap?
Well, the answer is Swift keeps
a count of the total number
of references to any
instance on the heap.
And it keeps it on
the instance itself.
When you add a reference
or remove a reference,
that reference count is
incremented or decremented.
When that count hits zero,
Swift knows no one is pointing
to this instance on the
heap anymore and it's safe
to deallocate that memory.
The key thing to keep in mind
with reference counting is this
is a really frequent operation
and there's actually more
to it than just incrementing
and decrementing an integer.
First, there's a couple
levels of indirection involved
to just go and execute the
increment and decrement.
But, more importantly, just
like with heap allocation,
there is thread safety to
take into consideration
because references can be added
or removed to any heap instance
on multiple threads at the
same time, we actually have
to atomically increment and
decrement the reference count.
And because of the frequency
of reference counting
operations,
this cost can add up.
So, let's go back to our point
class and our program and look
at what Swift is actually
doing on our behalf.
So, here now we have,
in comparison,
some generated pseudocode.
We see our point has gained an
additional property, refCount.
And we see that Swift has added
a couple calls to retain --
or a call to retain and a
couple calls to release.
Retain is going to atomically
increment our reference count
and release is going
to atomically decrement
our reference count.
In this way Swift will
be able to keep track
of how many references are
alive to our point on the heap.
All right.
And if we trace through
this quickly,
we can see that after
constructing our point
on the heap, it's initialized
with a reference count of one
because we have one live
reference to that point.
As we go through our program
and we assign point1 to point2,
we now have two references
and so Swift has added a call
to atomically increment
the reference count
of our point instance.
As we keep executing, once
we've finished using point1,
Swift has added a call
to atomically decrement
the reference count
because point1 is no longer
really a living reference
as far as it's concerned.
Similarly, once we're
done using point2,
Swift has added another
atomic decrement
of the reference count.
At this point, there's no more
references that are making use
of our point instance and
so Swift knows it's safe
to lock the heap and return
that block of memory to it.
So, what about structs?
Is there any reference
counting involved with structs?
Well, when we constructed
our point struct,
there was no heap
allocation involved.
When we copied, there was
no heap allocation involved.
There were no references
involved in any of this.
So, there's no reference
counting overhead
for our point struct.
What about a more
complicated struct, though?
Here we have a label struct
which contains text which is
of type String and
font of type UIFont.
String, as we heard earlier,
actually stores its --
the contents of its
characters on the heap.
So, that needs to be
reference counted.
And font is a class.
And so that also needs
to be reference counted.
If we look at our
memory representation,
labels got two references.
And when we make a copy of it,
we're actually adding
two more references,
another one to the text storage
and another one to the font.
The way Swift tracks this --
these heap allocations
is by adding calls
to retain and release.
So, here we see the
label is actually going
to be incurring twice the
reference counting overhead
that a class would have.
All right.
So, in summary, because classes
are allocated on the heap,
Swift has to manage the lifetime
of that heap allocation.
It does so with reference
counting.
This is nontrivial because
reference counting operations
are relatively frequently
and because of the atomicity
of the reference counting.
This is just one more
resent to use structs.
But if structs contain
references, they're going
to be paying reference
counting overhead as well.
In fact, structs are going
to be paying reference
counting overhead proportional
to the number of
references that they contain.
So, if they have more than
one reference, they're going
to retain more reference
counting overhead than a class.
Let's see how we chain apply
this to another example coming
from my theoretical
messaging application.
So, my users weren't satisfied
with just sending text messages.
They also wanted
to send attachments
like images to each other.
And so I have this
struct attachment,
which is a model object
in my application.
It's got a fileURL property,
which stores the path of my data
on disk for this attachment.
It has a uuid, which is a unique
randomly generated identifier
so that we can recognize this
attachment on client and server
and different client devices.
It's got a mimeType, which
stores the type of data
that this attachment represents
like JPG or PNG or GIF.
Probably the only
nontrivial code
in this example is the failable
initializer, which checks
if the mimeType is one
of my supported mimeTypes
for this application because
I don't support all mimeTypes.
And if it's not supported, we're
going to abort out of this.
Otherwise, we're going
to initialize our fileURL,
uuid, and mimeType.
So, we noticed a lot of
reference counting overhead
and if we actually look at
our memory representation
of this struct, all 3
of our properties are incurring
reference counting overhead
when you pass them around
because there are references
to heap allocations underlying
each of these structs.
We can do better.
First, just like we saw before,
uuid is a really
well defined concept.
It's a 128 bit randomly
generated identifier.
And we don't want
to just allow you
to put anything in
the uuid field.
And, as a String,
you really can.
Well, Foundation this year
added a new value type and so --
for uuid, which is really great
because it stores those 128 bits
in line directly in the struct.
And so let's use that.
What this is going to do is
it's going to eliminate any
of the reference counting
overhead we're paying
for that uuid field, the
one that was a String.
And we've got much
more tight safety
because I can't just
put anything in here.
I can only put a uuid.
That's fantastic.
Let's take a look at
mimeType and let's look
at how I've implemented
this isMimeType check.
I'm actually only
supporting a closed set
of mimeTypes today,
JPG, PNG, GIF.
And, you know, Swift has a
great abstraction mechanism
for representing a
fixed set of things.
And that's an enumeration.
So, I'm going to take
that switch statement,
put it inside a failable
initializer
and map those mimeTypes
to an appropriate --
to the appropriate
case in my enum.
So, now I've got more type
safety with this mimeType enum
and I've also got more
performance because I don't need
to be storing these different
cases indirectly on the heap.
Swift actually has a really
compact and convenient way
for writing this exact code,
which is using enum that's
backed by a raw String value.
And so this is effectively the
exact same code except it's even
more powerful, has the same
performance characteristics,
but it's way more
convenient to write.
So, if we looked at our
attachment struct now,
it's way more type safe.
We've got a strongly typed
uuid and mimeType field
and we're not paying nearly as
much reference counting overhead
because uuid and
mimeType don't need
to be reference counted
or heap allocated.
All right.
Let's move on to
our final dimension
of performance, method dispatch.
When you call a method
at runtime,
Swift needs to execute the
correct implementation.
If it can determine the
implementation to execute
at compile time, that's
known as a static dispatch.
And at runtime, we're just going
to be able to jump directly
to the correct implementation.
And this is really cool because
the compiler actually going
to be able to have visibility
into which implementations
are going to be executed.
And so it's going to be able
to optimize this code pretty
aggressively including things
like inlining.
This is in contrast
to a dynamic dispatch.
Dynamic dispatch isn't going --
we're not going to be able
to determine a compile
time directly
which implementation to go to.
And so at runtime, we're
actually going to look
up the implementation
and then jump to it.
So, on its own, a
dynamic dispatch is not
that much more expensive
than a static dispatch.
There's just one
level of indirection.
None of this thread
synchronization overhead
like we had with reference
counting and heap allocation.
But this dynamic dispatch blocks
the visibility of the compiler
and so while the compiler
could do all these really cool
optimizations for our static
dispatches, a dynamic dispatch,
the compiler is not going to
be able to reason through it.
So, I mentioned inlining.
What is inlining?
Well, let's return to our
familiar struct point.
It's got an x and y and
it's got a draw method.
I've also added this
drawAPoint method.
The drawAPoint method takes in a
point and just calls draw on it.
Really fancy.
And then the body of my program
constructs a point at (0,
0) and passes that
point to drawAPoint.
Well, the drawAPoint function
and the point.draw method are
both statically dispatched.
What this means is that
the compiler knows exactly
which implementations
are going to be executed
and so it's actually going to
take our drawAPoint dispatch
and it's just going to replace
that with the implementation
of drawAPoint.
And then it's going to take
our point.draw method and,
because that's a static
dispatch, it can replace
that with the actual
implementation of point.draw.
So, when we go and execute
this code at runtime,
we're going to be able to
just construct our point,
run the implementation,
and we're done.
We didn't need those two --
the overhead of those
two static dispatches
and the associated setting
up of the call stack
and tearing it down.
So, this is really cool.
And this gets to why
static dispatches
and how static dispatches are
faster than dynamic dispatches.
Whereas like a single
static dispatch compared
to a single dynamic dispatch,
there isn't that much
of a difference, but a whole
chain of static dispatches,
the compiler is going
to have visibility
through that whole chain.
Whereas the chain of
dynamic dispatches is going
to be blocked at every
single step from reasoning
at a higher level without it.
And so the compiler is going
to be able to collapse a chain
of static method dispatches just
like into a single
implementation
with no call stack overhead.
So, that's really cool.
So, why do we have
this dynamic --
this dynamic dispatch
thing at all?
Well, one of the reasons is it
enables really powerful things
like polymorphism.
If we look at a traditional
object oriented program here
with a drawable abstract
superclass,
I could define a point
subclass and a line subclass
that override draw with their
own custom implementation.
And then I have a program
that can polymorphically --
can create an array
of drawables.
Might contain lines.
Might contain points.
And it can call draw
on each of them.
So, how does this work?
Well, because point --
because drawable, point,
and line are all classes, we can
create an array of these things
and they're all the same size
because we're storing them
by reference in the array.
And then when we go
through each of them,
we're going to call
draw on them.
So, we can understand -- or
hopefully we have some intuition
about why the compiler can't
determine at compile time
which is the correct
implementation to execute.
Because this d.draw, it could
be a point, it could be a line.
They are different code paths.
So, how does it determine
which one to call?
Well, the compiler adds
another field to classes
which is a pointer to the
type information of that class
and it's stored in
static memory.
And so when we go and call draw,
what the compiler
actually generates
on our behalf is a
lookup through the type
to something called the
virtual method table on the type
and static memory,
which contains a pointer
to the correct implementation
to execute.
And so if we change this d.draw
to what the compiler is doing
on our behalf, we see
it's actually looking
up through the virtual
method table
to find the correct draw
implementation to execute.
And then it passes
the actual instance
as the implicit self-parameter.
All right.
So, what have we seen here?
Well, classes by default
dynamically dispatch
their methods.
This doesn't make a big
difference on its own,
but when it comes to method
chaining and other things,
it can prevent optimizations
like inlining and
that can add up.
Not all classes, though,
require dynamic dispatch.
If you never intend for
a class to be subclassed,
you can mark it as final to
convey to your follow teammates
and to your future self that
that was your intention.
The compiler will pick
up on this and it's going
to statically dispatch
those methods.
Furthermore, if the
compiler can reason and prove
that you're never going
to be subclassing a class
in your application,
it'll opportunistically turn
those dynamic dispatches
into static dispatches
on your behalf.
If you want to hear about
more about how this is done,
check out this great
talk from last year
on optimizing Swift performance.
All right.
So, where does that leave us?
What I want you to take
away from this first half
of the talk is these
questions to ask yourself.
Whenever you're reading
and writing Swift code,
you should be looking
at it and thinking,
"Is this instance
going to be allocated
on the stack or the heap?
When I pass this
instance around,
how much reference containing
overhead I'm going to incur?
When I call a method
on this instance,
is it going to be statically
or dynamically dispatched?"
If we're paying for
dynamism we don't need,
it's going to hurt
our performance.
And if you're new to
Swift or you're working
in a code base that's been
ported from objective C
over to Swift, you can likely
take more advantage of structs
than you currently are today.
Like we've seen with my examples
here why I use structs instead
of strings.
One question, though,
is, "How does one go
about writing polymorphic
code with structs?"
We haven't seen that yet.
Well, the answer is protocol
oriented programming.
And to tell you all about it,
I'd like to invite
Arnold up to the stage.
[ Applause ]
Go get it.
>> Thank you, Kyle.
Hello. I'm Arnold.
Come and join me on a journey
through the implementation
of protocol types and
generic code starting
with protocol types.
We will look at how variables
of protocol type are stored
and copied and how
method dispatch works.
Let's come back
to our application this
time implemented using
protocol types.
Instead of a drawable
abstract base class,
we now have protocol drawable
that declares the draw method.
And we have value
type struct Point
and struct Line conformed
to the protocol.
Note, we could have also had
a class SharedLine conformed
to the protocol.
However, we decided because
of the unintended sharing
that reference semantics that
comes with classes brings
with it to not to do that.
So, let's drop it.
Our program was still
polymorphic.
We could store both values of
types Point and of type Line
in our array of drawable
protocol type.
However, compared to before,
one thing was different.
Note that our value
type struct Line
and struct Point don't share a
common inheritance relationship
necessary to do V-Table
dispatch, the mechanism
that Kyle just showed us.
So, how does Swift dispatch
to the correct method?
While it's going over
the array in this case.
The answer to this question is a
table based mechanism called the
Protocol Witness Table.
There's one of those
tables per type
that implements the
protocol in your application.
And the entries in
that table link
to an implementation
in the type.
OK. So, now we know how
to find that method.
But there's still a question,
"How do we get from the element
in the array to the table?"
And there's another question.
Note that we now have
value types Line and Point.
Our Line needs four words.
Point needs two words.
They don't have the same size.
But our array wants to
store its elements uniformly
at fixed offsets in the array.
So, how does that work?
The answer to this question is
that Swift uses a special
storage layout called the
Existential Container.
Now, what's in there?
The first three words in that
existential container are
reserved for the valueBuffer.
Small types like our Point,
which only needs two words,
fit into this valueBuffer.
Now, you might say,
"Wait a second.
What about our Line?
It needs four words.
Where do we put that?"
Well, in this case Swift
allocates memory on the heap
and stores the value there and
stores a pointer to that memory
in the existential container.
Now, you saw that
there was a difference
between Line and Point.
So, somehow the existential
container needs
to manage this difference.
So, how does it do that?
Hmmm. The answer to this, again,
is a table based mechanism.
In this case, we call it
the Value Witness Table.
The Value Witness Table manages
the lifetime of our value
and there is one of those
tables per type in your program.
Now, let's take a look at the
lifetime of a local variable
to see how this table operates.
So, at the beginning of the
lifetime of our local variable
of protocol type, Swift calls
the allocate function inside
of that table.
This function, because we
now have a -- in this case --
a Line Value Witness Table,
we'll allocate the memory
on the heap and store a
pointer to that memory inside
of the valueBuffer of the
existential container.
Next, Swift needs to copy
the value from the source
of the assignment that
initializes our local variable
into the existential container.
Again, we have a Line
here and so the copy entry
of our value witness table will
do the correct thing and copy it
into the valueBuffer
allocated in the heap.
OK. Program continues and we
are at the end of the lifetime
of our local variable.
And so Swift calls
the destruct entry
in the value witness table,
which will decrement any
reference counts for values
that might be contained
in our type.
Line doesn't have any so
nothing is necessary here.
And then at the very end,
Swift calls the deallocate
function in that table.
Again, we have a value
witness table for Line
so this will deallocate
the memory allocated
on the heap for our value.
OK. So, we've seen the mechanics
of how Swift can
generically deal
with different kind of values.
But somehow it still needs to
get to those tables, right?
Well, the answer is obvious.
The next entry in the value
witness table is a reference.
In the existential
container is a reference
to the value witness table.
And, finally, how do we get
to our protocol witness table?
Well, it is, again, referenced
in the existential container.
So, we've seen the mechanics
of how Swift manages
values of protocol type.
Let's take a look at an example
to see the existential
container in action.
So, in this example
we have a function
that takes a protocol
type parameter local
and executes the
draw method on it.
And then our program
creates a local variable
of drawable protocol type and
initializes it with a point.
And passes this local
variable off
to a drawACopy function
call as its argument.
In order to illustrate the code
that the Swift compiler
generates for us,
I will use Swift as a
pseudocode notation underneath
this example.
And so for the existential
container, I have a struct
that has three words storage
for valueBuffer and a reference
to the value witness and
protocol witness table.
When the drawACopy
function call executes,
it receives the argument and
passes it off to the function.
In the generated code we see
that Swift passes the
existential container
of the argument to
that function.
When the function
starts executing,
it creates a local
variable for that parameter
and assigns the argument to it.
And so in the generated code,
Swift will allocate an
existential container
on the heap.
Next it will read the
value witness table
and the protocol witness table
from the argument
existential container
and initializes the fields in
the local existential container.
Next, it will call a
value witness function
to allocate a buffer if
necessary and copy the value.
In this example we
passed a point
so no dynamic heap
allocation is necessary.
This function just copies
the value from the argument
into the local existential
container's valueBuffer.
However, had we passed
a line instead,
this function would allocate the
buffer and copy the value there.
Next, the draw method
executes and Swift looks
up the protocol witness
table from the field
in the existential container,
looks up the draw method
in the fixed offset in
that table and jumps
to the implementation.
But wait a second.
There's another value
witness call, projectBuffer.
Why is that there?
Well, the draw method
expects the address
of our value as its input.
And note that depending
on whether our value is
a small value which fits
into the inline buffer, this
address is the beginning
of our existential container,
or if we have a large value
that does not fit into
the inline valueBuffer,
the address is the beginning
of the memory allocated
on the heap for us.
So, this value witness function
abstracts away this difference
depending on the type.
A draw method executes,
finishes, and now we are
at the end of our function which
means our local variable created
for the parameter
goes out of scope.
And so Swift calls a
value witness function
to destruct the value,
which will decrement
any reference counts
if there are references in the
value and deallocate a buffer
if a buffer was allocated.
Our function finishes executing
and our stack is removed,
which removes the local
existential container created
on the stack for us.
OK. That was a lot of work.
Right? There is one thing
I want you to take away
from this is this work is what
enables combining value types
such as struct Line and struct
Point together with protocols
to get dynamic behavior,
dynamic polymorphism.
We can store a Line and
a Point in our array
of drawable protocol type.
If you need this dynamism,
this is a good price to pay
and compares to using
classes like in the example
that Kyle showed us
because classes also go
through a V-Table and they
have the additional overhead
of reference counting.
OK. So, we've seen how
local variables are copied
and how method dispatch works
for values of protocol type.
Let's look at stored properties.
So, in this example,
we have a pair
that contains two stored
properties, first and second,
of protocol -- drawable
protocol type.
How does Swift store those
two stored properties?
Hmm. Well, inline of
the enclosing struct.
So, if we look at --
when we allocate a pair,
Swift will store the two
existential containers necessary
for the storage of that pair
inline of the enclosing struct.
Our program then goes
and initializes this pair
of the Line and the Point
and so, as we've seen before,
for our Line, we will
allocate a buffer on the heap.
Point fits into the inline
valueBuffer and can be stored
in the -- inline in the
existential container.
Now, this representation allows
storing a differently typed
value later in the program.
So, the program goes and stores
a Line to the second element.
This works, but we have
two heap allocations now.
OK. Two heap allocations.
Well, let's look at a
different program to illustrate
that cost of heap allocation.
So, again, we create a
Line and we create a pair
and initialize this
pair with the Line.
So, we have one, two
heap allocations.
And then we create a
copy of that pair again,
two existential containers
on the stack
and then two heap allocations.
Now, you might say, "Kyle
just told us heap allocations
are expensive.
Four heap allocations?
Hmm." Can we do anything
about this?
Well, remember our
existential container has place
for three words and
references would fit into the --
into those three words because a
reference is basically one word.
So, if we implemented our Line
instead with a class, the --
and class is a reference
semantics so they're stored
by reference -- this reference
would fit into the valueBuffer.
And when we copy the first
reference to the second field
in our pair, only the
reference is copied and we --
the only price we pay is then
extra reference count increment.
Now, you might say,
"Wait a second.
Haven't we just heard about
unintended sharing of state
that reference semantics
brings with it."
So, if we store to the x1
field through the second field
in our pair, the first field
can observe the change.
And that's not what
we want to have.
We want value semantics.
Right? Hmmm.
What can we do about this?
Well, there's a technique
called copy and write
that allows us to
work around this.
So, before we write
to our class,
we check its reference count.
We've heard that
when there's more
than one reference outstanding
to the same instants,
the reference count will
be greater than one, two,
or three, or four, or five.
And so if this is the case,
before we write to our instance,
we copy the instance and
then write to that copy.
This will decouple the state.
OK. Let's take a look at how
we can do this for our Line.
Instead of directly implementing
the storage inside of our Line,
we create a class
called LineStorage
that has all the fields
of our Line struct.
And then our Line struct
references this storage.
And whenever we want
to read a value,
we just read the value
inside of that storage.
However, when we come to
modify, mutate our value,
we first check the
reference count.
Is it greater than one?
This is what the
isUniquelyReferenced call
here achieves.
The only thing it does is
check the reference count.
Is it greater or equal to one?
And if the reference
count is greater to one --
greater than one
-- we create a copy
of our Line storage
and mutate that.
OK. So, we've seen how we can
combine a struct and a class
to get indirect storage
using copy and write.
Let's come back to our example
to see what happens here this
time using indirect storage.
So, again, we create a Line.
This will create a line
storage object on the heap.
And then we use that line
to initialize our pair.
This time only the references
to the line storage are copied.
When we come to copy our Line --
Again, only the references
are copied
and the reference
count is incremented.
This is a lot cheaper
than heap allocation.
It's a good trade off to make.
OK. So, we've seen how variables
of protocol type are copied
and stored and how
method dispatch works.
Let's take a look what
that means for performance.
If we have protocol types
that contain small values
that can fit into the
inline valueBuffer
of the existential container,
there is no heap allocation.
If our struct does not
contain any references,
there's also no reference
counting.
So, this is really fast code.
However, because
of the indirection
through value witness and
protocol witness table,
we get the full power of
dynamic dispatch, which allows
for dynamically polymorph
behavior.
Compare this with large values.
Large values incur heap
allocations whenever we
initialize or assign
variables of protocol type.
Potentially reference counting
if our large value
struct contain references.
However, I showed
you a technique,
namely using indirect
storage with copy and write,
that you can use to trade the
expensive heap allocation.
For cheaper reference counting.
Note that this compares
favorably to using classes.
Classes also incur
reference counting.
And allocation on
initialization.
It's a good trade off to make.
OK. So, we went back
-- so, to summarize,
protocol types provide a
dynamic form of polymorphism.
We can use value types
together with protocols
and can store our
Lines and Points inside
of an array of protocol type.
This is achieved by
the use of protocol
and value witness tables
and existential container.
Copying of large values
incurs heap allocation.
However, I showed you a
technique how you can work
around this by implementing
your structs
with indirect storage
and copy and write.
OK. Let's come back
to our application
and take a look again.
So, in our application
we had to draw a copy --
a function that took a
parameter of protocol type.
However, the way that we use
that is we would always
use it on a concrete type.
Here we used it on a Line.
Later in our program we
would use it on a Point.
And we thought, "Hmm.
Could we use generic code here?"
Well, yes, we can.
So, let's take a look.
During this last part of the
talk, I'll look at how variables
of generic type are
stored and copied
and how method dispatch
works with them.
So, coming back
to our application this time
implemented using generic code.
DrawACopy method now takes a
generic parameter constraint
to be Drawable and the rest
of our program stays the same.
So, what is different when I
compare this to protocol types?
Generic code supports
a more static form
of polymorphism also known
as parametric polymorphism.
One type per call context.
What do I mean by that?
Well, let's take a
look at this example.
We have the function foo, which
takes a generic parameter,
T constraint to be drawable,
and it passes this parameter
off to the function bar.
This function, again, takes
a generic parameter T.
And then our program
creates a point
and passes this point
to the function foo.
When this function executes,
Swift will bind the generic
type T to the type used
at this call side, which
is in this case, the Point.
When the function foo executes
with this binding and it gets
to the function call
of bar, this --
the local variable has the type
that was just found,
namely Point.
And so, again, the
generic parameter T
in this call context is
bound through the type Point.
As we can see, the
type is substituted
down the call chain
along the parameters.
This is what we mean by a more
static form of polymorphism
or parametric polymorphism.
So, let's take a look
of how Swift implements
this under the hood.
Again, coming back to
our drawACopy function.
In this example,
we pass a point.
Like when we used
protocol types,
there is one shared
implementation.
And this shared implementation,
if I would show you the code
like I did before
for protocol types,
the code would look
pretty similar.
It would use protocol
and value witness table
to generically perform
the operations inside
of that function.
However, because we have
one type per call context,
Swift does not use an
existential container here.
Instead, it can pass both
the value witness table
and the protocol witness
table of the Point --
of the type used
at this call-site
as additional arguments
to the function.
So, in this case, we see
that the value witness table
for Point and Line is passed.
And then during execution
of that function,
when we create a local
variable for the parameter,
Swift will use the
value witness table
to allocate potentially any
necessary buffers on the heap
and execute the copy
from the source
of the assignment
to the destination.
And similar when it
executes the draw method
on the local parameter, it will
use the protocol witness table
passed, look up the draw method
of the fixed offset in the table
and jump to the implementation.
Now, I just told you there is
no existential container here.
So, how does Swift allocate
the memory necessary
for the local parameter --
for the local variable
created for this parameter?
Well, it allocates a
valueBuffer on the stack.
Again, this valueBuffer
is three words.
Small values like a Point
fit into the valueBuffer.
Large values like our Line
are, again, stored on the heap
and we store a pointer
to that memory inside
of the local existential
container.
And all of this is
managed for the use
of the value witness table.
Now, you might ask,
"Is this any faster?
Is this any better?
Could I not -- have not just
used protocol types here?"
Well, this static form
of polymorphism enables the
compiler optimization called
specialization of generics.
Let's take a look.
So, again, here is
our function drawACopy
that takes a generic
parameter and we pass a Point
to that function
call the method.
And we have static polymorphism
so there is one type
at the call-site.
Swift uses that type to
substitute the generic parameter
in the function and create
a version of that function
that is specific to that type.
So, here we have a drawACopy
of a Point function now
that takes a parameter
that is of type Point
and the code inside of
that function is, again,
specific to that type.
And, as Kyle showed us, this
can be really fast code.
Swift will create a
version per type used
at a call-site in your program.
So, if we call the drawACopy
function on a Line in the Point,
it will specialize and create
two versions of that function.
Now, you might say,
"Wait a second.
This has the potential to
increase code size by a lot.
Right?" But because the
static typing information
that is not available
enables aggressive compiler
optimization, Swift can actually
potentially reduce the code
size here.
So, for example, it will
inline the drawACopy
of a Point method -- function.
And then further
optimize the code
because it now has
a lot more context.
And so that function
call can basically reduce
to this one line and,
as Kyle showed us,
this can be even further reduced
to the implementation of draw.
Now that the drawACopy
of a Point method is
no longer referenced,
the compiler will also remove it
and perform similar optimization
for the Line example.
So, it's not necessarily
the case
that this compiler optimization
will increase code size.
Can happen.
Not necessarily the case.
OK. So, we've seen how
specialization works,
but one question to ask
is, "When does it happen?"
Well, let's take a look
at a very small example.
So, we define a Point and
then create a local variable
of that type.
Point -- initialize it to a
Point and then pass that Point
as a -- for argument to
the drawACopy function.
Now, in order to specialize this
code, Swift needs to be able
to infer the type
at this call-site.
It can do that because it can
look at that local variable,
walk back to its initialization,
and see that it has been
initialized to a Point.
Swift also needs to
have the definition
of both the type used
during the specialization
and the function -- the generic
function itself available.
Again, this is the case here.
It's all defined in one file.
This is a place where whole
module optimization can greatly
improve the optimization
opportunity.
Let's take a look why that is.
So, let's say I've
moved the definition
of my Point into
a separate file.
Now, if we compile those
two files separately,
when I come to compile the
file UsePoint, the definition
of my Point is no
longer available
because the compiler
has compiled those two
files separately.
However, with whole
module optimization,
the compiler will compile both
files together as one unit
and will have insight into the
definition of the Point file
and optimization can take place.
Because this so greatly improves
the optimization opportunity,
we have now enabled a
whole module optimization
for default in Xcode 8.
OK. Let's come back
to our program.
So, in our program we had this
pair of Drawable protocol type.
And, again, we noticed
something about how we used it.
Whenever we wanted to create
a pair, we actually wanted
to create a pair
of the same type,
say a pair of Lines
or a pair of Point.
Now, remember that the storage
representation of a pair
of Lines would cost
two heap allocations.
When we looked at this program,
we realized that we could
use a generic type here.
So, if we define our pair to
be generic and then the first
and second property of that
generic type have this generic
type, then the compiler
could actually enforce
that we only ever create
a pair of the same type.
Furthermore, we can't store a
Point to a pair of Lines later
in the program either.
So, this is what we
wanted, but is this --
the representation of that any
better or worse for performance?
Let's take a look.
So, here we have our pair.
This time the store
properties are of generic type.
Remember that I said that the
type cannot change at runtime.
What that means for
the generated code is
that Swift can allocate
the storage inline
of the enclosing type.
So, when we create
a pair of Lines,
the memory for the Line will
actually be allocated inline
of the enclosing pair.
No extra heap allocation
is necessary.
That's pretty cool.
However, as I said, you cannot
store a differently typed value
later to that stored property.
But this is what we wanted.
OK. So, we've seen how
unspecialized code works using
the value witness and the
protocol witness table
and how the compiler can
specialize code creating
type-specific versions
of the generic function.
Let's take a look
at the performance
of this first looking
at specialized generic
code containing structs.
In this case, we have
performance characteristics
identical to using struct
types because, as we just saw,
the generated code
is essentially
as if you had written this
function in terms of a struct.
No heap allocation is
necessary when we copy values
of struct type around.
No reference counting
if our struct didn't
contain any references.
And we have static
method dispatch
which enables further
compiler optimization
and reduces your runtime
-- execution time.
Comparing this with class
types, if we use class types,
we get similar characteristics
to classes so heap allocation
and creating the
instance, reference counting
for passing the value around,
and dynamic dispatch
through the V-Table.
Now, let's look at unspecialized
generic code containing
small values.
There's no heap allocation
necessary for local variables,
as we've seen, because
small values fit
into the valueBuffer
allocated in the stack.
There's no reference counting
if the value didn't
contain any references.
However, we get to
share one implementation
across all potential
call-sites through the use
of the witness table
-- witness tables.
OK. So, we've seen during this
talk today how the performance
characteristics of struct
and classes looks like
and how generic code works
and how protocol types work.
What -- what can we
take away from this?
Oh. Hmm. There you go.
I forgot the punchline.
So, if we are using large
values and generic code,
we are incurring
heap allocation.
But I showed you that
technique before, namely,
using indirect storage
as a workaround.
If the large value
contained references,
then there's reference counting
and, again, we get the power
of dynamic dispatch, which
means we can share one generic
implementation across our code.
All right.
So, let's come to
the takeaway finally.
Choose a fitting
abstraction for your --
for the entities
in your application
with the least dynamic
runtime type requirements.
This will enable static type
checking, compiler can make sure
that your program is correct at
compile time, and, in addition,
the compiler has
more information
to optimize your code so
you'll get faster code.
So, if you can express
the entities
in your program using value
types such as structs and enums,
you'll get value
semantics, which is great,
no unintended sharing of state,
and you'll get highly
optimizable code.
If you need to use classes
because you need, for example,
an entity or you're working with
an object oriented framework,
Kyle showed us some techniques
how to reduce the cost
of reference counting.
If parts of your program can be
expressed using a more static
form of polymorphism, you
can combine generic code
with value types and,
again, get really fast code,
but share the implementation
for that code.
And if you need dynamic
polymorphism such as
in our array of drawable
protocol type example,
you can combine protocol types
with value types and get --
get a code that is comparably
fast to using classes,
but you still can stay
within value semantics.
And if you run into
issues with heap allocation
because you're copying large
values inside of protocol types
or generic types, I showed
you that technique, namely,
using indirect storage with copy
and write how to
work around this.
OK. So, here's some related
sessions about modeling
and about performance.
And I especially want to call
out the talk this afternoon
about Protocol and Value
Oriented Programming
in your UIKit Apps.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]