[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Good afternoon.
My name is Kris Markel.
I'm a member of Apple's
Performance Tools Team.
And today we're going to talk
about using Time
Profiler in Instruments.
So here's our agenda.
We're going to start with an
introduction to profiling.
What it is, and how
you get started.
And then we're going
to show an example
of making an application
go faster and do less.
And then finally, ensuring we
have really great user responses
in our application.
But before we do that,
let's talk about why
we want to do this.
And the reason we're doing
this is because we want
to provide a great
user experience.
We want our users to love
using our applications.
We want them to love
our user applications
because they're fast.
Cheetah fast.
So it saves them time and
they can get more done.
We want to make sure our users
have all-day battery life.
So that they're able
to use their devices
throughout the day.
And you don't want to be that
application that's at the top
of the battery usage chart.
And finally, we want to make
sure we have smooth scrolling,
and a really responsive
UI in our applications,
so users love using it.
And how are we going to do this?
We're going to use a
technique called profiling.
Profiling is answering
two questions
about your application.
How much work is it doing?
And what kind of
work is it doing?
And, if you hadn't
guessed from the title,
we're going to use a tool
called Time Profiler to do this.
Time Profiler answers
an additional question
of when is my app
doing that work?
Time Profiler is part of an
application called Instruments
that is a collection of
a wide variety of tools
that measure all kinds of
aspects of your application.
And how do we get started?
Well, it's really easy.
From Xcode's Product menu,
you just go ahead
and choose Profile.
So let's go ahead
and do that now.
Okay. So first I'm going
to show you my application.
Give you an idea
of what it's doing.
My application uses the
Photo's framework to look
at the user's photo library
and check for duplicates.
So I'm going to go
ahead and do that now.
And it takes a little while
when my test data has
lots of duplicates.
So it comes up with
a pretty big number.
Okay, that's done.
Now I'm going to go ahead
and select some photos.
And then let's find a good one.
Here is one.
And then it uses the core
image face detection.
So I can add some
googly eyes to my face.
And then it uses UI
dynamics in CoreMotion
to make the googly eyes jump
around when you shake
the device.
Okay. So that's the application.
Let's go ahead and profile
it to see what it's doing.
So from Xcode's Product
menu, I'm going to go ahead,
and just like I said,
choose Profile.
This is going to do a release
build of my application,
and then launch Instruments
so I can start measuring it.
It's important to do
profile release builds,
because you want all
the optimizations
that you'll get from
the compiler.
So this will take just a moment.
And it's copying the
application to the device.
Here we go.
So now Instruments comes up.
And it's going to show
me the template chooser.
And this you get an idea
of exactly what kind
of tools Instruments
provides for you.
Today, of course, we
want Time Profiler.
So I'm going to go
ahead and click Choose.
Now if you've never
used Instruments before,
this user interface can
be a little intimidating.
But getting started
is really simple.
All I have to do is go
up to this Record button
up in the corner, and click it.
That's going to start
my application,
and start measuring it.
So let's go ahead
and do that now.
Okay, so now my application
is started.
It is starting.
There we go.
Right? I'm going to do
my duplicate checking.
Just one moment.
Okay. And then I'm
going to go ahead
and do my duplicate checking.
And let's see if we
start getting data now.
There we go.
Okay, now that's done.
Now I'm going to
select my photos.
And then I'm going
to pick a photo.
Add some googly eyes.
Shake it around.
Now let's go ahead and
dismiss that photo.
And then I'm going to go
ahead and stop the recording.
I'm clicking the Stop button.
And now we can see here, I have
a nice, high-level overview
of what my app was doing.
Time Profiler gives
me two graphs.
This top part of Instruments
is known as the Timeline view.
The first graph is my CPU usage.
How much CPU my app is using.
And I can actually hover over
it, and see the precise values.
The second graph is what
lifecycle state my application
is in, and how long
it's been in that state.
So that gives me
a really good idea
of how much work my
application is doing,
and when it's doing it.
But how do I know what
is my application doing?
And to figure that out,
we go down to Instrument's
Call Tree View.
Which is this part here
in the Detail view.
And the Call Tree View
represents the collected call
stack samples aggregated
by weight,
and shown in the Detail view.
Now what exactly does this mean?
Well, this is a lot
easier to show
in pictures, rather than words.
So let's go ahead and
look at a diagram.
So here we have time,
moving along to the right.
And here is our very
simple application.
We have a main method
that's calling into method1.
That's calling into method2.
At this point in time,
Time Profiler is going
to get a call stack
from our application,
and it looks like this.
This is just like the call
stacks you see when you're
in the debugger in Xcode.
But Instruments or Time Profiler
indents each subsequent line.
And it does that so it can
build a tree structure,
which we'll see in a moment.
So time continues on.
Oh, and then it records
that call stack.
And it records the number of
times it's seeing each method
or function within
that call stack.
So time continues, and
we can see method2 exits,
method1 calls method3 which
exists, calls method2 again.
Then we go ahead, one
millisecond has passed.
And Time Profiler's going
to take another sample.
And in this case, it looks
identical to the first.
So we'll go ahead
and update our table.
And we just increment
each of those numbers.
And time's going to
continue forward again.
And now we see our application
is doing something different.
We have main calling directly
into method2; calling
into method3.
Time Profiler's going to take
another sample right here.
And now we can see our
different call stack.
It only has two methods
in this case.
And then so when we update our
table, this represents a branch.
So now we know that
sometimes main calls method1,
and sometimes it calls method2.
And we know exactly how
many times it's done each
of those things.
So time continues on, and we
collect a couple more samples.
These happen to be identical
to our first samples.
And so we're going to update
our table appropriately.
So now let's take a look at
what this table is actually
telling us.
One thing to note is that
Time Profiler's not actually
measuring duration.
It's not recording
when the method starts,
and then when it exits and
subtracting those two numbers.
It's aggregating the samples
into a useful summary.
So when you see time
values in Time Profiler,
it's not an actual
measurement of duration.
That's the number of
samples multiplied
by the time between samples.
Which is 1 millisecond,
in most cases.
This does have some
side effects.
And one of them is that Time
Profiler doesn't distinguish
between long running methods,
or much faster methods
that are called repetitively.
And we can actually see that in
our call tree here of method1
and method2 show up in the
same number of samples.
From Time Profiler's
perspective,
they incurred the
same amount of work.
But we know that method1
was actually called twice,
and ran for longer, method2
was called four times
and was much shorter.
Time Profiler's also really
focused on CPU usage, right?
It's answering the question;
what work is my application
doing?
And another result of this
is it doesn't necessarily
capture everything.
In fact, what's missing
from our table?
There's no method3, right?
If you have really
fast functions,
or really fast methods that
aren't called very often,
they won't appear
in your call tree.
And this is actually okay.
This is what we want.
Because they're not having an
impact in how much work I have
to be doing over time.
So now that we have a better
understanding of the call tree,
let's see how we can use it to
make our app faster and do less.
Okay. So looking back at my
timeline, I want to take a look
at this big, first
block of CPU usage here.
I can see that I'm
using 100% CPU
for a significant
amount of time.
So I want to see exactly
what work I'm doing there.
I happen to know, that's when I
was doing my duplicate checking.
I know I expect that
to take a fair amount
of work, so I'm not surprised.
But wherever you're
using a lot of CPU,
there's usually an
opportunity to make it faster.
So in order to get a better
idea of what's going on here,
I'm going to use the
trackpad, and I'm just going
to pinch to zoom in; un-pinch.
So I can get a much better
idea of exactly what's going
on in this time period.
And then I'm going to go
ahead and click and drag
across the Timeline view.
And this is going
to apply a filter.
So now my call tree is only
going to show data from samples
that were collected
within that timeframe.
If you notice, now you can see
that the call tree is actually
showing much less data.
It's only really focused
on this period of time.
So now let's take a look at
our call tree in more detail.
You'll see a few columns here.
There's Weight and Self
Weight, and then Symbol Name.
The weight represents
the percentage of samples
that that particular portion
of the call tree appeared in.
And you'll see next to the
weight there's also a time.
And like I said before,
that's not duration.
That's the number of
samples multiplied
by the time between each sample.
And then there's
also Self Weight,
which is actually the amount
of time that was spent
within that method itself,
and not some other
method that it called.
And you can see actually
here, these are 0.
If I go ahead and just
close this, it's still 0.
It's still 0.
What this is telling
me is that, you know,
99% of my samples were in main.
But actually, all of
those were also were also
within UIApplication main.
And all of those were
within whatever UIApplication
main calls.
And instead of disclosing
these one-by-one,
I'm going to use a new
feature in Instruments 8.
Where I hold down
the Option key,
and click the Disclosure
triangle.
And this gives me
a smart disclosure.
So it's going to just
close my call tree
until there's actually
interesting data in it.
And if we go ahead
and scroll down,
we can see now we
actually have some methods
that have some self
weight to them.
In fact, if I look at this
particular release call,
I can see, you know, its
weight is 117 milliseconds,
and its self weight is the same.
So it's spent all
its time in itself.
Didn't call any subsequent
functions or methods.
And actually, you know,
looking through these,
I see a lot of these
Objective-C runtime calls here.
And they're actually all have
pretty high self weights.
These runtime methods are
super highly optimized
and run really quickly.
And they're usually
the sort of thing
that Time Profiler
doesn't capture,
because they run so quickly.
But since they're showing up,
I know that generally
they're being called a lot.
So they're showing
up in samples.
This is usually the case if
you're looping through a lot
of Objective-C objects, you'll
see this show up in your trace.
So the other thing the
call tree shows us is
over here on the right.
We can see which
library that portion
of the call tree came from.
That particular method call.
And here we can see
this is coming
with the photo's framework.
And we actually work our way up.
Scroll to the right here.
We can see, here's
the line of code
from my app that's causing
all this work to happen.
You know, this particular
line has 0 self weight.
It's not doing any
of the work itself.
But it's the thing that's
triggering all the work.
You know, I'm not
going to be able
to make Objective-C release
call any faster, but I can see
if there's something here I
can do to maybe call it less.
So I'm going to double
click on this line.
And it's going to
take me to my code.
And Instruments annotates
each line with the number
of samples that appeared in.
So looking at this
method I can see that most
of my time is spent on
that red line there.
But if I take a closer look,
I actually see something
else here.
I have nested four loops.
And in fact, each of
those loops is iterating
over my entire photos
collection.
And this is pretty much a
classic example of what's known
as N squared behavior.
As I throw more data at this
code, it's going to get slower,
and slower, and slower.
And since I know
it's going to operate
over a lot of data, this is bad.
So I want to go ahead
and change this.
So I'm going to go into Xcode.
And here's my code here.
A typical way of avoiding
nested four loops is use a
set-based implementation.
I'm not going to go into
details, but I've gone ahead
and created a new algorithm
for doing my duplicate
checking that uses --
That uses a counted set and
another set to find duplicates.
Now let's go ahead and verify
that I actually made
a difference.
So again I'm going to
go to the Product menu.
And I'm going to choose Profile.
It's going to rebuild
my application
and install it to the device.
And then since Instruments
is already running,
it's going to go ahead and
start the recording right away.
So as it's copying it
to the device let's see,
starting the profiling.
Here's Instruments.
And my application has started.
Okay, and it's starting
recording,
I'm going to zoom out.
Okay, I'll zoom out so
we can see some data.
And I'm going to go ahead
and do my duplicate checking.
Duplicates.
All Photos.
And I can see the data come in.
Oh, I'm actually at minutes.
I thought this was seconds.
Okay. So my duplicate checking
actually happened much faster.
In fact, we no longer
see that large bar going
across the timeline anymore.
So that's a good change.
I want to go ahead and
re-measure the rest of my apps.
I'm going to select some photos.
I'm going to add some eyes.
I'm going to shake it.
And then I'm going to
dismiss that photo.
So now my application is static.
It shouldn't be doing any work.
But let's go ahead
and take a look
at what the Time
Profiler is telling us.
Let's stop the recording.
It's taking a minute to
catch up with the data.
Whoa. Okay, so I can see
here at the end of this --
at the end of the call,
there's some CPU usage here.
It's not much, but I'm
expecting it to be 0.
So I want go ahead and
see what that's doing.
I'm going to zoom in
again with the trackpad.
And then I'm going
to drag to select
to see what's going on here.
And then I'm going to go ahead
and option click through here
to see what's going on.
And now if you look
at my call tree,
this time I can see
there are a lot
of calls in CoreMotion, right?
And I know what my app is doing
here, it's using CoreMotion
to detect and make
the eyes move.
But moving back up the call
tree, there's actually none
of my code in this call tree.
So there's nothing I'm doing
that's directly invoking this.
But something in my app is
making CoreMotion do work
when it shouldn't be.
And what I know about
my app, is I realize
that I'm not turning off
the CoreMotion monitoring
when there are no
eyes on the screen.
So let's go ahead
and make that change.
We go back to Xcode.
And then I actually have
the methods all written.
It's just a matter
of calling them.
So let me go ahead
and add them here.
And then we stop observing here.
Okay. Now let's measure this
and make sure it changed
as we expect it to.
And again, Instruments is going
to rebuild the application;
put it on the device.
And also, since Instruments
is already up and running,
it'll start recording again.
This time I'm going to
zoom out ahead of time.
And I also click outside of the
filter, and that removes it.
Okay. And once the
application is on the device,
Instruments will start
recording it once more.
Okay, there we go.
Okay, so this time
I'm going to go ahead
and just go ahead
and add my photos.
And then I'm going
to scroll to a photo.
Select it.
Add the eyes.
Do the shaking let's actually
zoom this in a little more.
I'm going to choose a new photo
so the eyes move off the screen.
And then let's go ahead
and stop the recording,
and see if it changes
as we expected.
And now if I zoom in on the end
here once Instruments is done
processing the data.
I can see that my CPU usage
is now 0 here at the end.
So I'm no longer doing that
work when I didn't need to be.
So let's take a look and
review what we've done.
So the first thing we did, is
we used the trackpad to figure
out how much work our app was
doing and when it was doing it.
And it was a good way to find
areas of interest to focus on.
And the trackpad or the timeline
is really trackpad friendly.
But it also works
great with a mouse.
You can option-drag, and
control-drag to zoom in and out.
So we found an area
on the track view
that was using a lot of CPU.
And we wanted to
make it go faster.
So we went ahead, we zoomed in,
and we filtered on that area.
We examined the call
tree and we found
out where the work was happening
in that portion of our app.
And then we walked
back up the call tree
until we actually
encountered our code.
What part of our app is
causing this work to happen,
even though it's not
doing the work itself?
We took a look at our code.
We thought about it.
Scratched our heads.
We ate a sandwich,
and we figured
out a way to make it faster.
So we went ahead and implemented
those changes, and verified
that they actually
did make it faster.
It was a significant
improvement in this case.
And as a result, we saved
a bunch of the user's time.
Now when they're using my
app to find duplicates,
they won't be looking
at that spinner forever.
It'll finish much more quickly.
Now in terms of doing
less, what did we do?
Again, we focused on an
area of the track view,
where this time it
wasn't using a lot of CPU,
but it was using an
unexpected amount of CPU.
We zoomed in.
We applied a filter.
We took a look at the call
tree, and this time we looked
at the frameworks involved
again, we saw it was CoreMotion,
but none of our code
was being evoked.
So this time we had to think
about our app in
a different way.
What portion of our app is
making this work happen?
We went ahead and again,
maybe took a little break.
Ate another sandwich.
And figured out how to make
our app stop doing that work
so it's no longer happening.
We went ahead and
reprofiled the app.
Verified that our changes did
what we expected them to do.
And actually, as
a result of this,
we significantly improved the
battery life while our app
is running.
Any time the CPU can go
to 0 and go to sleep,
that represents significant
savings.
So even though our
CPU usage was low,
it still has a battery cost.
So now that we've gone
faster, and done less,
let's talk about making
our apps more responsive.
So the way your application
works, is the main thread
that does all the
user interface work.
It's responsible for
responding to user input,
and then updating your views.
And the way it handles
the user input,
is that it's got a main thread.
And the main thread has a run
loop that's just watching a
queue called an Event
Queue and waiting
for events to appear on it.
When an event appears, it
sends it to your UIApplication,
or NS application instance.
Which then passes the event
down through the responder
chain in your application.
And if you application wants
to respond to that event,
then it goes ahead
and invokes your code.
And you can actually see
this in a call stack here.
Here's the call stack
from my application.
And we can see there,
there's the main thread.
It calls the main function
which is, you know,
where all our applications
start.
Now in here, I don't know
exactly what these functions do,
but they're clearly
related to a run loop.
And I can see here, here's
a handleEventQueue function.
So it's clearly got an
event off the event queue,
and it's handling it.
I can see it gets passed into my
UIApplication, and then passed
through the responder chain
until it gets to my code.
And in this case, this is
an IB action on a button.
And then my code does its work.
So what does this mean in terms
of keeping your apps responsive?
Well, when busy, the main
thread can't process the queue.
So it starts to back up
your user events back up.
And then as a result, you
get stuttering and hiccups.
And in the worst case, your app
becomes completely unresponsive.
The user closes it, and maybe
deletes it from the device.
So it's really important to
keep your main thread free,
so it's able to respond
to the user input
in a very quick manner.
So now with that in our
pocket, let's see what we can do
with our app in order to
make it more responsive.
All right, I'm going to
zoom out of my track --
on the track view this time.
And now the area I want to focus
on is this big CPU
spike right here.
And here I'm seeing
well over 100% CPU.
So there's probably
an opportunity
for optimization here.
And I happen to know,
this is also
when I'm adding my
eyes to the image.
So again, I'm going to just
zoom in using the trackpad.
I'm going to go ahead and click
and drag to apply a filter.
Now if we look at the call
tree, this time I want
to specifically focus on what
the main thread is doing.
I can see here that actually,
my main thread is showing up in
about 63%, 64% of my samples.
And so I know that
during this time,
it's clearly doing some work.
But I want to know exactly
how much work it's doing.
And to do that, I'm going
to go ahead and up here
in the upper right-hand corner,
we have what we call
the different strategies
and Instruments.
So you can view your data,
either per CPU or per thread.
This time I want to look
at the data per thread.
And I can actually see, if I
make this a little bit bigger,
that over here on the left,
you can see all the
threads in my app.
And the main thread
is at the top.
And so I can actually
see the CPU usage
on just the main thread.
And here, clearly, it's
getting up to 100%.
And when it's in that state,
it absolutely can't
respond to user events.
There's no way it's going
to be able to handle things
on the queue if it's busy
doing the work in my app.
So what work is it doing
on the main thread exactly?
This time, I'm going
go ahead and click
on our extended detail view
over here on the right.
And this is going to show me my
call stack that's doing the most
work on my main thread.
Because my main thread is what's
selected over on the left.
So I scroll through here,
I can see again here's
the run loop stuff.
And then here we
actually get to my code.
And this is the code where
it's adding the eyes.
And then doing some
more add eyes work.
And then here it's
calling Find Faces.
So that's the face detection
code in my application.
And then we can actually see the
next line is actually calling
into Core Image.
If I go ahead and click on
this in the Detail view,
it'll expand the call
tree to that line.
Now again, reasoning
about my code.
There's no reason for me
to do face detection
on the main thread.
It's not a responding
to user input thing.
And it's not an updating
views thing.
So this can easily be moved
to a background thread.
So here's my code that
does the face detection.
And I can see once the face
detection is done, it goes ahead
and calls the displayEyes
method.
Now an important
thing to note here is
that displayEyes is
actually updating my UI.
So that's work that has to
happen on the main thread.
So what I need to do
is do my face detection
on a background thread.
Switch back to the main thread.
In order to update my UI.
Oh, there we go.
Okay [applause] thank
you [applause].
That's not supposed to be
the applause line [laughter],
but I'll take it.
So here we go.
Here's my code that does
this on the background.
I'm going to very
quickly talk about this.
So we go ahead and we get
one of our background queues.
And we dispatch our
find faces code to it.
Then just like I said,
we're going to dispatch back
to the main queue,
and update our UI.
This time to do my
profiling, I'm going to hold
on the Run menu,
and choose Profile.
This will do the same thing.
Hopefully rather quickly.
Oh, I deleted my code.
Let's do that again.
So now since I've already done
it, I can just go ahead and --
is it going to be happy --
click the Profile button.
There we go.
It's going to build
my application.
Install it to the device.
Okay. Now Instruments
should show up
and start recording
my application.
Oh, so I'm going to go
ahead and switch back
to the Instruments view.
And then let's zoom out so we
can see the data coming in.
Okay. Very quickly, let's
add some photos to my app.
And then let's do
the eye detection.
So there we go.
So there I can see
my big CPU spike.
Let's go ahead and
stop the recording.
And now let's see if this
made the changes I expected.
So again, I'm going to
zoom in on this area
of the graph using a trackpad.
I'm going to click and drag
across the Timeline
view to apply a filter.
Now, if we go ahead and look
at our call tree this time,
actually what I see here
now, the main thread is only
in 4.8% of my samples.
So that's a really good sign.
I already know my main
thread is doing less work.
And those two worker threads
are doing much more of the work.
So let's go ahead and switch
to the thread strategy.
And now I can see here, my main
thread is actually completely
free for the vast majority
of this time, thank you.
[ Applause ]
So let's go ahead and
go back to the slides,
and talk about what
we've just done.
So in order to make my
application more responsive,
I've found an area where the
CPU was being used a lot.
And I went ahead and zoomed in
and applied a filter
it's a common theme here.
I focused on the main
thread, because I wanted
to make sure my app
continued to be responsive.
I identified some work
that we were doing
on the main thread
that wasn't UI work.
So I went ahead and moved
that to a background thread.
Once again you can probably
guess the next step.
I verified my changes.
Made sure the app was behaving
as I now expected it to.
And as a result, I got a
much better user experience.
My user interface will remain
responsive while I'm doing my
face detection.
Which is really great.
A couple notes regarding
optimization.
The fixes we made today
were relatively simple,
but they did add
complexity to our app.
And in general, the practice
of optimization is trading
simplicity for performance.
But fortunately, because
I did my profiling early
in my development cycle I
didn't wait to the very end.
I now have time to verify
that my app continues
to behave correctly.
I can add additional unit tests
if I think that's
necessary or UI tests.
And focus on where
I added complexity,
and make sure it still works.
Just before you're about to ship
the app is the very last time
you want to be adding
complexity to it.
So the real takeaway
here, is that it pays
to profile your app
continuously.
Especially after you
add new functionality.
And profile early.
And then profile it
ongoing on an ongoing basis.
And sometimes, just
running time profiling
and seeing what you can find,
you can find a really
big win quickly.
So it pays just to
run it and see
if there's anything
interesting going on.
Some best practices about
using Time Profiler.
The general overview here is
that you want to be profiling
as close as you can to what
your customers will be running.
So you always want to
profile release builds.
Not only do you want the
optimizations from the compiler,
but release builds are what your
customers are going to be using.
You always want to
profile on the device.
The simulator is not going
to give you useful
data to work with.
Profile on the oldest, slowest
devices you intend to support.
A pretty good rule is, if
you can make it run well
on slower devices; you
get it running well
on faster devices for free.
And you want all of your users
to have a great experience
using your app.
Even the ones on slower devices.
And use large data sets
where it makes sense.
In my case, you know, sometimes
users have tens of thousands
or hundreds of thousands or
a hundred thousand photos
in their photos collection.
It's important that I
profile how my app behaves
under those circumstances.
So I can make sure it runs well
as my customers will
be running it.
So, to wrap everything up,
if you want your customers
to love using your app because
it helps save them time.
It helps them achieve
all-day battery life.
And your UI is really
responsive, then what you need
to do is profile early
and profile often.
If you want more information,
you can go to this URL.
Here are some related -- oh,
here are some related sessions.
Last year we did a session
called Profiling in Depth.
Which goes into more detail
about the Time Profiler,
if you want to know more.
And then this year we
did a sequel to that,
System Trace in Depth.
Which is how you can use
the System Trace instrument
in situations where Time
Profiler's not helping you.
Thank you, and have
a good afternoon.
[ Applause ]