[ Music ]
>> Good morning.
Morning everyone and
welcome to session 501.
I'm Brad Ford.
I work on the Core Media
and AV Foundation
Capture Teams at Apple.
And this session is all
about the iOS camera.
Hopefully you've
figured that out by now.
This is the most popular
camera in the world.
And it's also about photography.
If you develop a photography
app, or even just thinking
about developing
a photography app,
then this is a very
good OS for you.
I think you and iOS 10 are
about to become fast friends.
Today we'll be focusing on
the AV Foundation framework,
which is our lowest level
and most powerful framework
for accessing the camera.
AV Foundation is broad and deep.
If you're new to camera
capture on iOS, I invite you
to review our past WWC camera
presentation videos listed here.
They give you a good base for
today's presentation and plus,
you get to watch
me age gracefully.
Here's what we're going to
do for the next 58 minutes.
I'll present a brand
new AVCaptureOutput
for capturing photographic
content, and then we're going
to focus on four feature areas.
We're going to focus
on Live Photos.
You'll learn how to capture
Live Photos in your app,
just like Apple's camera app.
You'll learn how to capture
bare RAW images and store them
to DNG files, which is a
first on our platform in iOS.
You'll learn about
how to get preview
or thumbnail images along with
your regular photo captures
for a more responsive UI.
And lastly, you'll learn
how to capture gorgeous,
vivid images in wide color.
Let's get started.
Here's a quick refresher
on how AV Foundation's
capture classes work.
At the center of our
capture universe is
the AVCaptureSession.
This is the object you tell
it to start or stop running.
In order to do anything useful,
though, it needs some inputs.
Inputs like a camera
or a microphone.
And they provide
data to the session.
And it also needs outputs
to receive the data,
such as a StillImageOutput
which can capture still images
or a QuickTime movie
file output,
which records QuickTime movies.
There are also connections, and
these are represented in the API
as AVCaptureConnections.
That's our overall object graph.
You've kind of seen how we
all put things together.
All of these features,
I just mentioned,
relate to taking still images.
So we might expect that we'd
be spending a lot of time
in the AVCaptureStillImageOutput
today but you'd be wrong.
Today we're introducing a brand
new CaptureOutput in iOS 10.
And it's called the
AVCapturePhotoOutput,
emphasizing the fact that
our photos are much more
than static still images now.
AVCapturePhotoOutput addresses
AVStillImageOutput's design
challenges in four main areas.
It features a functional
programming model.
There are clear delineations
between mutable and
immutable data.
We've encapsulated
photo settings
into a distinct object
unto itself.
And the PhotoOutput can
track your photo's progress
from request to completion
through a delegate-style
interface of callbacks.
And lastly, it resolves your
indeterminate photo settings
early in the capture process,
so you know what you're
going to be getting.
Let's talk a little bit more
about that last feature there.
Here's what an
AVCapturePhotoOutput looks like.
Even with all its new features,
it's a very thin interface,
smaller even than
AVCaptureStillImageOutput.
It has a small set of
read-only properties
that tell you whether particular
features are supported,
such as is
LivePhotoCaptureSupported?
It has a smaller set of writable
properties that let you opt
in for particular
features when supported.
Some capture features affect how
the capture render pipeline is
built, so you have to
specify them upfront.
One such is
HighResolutionCapture.
If you ever intend to capture
high-resolution photos,
such as five-megapixel
selfies on the iPhone 6s,
you have to opt-in for the
feature first before calling
startRunning on the
AVCapture Session.
Lastly, there's a single
method that you can call
to kick off a photo capture.
Just one verb.
That's it.
Now you're probably asking
yourself, well what happened
to all the per photo state?
How do I request
the flash capture?
How do I get BGRA?
How do I get still
image stabilization?
These features and
others have moved
to a new object called
AVCapturePhotoSettings.
This object contains all
the settings that pertain
to one single photo
capture request.
Think of it like the
list of options to choose
from when you're buying a MAC
on the Apple online store.
You fill out the online
form with all the features
that you want and then you
hit the place order button.
And placing the order is
like calling capturePhoto,
passing the
AVCapturePhotoSettings
as your first parameter.
Now when you place
an order online,
the store needs your email
address to communicate
with you about your order.
Within AVCapturePhotoOutput's
world,
the email address you provide
is an object conforming
to AVCapturePhotoCaptureDelegate
protocol.
This delegate gets called
back as events related
to your photo capture occur.
This object gets passed
as your second parameter
to CapturePhoto.
Okay, so what's good about
AVCapturePhotoSettings?
First of all, they are atomic.
All settings are
encapsulated in a single object.
There's no potential for
settings getting out of sync
because they are not properties
of the AVCapturePhotoOutput,
but rather, a per-settings
object.
They're unique.
Each photo settings instance
has a unique ID property.
You're only allowed to use
one photo settings once
and never again.
So you'll receive
exactly one set of results
for each photo capture request.
After requesting a photo
capture with a set of settings,
you can hold onto it and
validate results against it
as they're returned to you.
Sort of like making a
copy of your order form,
your online order form.
So then, what's good
about the photo delegates?
Well, it's a single
set of callbacks.
Again, per photo settings.
The ordering is documented.
You know exactly which
callbacks you're going to get
and at what time
and in what order.
And it's a vehicle for resolving
indeterminate settings.
That one I think I need to
explain a little bit more.
Let's say your app requests
the photo right here
on this timeline.
You've specified photo
settings with auto flash
and auto still image
stabilization.
I shortened still image
stabilization to SIS
so it would fit on
the slide better.
You're telling the PhotoOutput
I want you to use flash or SIS
but only if you need to, only
if they're appropriate
for the scene.
So very soon after
you make the request,
the PhotoOutput calls your
delegates first callback,
which is willBegin
CaptureFor ResolvedSettings.
This callback is always,
always, always called first.
It's sort of like the
courtesy email you get
from Apple saying we've
received your order.
Here's what we'll
be sending you.
The callback passes
you an instance
of a new object called
AVCapturePhotoResolvedSettings.
It's just like the photo
settings you filled out,
except now everything
is resolved.
They have the same unique ID.
Your unresolved version
and resolved version
share a unique ID,
so you compare them together.
It also tells you what features
the photo output picked for you.
So notice, in this case,
flash has been resolved to on
and SIS has been
resolved to off.
So clearly we're in a
very low light situation
such as this conference room.
Next comes willCapture
PhotoFor ResolvedSettings.
It's delivered right when
the photo is being taken,
or like when the virtual
camera shudder is closing
and the shudder sound
is being played.
If you want to perform some
sort of a shudder animation,
this is the appropriate
time to do it.
And then shortly thereafter
comes didCapture PhotoFor
ResolvedSettings, just after
the image has been fully exposed
and read out, and the
virtual shudder opens.
Then some time has to pass
because the image
is being processed,
applying all the features
that you asked for.
And when the photo
is finally ready,
you get the
didProcessingPhotoSampleBuffer
callback, along with an
ImageSampleBuffer you've been
waiting for.
So, yay. It's like getting the
shiny new MAC on your doorstep.
And finally, you get
the didFinish CaptureFor
ResolvedSettings callback,
which is guaranteed
to be delivered last.
It's like the follow-up
email that you get
from Apple saying all your
packages have been delivered.
A pleasure doing business
with you over and out.
This is a good time to clean up
any of your per-photo storage.
So let's talk about those
delegates in specifics.
The callbacks track a single
photo capture request.
The photo output holds a weak
reference to your delegate,
so it will not keep that
object alive for you.
Remember to keep a strong
reference to it in your code.
All the callbacks in this
protocol are marked optional,
but some of them become
required at runtime,
depending on your
photo settings.
For instance, when you're
capturing a compressed run
compressed photo,
your delegate has
to implement the one callback
where you get the photo.
Otherwise, we would have
nowhere to deliver it.
The rules are clearly spelled
out in the
AVCapturePhotoOutput.h
headerDoc.
All callbacks pass an instance
of that nice
ResolvedPhotoSettingsObject I
talked to you about.
So you always know what you're
about to get or what
you just got.
So speaking of settings, let's
look at some code showing how
to initiate photo captures
with various
AVCapturePhotoSettings features.
Okay, the first one,
takeHighResolutionPhoto,
as I said before, the
front facing camera
on iPhone 6s supports
five-megapixel high resolution
selfies, but it can't
stream at five megapixels.
It can only do individual
high res stills.
So you have to create
a PhotoSettingsObject,
opting in for the HighResolution
Photo CaptureEnabled.
This gives you the
default constructor,
AVCapturePhotoSettings,
with friends.
And then, by default, it sets
the output format to JPEG
and opts you in for still
image stabilization.
I then set
isHighResolutionPhotoEnabled
to true and then
call CapturePhoto.
In the second example,
takeFlashPhoto.
Notice that the flashMode
is now a property
of the settings object.
If you've worked with
StillImageOutput in the past,
you'll know that Flash was
part of the AVCapture device,
so we had a problem
there that you had
to access two different objects
in order to set settings.
Here, it's all part of
one single atomic object.
Nice. The final sample here
uses a more complex constructor
of AVCapturePhotoSettings.
This time we're going to pass
the output format that we want.
In this case, we want an
uncompressed BGRA format.
So we make a dictionary of
CV pixel buffer attributes
and then pass it
as the parameter
AVCapturePhotoSettings,
and we're good to go.
Now when you call capturePhoto,
AVCapturePhotoOutput will
validate your settings
and make sure you haven't
asked for crazy stuff.
It'll ensure self-consistency,
and it'll ensure that the stuff
that you've asked for
is actually supported.
And if it's not, it
will throw an exception.
Result settings, as you might
expect, are entirely immutable.
All the properties
are read-only.
They're purely for
your information.
Again, this is the functional
programming immutable part.
It has a unique ID
that you compare
with the unresolved settings
object that you have.
This is kind of a nice feature.
It tells you the dimensions
of the photo you're going
to get before you get it.
So you can plan, do
some allocations,
whatever you need to do.
It tells you whether it was
resolved to flash on or off.
And still image stabilization
on or off.
It also supports
bracketed capture.
It's a specialized
type of capture
where you request
a number of images,
sometimes with differing
exposure values.
This might be done, for
instance, if you wanted
to fuse differently
exposed images together
to produce an effect
such as an HDR effect.
I spoke at length
about these kinds
of captures in 2014 Session 508.
Go check that video
out for a refresher.
As with
AVCaptureStillImageOutput,
we support auto exposure
brackets
and custom exposure brackets.
But the new way to request
a bracketed capture is
to instantiate an
AVCapturePhotoBracketSettings.
So it's like the photo
settings but it's a subclass,
and it has the extra
stuff that you would need
for doing a bracketed capture.
When you create one of
these you specify an array
of AVCapture BracketedStill
ImageSettings.
This is an existing object
from the
AVCaptureStillImageOutput days.
You specify one of
these per exposure.
For instance, -2EV, +2EV, 0EV.
Also, if you're on
an iPhone 6+ or 6s+,
you can optionally enable
lens stabilization using the
isLensStabilizationEnabled
property.
So you recall the
timeline I just showed you
on the previous slide, where
the photo was delivered
to didFinish ProcessingPhoto
SampleBuffer callback.
When you request a bracket
of say three images,
that callback is going
to be called three times.
Once per image.
And the fifth parameter
tells you
which particular
bracket settings
in this image request
this corresponds to.
Okay. So we like the new
AVCapturePhotoOutput so much
that we want you to move
over to it right away.
And so we're deprecating in iOS
10 the AVCaptureStillImageOutput
and all of the flash-related
properties of AVCaptureDevice,
and instead, this is
what you should use.
Like I said, there are parts
of flash capture that are part
and parcel to the
photo settings and so,
it's a much better
programming interface.
Move over as soon as you can.
The last item is -- let's talk
about the photo benefits
before we move on.
They're good for
easier bookkeeping.
Immediate settings resolution.
Confident request tracking.
And it's good for Apple.
It's good for us because
it's an expandable palette
of callbacks for us.
We can add new ways to
call you back in the future
and that last little bit is
important to the next feature
that I'm going to talk
about, which is Live Photos.
So Apple.com has a
great little blurb
on Live Photos and
what they are.
It says, "A still photo captures
an instant frozen in time.
With Live Photos, you
can turn those instants
into unforgettable
living memories."
The beautiful thing about Live
Photos is that they appreciate
in value the further
you get from the memory.
So, in this picture, this
is a great still image
in and of itself.
Huge disgusting sand crabs my
nephew dug up on the beach.
A great photo.
But if I 3D touch it --
[ Inaudible ]
Okay. So now I remember.
It was a freezing day.
He'd never been in the ocean
before and his lips were blue.
He'd been in for too long
and his hands were shaking.
And I also hear my brother's
voice speaking at the beginning.
So all of these things
aid in memory recall
because I have more
senses being activated.
Then there are people
finding inventive ways
to use Live Photos as an
artistic medium unto itself.
This shot is a twist
on the selfie.
Our camera products team calls
this The Doughnut Selfie.
A high degree of
difficulty to do it well.
Also popular is the
spinning swivel chair selfie
with Live Photo.
Try that one out.
I'm a big fan of the
surprise reveal live photo,
but unfortunately,
my kids are too.
A three-second window
is just way too tempting
for my natural-borne
photobombers.
So Live Photos began life
as a thought experiment
from Apple's design studio.
The premise was, even though
we've got these remarkable
screens now for sharing
and viewing content,
the photo experience itself has
remained static for 150 years.
JPEGs that we swipe through
on the screen are just digital
versions of the chemicals
on paper that we leaf
through in our shoeboxes.
And yet, it's the primary way
that people store
their memories.
So isn't there something
better that we can do?
And after a lot of
experimentation and prototyping,
we converged on what this
new media experience is.
A moment or a memory.
Well, first of all and
foremost it is a still photo.
It's still as good
quality as before.
It's a 12-megapixel JPEG
full resolution still image,
and it has the same
quality as non-Live Photos.
Let me emphasize that again.
Live Photos get all
the great secret sauce
that Apple's non-Live Photos do,
so you are not sacrificing
anything by turning it on.
Also a big deal was the idea
of frictionless capture.
That means there's
nothing new to learn.
You take photos the same
way you always have.
Still the same spontaneous
frame the shot, push a button,
nothing additional
to think about.
A Live Photo is also
a memory, though.
It has to engage more senses
than the static image.
It has to aid in memory recall.
So it's nominally a short
movie, a three-second movie
with 1.5 seconds coming before
the still and 1.5 coming
after the still, and we take it
at about screen resolution
or targeting 1080p.
And it includes audio.
And we're constantly
improving on the design.
In iOS 9.1, we added
this great feature
of automatically
trimming Live Photos
in case you did a sweeping
movement towards your shoes
or your pockets.
So now we'll auto trim them
and get rid of the parts
that you don't want
see in the movie.
New in iOS 10, we've
made it even better.
Now all of the Live Photo
movies are stabilized.
Also new in iOS 10,
interruption-free
music during captures.
So if you happen
to be playing --
[ Applause ]
Yeah. That's a good one.
I like that one, too.
So in order to be both
a moment and a memory,
a Live Photo consists of two
assets, as you would expect.
JPEG file, QuickTime Movie file.
These two assets
share a common UUID
that uniquely pairs
them together.
The JPEG file's UUID is stored
within the Apple Maker
Note of the [inaudible].
And the movie asset
is, like I said,
nominally three seconds
long, has a video track,
roughly 1080p, with a
forward by 3 aspect ratio.
It contains a timed metadata
track with one single sample
in it that corresponds to the
exact time of the still photo
within the movie's timeline.
It also contains a piece
of top level movie metadata
that pairs it with
the JPEG's metadata
and that's called the
QuickTime content identifier.
And its value is a
UUID-style stream.
Okay. So what do you have to
do to capture Live Photos?
In AVCapturePhotoOutput,
there is a property called
isLivePhotoCaptureSupported?
You have to make
sure it's supported.
It's not supported
on all devices.
And currently it's
only supported
when you're using
the preset photo.
You opt in for it using
AVCapture PhotoOutput.isLive
PhotoCaptureEnabled,
setting it to true.
You have to opt in for it before
you start the session running.
Otherwise, it will cause a
disruptive reconfiguration
of the session, and
you don't want that.
Also if you want audio in
your Live Photo movies,
you have to add an
AVCaptureDeviceInput
for the microphone.
Very important.
Don't forget to do that.
Also not supported is
simultaneous recording
of regular movies using
AVCaptureMovieOutput
and Live Photos at
the same time.
So if you have a
movie file output
in your session's topology, it
will disable LivePhotoCapture.
You configure a LivePhotoCapture
the usual way.
It's got the default
constructors you would expect,
but additionally you specify a
URL, a LivePhotoMovieFileURL.
This is where you want
us to write the movie to.
And it has to be
in your sandbox,
and it has to be
accessible to you.
You're not required to specify
any livePhotoMovieMetadata
but you can if you'd like to.
Here I gave an example of
using the author metadata.
And I set myself as the author,
so that the world will
know that it's my movie.
But you could also
do interesting stuff
like add GPS tagging
to your movie.
So now let's talk about Live
Photo-related delegate methods.
Like I said, we have
this expandable palette
of delegate callbacks,
and we're going to use it.
When capturing a Live Photo,
your first callback
lets you know
that a Live Photo
will be recorded,
by telling you the movie's
resolved dimensions.
See that? Now, in addition
to just the photo dimensions,
you also know what dimensions
the Live Photo is going to be.
You receive the expected
callbacks,
including a JPEG being delivered
to you in memory as before.
But now we're going to
give you some new ones.
A Live Photo movie is
nominally three seconds
with a still image
right in the middle.
So that means up to 1.5 seconds
after your capture request,
you're going to receive
a new callback.
And this one has a strange name,
didFinishRecording
LivePhotoMovieFor
EventualFileAtURL.
Try to parse that.
It means the file hasn't been
written yet but all the samples
that need to be collected
for the movie are
done being collected.
In other words, if you have a
Live Photo badge up in your UI,
this is an appropriate
time to take it down.
Let people know that they don't
need to hold still anymore.
A good time to dismiss
the Live Photo badge.
And soon after, the movie file
will be finished being written.
And you'll get the
didFinishProcessing
LivePhotoTo MovieFileAtURL.
That is a required callback,
if you're doing Live Photos.
And now the movie's
ready to be consumed.
Lastly you get the
thumbs up, all done.
We've delivered everything
that we're going to.
So note that the JPEG portion
of the LivePhotoCapture is
delivered in the same way
as static still photos.
It comes as a sample
buffer in memory,
using didFinishing
ProcessingPhoto SampleBuffer
callback, as we've already seen.
If you want to write this
to disk, it's a trivial job.
We have a class method
in AVCapturePhotoOutput
for rewriting JPEGs as a
Data, that's with a capital D,
that's suitable for writing
to a JPEG file on disk.
And you can see it
in action here.
I'm going to gloss over
the second parameter
to that function, the
previewPhotoSampleBuffer.
We'll discuss it
in a little while.
So here's a suggestion for you
when you're doing Live Photos.
LivePhotoCapture is an
example of the kind of capture
that delivers multiple assets.
Sort of like a multi-order,
where you're going
to get the computer in one
order, and you're going
to get the dongle
in another order.
So when it delivers multiple
assets, we have found it handy,
in our own test apps
that we've written,
to instantiate a new
AVCapturePhotoDelegate object
for each photo request
in this situation.
So then, within that
object, you can aggregate all
of the things that
you're getting.
The sample buffer, the movie,
et cetera, for this request.
And then, there's a convenient
place to dispose of that object
when you get the
thumbs up callback,
saying that we're done.
That's just a helpful tip there.
Once your assets have
been written to disk,
there are still several more
steps that you need to take
to get the full live
photo experience.
Though the video complement
is a standard QuickTime movie,
it's not meant to be
played start to finish
with an AV Player like
you would a regular movie.
There's a special recipe
for playing it back.
It's supposed to ease in and out
of the photo still image time.
When you swipe between
them, these particular kinds
of assets have a little bit
of movement in the photos app.
So to get the full Live
Photo playback experience,
you need to use the photos
and photos UI frameworks.
And there are classes
relating to Live Photo,
to ingest your RAW assets
into the photo library
and properly play them
back, for instance,
with the LivePhotoView.
And new in iOS 10,
photos framework lets you
edit Live Photo content just
as you would a still
photo, and that's great news
and I'd like to demo it.
Okay. So we have a bit of sample
code here, the venerable AVCam,
which has been out
for five years,
but now we have spruced it up,
so that it has a specific
photo mode and a movie mode.
That's because you can only
do Live Photos in photo mode.
And notice it's got some badging
at the top that tells you
that Live Photo mode
is on or off.
And you can switch cameras.
I'm going to try to do the
difficult doughnut selfie.
Let's see how successful I am.
So you have to start and
then take it somewhere
in the middle and then finish.
So notice, while I was doing
that, there was a live badge
that came up, and that's
using the callbacks
that I talked to
you about earlier.
So here it is.
It was written to the
Photos Library and --
then take it somewhere in
the middle -- nice, right?
But that's not all we
can do with it now.
In iOS 9, when you tried
to edit a Live Photo,
you would lose the
movie portion of it.
But now we can either, in the
photos app natively or with code
that you provide in your app,
such as this little sample
called LivePhotoEditor
that I've included as a
photo editing extension,
I can apply a simple
filter or trim the movie.
This just does a
really simple thing
of applying a tonal filter,
but notice it didn't
get rid of the movie.
I can still play it --
and then take it somewhere
in the middle -- so, nice.
You can now edit
your Live Photos.
[ Applause ]
All right.
AVCam. Now, like I
said, has separate video
and photo recording modes,
so you get the best
photo experience.
You get the best
movie-making experience.
And it shows the proper
live badging technique
that I was talking about.
It also shows you how to
write it to the Assets Library
and that sample code
is available right now.
If you go to our sessions'
page, you'll find it.
It was even Swiftified.
If you want to know more
about Live Photo editing,
please come to session
505 on Thursday at 11.
You'll hear all about it.
Okay. We also support
a feature called
LivePhotoCaptureSuspension.
Here's a quick example of
when this might be useful.
Let's say you have an
app that takes pictures
and makes obnoxious
foghorn sounds.
Okay, just go with
me on this one.
It takes pictures.
Makes obnoxious foghorn sounds.
Now let's say that
on a timeline,
your user takes a
Live Photo here
and then they play an
obnoxious foghorn sound here.
And then after it's done
playing they take another Live
Photo there.
So this is a problem because
since the movie portions
of photos one and two overlap
with the obnoxious
foghorn sound,
you have now ruined
two Live Photo movies.
You're going to hear the end
of the foghorn in one of them
and the beginning of the
foghorn in the other.
That's no good.
So to cope with this problem,
you can set
isLivePhotoCaptureSuspended
to true, just before you
do your obnoxious thing.
And that will cause any
Live Photos in progress
to abruptly be trimmed
right to that point.
And you can do the same thing
by setting
isLivePhotoCaptureSuspended
to false, and that will
cause a nice clean break
on the endpoint, so
that no content earlier
than that point will appear in
your movies when you unsuspend.
A nice little feature.
So let's talk about support.
Where do we support
LivePhotoCapture?
We support it on all the recent
iOS devices, and the easy way
to remember it is every device
that has a 12-megapixel camera,
that's where we support
Live Photos.
All right, onto our next
major feature of the day
and that's RAW Photo Capture.
So to explain what RAW
images are, I need to start
with a very high level overview
of how CMOS sensors work.
CMOS sensors collect
photons of light
through two-dimensional
arrays of detectors.
The top layer of the array is
called a color filter array
and as light passes
through from the top,
it only allows one color
component through, either red,
green or blue, in
a Bayer pattern.
Green is twice as prevalent in
this little checkerboard here
because our eyes are twice
as sensitive to green light
as they are to the other colors.
The bottom layer here is
known as the sensor array.
Now what actually gets stored
in a RAW file is the intensity
of the amount of either
red, green or blue light
that hit the sensor through each
of those detectors also needs
to be stored that Bayer pattern.
In other words, the arrangement
of reds, greens and blues,
so that later on it
can be demosaiced.
You have to store a lot
of other metadata too
about color information,
exposure information.
And so RAW converters
have a really hard job.
A RAW converter that basically
takes all of this stuff
and turns it into an RGB image.
Demosaicing is just
the tip of the iceberg.
A lot of stuff needs to
happen before it can be
presented onscreen.
So to draw an analogy,
storing a RAW file is a lot
like storing the ingredients
to bake a cake, okay?
And then you have to
carry the ingredients
around with you wherever you go.
It's kind of heavy.
It's kind of awkward.
It takes some time to
bake it every time.
If you ask two different bakers
to bake the cake using
the same ingredients,
you might get a slightly
different tasting cake.
But there are also some
huge advantages to RAW.
First and foremost, you have
bake-time flexibility, right?
So you're carrying
the ingredients around
but you can make a
better cake next year.
There's no compression involved
like there would
be in BGRA or 420.
You have more bits to work with.
It's a 10-bit sensor
RAW packaged
in 14 bits per pixel
instead of eight.
Also, you have lots of
headroom for editing.
And some greater
artistic freedom
to make different
decisions in post.
So basically you're just
deferring the baking
until later.
Okay? Now what's JPEG?
RAW images offer many benefits
but they're not the
be-all-end-all of existence.
It's important to understand
that there are tradeoffs
involved when you choose RAW
and that JPEGs are still
a very attractive option.
JPEGs are the cake, the lovingly
baked Apple cake, just for you,
and it's a pretty good cake.
It's got all of the
Apple goodness in it.
Much faster rendering.
You don't have to carry as
many ingredients around.
You also get some secret
sauce, like stabilization.
As I mentioned, we use multiple
image fusion for stabilization.
You can't get that with
a single RAW image,
no matter how good it is,
because we're taking --
I guess it's kind of
like a multilayer cake.
Okay? So yeah, you can't do
that with a single image.
Also you get smaller file size.
So all of these things make JPEG
a really attractive alternative
and you should decide
which one you want to use,
which is better for your app.
We identify RAW formats
using four-character codes,
just like we do for
regular pixel formats
in the Core Video framework.
We've added four new
constants to CVPixelBuffer.h
to describe the four
different Bayer patterns
that you'll encounter
on our cameras,
and they're listed there.
Basically they describe
the order of the reds,
greens and blues in
the checkerboard.
How do you capture RAW
with AVCapturePhotoOutput?
It's pretty simple.
RAW is only supported when
using the photo format,
the preset photo,
same as Live Photo.
It's only supported
on the rear camera.
And we do support RAW brackets,
so you can take a bracket
of three RAW images,
for instance.
To request a RAW capture,
you create an
AVCapturePhotoSettings object
but surprise, surprise,
there's a different instructor.
This one takes a
RAW pixel format.
So how do you decide which
RAW format you should ask it
to deliver to you?
Well you can ask the
PhotoOutput itself.
It'll tell you here are my
available RAW photo pixel
formats, and you can
select one of those.
The RAW format you specify has
to be supported by the hardware.
Now also important is that
in these RAW settings,
SIS has no meaning because
it's not a multiple image
fusion scenario.
So autoStillImage
StabilizationEnabled has
to be set to no or it
will throw an exception.
And also
highResolutionPhotoEnabled is
meaningless because you're
just getting the sense of RAW,
so it also must be set to false.
There's a separate
delegate callback
for RAW photos called didFinish
ProcessingRAW PhotoSampleBuffer.
And if you are really sharp-eyed
and really fast, you'll notice
that it has exactly
the same parameters
as the previous callback,
where you get the regular kind
of image, the didFinish
ProcessingRAW
PhotoSampleBuffer callback.
So now you might ask yourself
why did we bother making a whole
new delegate callback
for RAW sample buffers
if it has the same exact
parameters as the other one?
There's a good reason, and that
reason is RAW plus processed
image support.
So we do support, just
like on DSLR cameras,
mirrorless cameras, a workflow
where you can get both RAW
and JPEG simultaneously.
That's what I mean
by processed image.
The ability to shoot
RAW and JPEG is kind
of a professional feature,
kind of a big deal.
So you can get RAW
plus a processed image.
It doesn't have to be a
JPEG, it could be BGRA, 420.
The processed image is
delivered to the other callback,
the didFinish ProcessingPhoto
SampleBuffer callback,
and the RAW is delivered to
the one with RAW in the name.
RAW plus processed
brackets are supported,
so see if you can wrap
your head around that.
That would be --
I'm doing a bracket
and I'm asking for
RAW plus JPEG.
So if I'm doing a
bracket of three,
I'm going to get three
RAWs and three JPEGs.
RAW plus still image
stabilization,
though, is not supported.
Okay, so to capture RAW plus
JPEG, as you might expect,
there's yet another constructor
of AVCapturePhotoSettings.
In this one, you specify
both the RAW pixel format
and the processed
format that you want.
Here I'm choosing JPEG as the
output format and a RAW format.
Now when you select JPEGPlusRAW,
HighResolutionPhotoEnabled
does mean something.
Because now it's
applying to the JPEG.
All right.
Let's talk about
storing RAW buffers.
They're not that useful
if all you can do is
work with them in memory.
So rather than introduce an
Apple proprietary RAW file
format, like so many other
camera vendors do, we've elected
to use Adobe's digital
negative format for storage.
DNG is a standard way of just
storing bits and metadata.
It doesn't imply a file
format in any other way.
So going back to our cake-baking
analogy, a DNG is just
like a standard box for
holding ingredients.
It's still up to individual
RAW converters to decide how
to interpret those ingredients.
So DNGs opened by one third
party app might look different
than DNGs opened
in a different app.
So storing in DNG
is pretty trivial.
You just call the class function
dngPhotoDataRepresentation,
passing the RAW buffer
you received
in the delegate callback.
This creates a capital
D Data in memory
that can be written to file.
And this API always writes
[inaudible] compressed DNG files
to save space.
All right.
I feel a demo coming on.
Okay. So for RAW capture, we've
updated another venerable piece
of sample code and
that's AVCamManual.
We released this one in 2014,
when we showed off our
manual control APIs.
So it lets you choose focus,
exposure, white balance,
and you can manually
or auto control those.
And then there's a new thing
in the HUD on the left side
that lets you select
either RAW off or on.
So you can choose to shoot
RAW photos in this app.
Let's go to exposure.
Let me see if I can purposely
overexpose a little bit,
and then I'll take a photo.
And now I'm going
to leave the app.
I'm going to go to an
app called RAWExpose.
Now this was not written
by the AV Foundation Team.
This was written by
the Core Image Team,
but they graciously let
me borrow it for my demo.
And we'll go down and we can see
the picture that we just took.
Now this one is a RAW.
It's reading the DNG file.
And we can do things with
it that we could never do
with the JPEGs, like we restore
the EV to a more same value.
We can adjust the
temperature and tint.
All of these things
are being done in post
and are completely reversible.
You can also look and see
what it looks like with
or without noise reduction.
So all of these are part
of a new Core image
API for editing RAW.
Okay, let's go back to slides.
The AVCamManual sample code
is available right now.
You can go get it.
It's associated with
this session's slides.
And also, if you want to
learn more about RAW editing,
you need to come to that
same session as I talked
about before, session 505, where
they talk about both of these.
The second part is RAW
Processing with Core Image.
It's a great session.
Where is RAW photo
capture supported?
By happy coincidence, it's
exactly the same products
as where we support Live Photos.
So anything with a
12-megapixel camera is
where you can do RAW photos.
Onto our next topic, which
is capturing preview images,
also known as thumbnails.
Photography apps commonly
take pictures and want
to quickly show a
preview of the results,
such as Apple Zone camera app.
So take a look in the bottom
left while this is playing.
And you see, as soon as it
hits the shutter button,
almost instantaneously
you have a preview
in the image well
on the bottom left.
That's good.
That's comforting to
your users to know
that what they did just worked.
It gives them instant feedback.
Also a number of image
processing algorithms
such as Core Images,
CI Rectangle Detector
or CI QR Code Detector work
better with smaller images,
smaller uncompressed images.
They don't need the full
12-megapixel JPEG to find faces.
Unfortunately there is an
inherit impedance mismatch here.
You request a high-quality JPEG
because that's what you
want to store on disk.
That's what you want to
survive, but you also want
to get a preview on
screen really fast.
So if you have to do
that work yourself,
you're decompressing the JPEG.
You're downscaling it.
And finally displaying it.
All of this takes time
and buffer copies
and added complexity.
Nicer would be to get both the
high-quality JPEG for storage
and if the camera could give
you a smaller version of it,
directly from the camera, not
decompressed from the JPEG.
Then you could skip all those
steps and go straight to display
with the preview image.
And this is exactly the
workflow that we support
in AVCapturePhotoOutput.
The delegate --
[ Applause ]
I'll pander.
The delegate callback can
deliver a preview image along
with the processed or RAW image.
The preview is uncompressed,
so it's 420fv
or BGRA, you're choice.
If you know the size you want,
you can specify the
dimensions that you want.
Or if you're not sure what
a good preview size would be
for this current platform,
the PhotoOutput can pick a
good default size for you.
Here's some sample code showing
how to request a preview image.
After creating a photo
settings instance in one
of the usual ways, you can
select a previewPixelType.
Again, the photo settings
themselves can tell you
which formats are
available, and they are sorted
so that the most
optimal one is first.
So here, I'm getting the very
first one from the array.
And when I say optimal,
I mean the one
that requires the
fewest conversions
from the native camera.
You create a CVPixelBuffer
attributes dictionary
with that format type key, and
that first part is required.
So if you want preview images,
you have to at least specify
the format that you want.
Optionally, you can also
specify a width and a height,
if you want to custom size.
And you don't need to know
exactly the aspect ratio
of the image that
you're getting.
Here I just specified
160 by 160.
I don't really expect to get
a box out, but I'm using those
as the max for both
width and height.
And AVCapturePhotoOutput
will do the job
of resizing the preview image
so that it fits in the box,
preserving aspect ratio.
Retrieving preview images is
also very straightforward.
Here we've requested a JPEG plus
a preview image at 160 by 160.
So when we get our first
callback saying we've received
your order, you get a willBegin
CaptureFor ResolvedSettings
and a ResolvedPhotoSettings
object which, if you notice,
the previewPhotoDimensions
are not 160 by 160.
They're 160 by 120
because it's been resolved
to something that's
aspect ratio appropriate
for the 12-megapixel
photo that you want.
When the didFinish
ProcessingPhoto SampleBuffer
callback finally comes, you
get not one but two images.
The full-sized JPEG is
the first parameter,
and the previewPhotoSampleBuffer
is the second.
So if you're following
along here
and adding things
up in your mind.
If you do a RAW plus bracket
plus JPEG plus preview image,
then you're going to get mRAWs,
mJPEGs and mpreview images.
Another great use of
the preview image is
as an embedded thumbnail in your
high-quality JPEG or DNG files.
In this code sample, I'm using
the previewPhotoSampleBuffer
parameter of my didFinish
ProcessingRAW PhotoSampleBuffer
callback as an embedded
thumbnail to the DNG file.
So when I call PhotoOutput's
dngPhotoDataRepresentation,
I'm passing that as
the second parameter.
You should always do this, okay?
Embedding a thumbnail
image is always a good idea
because you don't know where
it's going to be viewed.
Some apps can handle
looking at the DNG bits,
the RAW bits, and some can't.
But if you have an
embedded thumbnail in there,
everyone's going to be
able to look at something.
You definitely want to do
it if you're adding a DNG
to the Photo Library so
that it can give you a nice
quick preview.
Preview image delivery
is supported everywhere.
All right, onto the last topic
of the day, which is wide color.
And as you might suspect,
it's a wide topic.
You've no doubt heard about the
beautiful new true toned display
on our iPad Pro 9.7 inch.
It's a wide-gamut
display and it's on par
with the 4K and 5K iMax.
It's capable of displaying
strikingly vivid reds
and yellows and deeply
saturated cyans and greens.
To take advantage of the
display's extended color range,
we introduced color management
for the first time in iOS 9.3.
I'm not sure if you
were aware of that,
but we're now color managed
for the iPad Pro 9.7.
And with displays this
pretty, it only makes sense
to also capture photos
with equally wide color
so that we enhance the
viewing experience.
And so that when you look at
those several years from now,
you've got more color
information.
Beginning in iOS
10, photo captures
on the iPad Pro 9.7 will
magically become wide
color captures.
Let me give you a brief overview
of what wide color means,
wide color terminology, starting
with the concept
of a color space.
A color space describes
an environment
in which colors are represented,
ordered, compared, or computed.
And the most common
color space used
in computer displays is sRGB.
The s stands for
standards, so standard RGB.
It's based on an
international spec ITU 709.
It has a gamma of roughly
2.2 and a white point
of 6500 degrees Kelvin.
sRGB does a really good job of
representing many common colors,
like faces, sky, grass,
but there are many colors
that sRGB does not
reproduce very well.
For instance, more than 40%
of pro football jerseys are
outside of the sRBG gamut.
Who knew? The iPad Pro 9.7
supports wide color using a new
color space that
we call Display P3.
It's similar to the
SMPTE standard DCI P3.
That's a color space that's used
in digital cinema projectors.
The color primaries are the same
as DCI P3, but then it differs
in gamma and white point.
The gamma and white point
are identical to sRGBs.
Why would we do that?
The reason for that is that the
DCI P3 white point is slanted
toward the green side.
It was chosen to
maximize brightness
in dark home theater
situations and we found
that with the white
point at 6500,
we get a more compatible
superset of the sRGB standard.
So here on this slide you
can see, in gray, the sRGB
and then you can
see, super-imposed
around it, the Display P3.
And it does a nice job of kind
of broadly covering
the superset of sRGB.
And that's why we chose it.
Using Apple's color
sync utility on OS 10,
you can see a visual
representation of Display P3.
So I took a little screen
capture here to show you.
You can compare it with
sRGB in three dimensions.
So here I'm selecting
Display P3,
and then I do the hold
for comparison thing.
That's a neat trick.
And then I select sRGB.
And then I see the one
super-imposed on top
of the other, so you can see
sRGB inside and Display P3
on the outside, and
you get a feel
for just how wide the Display
P3 is compared to sRGB.
And the range of representable
colors is visibly bigger.
So now let's get down
to the nuts and bolts
of capturing Display P3 content.
For highest fidelity, the color
space of capture content has
to be determined at the source.
That's not something that
can flow down in sRGB
and then be up-converted
to the wide.
It has to start wide.
So, as you might expect,
the color space is
fundamentally a property
of the AVCaptureDevice,
the source.
So we're going to
spend some time talking
about the AVCaptureDevice
and we're also going to talk
about the AVCaptureSession.
The session is where automatic
wide color selection can be
determined for the whole session
configuration as a whole.
Okay. AVCaptureDevice is how AV
Foundation represents a camera
or a mic.
Each AVCaptureDevice
has a format property.
Formats is an array of
AVCaptureDevice formats.
They are objects themselves,
and they represent the formats
that the device can capture in.
They come in pairs,
as you see here.
For each resolution
and frame rate,
there's a 402v version
and a 420f.
That stands for v for
video range, 16 to 235
or f for full range,
the 0 to 255.
So new in iOS 10,
AVCaptureDevice formats
have a new supported color
spaces property.
It's an array of numbers
with the possible values of 0
for sRGB or 1 for P3 D65.
We refer to it as Display P3
but in the API, it's referred
to as P3 D65, the d
standing for display and 65
for the 6500 Kelvin white point.
On an iPad Pro 9.7, the 420v
formats only support sRGB.
But the full-range 420f
formats support either sRGB
or Display P3.
The device has a settable
active format property.
That's not new.
So that one of the formats
in the list is always
the activeFormat.
As you can see here,
I've put a yellow box
around the one that is active.
It happens to be the
12-megapixel 30 FPS version.
And if that activeFormat,
the f format,
happens to support Display P3,
then there's a new property
that you can set
called activeColorSpace.
And if the activeFormat supports
it, you get wide color flowing
from your source to all
outputs in the session.
That was longwinded, but what
I wanted you to take home
from this is hopefully you
don't have to do any of this.
Most clients will never need
to set the activeColorSpace
directly and that's
because AVCaptureSession
will try to do it
for you automatically.
So in iOS 10, AVCaptureSession
has a new property that's long,
automaticallyConfigures
CaptureDeviceForWideColor.
When does it want to
choose wide color for you?
Wide color, in iOS 10,
is only for photography.
Let me say that again.
Wide color, in iOS 10, is only
for photography, not for video.
I'll explain why in a minute.
It can automatically,
the session can automatically
choose whether
to configure the whole session
configuration for wide color.
It will set the activeColorSpace
of your device on your behalf
to P3, depending on your config.
You have to have a PhotoOutput
in your session for
this to happen.
If you don't have a PhotoOutput,
you're obviously not
doing photography,
so you don't need wide color.
There are some caveats here.
Like, if you start adding
other outputs to your session,
maybe it's not as clear
what you're trying to do.
If you add an
AVCaptureVideoPreviewLayer,
the session will automatically
still pick Display P3 for you
because you're just previewing
and also doing photography.
If you have a MovieFileOutput
and a PhotoOutput,
now it's ambiguous.
You might really care
more about movies,
so it will not automatically
pick Display P3 for you.
VideoDataOutput is a special
case where we deliver buffers
to you via a callback and there,
the session will
only pick Display P3
if you're using the
photo preset.
It's pretty sure if you're
doing that that you mean
to do photography stuff
with those display buffers.
If you really, really want to,
you can force the capture device
to do wide color and here's how.
First you would tell the
session stop automatically doing
that thing for me.
Get out of my way.
And then you would
go to the device
and set the active
format yourself
to a format that's
supports wide color.
And then you would set the
activeColorSpace to P3.
Once you do this, wide color
buffers will flow to all outputs
that accept video data.
That includes VideoDataOutput,
MovieFileOutput,
even the deprecated
AVCaptureStillImageOutput.
So while you can forcibly set
the device's activeColorSpace
to display P3, I want
to strongly caution you
against doing it
unless you really,
really know what you're doing.
The reason is wide
color is for photos
because we have a good photo
ecosystem story for wide color,
not so much for video.
So the main worry with
Display P3 content is
that the consumer has
to be wide color-aware
or your content will
be rendered as sRGB,
and the colors will
all look wrong.
They'll be rendered badly.
Most video playback
services are not color-aware.
So if you store a wide Display
P3 movie and then you try
to play it back with
some service,
it will likely render
the colors wrong.
So if you do choose to do this,
make sure that your
VideoDataOutput is color-aware.
That it's propagating
the color tags.
That it's doing something
sensible.
That it's color-aware.
And if you do choose to capture
Display P3 movies using the
MovieFileOutput, just be aware
that they may render
incorrectly on other platforms.
This is -- we do allow this,
though, because we recognize
that it's important for some
pro workflows to be able
to do wide color movies as well.
So now dire warnings out
of the way, I can tell you
that we do have a very
good solution for photos
in sharing wide colors.
We should be aware that wide
color JPEGs use a Display P3
profile and consumers of
these images also need
to be color-aware.
The good news is photo services,
in general, are photo color --
they are color-aware these days.
iCloud Photo Library
is one of them.
It can intelligently convert
your images to sRGB on devices
that don't support wide color,
but store the nice wide
color in the cloud.
We're also an industry
in transition right now,
so some photo services
don't understand wide color,
but most of them at
least are smart enough
to render it as sRGB.
For mixed sharing scenarios,
like say sending a photo
via Messages or Mail.
You don't know where it's going.
It might be going
to multiple devices.
Some of them might
support wide color.
Some might not.
So for this situation, we have
added a new service called Apple
Wide Color Sharing Profile.
Your content can be
manipulated in a way
that we generate a content
specific table-based ICC profile
that's specific to
that particular JPEG.
And what's nice about it is
if it's rendered by someone
who doesn't know about
wide color, the part that's
in the sRGB gamut renders
absolutely correctly.
The extra information is carried
in the extra ICC profile
information in a way
that they can recover the
wide color information
with minimal quality loss.
You can learn more about how
to share wide color content
in sessions 505 and 712.
Both of those are on Thursday.
I've talked about the
first one three times now.
The working with wide color one
is also an excellent session.
On iPad Pro 9.7,
the AVCapturePhotoOutput
supports wide color broadly.
It supports it in 420f, BGRA
and JPEG, just not for 420v.
So if you have your session
configured to give Display P3
but then you say you
want a 420v image,
it will be converted to sRGB.
Live Photos support wide color.
Both the still and the movie.
These are special movies.
This is part of the
Apple ecosystem.
So those are just
going to be wide color.
And bracketed captures also
support wide color, too.
Here's an interesting twist.
While I've been talking
about iPad Pro, iPad Pro,
iPad Pro, we support RAW.
And RAW capture is inherently
wide color because it has all
of those extra bits
of information.
We store it in the
sensor primaries
and there is enough
color information there
to be either rendered
as wide or sRGB.
Again, you're carrying the
ingredients around with you.
You can decide later if you want
to render it as wide or sRGB.
So shooting RAW and
rendering in post,
you can produce wide
color content on lots
of iOS devices, not
just iPad Pro.
As I just said, you can learn
more on wide color, in general,
not just sharing but
all about wide color.
The best session to view is
the working with wide color one
on Thursday afternoon.
Use AVCapturePhotoOutput
for improved usability.
And we talked about four
main feature areas today.
We talked about capturing
Live Photos
in your app, RAW,
RAW + JPEG, DNG.
Nice little preview images
for faster rendering.
And wide color photos.
And believe it or not,
one hour was not enough
to cover everything
that we wanted to cover.
So we've done an
addendum to this session.
It's already recorded.
It should already be online.
It's a slide plus
voiceover thing
that we're calling a Chalk Talk.
And it tells you
about in-depth topics
that we didn't have time for.
Scene monitoring in
AVCapturePhotoOutput.
Resource preparation
and reclamation.
And then an unrelated topic,
changes to camera
privacy policy in iOS 10.
So please take a
look at that video.
It's about 20 minutes long.
More information.
All you need to remember
is the 501 at the end.
Go to that and you'll find,
I believe, seven pieces
of sample code as well
as new documentation
for AVCapturePhotoOutput.
The documentation folks
have been working very hard
and they've documented
the heck out of it.
And here are the related
sessions one more time.
The one that is the Chalk Talk,
we're calling
AVCapturePhotoOutput beyond
the basics.
And you can look at
that any time you want.
All right.
Have a great rest of the show,
and thank you for coming.
[ Applause ]