[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you so much,
and good morning.
And my name is David Hayward and
I'm here to talk to you today
about editing Live Photos
and processing RAW
images with Core Image.
We got a bunch of great
stuff to talk about today.
First I'll give a brief
introduction to Core Image
for those of you who
are new to the subject.
Then we'll be talking about
our three main subjects
for this morning.
First we'll be adjusting
RAW images on iOS.
Second, we'll be
editing Live Photos.
And third, we'll be talking
about how to extend Core Image
in a new way using
CIImageProcessor nodes.
So first, so a very brief
introduction to Core Image.
The reason for Core Image is
that it provides a very simple,
high-performance API to
apply filters to images.
The basic idea is you start with
an input image that may come
from a JPEG or a file or
memory, and you can choose
to apply a filter to it and
the result is an output image,
and it's very, very easy
to do this in your code.
All you do is you take your
image, call applyingFilter,
and specify the name of the
filter and any parameters
that are appropriate
for that filter.
It's super easy.
And, of course, you can do
much more complex things.
You can chain together multiple
filters in either sequences
or graphs and get
very complex effects.
One of the great features
of Core Image is it provides
automatic color management,
and this is very
important these days.
We now have a variety of devices
that support wide gamut input
and wide gamut output.
And what Core Image will do is
it will automatically insert the
appropriate nodes
into the render graph
so that it will match
your input image
to the Core Image working
space, and when it comes time
to display, it will match
from the working space
to the display space.
And this is something you
should be very much aware
of because wide color images
and wide color displays
are common now
and many open source libraries
for doing image processing
don't handle this automatically.
So this is a great feature of
Core Image because it takes care
of all that for you in
a very easy to use way.
Another thing to be aware of is
that each filter actually has
a little bit of code associated
with it, a small
subroutine called a kernel.
And all of our built-in filters
have these kernels and one
of the great features is if
you chain together a sequence
of filters, Core Image will
automatically concatenate these
subroutines into
a single program.
The idea behind this is
to improve performance
by reducing the -- and
quality, by reducing the number
of intermediate buffers.
Core Image has over
180 built-in filters.
They are the exact
same filters on all
of our platforms;
macOS, tvOS and iOS.
We have a few new ones this year
which I'd like to talk about.
One is a new filter
for generating hue
saturation and value gradient.
It creates a gradient
in hue and saturation,
and then you can specify, as
a parameter, the brightness
of the image and also
specify the color space
that the wheel is in.
And as you might guess, this
filter is now used on macOS
as the basis of the color
picker, which is now aware
of the different types
of display color spaces.
Another new filter we have
is CINinePartStretched
and NinePartTiled.
The idea behind this is you
might have a small asset,
like this picture frame here,
and you want to stretch it
up to fit an arbitrary size.
This filter is very easy to use.
You provide an input image and
you provide four breakpoints,
two horizontal and two vertical.
Once you've specified
those points,
you can specify the size
you want it to stretch to.
It's very easy to use.
The third new filter is
something that's also
quite interesting.
The idea is to start
with a small input image.
In this case it's an image
containing color data,
but it can also contain
parametric data.
So imagine you have a small
set of colors or parameters
and maybe it's only 6 by 7
pixels and you want to upsample
that to the full
size of an image.
The idea is to upsample
the color image,
the small color image,
but respect the edges
in the guide image.
Now, if you weren't to
respect the guide images,
if you were just to stretch the
small image up to the same size
as the full image, you'd
just get a blend of colors,
but with this filter
you can get more.
You can actually get something
that preserves the edges while
also respecting the colors.
And this is actually a
useful feature for a lot
of other types of algorithms.
In fact, in the new version
of Photos app we use this
to improve the behavior of
the light adjustment sliders.
I look forward to
seeing how you can use
that in your application.
We also have some new
performance controls this year
and do things that
improve performance
in Core Image this year.
One is we have Metal
turned on by default.
So if you use any of
our built-in 180 filters
or your own custom kernels,
all of those kernels
will be converted
to Metal on the fly for you.
It's a great way of
leveraging the power of Metal
with very little
effort on your part.
We've also made some great
improvements to a critical API,
which is creating a
UIImage from a CIImage,
and this now produces
much better performance
than it has in the past.
So you can actually use
this very efficiently
to animate an image
in a UIImage view.
Also another new feature is
that Core Image now
supports a feature that's new
to Core Graphics, which is
that Core Graphics
supports half-floats.
Let me just talk for a
second about pixel formats
because this brings up
an interesting point.
We're all familiar with the
conventional pixel format
of RGBA8 and it takes just
4 bytes per pixel to store
and has 8 bits of depth,
and can encode values
in the range of 0 to 1.
However, this format
is not great
for representing wide-colored
data because it only has 8 bits
and it's limited to the
values in the range 0 to 1.
So in the past the alternative
has been to use RGBAfloat,
which takes 16 bytes per pixel,
so four times as much memory,
but gives you all the depth and
range you could ever hope for.
Another feature of the fact
that it's using floats is
that what quantization there is,
it's distributed
logarithmically,
which is a good fit for the way
the human eye perceives color.
Well, there's a new format
which Core Image has supported
and now Core Graphics does
as well, which I refer
to as the Goldilocks pixel
format, which is RGBAh,
and this allows you to,
in just 8 bytes per pixel,
store data that is 10 bits
of depth and allows values
in the range of minus
65,000 to positive 65,000.
And again, those values are
quantized logarithmically,
so it's great to store
linear data in a way
that won't be perceived
as quantized.
So I highly recommend
this pixel format.
There's another new format
which I should mention,
which is that Core Video
supports a pixel format
with the long name
of 30RGBLittle [inaudible]
PackedWideGamut,
and this also supports 10
bits of depth, but stores it
in an only 4 bytes per pixel by
sacrificing the alpha channel.
So there's many cases where
this is useful as well
and Core Image supports
either rendering from
or to CV pixel buffers
in this format.
So now I'd like to actually talk
about the next major subject
of our discussion today,
which is adjusting RAW images
with Core Image, and
I'm really excited
to talk about this today.
We've been working on
this for a long time.
It's been a lot of hard
work and I'm really excited
about the fact that we've
brought this to iOS.
In talking about this, I'd like
to discuss what is a RAW file,
how to use the CIRAWFilter API,
some notes on supporting
wide-gamut output,
and also tips for
managing memory.
So first, what is a RAW file?
Well, the way most cameras work
is that they have two key parts;
a color filter array
and a sensor array.
And the idea is light from the
scene enters from the scene
through the color filter array
and it's counted by
the sensor array.
And this data is actually
part of a much larger image,
of course, but in order to turn
this data into a usable image,
a lot of image processing
is needed in order
to produce a pleasing
image for the user.
So I want to talk a
little bit about that.
But the main idea here is
that if you take the data
that was captured by the
sensor, that is a RAW file.
If you take the data
that was captured
after the image processing,
that's a TIFF or a JPEG.
RAW files store the
unprocessed scene data,
and JPEG files store the
processed output image.
Another way to think of it is
that the RAW file
stores the ingredients
from which you can
make an image; whereas,
a JPEG stores the
results of the ingredients
after they've been baked
into a beautiful cake.
In order to go from
the ingredients
to a final baked product,
however, there is a lot
of stages, so let me just
outline a few of those here.
First of all, we have to
extract metadata from the file
that tells us how
long to cook the cake,
to extend the metaphor.
Also, we need to decode the
RAW data from the sensor.
We need to demosaic the image to
reconstruct the full color image
from the data that was captured
with only one RGB value
per pixel location.
We need to apply geometric
distortions for lens correction.
Noise reduction, which is a
huge piece of the processing.
We need to do color matching
from the scene-referred datas
that the sensor captured
into the output-referred
data for display.
And then we need to do
things like adjust exposure
and temperature and tint.
And lastly, but very
importantly, add sharpening,
contrast and saturation to
make an image look pleasing.
That's a lot of stages.
What are some of the
advantages of RAW?
Well, one of the great things is
that the RAW file contains
linear and deep pixel data,
which is what enables
great editability.
Another feature is that RAW
image processing gets better
every year.
So with the RAW you
have the promise
that an image you took yesterday
might have better quality
when you process it next year.
Also, RAW files are
color space agnostic.
They can actually be rendered
to any target output space,
which is also a good
feature, given the variety
of displays we have today.
Also, a user can choose
to use different software
to interpret the RAW file.
Just like giving
the same ingredient
to two different chefs, you
can get two different results,
and some users might prefer
one chef over another.
That said, there are some great
advantages to JPEG as well.
First of all, because the
processing has been applied,
they are fast to
load and display.
They contain colors
and adjustments
that target a specific
output, which can be useful.
And that also gives
predictable results.
Also, it's worth mentioning that
cameras do a great job today
of producing JPEG images,
and our iOS cameras are an
especially good example of that.
So on the subject of RAW,
let me talk a little bit
about how our platforms
support RAW.
So the great news is that now
we fully support RAW on iOS
and upcoming seed
on tvOS as well.
This means we support over
400 unique camera models
from 16 different vendors.
And also, we support DNG
files such as those captured
by our own iOS devices.
The iOS devices include
the iPhone 6S, 6S Plus, SE,
and also the iPad Pro 9.7.
That is really exciting.
I recommend you all go back,
if you haven't already,
and watch the Advances
in iOS Photography,
which talks about the new
APIs that are available
to capture RAW on these devices.
Another great thing is that
we now have the same high
performance RAW pipeline
on iOS as we do on macOS,
and this is actually
quite an achievement.
I counted the other day
and looked at our pipeline
and it involves over 4,500
lines of CIKernel code
and this all works
very efficiently
and it's a great testament to
our ability and the abilities
of Core Image to be able
to handle complex
rendering situations.
Our pipeline on iOS
requires A8 devices or later,
and you can test for this in
your application by looking
for the iOS GPU Family 2.
Another note on platform
support.
We continuously add
support for new cameras
as new ones become available,
and also to improve the quality
of existing cameras
that we already support.
New cameras are added in
future software updates.
And also, we improve our
pipeline periodically as well.
And our pipelines are versions,
so you can either use our
latest version or go back
and use previous
versions if you desire.
So without further ado, I
want to give a demonstration
of how this looks in action.
So what I have here
is some sample code.
There's an early version of that
that's available for download,
and it's called RAWExposed,
and this is both an application
and this latest version is
also a photo editing extension.
So what we can do is
we can go into Photos
and actually use
this sample code.
We have three RAW images here
that are 24 megapixels each
that were taken with
a Canon 5D Mark III.
And you can see here that
this image is pretty poorly
overexposed, but one of the
great features of RAW is
that you can actually
salvage images like this.
So we can go here and edit it
and use our photo
editing extension
to edit this as a RAW file.
So now, since we're
editing this as a RAW file,
we can actually make
adjustments [inaudible].
We can adjust the
exposure up and down.
You can see we can pan
across all the 24 megapixels
and we get great results.
Once I'm happy with the
image, this looks much better
than it did before,
I can hit Done
and it will generate a new
full resolution image of that,
and now it is actually
available to see
in the Photos application.
[ Applause ]
One of the other things
that's great in RAW files is
that you can make
great adjustments
on white balance in an image.
Again, on this image
the image is fine,
but it may be a little crooked,
but also the white
balance is off.
So I'm going to go in here
and adjust the white
balance just a little bit
and I can make a much
more pleasant image.
And again, we can zoom
in and see the results.
And we can adjust
these results live.
So we hit Done and save that.
Another image I want to
show is this image here,
which is actually
a very noisy image.
I want to show you a little bit
about our noise reduction
algorithms.
Over half of our 4,500 lines
of kernel code relate
to noise reduction.
So if I go in here
and edit this one,
you can see that there's some --
hopefully at least
in the front rows,
you can see the grain
that's in this image.
One of the features we expose
in our API is the ability
to turn off our noise
reduction algorithm,
and then you can actually
see the colorful nature
of the noise that's actually
present in the RAW file.
And it's this very
challenging task
of doing the noise
reduction to make an image
that doesn't have
those colorful speckles
but still preserves
nice color edges
that are intended in the image.
So I'll save that as well.
Lastly, I want to demonstrate an
image we took earlier this week
out in the lobby, which
was taken with this iPad.
Yes, I was one of those people
taking a picture with an iPad.
[ Laughter ]
And here I want to
show you, you know,
this is an image that's
challenging in its own way
because it's got some
areas that are dark
and some areas that
are overexposed.
One thing I could do here is I
could bring down the exposure --
well, I have a highlight
slider which can allow me
to bring the highlights
in a bit.
I can also bring
down the exposure.
And now I can really see what's
going on outside the windows.
But now the shadows
are too dark,
so I can then increase those.
So this gives you an idea of the
kind of adjustments you can do
on RAW files, and
this is the benefit
of having deeper
precision on your pixel data
that you get in a RAW file.
So I'll hit Done on that.
So that's our demo
of RAW in iOS.
[ Applause ]
And a huge thanks to the team
for making this possible.
So let me talk about the API,
because it's not just enough
to provide a demo application.
We want to enable your
applications to be able
to do this in your apps as well.
So we have an API
that's referred
to as the CIRAWFilter API,
and it gives your application
some critical things.
It gives your application
a CIImage with wide-gamut,
extended range, half-float
precision math behind it.
It also gives you control
over many of the stages
in the RAW processing pipeline,
such as those that
I demonstrated.
It also provides fast
interactive performance using
the GPU on all our devices.
So how does this
work in practice?
The API is actually very simple.
You start with an input, which
is either a file URL or data,
or even in our next
seed we'll have an API
that works using CVPixelBuffer.
That is our input.
We're then going to
create an instance
of a CIRAWFilter
from that input.
At the time that filter is
instantiated it will have
default values for all the
user adjustable parameters
that you might want to
present to your user.
Once you have the
CIRAWFilter, you can then ask it
for a CIImage, and you can
do lots of things from there.
Let me just show you the code
and how simple it
is just to do this.
All we need to do
is give it a URL.
We're going to create
an instance
of the CIFilter given that URL.
Then, for example, if
we want to get the value
of the current noise
reduction amount,
we can just access the value
for key kCIInput
ImageNoiseReductionAmount.
If we want to alter
that, it's equally easy.
We just set a new
value for that key.
When we're done making changes,
we ask for the outputImage
and we're done.
That's all we need to do.
Of course, you might want
to display this image,
so typically you'll take that
image and display it either
in a UIImage view or
in a MetalKit view
or other type of view system.
In this case the user might
suggest though that, well,
maybe this image is a
little underexposed,
so in your UI you can have
adjustable sliders for exposure
and then the user can
make that adjustment.
You can then pass that in as a
new value to the CIRAWFilter.
Then you can ask for
a CIImage from that,
and then you can then
display that new image
with the exposure
slightly brighter.
And this is very easy as well.
You also might want to take your
CIImage -- at times, let's say,
you want to export your
image in the background
to produce a full-size image,
or you may be exporting several
images in the background.
So you might want to, in those
cases, either create a CGImage
for passing to other APIs, or
go directly to a JPEG or a TIFF,
and we have some easy to
use APIs for that now.
If you're going to be
doing background processing
of large files like RAWs,
we recommend you create
a CIContext explicitly
for that purpose.
Specifically, you want to
specify a context that is saved
in a singleton variable,
so there's no need
to create a new context
for every image.
This allows CI to
cache the compilation
of all the kernels
that are involved.
However, because we're going to
be rendering an image only once,
we don't need Core Image to be
able to cache intermediates,
so you can specify false there,
and that will help reduce
the memory requirements
in this situation.
Also, there's a setting
to say that you want
to use a low priority
GPU render.
The idea behind this, if
you're doing a background save,
you don't want the
GPU usages required
for that background operation
to slow down the performance
of your foreground UI,
either if that's done
in Core Image or Core Animation.
So this is great for
background processing.
And a great new thing we're
announcing this year is
that this option is also
available on macOS, too.
Once you have your context,
then it's very simple.
You get to decide what color
space you want to render to.
For example, the
DisplayP3 colorSpace.
And then we have a
new convenience API
for taking a CIImage and
writing it to a JPEG.
Super easy.
You specify the CIImage,
the destination URL,
and the colorSpace.
This is also a good time
to specify what compression
quality you want for the JPEG.
Now, in this case this will
produce an image that is a JPEG
that has been tagged with a
P3 space, which is a great way
of producing a wide-gamut image
that will display correctly
on any platform that supports
ICC-based color management.
However, if you think your
image will go to a platform
that doesn't support
color management,
we have a new option
that's available for you.
This is an option
that's available as part
of the CGImageDestination API,
and it's CGImageDestination
OptimizeForSharing.
The idea behind this is it
stores all the colors that are
in the P3 colorSpace, but
stores them in such a way
and with a custom profile,
such that that image will
still display correctly
if your recipient of that
image doesn't support
color management.
So this is a great
feature as well.
Another thing is if you want
to actually create a CGImage
from a CIImage, we have a
new API for that as well
with some new options.
We have this convenience
API which allows you
to specify what the
colorSpace and the pixel format
that you want to render to is.
You may choose, however,
now you to create a CGImage
that has the format of RGBAh,
the Goldilocks pixel format
I was talking about earlier.
And in that case you
might also choose
to use a special color space,
which is the extendedLinearSRGB
space.
Because the pixel format
supports values outside
of the range 0 to 1, you want
your color space to as well.
Another option that we have
that's new is being able
to specify whether the act
of creating the CGImage
does the work
in a deferred or
immediate fashion.
If you specify deferred,
then the work that's involved
in rendering the CIImage
into a CGImage takes place
when the CGImage is drawn.
This is a great way
of minimizing memory,
especially if you're only
going to be drawing part
of that CGImage later,
or if you're only going
to be drawing that CGImage once.
However, if you're
going to be rendering
that image multiple times, you
can specify deferred false,
and in that case Core Image
will do the work of rendering
into the CGImage at the time
this function is called.
So this is a great new,
flexible API that we have
for your applications.
Another advanced feature of this
Core Image filter API that I'd
like to talk about
today is this.
As I mentioned before, there's
a long stage of pipeline
in processing RAW files, and
a lot of people ask me, well,
how can I add my own
processing to that pipeline.
Well, one common place
where developers will want
to add processing to the
RAW pipeline is somewhere
in the middle; after the
demosaic has occurred,
but before all the nonlinear
operations like sharpening
and contrast and color
boosting has occurred.
So we have an API just for this.
It's a property on the
CIRAWFilter which allows you
to specify a filter
that gets inserted
into the middle of our graph.
So I look forward to seeing what
you guys can imagine and think
of and what can go
into this location.
Some notes on wide-gamut
output that I mentioned before.
The CIKernel language supports
float precision as a language.
However, whenever a
CIFilter needs to render
to an intermediate buffer, we
will use the working format
of the current CIContext.
On macOS the default
working format is RGBA,
our Goldilocks format.
On iOS and tvOS our default
format is still BGRA8,
which is good for performance,
but if you're rendering
extended range data,
that may not be what you want.
Our RAW pipeline, with this
in mind, all of the kernels
in our pipeline force the usage
of RGBA half-float precision,
which is critical for RAW files.
But as you might guess,
if you are concerned
about wide-gamut input
and output and preserving
that data throughout
a rendered graph,
you should modify your CIContext
when you create it to specify
that you want a working
format that is RGBAh.
I should also mention again
that Core Image supports
a wide variety
of wide-gamut output spaces.
For example, you can render to
extendedLinearSRGB or Adobe RGB
or DisplayP3, whatever
format you wish.
Now, as I mentioned before,
I was demonstrating
a 24-megapixel image.
RAW files can be a lot
larger than you might think.
RAW files can be large and
they also require several
intermediate buffers to render
all the stages of the pipeline.
And so it's important
that in order
to reduce the high water
memory mark of your application
that you use some of these APIs
that I've talked about today,
such as turning off caching
intermediates in cases
where you don't need it,
or using the new write JPEG
representation of image,
which is very efficient,
or specifying the
deferred rendering
when creating a CGImage.
Some notes on limits
of RAW files.
On iOS devices with 2
gigabytes of memory or more,
we support RAW files
up to 120 megapixels.
So we're really proud to
be able to pull that off.
[ Applause ]
On apps running on devices with
1 gigabyte of memory we support
up to 60 megapixels, which is
also really quite impressive.
And this also holds true for
photo editing extensions,
which run in a lesser
amount of memory.
So that's our discussion of RAW.
Again, I'm super proud to be
able to demonstrate this today.
I would like to hand the
stage over to Etienne
who will be talking about
another great new image format
and how you can edit those in
your application, Live Photos.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, David.
Hello everyone.
I'm really excited to be
here today to talk to you
about how you can edit Live
Photos in your application.
So first, we're going to go
over a quick introduction
of what are Live Photos, then
we see what you can edit,
and then we'll go
step-by-step into the code
and see how you can get
a Live Photo for editing,
how you can then set up a
Live Photo Editing context,
how you can apply Core Image
filters to your Live Photo,
and how you can preview your
Live Photo in your application,
and finally, how you can save
an edited Live Photo back
into the Photo Library, and
we'll finish with a quick demo.
All right.
So let's get started.
So Live Photos, as you may know,
are photos that also include
motion and sound from before
and after the time
of the capture.
And Live Photos can be
captured on the new devices
such as iPhone 6S, 6S Plus,
iPhone SE and iPod Pro.
In fact, Live Photo is
actually a default capture mode
on those devices, so you
can expect your users
to already have plenty of Live
Photos in their Photo Library.
So what's new this
year about Live Photos?
So first, users can now
fully edit their Live Photos
in Photos.
They can apply -- all the
adjustment that they would
to a regular photo they
can apply to a Live Photo.
Next we have a new API
to capture Live Photos
in your application and for
that, for more information
about that, I strongly recommend
that you watch this Advances
in iOS Photography session that
took place earlier this week.
It also includes a lot of
information about Live Photos
from the capturer point of view.
And finally, we have a new
API to edit Live Photos,
and that's why I'm here
to talk about today.
All right.
So what can be edited exactly?
Right. So first, of course,
you can edit the content
of the photo, but
you can also edit all
of the video frames as well.
You can also address
the audio volume,
and you can change the
dimensions of the Live Photo.
Things you can't do though is
that you can't change
the duration
or the timing of the Live Photo.
So in order to get a Live Photo
for editing, the first thing
to do is to actually get a Live
Photo out of the Photo Library.
So there's two ways to do that,
depending on whether you're
building a photo editing
extension or a PhotoKit
application.
In the case of a photo
editing extension you need
to start first by opting
in to Live Photo editing
by adding the LivePhoto
string in your array
of supported media types
for your extension.
And next, in your implementation
of startContentEditing,
that's called automatically,
you can expect the content
editing input that you receive
and you can check the media
type and the media subtypes
to make sure that
this is a Live Photo.
Okay. On the other hand,
if you're building a
PhotoKit application,
you have to request the
contentEditingInput yourself
from a PHAsset, and then
you can check the media type
and media subtypes
in the same way.
All right.
So the next step would be to set
up a LivePhotoEditingContext.
A LivePhotoEditingContext
includes all the resources
that are needed to
edit Live Photos.
It includes information
about the Live Photo,
such as its duration,
the time of the photo,
the size of the Live Photo,
also the orientation, all that.
It also has a frame processor
property that you can set
to actually edit the
contents of Live Photo,
and I'll tell you more
about that in a minute.
You can adjust the
audio volume as well.
You can ask the
LivePhotoEditingContext
to prepare a Live
Photo for playback,
and you can ask the
LivePhotoEditingContext to save
and process a Live Photo
for saving back to
the Photo Library.
Creating a
LivePhotoEditingContext is
really easy.
All you need to do is
institute a new one
from a LivePhotoEditingInput
for a Live Photo.
All right.
So now let's take a look at how
to use the frame processor
I mentioned earlier.
So the frame of a Live
Photo I'll describe
by a PHLivePhotoFrame object
that contains an input image,
which is a CIImage
for that frame.
Type, which is whether it's a
video frame or a photo frame.
And the time of the
frame in the Live Photo,
as well as the resolution
at which
that frame is being rendered.
In order to implement a frame
processor you would set the
frame processor property on
the LivePhotoEditingContext
to be a block that takes
a frame as parameter
and returns an image
or an error.
And here we just simply return
the input image of the frame,
so that's just necessarily
a node frame processor.
So now let's take a
look at the real case.
This is a Live Photo, as
you can see in Photos,
and I can play it right there.
And so let's say we want
to apply a simple basic
adjustment to the Live Photo.
That's start with a
simple square crop.
Here's how to do that.
In the implementation of
your frame processor you want
to start with the input
image for the frame.
Then you compute your crop rect.
Then you crop the image
using [inaudible] here,
which is called the
cropping through rect,
and just return that
cropped image.
That's all it takes to actually
edit and crop the Live Photo.
Here's the result.
I can place side photo, you
can see the photo is cropped,
but the video is also
cropped as I play it.
All right.
So that's an example of a
very basic static adjustment.
Now, what if we want to apply
a more dynamic adjustment,
and that is one that will
actually depend on the time
and will change while the
Live Photo is being played.
So you can do that, too.
So here let's build up
on that crop example
and implement the dynamic crop.
So here's how to do it.
So first we need to capture
a couple of information
about the timing of the Live
Photo, such as the exact time
of the photo because we want
the effect to stay the same
and have your crop rect really
centered on the Live Photo.
Next we take it so we capture
the duration of the Live Photo.
And you can notice
that we do that outside
of the frame processor
block and that's
to avoid cycling dependency.
Here in the block we can ask for
the exact time of that frame,
and then we can build a
function of time using all
that information to
drive a crop rect.
And here's what the result.
So you can see the Live Photo
is cropped the same way,
the photo is the same,
but when I play it,
you can see that the crop rect
now moves from bottom to top.
All right.
So that's an example of
a time-based adjustment.
Now let's take a look
at something else.
This effect is interesting
because it's a
resolution-dependent effect.
What I mean by that is that the
way the filter parameters are
specified, they're
specified in pixels, right,
which mean that you
need to be extra careful
when you apply these kind
of effects to make sure
that the effect is visually
consistent regardless
of the resolution at which the
Live Photo is being rendered.
So here if I play it, you
can see that the video --
the effect is applied
to the video the same way
it's applied to the photos.
So that's great.
So let's see how to
do that correctly.
So in your frame processor
you want to pay attention
to this renderScale
property on the frame.
This will give you
the resolution
of the current frame compared
to the one-to-one full-size
still image in the Live Photo.
So keep in mind that
the video frames
and the photo are
different size as well.
Right. Usually the video is
way smaller than the photo is.
So you want to make sure
to apply that correctly.
In order to do that, you can
use the scale here to scale
down that width parameter
so that at one-to-one
on the full-size photo
the parameter will be 50,
but it will be smaller on
the smaller resolution.
Another way to apply your
resolution-dependent adjustment
is to use the extent of
the image like I do here
for the inputCenter parameter.
I actually use the midpoint of
the image and that's granted
to also scale [inaudible].
All right.
One more edit on that image.
You can notice that I did a logo
here that might be familiar,
and when I play it, you see
that the logo actually
disappears from the video.
So this is how you would apply
an adjustment just to the photo
and not to the video,
and here's how to do it.
In your implementation of your
frame processor you want to look
at the frame type, and here
we just check if it's a photo,
then we composite the still logo
into the image, but
not on the video.
So that's as easy as that.
And you may have, you
know, some adjustments
that are local advertisement or
single ad that you don't want
to apply or you can't
apply to the video,
and so that's a good
way to do it.
All right.
Now that we have an
edited Live Photo,
let's see how we can
preview it in our app.
So in order to preview a
Live Photo you want to work
with the PHLivePhotoView.
So this view is readily
available on iOS
and is new this year on macOS.
So in order to preview
Live Photo you need
to ask the
LivePhotoEditingContext
to prepare a Live Photo
for playback and you pass
in the target size, which is
typically the size of your view
in pixels, and then you get
called back asynchronously
on the main thread with
a rendered Live Photo.
And then all you need to do
is set the Live Photo property
of the LivePhotoView so that
your users can now interact
with their Live Photo
and get an idea
of what the edited Live
Photo will look like.
Now, the final set will be to
save back to the Photo Library.
And that, again, depends whether
you're building a photo editing
extension or a PhotoKit
application.
In the case of a photo
editing extension you will
implement finishContentEditing.
And the first step is to create
a new contentEditingOutput
from that contentEditingInput
that you received earlier.
And next you will ask your
LivePhotoEditingContext
to save the Live
Photo to that output.
And again, that will process
the full resolution Live Photo
asynchronously and call
you back on the main thread
with success or error.
And in the case everything
goes fine,
make sure you save also
your adjustment data along
with your edits and that will
allow your users to go back
to your app or extension later
and continue editing there.
And then last step is
to actually call the
completionHandler
for that extension
and you're done.
If you're building a
PhotoKit application,
the steps are really similar.
The only difference really
that you have to make your --
they are from the changes
[inaudible] yourself using
a PHAssetChangeRequest.
All right.
So now I'd like to
show you a quick demo.
All right.
So I've built a simple demo
Live Photo extension that I'd
like to show you today.
So here I am in Photos and I can
see a couple Live Photos here,
can pick to see the contents.
I can swipe and see
them animate.
All right.
That's the one I
want to edit today.
So I can go to edit.
And as I mentioned earlier,
I can actually edit the Live
Photo right there in Photos.
Let me do that.
I'd like to apply
this new light slider
that David mentioned earlier.
All right.
So here in Photos I
can just play that.
Right. Of course, I could
stop here, but I actually want
to apply my sample
edits as well.
So I'm going to pick
my extension here.
And, yes, we actually apply the
same adjustment that we went
through for the slides.
And you can see this is
really a simple extension,
but it shows a LivePhotoView,
so I can interact with this
and I can actually press
to play it, like this,
right in my extension.
So that's real easy.
And the next step is to actually
save by hitting Done here.
And this is going to process
a full resolution Live Photo
and send it back to
the Photo Library.
And there it is,
right there in Photos.
All right.
So that was for the quick demo.
Now back to slides.
[ Applause ]
Thank you.
All right.
So here's a quick summary of
what we've learned so far today.
So we've learned how
to get a Live Photo
out of the Photo Library
and how to use and set
up a LivePhotoEditingContext,
how to use a frame processor
to edit the contents
of the Live Photo.
We've seen how to
preview a Live Photo
in your app using
the LivePhotoView.
And we've seen how to
save a Live Photo back
into the Photo Library.
Now I can't wait to see what
you will do with this new API.
A few things to remember.
First, if you're building
a photo editing extension,
do not forget to opt
in to LivePhotoEditing
in your info.plist
for your extension.
Otherwise, you'll get a still
image instead of a Live Photo.
And as I said, make sure you
always save adjustment data
as well so that your users
can go back to your app
and continue the edit
nondestructively.
Finally, I think if you
already have an image editing
application, adopting Live
Photo and adding support
for LivePhotoEditing should be
really easy with this new API,
especially if your app is
using Core Image already.
And if not, there's actually
a new API in Core Image
to let you integrate your
own custom processing
into Core Image.
And to tell you all about it,
I'd like to invite
Alex on stage.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Etienne.
So my name is Alexandre Naaman,
and today I'm going to talk
to you about some new
functionality we have inside
of Core Image to do
additional effects
that weren't possible
previously, and that's going
to be using a new API
called CIImageProcessor.
As David mentioned earlier,
there's a lot you can do inside
of Core Image using our
existing built-in 180 filters,
and you can extend
that even further
by writing your own
custom kernels.
Now with CIImageProcessor
we can do even more,
and we can insert a new node
inside of our render graph
that can do basically
anything we want and will fit
in perfectly with
the existing graph.
So we can write our own custom
CPU code or custom Metal code.
So there are some analogies
when using CIImageProcessor
with writing general kernels.
So in the past you would
write a general kernel,
specify some string, and then
override the output image method
on your CIFilter and
provide the extent,
which is the output image
size that you're going
to be creating, and
an roiCallback,
and then finally whatever
arguments you need
to pass to your kernel.
Now, there are a
lot of similarities
with creating CIImageProcessors,
and we're not going to go
into detail with them
about that today.
Instead we refer
you to Session 515
from our WWDC talk from 2014.
So if you want to
create CIImageProcessors,
we strongly suggest you go
and look back at that talk
because we talked about
how to deal with the extent
and ROI parameters
in great length.
So now let's look
at what the API
for creating a CIImage
Processor looks like,
and this may change a
little bit in future seeds,
but this is what it
looks like right now.
So the similarities are there.
We need to provide the extent,
which is the output image size
we're going to be producing,
give it an input
image, and the ROI.
There are a bunch of additional
parameters we need to provide,
however, such as, for example,
the description of the node
that we'll be creating.
We then need to provide a
digest with some sort of hash
of all our input parameters.
And this is really
important for Core Image
because this is how Core
Image determines whether
or not we can cache the
values or not, and whether
or not we need to rerender.
So you need to make sure
that every time your
parameter changes,
that you update the hash.
The next thing we can
specify is an input format.
In this case here
we've used BGRA8,
but you can also specify zero,
which means you'll get the
working format for the context
as an input image format.
You can specify the
output format as well.
In this case we're using
RGBAf because the example
that we're going to be going
over in more detail needs a lot
of precision, so we'll
need full flow here.
And then finally we get
to our processor block,
which is where we have
exactly two parameters;
our CIImageProcessorInput
and CIImageProcessorOutput,
and it's inside of here that
we can do all the work we need
to do.
So let's take a look
at how we can do this,
and why you would
want to do this.
So CIImageProcessor
is particularly useful
for when you have some algorithm
or you want to use a library
that implements something
outside of Core Image
and something that
isn't suitable
for the CIKernel language.
A really good example of this is
what we call an integral image.
An integral image is an image
whereby the output pixel
contains the sum of
all the pixels above it
and to the left,
including itself.
And this is a very good
example of the kind of thing
that can't be done in a
data parallel-type shader,
which is the kind of
shader that you write
when you're writing CIKernels.
So let's take a look at
what an integral image is
in a little bit more detail.
If we start off with the input
image on the left, which,
let's say, corresponds to some
single channel, 8-bit data,
our integral image would
be the image on the right.
So if we take a look
at this pixel here, 7,
it actually corresponds to
the sum of all of those pixels
on the left, which would
be 1 plus 4 plus 0 plus 2.
The same goes for this other
pixel; 45 corresponds to the sum
of all those other pixels above
it and to the left, plus itself.
So now let's take a look
at what you would do inside
of the image processor block
if you were writing a CPU code,
and you could also use V Image
or any number of other libraries
that we have on the system.
So first things first.
We're going to get some
pointers back to our input data.
So from the
CIImageProcessorInput we'll get
the base address,
and we'll make sure
that we use 8-bit
data, so UInt8.
And then we'll get
our outputPointer,
which is where we're going
to write all of our results
as float, because we specified
that we wanted to
write to RGBAf.
The next thing we do
is we make sure to deal
with the relative offsets of
our input and output image.
It's highly likely that
Core Image will provide you
with an input image that
is going to be larger,
or at least not equivalent
to your output image,
so you have to take care of
whatever offset might be in play
when you're creating your output
image and doing your four loops.
And in this case,
once we have figured
out whatever offsets
we need, we can then go
and execute our four-loop to
calculate the output values
at location i, j by using
the input at location i, j,
plus whatever offset we had.
Now that we've seen how to do
this with a custom CPU loop,
let's take a look at how
this can be done using Metal.
In this case we're going to be
using Metal Performance Shaders.
And there's a great
primitive inside
of Metal Performance Shaders
to compute integral images
called MPSImageIntegral.
From our CIImageProcessorOutput
we can get the commandBuffer,
the Metal command buffer, so we
just create an MPSImageIntegral
with that commandBuffer.
Once again we take care of
whatever offsets we may need
to deal with, and then we
simply encode that kernel
to the commandBuffer,
and providing
as input the input
texture that we get
from the CIImageProcessorInput,
and as a destination
the output.MetalTexture.
And this is how we can use
Metal very simply inside
of an existing CIFilter graph.
So now let's take a look
at what we can actually do
with this integral image
now that we have it.
So let's say we start
with an image like this.
Our goal is going to be
to produce a new image
where we have a per
pixel variable box blur.
So each pixel in that image
can have a different amount
of blur applied to it,
and we can do this really
quickly using an integral image.
So, as I was saying, box
blurs are very useful
for doing very fast box sums.
So if we start right off with
this input image and we wanted
to get the sum of those nine
pixels, traditionally speaking,
this would require nine reads,
which means it's an
n squared problem.
That's obviously not
going to be very fast.
That's not completely true.
If you were a little
more smart about it,
you could probably do this as
a multipass approach and do it
in two n reads, but that
still means you're looking
at six reads, and obviously
that doesn't scale very well.
With an integral image,
however, we can just --
if we want to get the sum of
those nine pixels, we just have
to read at a few locations.
We will read at the lower right
corner and then we can read
from just one pixel off to the
left, the sum of all the values,
and subtract that from the
first value we just read.
And then we read at a pixel
right above where we need to be
and subtract the row which
corresponds to the sum
of all the pixels
up to that stage.
But now you can see we've
highlighted the upper left
corner with a 1 because we've
subtracted that value twice,
so we need to add it back in.
So what this means is we can
create an arbitrarily-sized box
blur with just four reads.
And if we were to --
[ Applause ]
Thank you.
If we were to actually do the
math manually, you could see
that these numbers do add up.
So 2 plus 4 plus 6, et cetera,
is equal to the exact same thing
as 66 minus 10 minus 13 plus 1.
Now let's jump back into
Core Image kernel language
and see how we can
use our integral image
that we've computed
either with a CPU code
or using the Metal
Performance Shader primitives
and continue doing the work
of actually creating
the box blur effect.
So the first thing we're
going to do is we're going
to compute our lower left corner
and upper right corner
from our image.
Those will tell us where we
need to subtract and add from.
We're then going to compute
a few additional values
and they're going to help us
determine what the alpha value
should be, so how
transparent the pixel
that we're currently
trying to produce is.
We take our four
samples, the four corners,
and then finally we do our
additions and subtractions
and multiply by what we've
decided is the appropriate
amount of transparency
for this output pixel.
Now, this particular kernel
takes a single parameter
as an input radius, which
would mean that if you were
to call this on an
image, you would get
that same radius applied
to the entire image,
but we can very simply go and
create a variable box blur
by passing in a mask image,
and we can use this mask image
to determine how large
the radius should be
on a per pixel basis.
So we just pass in an additional
parameter, mask image.
We read from it.
We take a look at what's in the
red channel, say, or it could be
from any channel, and we then
multiply our radius by that.
So if we had a radius
of 15 and at
that current pixel
location we had .5,
it would give us
a radius of 7.5.
We can then take those
values and pass it
into the box blur kernel
that we just wrote.
And this is how we can very
simply create a variable box
blur using Metal
Performance Shaders
and the CIImageProcessor nodes.
One additional thing we haven't
mentioned so far today is
that we now have some
attributes you can specify
on your CIKernels when you
write them and, in fact,
we have this just one right
now, which is the output format.
In this case we're
asking for RGBAf,
which is not really
necessarily useful,
but the key thing here is
that you can say that you'd
like to write only
single-channel
or two-channel data.
So if you wanted to do --
[ Applause ]
As some people have
noticed, this is a great way
to reduce your memory usage,
and it's also a way to specify
that you want a certain
precision for a specific kernel
in your graph that may
not correspond to the rest
of the graph, which
is also what we do
when we're processing
RAW images on iOS.
All of our kernels
are tagged with RGBAh.
So one or more thing we need
to do to create this effect is
to provide some sort
of mask image.
We can do this very simply
by calling CIFilter(name,
and then ask for
a CIRadialGradient
with a few parameters,
which are going
to determine how
large the mask will be
and where it will be located.
And then we're going to be
interpolating between 0 and 1,
which is going to
be black and white.
And then we ask for the
output image from the CIFilter
and we have a perfectly
usable mask.
So now let's take a look
at what this actually looks
like when running on device,
and this is recorded
from an iPhone 6S.
If we start with our input
image and then look at our mask,
we can move it around.
It's all very interactive.
Change the radius, even
make it go negative.
And then if we apply this
mask image and use it inside
of our variable box
blur kernel code,
we then get this type of result.
And it's very interactive
because the integral image
only needs to be computed once,
and Core Image caches
those results for you.
So it literally, everything
you're seeing right now,
is just involving four reads.
So it's superfast.
[ Applause ]
Some things to keep in mind.
When you're using
the CIImageProcessor,
if the data that you
would like to use inside
of your image processor
is not inside
of the context current
workingColorSpace, you're going
to want to call
CIImage.byColorMatching
WorkingSpace(to, and then
provide a color space.
Similarly, on the way out,
if you would like the data
in a different color space,
you can call
CIImage.byColorMatching
ColorSpace(toWorking, and
then give it a color space.
Now that we've seen how to
create the CIImageProcessor
and how to use it, let's
take a look at what happens
when we use the environment
variable CI PRINT TREE,
which we use to get an idea
of what the actual graph
that we're trying to
render looks like.
So this is what it looks
like when you use the
environment variable CI PRINT
TREE with the value
equal to the 1.
And this is read
from bottom to top.
And it can be quite verbose.
It starts off with our input
radialGradient that we created.
We then have our input image
which gets matched
to the workingspace.
And then here's our processor
node that gets called,
and that hex value is the
digest that we've computed.
And then both the processor
and the color kernel result
from the radialGradient get
fed into the variableBoxBlur.
And finally we do the color
matching to our output display.
So this is the original
recipe that we use
to specify this effect, but it's
not what actually gets rendered.
If we were to set the
environmental variable CI PRINT
TREE to 8, we can now see that
many things have been collapsed
and the processing looks
to be less involved.
We still, once again,
have our processor node,
which lives on a
line on its own,
which means that it
does require the need
of an intermediate buffer,
which is why the
CIImageProcessors are great,
but you should only use them
when the kind of things --
the effect that you're trying
to produce, the algorithms
that you have cannot
be expressed inside
of the CIKernel language.
As you can see, the rest
of the processing all
gets concatenated.
So we have our variableBoxBlur
with the rest
of the color matching, and
the clamptoalpha all happening
in a single pass.
So this is why there are always
tradeoffs in between these APIs.
And if you can write something
inside the CIKernel language,
you should.
That may be a little
difficult to read.
So we have an additional
option now that you can specify
when you're using CI PRINT
TREE, which is graphviz.
In this case we're
using CI PRINT TREE=8,
along with the graphviz option,
and we can see our
processor node and how it fits
in perfectly with the
rest of the graph.
And we can also see that
we've asked for RGBAf output.
So let's do a little recap
of what we learned today.
We saw, David showed us how
to edit RAW images on iOS.
Then Etienne spoke to us
about how you can edit Live
Photos using Core Image.
And then finally, we got to
see how to use this new API
on CIImage called
CIImageProcessor, as well as how
to specify an output
format on your kernels
to help reduce the memory usage.
For additional information
please
visit developer.apple.com.
There are a few related sessions
that may be of interest to you,
especially if you're planning
on doing RAW processing on iOS.
There's Advances
in iOS Photography
that Etienne mentioned as well.
There's also a talk later on
today, Working with Wide Color,
that's taking place right here.
And on that note, I would like
to thank you all for coming.
I hope you enjoy
the rest of WWDC.
[ Applause ]