[ Music ]
>> Morning, everyone.
Thanks.
[ Applause ]
>> My name is Aaftab Munshi.
And my colleagues and I
are really excited to share
with you the new
features in Metal
in macOS Sierra and iOS 10.
But let's begin by highlighting
the sessions we have
on Metal this year at WWDC.
So yesterday we had two
sessions that talked
about adopting Metal
in your application.
And today we have
three sessions.
So this session and
the two sessions
that cover the new features in
Metal, which is then followed
by another session
where we'll talk
about optimizing
your Metal shaders.
All right.
So let's look at the features
we're going to talk about.
So in the second session the
features we will be talking
about are function or shader
specialization and being able
to write to resources such
as buffers and textures
from your fragment
and vortex shader,
wide color using wide color
displays in your application
and texture assets, and some
new additions we've added
to Metal performance shaders,
specifically using axillary
and [inaudible] networks
on the GPU with Metal.
In this session we're
going to talk about some
of the improvements we
have added to Tools,
which we think you guys
are going to really love.
We've also made resource heaps
and resource allocations
much faster
and given you more control.
So we'll talk about
that resource heaps
and memoryless render targets.
And I'm going to be
talking about tessellation.
So let's begin.
All right.
So the first thing, let's spend
a little bit of time trying
to understand why we
need tessellation.
So we are seeing applications
such as games rendering more
and more realistic
visual content.
So what that means is in
order to render such content,
we need to be able to
send detailed amount
of geometry to the GPU.
That's where we're going
to send this input.
That means lots and lots
of triangles that have
to be processed, which
means a large increase
in memory bandwidth.
It would be really nice
if instead we could just
describe this geometry
that we want to send to the GPU
as a lower resolution model,
call it a core smash, and
then have the GPU generate the
high-resolution model.
So in fact, that's
what tessellation does.
Tessellation is a technique
that you can use to amplify
and refine the details
of your geometric object.
We have two important
requirements we need to meet.
The first is that the
high-resolution model,
the triangles that are
generated do not get stored
in graphics memory.
We don't want to pay
that bandwidth cost.
And the second is a
method that's used needs
to be programmable.
So let's look at an example.
So here is a screenshot
from GFXBench 4.0,
which is a benchmark
released by [inaudible].
And one of the key features
it focuses on is tessellation.
So here's a screenshot
of the car that's being
rendered without tessellation.
You can see those rims.
They're very polygonal.
You wouldn't drive a car
like that, would you?
Even the body panels
have cracks in them.
And the reason for that is this
is the actual geometry that's
being sent.
So you can see not a lot of
triangles, which is great --
it's exactly what we want.
What tessellation does is
takes that input geometry
and produces something
like that.
I think this is really cool.
So if you look at
the wire frame,
you can see the GPUs
actually generating,
now we're rendering lots
and lots of triangles, okay?
And that's the power
of tessellation.
All right.
So let's look at how
tessellation works in Metal.
So just like we did
with Metal, you know,
we wanted to take a clean
sheet approach, right?
We wanted to design
something that was --
even though there
are existing API's
that do support tessellation
that you may be familiar with,
we wanted something that
was really simple to graph,
you know, easy to use,
and we did not want
to leave any performance
on the table.
And we think we have achieved
that, and I hope you agree
after this presentation.
So tessellation is available
in macOS Sierra and on iOS
with the A9 processor.
All right.
So let's -- the things I'm
going to talk about is well,
how does the Metal
graphics pipeline look
like for tessellation?
How do I render my
geometry with tessellation?
And then how do I adopt
it in my application?
So let's begin.
So today when you send
primitives to the GPU
with Metal, you're sending
triangles, lines, or points.
With tessellation, you're
sending what we call a patch.
And put simply, a patch is
just a parametric surface
that is made up of
spline curves.
What does that mean?
You may have heard of things
like Bezier patches
or B-spline patches.
So you describe a patch by
a set of control-points.
So in this figure you
see is a B-spline patch.
So you have 16 control-points
or control vertices.
And what tessellation does put
simply is allows you to control,
okay, how many triangles do
I use to render this patch?
So you may decide,
"You know what?
I don't really want
a lot of triangles.
I don't care how it looks."
So you may decide just four
triangles is more than enough
and you'll get a polygonal look.
Or you decide, "Hey, I
really want this looking nice
and smooth."
That would take a
lot more triangles.
But you have that control.
So let's start.
So the first stage in
the graphics pipeline
when we're doing
tessellation is we call it a
tessellation kernel.
And what it does is
it takes the patch --
we talked about the patch with
the control-points as input --
and decides, okay, how much
do I need to subdivide this?
How many triangles do I want
the GPU to generate, right?
This information is
captured in what we call
as tessellation factors.
And I'll talk a little bit
about what these factors
are a few slides later.
And you can also generate
additional patch data
if you need it in a later stage.
The key thing this is
a programmable stage,
that means you're writing code.
So once you've written
[inaudible] tessellation
factors, the next stage
is called the tessellator.
So this is a fixed
function stage.
So no code to write.
But you do net knobs
to configure it, okay?
So it takes those
tessellation factors
and breaks the patch
up into triangles.
And the key thing the
tessellator does here is
that it does not store
that triangle list it
generates in graphics memory.
In addition to the triangle
list it has generated,
for each vertex in the triangle
list it will generate what we
call a parametric coordinate
-- the U and the V value.
And it uses this along
with the control-points
to compute the actual
position on the surface.
Okay? All right.
So the tessellator
generates triangles.
Today in Metal when you
want to render primitives,
you send triangles to the GPU.
What is the first thing
that happens is a vertex
shader is executed, right?
Well, here the tessellator's
generating triangles.
So if you think logically,
the next stage would be a
vertex shader, and it is.
We just call it the
post-tessellation vertex shader
because it's operating
on the triangles
that are generated
by the tessellator.
And so it's going to execute for
the vertices of the triangles
that the tessellator
generated and it's going
to output transform positions.
So if you're familiar
with DirectX,
it's this shader plays
the same, similar role
as the domain shader
does in DirectX.
All right.
And then the rest of the
pipeline remains the same.
We have the rasterizer and
the fragment shader, right?
So you may ask, "Well, so I need
to write this compute kernel
to generate the tessellation
factors.
Well, can I use the
vertex or fragment shader?"
Of course you can.
In fact, you don't even
need to write a shader
to generate these factors;
you may have precomputed them
and you can just load
them in a buffer and pass
that to the tessellator.
So you have a lot of control.
But if you are generating these
factors in the GPU, we recommend
that you use a compute kernel.
Because guess what?
That allows us to run
that kernel asynchronously
with other draw commands.
So netting you a performance win
and I think you guys
will like that.
Well, actually let's
take it a step further.
You don't even need to run
this kernel every frame.
Because guess what?
If you have computed the
tessellation factors --
let's say you decide,
"Hey, objects close
to the camera get much
more tessellation,
objects further away
not as much."
So once I've computed
them, then depending
on how the object is moving,
I can just apply a scale
and the tessellator takes that.
So really, the pipeline
is really, really simple.
We have four stages.
So let's compare it with
the graphics pipeline
without tessellation.
So without tessellation
we have three stages --
we have vertex shade,
the rasterizer,
and the fragment stage.
With tessellation we added a
new stage, the tessellator.
It's fixed function so you
don't have to write any shader.
And the vertex shader became the
post-tessellation vertex shader.
We think this is really
simple to understand.
I hope you agree.
All right.
So how do I render my
geometry with tessellation?
There are four things
I'm going to talk about.
Okay. Let's look at
this post-tessellation
or post-tess vertex shader;
how is this different
from the regular vertex shader?
How do I pass my patch inputs?
And I told you that the
tessellator's configurable.
So let's look at
how we configure it
and then draw patches.
So, well, meet the new shader,
same with the old shader.
So in fact, you declare a
post-tessellation vertex shader
with a vertex qualifier.
But in addition to that, you
also specify this attribute
which says, "Hey, it's
working on a patch."
There are two kinds of patches
-- a quad and triangle patch.
And you see the number
next to that?
That number tells you how many
control-points this patch is
working on.
So if you had a regular
vertex shader,
you would have passed
a vertex ideas input.
Now you pass a patchID as input.
Remember I told you the
tessellator generated a
parametric UV coordinate?
Well, that's what this
position in patch input is.
And then if you had a
regular vertex shader,
you would have passed
something as stage in,
the patch input we
passed at the stage in.
Everything else you
just bring computations
and you're generating a
transformed vertex output.
And that's actually going
to be exactly identical
because the next stage with
or without tessellation
is a rasterizer.
All right.
So let's look at patch inputs.
So if you had a regular
vertex shader,
you would have described
your vertex input
as a struct, okay,
in your shader.
And if you had decoupled the
date type, that means the layout
and the buffers where the
vertex inputs are coming
from do not match the
declaration in the shader,
then you would have used
the MTLVertexDescriptor
to describe the layout.
Well, for patches
there are two inputs.
One is the per-patch input.
And remember, I told there are
one or more control-points?
So we need to specify
those as inputs as well.
But it looks identical
how you specify these.
So you use a MTLVertexDescriptor
to specify the layout
of the patch input
data in memory.
And as I showed you the slide
before, we declared that input
as a stage in as well.
And you use the attribute index
to identify an element as input
in the shader with the
corresponding declaration
in your MTLVertexDescriptor.
Since there can be more than one
control-point, we basically have
to declare it using
a template type.
And I'll talk about
that in the next slide.
So let's look at an example.
So here I have my
control-point data.
It has two elements.
So I'm using attributes
zero and one.
And my per-patch data, which
is attributes two and three.
So we combine these
two things together
and this is my patch
input for every patch.
So notice that control templated
type patch underscore control
underscore point.
So that's what tells the
Metal shading compiler "Hey,
this is referring to
control-point input."
Okay? And remember I told
you about this number 16
or whatever the number is?
That also tells the Metal
shading compiler how many
control-points there are.
So now we have all information
we need to get the patch input.
And so we just pass
that as stage in.
It's pretty simple, I think.
All right.
So okay, how do I
configure knobs?
So there are properties
in the
MTLRenderPipelineDescriptor you
can set.
A few examples are you can tell
the tessellator the method you
want to use to generate
the triangles;
it's called the partitioning
mode.
You can also specify a
max tessellation level.
And we think this is
really, really useful
because it allows you to control
the maximum amount of geometry
that the GPU will generate
for your tessellated objects.
Remember, the tessellator
needs to read these factors.
So you need to specify the
buffer of where they come from.
So use the
setTessellationFactorBuffer API
to do that.
Now, these factors,
so they tell how much
to subdivide the patches along
the edges and on the inside.
So we have two kinds of patches.
If it's a triangular patch,
there are three edges
and one inside.
If it's a quad, then you have
four edges and two insides.
So you specify these as half
precision floating point values
that you pass in.
And then drawing.
So today when you're
drawing primitives,
you're sending triangles
to be rendered by the GPU,
you're either going
to call drawPrimitives
or drawIndexPrimitives.
You the specify the start
vertex, number of vertices.
And if your vertex
indexes are not continuous,
you will pass an index buffer.
Well, to draw patches,
you call drawPatches
or drawIndexedPatches.
You specify the start patch,
the number of patches.
And if you're control-point
indexes are not continuous,
you specify an index buffer.
So it's just a one-to-one
mapping.
And then there is the
DrawIndirect variants.
And what these are is
that you do not specify
where the start patch
and how many patches
and other information when
you make the draw call,
but instead you pass a buffer.
And that gets filled out
with this information
by a command that's running on
the GPU, just like you would do
for drawPrimitives as well.
So really, if you don't know
how to use drawPrimitives,
then drawPatches just
works very similarly.
Okay? So we think this
is really easy to use.
All right?
So hold on.
So I've shown you what
Metal tessellation is
and how to use it.
As many of you may
be familiar with
or already using tessellation in
your application using DirectX
or OpenGL, you will notice
Metal tessellation's a
little different.
Don't worry.
We've designed Metal
tessellation
so it's incredibly
straightforward
to move your existing
tessellation code to Metal.
As an example, for the past
few weeks we've been working
with Unity.
And in an incredibly short
period of time they've been able
to integrate Metal
Tessellation in the engine.
And here's what they
have to say.
So we're really excited that
support for Metal Tessellation,
Metal Compute and the ability
to write native Metal shaders
in Unity's coming
later this year.
It's incredibly exciting.
And we've also been
working with Epic
to efficiently integrate Metal
Tessellation in Unreal Engine 4.
And Epic is planning to
release their support
in UE4 later this year, okay?
So we have UE4, we have Unity
supporting Metal Tessellation.
Well, let me show you
tessellation in action
in these game engines
by demonstrating two commonly
used rendering techniques called
adaptive tessellation
and displacement mapping.
All right.
So here we have a
simple demo developed
by a few Apple engineers
using Unreal Engine 4.
So let's turn tessellation
off, which I have,
and get wire frame mode.
You can see there are not a lot
of triangles being
sent to the GPU.
This is great.
This is exactly what we want.
We want to keep the amount of
geometry we send to the GPU
to be as little as possible.
Let's turn tessellation
on and see what happens.
You can see now the GPU is
generating a lot more triangles.
And adaptive tessellation
is a technique that allows
to control the geometric
detail where it matters.
So in this example we've decided
that objects that are closer
to the camera need more detail.
So let's draw them with
a lot more triangles
versus objects further
away do not.
So the regions in blue represent
regions of lowest amount
of tessellation, and the region
in red represents the regions
with the highest
amount of tessellation.
I can show you as I move
the slider to the right,
I can use that to increase
my tessellation level
and you can see objects
closer will become red.
Okay? Well, let's turn
wire frame mode off.
And if you run -- as we
go through this cave,
you can see there's a
lot more detail, right?
If I turn tessellation off, all
that detail is gone, it's lost.
Turn tessellation on,
it looks really amazing.
So this is an example of
how I can use tessellation
to really create rich visual
scenes in my application.
And I wanted to thank
the great folks at Epic
for making this happen.
So the next demo is displacement
mapping running on Unity.
So here we have a
sphere being rendered.
Well, let's look at how
many triangles we're using
to render the sphere.
Not a lot, right?
There are about 3,000 triangles.
And what displacement
mapping is, is a technique
that allows you to
displace the geometry
to create incredible detail.
And it does that
by looking up --
using a displacement
map, which is a texture.
So you look up, you know, from
a texture, from this texture
and then use that to
[inaudible] the vertex position.
Or you may actually do this
procedurally if you wanted to.
But displacement mapping
requires that, you know,
you're drawing lots and
lots of really, really,
really small triangles.
Otherwise it doesn't work.
It creates artifacts,
it just cracks.
But that's fine, you know?
We can use tessellation.
That's what it's here for.
Because we still want
to send 3,000 triangles,
smaller triangles to the GPU
and use tessellation
to generate that.
So let's turn wire
frame mode off
and let's turn displacement
mapping on.
As you can see now incredible
detail on the sphere, right?
If I turn wire frame mode on,
you can see we're generating
a lot more triangles
and they are really,
really small.
In fact, let's actually
animate the displacement map
so you can see the
shapes changing
and let's zoom in to see detail.
You can see self-shadowing
happening.
And the reason self-shadowing
is happening here is
because we're actually
changing the geometry,
unlike a technique many
of you may be familiar
with called bump mapping
which just creates an
illusion of realism.
So this is another
technique which you can use
with tessellation to
create incredible detail
in your application
that you're rendering.
And hey, thank you to
Unity for this demo.
[ Applause ]
All right.
So
Metal Tessellation
can also be used
to accelerate digital
content creation tools.
As an example OpenSubdiv is an
open source library released
by Pixar.
And it implements
high-performance
subdivision surfaces.
Actually, it has been
integrated into a number
of third-party digital
content creation tools,
such as Maya from Autodesk.
And OpenSubdiv uses tessellation
to render these subdivision
surfaces.
Well, we -- Apple -- have
added Metal Tessellation
into OpenSubdiv.
And I'm really excited to
announce here that we plan
to release these changes
to the OpenSubdiv open source
project later this summer.
Okay. I mean, here's
what Pixar has to say.
As you can see, Pixar's
really excited
to see a native Metal
implementation
of OpenSubdiv in iOS and macOS.
All right.
So now you may be asking,
"Well, what about me?
How do I move my existing
tessellation code to Metal?"
Well, let me show you how.
So we'll take DirectX
an as example here,
but the same rules
apply to OpenGL.
So here is what the DirectX
graphics pipeline looks
like with tessellation.
We have three new stages --
two of them are programmable.
They're called the hull
and the domain shader.
And then we have this
tessellator in the middle.
Right? So, well, okay.
How do I move this to Metal?
Notice where the
domain shader sits.
It sits right after
the tessellator.
Does it remind you of any
other shader I showed you
in the Metal pipeline?
Yeah, I think so.
Yeah, post-tessellation
vertex shader.
Because guess what?
The domain shader
with tessellation really
becomes the new vertex shader.
And just like you can
very easily move your HLSL
or GLSL vertex functions
to Metal,
you can move these domain
shaders pretty easily
to the post-tessellation
vertex shader.
The tessellator is exactly
the same, no changes.
So really, we have this
guy, these two shaders,
the vertex and hull shader.
And we got to make
them into a kernel.
Okay. Let's look at
how we can do that.
So let's look at some --
since we have a vertex shader,
that means there's probably
a vertex descriptor described
at runtime by the application.
And that means -- because
the data's probably going
to be decoupled.
So that means I need
to declare stage in.
But I don't do stage
in in a kernel.
Right? Well, now you can.
We've added support for it.
So just like in a vertex
shader you use stage
in to say this is my vertex
input, you can use stage
in to say this my
per thread input.
And you can specify
the actual data layout
in a MTLStage
inputOutputDescriptor.
It behaves identically.
It's very similar to
a MTLVertexDescriptor.
Some of the things you
specify are a little different
because this is for
compute, not for vertex.
And then two things to observe.
With tessellation
DirectX or OpenGL,
the vertex shader executes on
the control-point of a patch.
And the hull shader has
these two functions.
One that executes on a
control-point and one
that executes on a patch.
The per-patch hull function is
what actually generates your
tessellation factors.
All right.
So the best thing to do?
Translate all these three
functions to Metal functions.
And then we'll write
a Metal kernel
that will call these functions.
But don't worry, we're not
going to make function calls.
The Metal compiler
will in-line these.
Okay? So let's look
at how this works.
So each thread basically
is going
to call the control-point
function for the vertex
and for the hull, right?
So let's say there
were 16 control-points.
So the first thread
calls the vertex
and control-point hull function,
second thread does the
same thing, and so on.
Right? And any intermittent data
that they produce that they want
to share, they'll put that
in thread group memory,
which is this local memory
which is high-performance,
very low-latency.
So we're not going
after graphics memory.
And then if there were
16 control-points,
there will be 16 threads
operating on these.
Only one of them need to execute
the per-patch hull function.
That means you typically
have a barrier,
and then you will execute --
only one of the thread will
execute the hull functions.
You have a conditional
check saying, "Hey,
is my thread in thread
group ID0?
Then call this thing."
And this is the function
that will output the
tessellation factors
to graphics memory.
If you had any additional
patch data you wanted
to output, you could do so.
And if you really, really,
really, really wanted
to output the control-point
data, you can do so.
But we find in most case the
control-point data is just
passed through.
It's the nature of
the graphics pipeline,
and these are the existing API's
which requires you
to pass them through.
But you're just passing them
through; don't write it out.
You already have them
in your buffer, okay?
All right.
Let me close.
So I hope I have shown you
that Metal Tessellation
is simple and easy to use.
We designed it from the
ground up for performance.
I've shown you how easy it is
to adapt your existing
tessellation code to Metal.
It's available on iOS and macOS.
So now it's your turn.
Show us, you know,
use tessellation
and create some amazing visuals
that you can render
in the application.
So I want to thank
you for your time.
I'm going to call my colleague,
James, and he's going to talk
to you about resource heaps
and memoryless render targets.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> All right.
Thank you, Aaftab.
For the next part of
this session I'm excited
to introduce two new Metal
features available in iOS
and tvOS - resource heaps and
memoryless render targets.
These features enable
you to take control
of your resource
management for greater CPU
and memory efficiency.
I'll introduce resource
heaps first,
followed by memoryless
render targets.
So resource heaps are a
new lower overhead resource
management option in Metal.
Now, you can already create
buffers and textures in Metal,
so why do we need another way?
Well, creating resources
through the existing Metal API
with a device is
easy and convenient
and many developers
appreciate the simplicity.
On the other hand, as many
of your Metal apps
render increasingly rich
and complex scenes, you
asked for finer control
over your Metal resources
to unlock greater CPU
and memory efficiency.
That's why we are
introducing resource heaps.
Resource heaps enable fast
resource creation and binding
through resource sub-allocation.
The flexibility of resource
heaps saves you memory
by allowing multiple
resources to alias in memory.
And finally, the
efficiency and flexibility
of resource heaps is made
possible by you taking control
over tracking resource
dependencies
with explicit command
synchronization.
Now, let's dive into each one
of these features starting
with resource sub-allocation.
Before talking about the
details of sub-allocation,
let's first discuss why
device-based resource creation
is expensive.
Creating an individual resource
with a Metal device
involves multiple steps:
Allocating the memory; preparing
the memory for the GPU;
clearing the memory for
security; and then, finally,
creating the Metal object.
Each one of these steps
takes time and a majority
of the time is spent
in memory operations.
But there are situations when
you need to create resources
on your performance-critical
path
without introducing
performance hitches.
Texture streaming is one example
or perhaps you have an image
processing app that needs
to generate a number
of temporary textures
to execute a filter.
The cost of binding resources
to command encoders can also
become a performance issue.
Metal must track each
unique resource bound
to a command encoder
to make sure
that the GPU can
access the memory.
And for complex scenes, this
cost can add up as well.
Resource sub-allocation
addresses both
of these performance issues.
Remember that the expensive
part of resource creation is
in the memory operations.
With resource heaps you can
perform the memory operations
ahead of time outside
of your game loop.
Resource heaps address the
binding cost by allowing you
to sub-allocate many logical
resources from a single heap.
By sub-allocating multiple
resources from one heap,
Metal tracks one memory
allocation instead
of one per individual resource.
This significantly reduces
your driver overhead.
Now, let's compare
resource creation
between the Metal device and
the new Metal resource heap.
When you create a resource with
a device, Metal will allocate
and prepare a block of memory
and then create the
Metal object.
So for four resources,
Metal will allocate
or prepare four blocks
of memory.
Now, compare that
to the MTLHeap.
When you use a MTLHeap
for resource creation,
you first create the heap
object ahead of time.
Memory will allocate and
prepare a block of memory
of the requested size.
And if you do this ahead of time
outside of your render loop,
the expensive part of
resource creation is complete.
Now, to create four
resources out of the MTLHeap,
Metal only needs to reserve
a piece of the heap's memory
and create the resource
metadata.
This is much faster.
Now let's see what
happens when we want
to release some resources.
When a device-based
resource is released,
the Metal object is destroyed,
but the device will also free
the memory resource allocation.
On the other hand, when
releasing a heap resource,
only the object is destroyed.
The memory is still
owned by the heap.
So creating a new resource
on the device will incur another
expensive memory allocation,
whereas the heap can quickly
reassign the free memory
to another resource.
Let me show you how easy it is
to sub-allocate Metal
resources with Swift.
So like many Metal objects,
the Metal resource heap has a
corresponding descriptor object.
So let's create a heap
descriptor and set the size
to the amount of
memory to back the heap.
With the heap descriptor
we can ask the device
to create us a heap object.
Remember, this is the slower
operation, so do this ahead
of time, like when
your app starts
or at content loading time.
With the constructed heap,
we can call its resource
creation methods,
which should look very
familiar since the name
and arguments are the same
as the device equivalents.
So before moving on
to the next topic I'd
like to share some
best practices
for using resource heaps
for sub-allocation.
Now, the most important tip
is to use resource heaps
to create resources on your
performance-critical path.
Creating resources using
the device is not designed
for your game loop;
resource heaps are.
Allocating resources of varying
sizes can lead to fragmentation
of a heap's memory
if the resources have
varying lifetimes.
So use multiple heaps and
bucket resources by size
to limit the effects
of fragmentation.
Now, you may also
be wondering how
to choose an appropriate
heap size.
Well, Metal provides two new
methods on the Metal device
to query the size and alignment
of a texture and buffer.
Use these queries to help
you calculate the heap size
that you need.
Okay. Let's move on
to the next feature
of resource heaps --
Resource aliasing.
Resource aliasing allows
multiple dynamic resources
to occupy the same memory,
therefore reducing the
total memory footprint
of the resources.
Dynamic resources have contents
that are regenerated each frame
and include things like your
shadow maps, your G buffer data,
or temporary textures
used in post-processing.
Here we have a heap containing
two nonaliasing resources.
Compare that to this heap
containing the same two
resources but now
they are aliasing.
Now, you can obviously see
that the aliasing resources can
fit inside a much smaller heap.
Let's apply resource
aliasing to this game frame.
The shadow map passes render
a set of shadow maps --
one for each light in the scene.
So here in our heap we have
a number of shadow maps.
And in the main pass during
fragment processing the shaders
will sample the shadow
maps to determine
if each object is in shadow.
Now, after the main
pass ends, the contents
for the shadow maps are
completely consumed.
They will be regenerated
in the next frame.
So after the main pass ends, we
execute a post-processing chain
that can consist of a number
of off-screen render passes,
each executing a specific
filter like a blur or bloom.
These filters will store
their contents into textures
to pass filter results to
the next stages the chain.
Now, the key takeaway
here is that the contents
for the shadow maps and the
post-processing textures are
never used at the same time.
So why not share the memory?
So let me show you how to create
these aliasing resource sets
with Swift.
Now, the first section
should look familiar.
First we ask the device
to create us a heap
and we create our
three shadow maps.
Okay. Now we see a new
method, makeAliasable.
By calling makeAliasable
on a heap resource you are
telling the heap to consider
that resource's memory
to be free.
The shadow maps are still
active, but their memory is free
to be reassigned by the
heap to new resources.
So now when we create the
post-processing textures
on the same heap, they
can occupy the same memory
as the shadow maps.
So now let's talk about
some best practices
for resource aliasing.
To maximize memory reuse
for dynamic resources call
resource creation methods
in the same sequence that their
resources are used in a frame.
That will allow you to
call makeAliasable --
that will allow you to
interleave makeAliasable calls
when the resource contents
have been consumed.
And you want to keep dynamic
and static resources
in separate heaps.
Static resources are generally
not aliasable and can end
up preventing dynamic
resources from aliasing
with each other due
to fragmentation of
the heap's memory.
Next I'm going to talk about how
to synchronize command access
to your heap resources.
So, so far we have discussed
fast resource creation
with sub-allocation and
efficient memory usage
with resource aliasing.
But remember that resource
heaps are fast and flexible
because you control
the synchronization
of heap resources.
This is something
you do not have to do
with device resources.
But unlike device
resources, Metal won't know
when a command modifies the
contents of a heap resource
like when a render pass stores
new contents to a texture.
Metal also doesn't know when
you're changing interpretation
of the heap's memory from
one aliasing set to another.
But for correctness,
Metal needs know
when a command is
updating a heap resource
so that other commands can
safely read the results.
This is especially important
because the GPU can execute
multiple commands in parallel.
So to synchronize
access to heap resources,
your application will
create and manage GPU fences
to communicate resource
dependencies across commands.
Let's take a closer look
at how GPU fences work.
So a GPU fence is the timestamp.
It is a reference point in
the GPUs execution timeline.
Now, you can encode
two actions with fences
to synchronize commands.
A command can update a fence
to move the timestamp forward
when the command is finished.
And a command can wait
on a fence to wait
until the GPU has reached
the most recent fence update
before executing.
Okay. Let's bring back
the previous game frame
and I will show you
how to use fences
to synchronize command access
to the aliasing heap resources.
So here again is the example
frame, a three-part frame,
but now we have five
boxes because two
of the render stages, render
passes are split in the vertex
and fragment processing steps.
So we have a shadow
pass, a main pass,
and finally a post-processing
pass
that we will execute
with compute.
So Metal commands are submitted
in serial order to
the command queue.
So maybe it's not quite clear
yet why we need any
synchronization across commands.
But GPUs are very parallel
machines and can operate
on multiple commands
in parallel.
GPUs in our iOS and tvOS
products can execute vertex,
fragment, and compute
commands all in parallel
to maximize GPU utilization.
The GPU can even be working
on multiple frames
at the same time.
All right.
So maybe now you spot a problem.
Look at these two commands
that are highlighted.
They are both updating
the aliasing
and heap resources
at the same time.
We have to use a
fence to fix this.
So first let's bring in a fence.
The post-process command
will update the fence
so that the shadow commands
fragment processing stage can
wait on the fence.
Right? So now the two
commands don't execute
at the same time anymore.
So I'm going to show you how
to encode this fence update
and fence wait with Swift.
First, we create a
fence with a device.
This is a new method
-- no arguments.
Next, let's encode the
post-processing compute encoder
at the end of the first frame.
We first create a
computeCommandEncoder
and encode the dispatches.
But before we end the encoder,
we first update the fence
so that subsequent
commands can wait
until this command has
finished executing.
So in the next frame we would
encode the shadow rendering.
So we create a
renderCommandEncoder
in commandBufB, which
represents the command buffer
for the next frame.
But before drawing the scene,
we first encode a fence wait
to wait until the
post-processing is completed
on the GPU.
Now, notice this time
there are two arguments.
There's a second argument
called beforeStages.
Render commands execute in two
stages -- vertex and fragment.
So Metal allows you to specify
the particular stage that needs
to wait for the fence.
In our example only the
fragment stage needs
to access the heap resources, so
we specify the fragment stage.
Finally, we can render
our shadow maps safely
because we know that this
command will only execute
after the previous frame's
post-processing is complete.
Okay. Let me talk about
some best practices
for command synchronization.
So you know that if you use
heaps, you have to use fences
to synchronize command access.
But you are given this control
because you know you
have more knowledge
about how your resources
are used
and your application will
be more CPU-efficient
than if Metal were to
track all of this for you.
For example, textures
that are initialized once
and never modified don't
even need to be tracked.
And as another example,
resources that are used
together can be tracked together
with a single fence.
So let me summarize the main
ideas of resource heaps.
Create resources faster
with suballocation.
Use your memory budget
more efficiently
with resource aliasing.
And synchronize your
heap updates
across GPU commands
with GPU fences.
Okay. Now I'd like to introduce
another new feature available
in iOS and tvOS:
Memoryless render targets.
Now, this sounds
a little magical,
but I will show you how almost
every Metal app can use this
feature to save a
significant amount of memory
with a single line of code.
So memoryless render
targets are simply textures
that do not allocate any system
memory for the texture contents.
Without any memory backing
the texture contents,
what remains is the
texture's metadata,
such as the texture's dimensions
and internal texture format.
Now obviously this is
a huge memory savings,
but when can you use a
memoryless render target?
You can use them for render pass
attachments that are not stored.
Most Metal apps will have
some attachments associated
with a store action of don't
care or multisample resolve.
And the textures used for those
render pass attachments can
be memoryless.
To make a memoryless
render target,
you can simply create the
texture as you normally would
with an additional
storage mode flag --
MTLStorageModeMemoryless.
That's it.
This feature is supported
only on iOS and tvOS
because it relies
on the tile-based
rendering architecture
of A7 and later GPUs.
Let me show you how
this feature works.
Here on your right we have
two render pass attachment --
a color attachment and
a depth attachment.
Now, A7 and later GPUs
execute render passes one tile
at a time, taking advantage
of a fast GPU tile storage
at the heart of the GPU.
The GPU tile storage contains
tile-sized representations
of your depth, stencil,
and color attachments.
And this tile storage
is completely separate
from the texture backing
and system memory.
Now, in Metal your load and
store actions control how
to initialize the GPU
tile storage and whether
to copy the results from
the GPU tile storage back
to system memory.
If an attachment is not loaded
from memory and it is not stored
to memory, you can
make the texture
for that attachment memoryless
to eliminate the
memory allocation.
Next, I'll describe some
very common scenarios
where you can apply this
feature to your app.
Depth attachments
are frequently used
to enable depth testing
in 3-D scenes.
But the A7 and later GPUs
perform depth testing completely
in GPU tile storage
one tile at a time.
Depth testing does not
need to use system memory.
So if you don't store the depth
texture for use in later passes,
make the texture memoryless
and save the memory.
Let me show you another
opportunity.
When executing multisample
rendering, again,
the A7 and later GPUs
perform all the rendering
in GPU tile storage.
The MSAA color attachment
texture is only used
if you choose to store the
sample data for a later use.
But most apps will choose the
multisample resolve store action
which results directly
from the GPU tile storage
to the resolve color
attachment texture.
So in that case make the
multisample color attachment
texture memoryless and this
is a massive memory savings.
As you can see, the savings
for adopting this
feature are substantial.
By making a 1080p depth
texture memoryless,
your app will save
almost 8 megabytes.
If you are rendering to
the native resolution
of a 12.9-inch iPad Pro,
the savings for the depth
buffer is over 20 megabytes.
And the savings for making a
four times multisample render
target memoryless are even
larger, four times larger.
So use memoryless render
targets to make the most
of your application's
memory budget.
Use the savings to lower the
memory footprint of your game.
Or better yet, use the
savings to add more beautiful
and unique content to your game.
Okay. I'd like to invite
Jose up to tell you all
about the improvements
to the Metal Tools.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, James.
So outside the great additions
to the Metal API we did
some great improvements
to Metal Developer Tools
I want to show you.
First we'll talk about
what's in Metal System Trace.
Than we'll introduce a new
feature called GPU Override.
And we have some very
exciting new features coming
to GPU Frame Debugger.
So what is Metal System Trace?
In the [inaudible] Metal session
we presented this graph showing
you Metal working on
power in CPU and GPU.
Metal System Trace is
a set of instruments
for visualizing just that,
helping you understand
the timeline
of your Metal applications
through the whole graphic
pipeline, from the CPU
to the GPU, and then
on to the display.
Last year at WWDC we
introduced Metal System Trace
for iOS platform.
I highly recommend checking
out last year's presentation
for a great overview
of Metal System Trace.
Later in the fall we
added support for tvOS.
And today we're happy to
announce Metal System Trace
for macOS to help you squeeze
out the last bit of performance
on all Metal platforms.
[ Applause ]
>> We improved Metal System
Trace across the board,
extending the events
that we report.
[Inaudible] events,
we visualized expensive resource
operations to just picking data
from system memory
to video memory.
Like in this case where we
can see painting in macOS,
which is causing a
delay in GPU execution.
Metal System Trace also
displays debug groups,
which make it easier for you
to understand command encoded
relations in your trace.
On macOS we support tracing
multiple GPUs at the same time,
which is unbelievable
for those use cases
where you're distributing
work across different GPUs.
And on iOS we now
display scalar workloads
so that you can diagnose when
you're introducing latency
by rotating or scaling
your views.
You can now use a wider range
of instruments alongside
Metal System Trace
such as Time Profiler,
File Activity,
Allocations, and many more.
Even different views
such as CPU data,
which will show you
CPU core time slices.
These will help you to correlate
Metal events into context,
deepening the understanding
of how the system is
running your application
and allowing you
to diagnose things
such as GPU starvation
caused by CPU stall due
to a [inaudible] operation.
Metal System Trace
captures a wealth of data.
So we made it easier for you
to interpret and navigate.
With the new workload
highlighting, you can focus
on any command encoder
or command buffer
as it works through
the pipeline.
And with with support
for keyboard navigation,
you can quickly move your
selection through your trace.
Finally, I want to introduce
Performance Observation.
And what Performance
Observation does is present you
with a comprehensive list of
the potential issues we found
in your trace from analyzing it.
From display surface
taking too long
to unexpected shader
compilations,
or high GPU execution times,
Performance Observations finds
for you the events which
you are looking for,
which you can navigate
straight to them
from the Performance
Observation list.
All these new additions
will allow you
to tune your Metal
applications to run as smoothly
as you want them to be.
And now for a demonstration
of our awesome GPU
debugging improvements,
let me hand over to
my colleague, Alp.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Jose.
I have a number of great
features to show you today.
So let's dive right in.
I have my app running here,
cruising over beautiful terrain
tessellated to finest details.
Wouldn't it be great to see
this terrain in wire frame
to see triangles individually?
The good news is our newest
feature, GPU Overrides,
gives you ability to modify
your Metal rendering right
from the debug bar while
your app is running.
We have a number of different
overrides you can mix and match,
including wire frame mode.
Let's switch to wire frame mode
to see how tessellated
the terrain is.
Visualizing each
triangle you might want
to tune your tessellation
to fine the balance
between performance
and visual quality.
Normally you'd have to go back
and change your code,
recompile, and run.
But with GPU Overrides,
you can experiment
with your tessellation scaling
right from the Overrides menu.
Let's set scaling to 25%.
Now we have far less
triangles but lost some
of the interesting details.
Let's try 75%.
I think this looks better.
Let's see it without
the wire frame.
Okay. I like this one.
Now, we have less triangles
than what we started with
but still have all
the nice details.
And with the performance gains,
I can add more cool
effects to my scene.
So as seen here, GPU Overrides
is a great tool to help
with initial diagnosis
for some of the visual
and performance problems
in your scene.
Next, let's capture the frame
to show you some of the features
that will greatly improve
your debugging workflow.
The frame capture is
done and I am looking
for the terrain resources to
see how we are [inaudible].
Let's switch to all GPU
objects in Resource Center
where you can see all
your textures and buffers.
So we have all of
resources here.
And going over everything
one by one
to find terrain resources
could take some time.
This is where the new
filter bar comes to help.
You can filter by any properties
you see here, such as label,
type, size, or details.
Since I labeled all
my resources,
I'll just filter by terrain.
And right here I have
all the resources used
for rendering the terrain.
Now that I found the terrain
patches buffer, what I would
like to do is to see where
I'm actually using it.
With a simple drag and drop I
can filter function navigator
to show me all the
calls that's made
to terrain patches
buffer just like that.
In this case, I see where it
is calculated using compute
and where it says [inaudible]
while rendering the terrain.
This filter is really powerful.
I can also use any
other properties
of the bound resources
to filter draw calls.
For example, if you
filter by SRGB,
you'll see all the draw calls
that are using a texture
with SRGB pixel format.
This is a natural
way of navigating
around your frame quickly.
Next, let's move
to bound GP objects
to see how we are using these
resources to render the terrain.
In bound mode your
resources are grouped
under different sections
based on the stage
of the Metal pipeline
they are used
in so you know exactly
where to look.
Looking at the vertex stage,
terrain patches is a buffer
bound to multiple binding points
with different offsets.
Let's use our only buffer
[inaudible] to inspect the data.
All the vertex data
has stayed nicely
with the layout except
[inaudible] Metal function
with patches.
So this is using the
exact same struct
as your post-vertex function.
And we have a color data here.
It recognizes the word color
and visualizes the real color
of the value right in there.
Since this is a large buffer
that contains different types
of data, I have added
some debug markers
with the new [inaudible] API,
which makes it extra easy
to find what you
are looking for.
With the layout menu,
you can jump straight
to any other available layout
you would like to inspect.
Looking at individual
buffers is great.
What is even better is the
new input attribute view
which lets you see
all your vertex data
as your vertex shader sees it.
Input attributes collects all
the data from your instances,
tessellation factor buffers,
and your stage in data,
then provides you a single view
to look at all of it together.
In this case we are rendering
instances with multiple patches
and I can see what data belongs
to which patch of an instance.
So that was a quick look at some
of our newest GPU Frame
Debugger features.
Let's switch back to
slides and wrap up.
[ Applause ]
So you've just seen some
of our newest GPU Frame
Debugger features.
I would like to tell
you about two more.
With the new Extended Validation
mode the GPU Frame Debugger can
perform even deeper
analysis of your application,
providing recommendations
[inaudible] the optimal texture
usage or storage mode
for your resources.
You can enable this mode from
the Xcode scheme editors.
And the new support
for stand-alone Metal Library
Projects lets you create Metal
libraries to be shared
in multiple apps
or include multiple of
them in a single app just
like any other framework
or library.
So we talked about features
that will greatly improve
your tool's experience.
Now let's summarize what we have
seen so far in this session.
We have seen the great additions
to Metal API with tessellation,
resource heaps and
memoryless render targets,
then we showed you improved
tools, Metal System Trace
and GPU Frame Debugger.
Be sure to stick around
for part two this afternoon
where I will talk about
function specialization
and function resource
read-writes, wide color
and texture assets,
and additions
to Metal performance shaders.
For more information
about this session,
please check the link online.
You can catch the
video and get links
to documentation
and sample code.
We had great sessions yesterday,
which are available online.
And this afternoon we have
What's New in Metal, Part2,
then Advanced Metal Shader
Optimization in this room.
Thanks for coming,
and have a great WWDC.
[ Applause ]