[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Good morning, everyone.
Thank you for coming.
My name is Megan Gardner.
I am a Software Engineer
on the Game Center Team
and today we're going
to be talking
about what's new in Game Center.
So if you don't know what
Game Center is already,
Game Center is Apple's
social gaming network.
It allows you, as developers,
to define leaderboards
which your users can
then submit scores to,
also define achievements
that your players can earn.
We also have challenges which
leverage both leaderboards
and achievements to add
a multiplayer element
to your single player games.
We also have two
multiplayer API's,
both real-time and turn-based.
And we ship all of these
things on iOS, macOS, tvOS,
and this year we are
announcing watchOS.
So what's new?
We've got a few new
things this year.
First is we have a great new way
of sending multiplayer invites.
Next we have big news
for the Game Center app
if you haven't figured
it out already.
We have a brand new API for
persistent game sessions
that we're really excited about.
And we're also announcing
Apple Watch support.
Now we don't have time
to talk about Apple Watch
in this session, but if that's
what you're interested in,
I really suggest that you
go to the "Game Technologies
for Apple Watch" later this
afternoon in this room.
So let's talk
about message-based
multiplayer invites.
Now you can play with
anyone that you can message.
Currently our multiplayer
for Game Center pretty
much looks like this.
This is our
GKMatchmakerViewController
and this is what most of you are
using to set up your matches.
This is a built-in
UI that we have done.
It allows your users to be able
to invite their Game
Center friends as well
as do play now which
is automatch.
Some of you have
implemented GKMatchmaker
which is our programmatic
API which allows you
to do your own UI and
set up your own invites.
But if you've been using
GKMatchmakerViewController,
it now looks like this.
This is our new integrated
Messages View Controller.
You'll notice some differences.
There's no bubbles but that's
not the most important part.
It now integrates
directly in with Messages
which will allow your users
to be able to send a message
to anyone in their
Contacts and then be able
to play a game with them.
So let's see what
this looks like.
This is the Multiplayer View
Controller in Doodle Jump.
You can click Play Now
and automatch will work
just as it has before.
However, we're more interested
in seeing what happens
when we click Invite Friends.
So that will bring in this
new Messages View Controller.
You can see we have this
beautiful rich link here
that we've got.
We've got the little Doodle
Jump icon in the corner.
I added a little bit of text
that can tell your users
about what this link is
going to let them do.
And this is all based on
iCloud technology so all
of your users will
need to be signed
into iCloud for this to work.
You can then start
typing in the To field.
This will autocomplete to
Contacts or you can just type
in a email address or phone
number of anyone that you know
or anyone that you just met.
Or you can click on that
Plus button which is going
to bring in the Contacts.
So these are all my Contacts
that I have Messages
information for.
You'll also see that there's
a Recents tab in the middle.
That is where your Game Center
friends are going to be located
as well as anyone that your
users have recently played
on Game Center.
And Nearby also functions the
same way that Nearby has worked
in that it will be looking
for players on local network
that are also playing this game.
So I'm going to click on Alisha,
invite my friend,
Alisha, to play.
And then we'll click Add
and it's going to fill her
in into that To field.
You can then, this functions
just exactly as Messages.
This is basically Messages UI
so you're users can
add additional text
and then it's going to
send to all the players.
If I clicked on a Game Center
player, their name is going
to show up in gray and
they will getting a Game
Center notification.
They're not going
to get some sort
of weird Game Center iMessage.
It will come in as
a notification.
So if we click on that Send
button, then that will send it
to Alisha and this is
what it's going to look
like on Alisha's screen.
She can then tap the link
to accept the invite,
and that will take her
directly into the game,
and start connecting
just like it would have
if she had tapped
on the notification.
And the same functionality
we'll have
if she did not have Doodle
Jump, then it will take her
to the store where she can
then download and play just
like she would be able
to from a notification.
Now I said that there's
nothing that you need to do
in order to implement this.
We have just replaced
the View Controller
so if you have been using
this View Controller,
then you've got this just
straight out of the box.
As soon as iOS 10 is shipped
all of your users will be able
to do this and invite
anyone that they know.
They will no longer be limited
to their Game Center friends.
However, we have one thing
that you can customize
if you would like, which
is this rich link image.
So you'll notice right here it's
the Game Center icon currently.
If you would like to change
that to be something else
that you feel more appropriately
represents your game,
or more appropriately indicates
that this is a gaming invite,
or a fun thing that people will
want to click on, then you can,
all you need to do
is add this file:
GKMessageInvite to your bundle.
And the same way that we will
just pull that out if you wanted
to customize your notification
sound, we'll just pull that out
and customize your rich link.
Notice this is the same
rich link technology
that is being used for
Safari and so it's used
to taking a wide
variety of images.
So what does this mean
for Game Center Friends?
Well, we don't need
friends anymore
because we can play with anyone.
So we're freezing
the friends list.
But you will still
be able to see any
of the Game Center
friends that you have
in that Recents Player tab.
And you can still
pull the friends.
Friends still exists.
We're not deleting them.
They're still there.
But you won't be able
to send, receive,
or respond to any
more friend Requests.
And because of that,
GKFriendRequestCompose
ViewController is
now deprecated.
It wasn't really used
that much anyway.
So what does that mean
for the Game Center app?
Well, if you've downloaded
The Siege,
you might notice some changes.
Well, what is the Game
Center app used for?
In iOS 9 it was basically used
to manage your account,
manage your friends.
You could browse
your games list.
You could look at
your leaderboards,
check out your achievements,
view your challenges,
send challenges, and
also view your turns.
Well, it turns out all of these
things you can basically do
in other places in the system
and more importantly,
in your app.
And so we have removed
the Game Center app.
So where did we do
all these things?
[ Laughter ]
[ Applause ]
If you want to manage
your account,
you can do that in settings.
If you want to manage
your friends,
you can still do
that in settings.
If you want to browse your
games, we've got the App Store,
you can look at your
Home screen.
You view your leaderboards,
achievements, and challenges
from GKGameCenterViewController.
If you're not using
the View Controller,
you can also do your own UI.
If you're not presenting
challenges or leaderboards
and achievements in your
game, we strongly suggest
that you start doing that now.
And you can also view and take
your turns from GKMatchmaker,
GKTurnBasedMatchmaker
ViewController.
So we've removed the app.
Everything is really
available in other places and,
more importantly, in your app.
We would love our users to
spend, your users to spend,
more time in your app.
We've got the rest of the phone.
We don't need any
more of their time.
And so we've removed the app.
Now let's talk about Sessions.
This is our brand new
API and we're really,
really excited about this.
This is a brand new
way to multiplay.
So Game Center Multiplayer,
what does it look right now?
We basically have
our two main API's
with real-time and turn-based.
Real-time will connect
just two to four players.
Those connections will require
like an immediate handshake.
If anyone drops from
that connection,
then that whole connection
will be lost.
You're just passing
data back and forth.
And as soon as that match is
over all of that data is gone.
Turn-based can connect
to 16 players.
We have a very formal
API for passing of turns
and also exchanges but
you kind of really have
to follow those rules and you
have to make sure your game
like fits within that structure.
And all games are stored
on the Game Center server
until they are aged out.
So what is Sessions?
Sessions is our new
iCloud-based multiplayer.
So we have this great
generalized interface for saving
and sharing game data.
These are easily shareable
little instances of data
that people can share
with people
that they would like
to play with.
It's a completely
flexible game structure.
We don't impose anything on you.
You can do whatever you want.
And we have really stable,
solid real-time streams
that you can set up
within these sessions.
And this is going to allow
you to play with anyone.
So what does a Session
look like?
So we have two main
items that we have.
We've got our game data.
It's probably one of the
more important parts.
But also equally
important is their players.
And really this is all that
you need and all the basics
that you have to have
to have a session,
is a player and some game data.
You can have multiple players
which is useful if you would
like to play with other people.
We also have the ability to send
messages between those players.
These messages will come in
as Game Center notifications.
So you can have those messages
being passed back and forth
between players or multiple
players can send multiple
messages all at the same time.
Along with these messages we
have the ability to badge.
So you can send those messages
and also badge those players
to let them know that there's
something within your game,
something within that session,
that they might want
to take care of.
Now I only show four players
here but we can actually have
up to 100 players in a single
session which is a lot more
than we've been able
to have before.
And we can have multiple
different kinds of sessions.
So you can have small sessions
that have one or two players.
You can have four players,
100 players, seven players.
Those players can be
functionally grouped
onto different teams.
And you can have all
of these sessions up
and your player can be in
all of these different kinds
of sessions all at
the same time.
We also have real-time streams
so if you're in this session
and you would like to be able to
pass data quickly back and forth
between your different players,
then your players merely need
to set their connection states
and we will be setting these
pipes up in the background
that will allow the
players to be able
to start communicating
with each other.
So, let's get into the
actual code, the actual API
of what makes up a session.
So we've got a couple
of classes.
We've got GKGameSession which
is going to allow your players
to basically interact
with that session data
as well as the other players.
We have GKCloudPlayer which
is a player in a session.
We have GKEventListener
which will help you know
when important things happen
on any of your sessions
that your players are in.
And we also have
GKGameSessionError
which will give you a little
bit more specific errors
that you might encounter
when working with Sessions.
So let's talk about
GKGameSession.
So this is your main workhorse.
This is where almost
all of the work is going
to be done per session.
It allows you to do
basically everything.
You can create a
session, leave sessions,
load and store your game
data, share your sessions,
add your players, remove your
players, see who's playing,
send your notifications,
set and clear your badges,
join your streams, send
data on those streams.
Basically everything you're
going to be doing is going
to be interacting
with GKGameSession.
Some more details about that.
With your game data
you can store
up to 512 kilobytes of data.
This data is going to be
stored in the user's iCloud
so it's not something
associated with your game.
And the user is going to
have it in their iCloud.
It will count against
their iCloud limits.
And it's going to follow
CloudKit conventions in terms
of who owns that data, how
the data is shared, privacy,
and what happens when
that data is deleted.
Messages and Badges,
as I've said,
come in as Game Center
notifications
and they're badged as such.
And badging is now going to
be more directly controlled
by you, as the developer.
We'll get into that a little
bit more but it's going
to be very clear where that
badge number is coming from
and you should be able to
understand why it is what it is
and change it to pretty
much whatever you want.
And we also have these
real-time streams
which basically leverage
existing Apple infrastructure.
This is running on the same
technology that runs FaceTime
as well as iMessage
so it's really strong,
it's really stable, and it's
built to carry a lot of data.
So if we want to make a
session, what do we need to do?
Well, first we need a title,
something to describe
the session.
Either you can define that or
you can get that from your user.
You need your container ID
which your iCloud container
that you set up with your app.
And also set up a container that
can be used across multiple apps
so if you want multiple
games to be able to access
that same data, say if
you had your free version,
your pay version, or, you
know, other different kinds
of versions of your
game, they will still,
if you set that up correctly,
they will still all be able
to access that same data.
And you can also set the max
number of streaming players.
There's a hard limit of
16 players that can be
in that real-time stream but
if you would like to make
that lower, or something
different, then you can lower
that when you create
the session but you need
to decide that when you create.
So once you've, so you just will
call createSessionInContainer
with all of that
relevant information
and that will give you a session
that you can start
manipulating and using.
One of the first things you're
probably going to want to do
with the session is
be able to figure how
to load and save your data.
Any player that's in a
session can access that data.
It's just one big blob
that everybody plays with.
And there's a little
bit of metadata provided
with that session that will help
you avoid and resolve conflicts
which is last modified date
and last modified player.
So you'll know who was
touching it last and whether
or not it's important for you
to save or if your data is more
than likely up to date.
So you can just call
loadDataWithCompletionHandler,
that will pass you your data.
You'd also probably
like to save your data.
As I said before, 512 kilobytes
but you can do whatever
you want with that data.
It can be whatever
will fit in that size.
So you'll call saveData
with completionHandler.
If there is a conflict, if
someone else has tried to save
in the interim, you will get
an error and you will get
that conflicting data back.
And we'll talk a little bit
more about that in a second.
Anytime someone does save
data there's an Event Listener
that goes along with that.
So if you set up your
Event Listener to listen
for a session player to save
data, then you will know
when someone else has saved
data and you will know
that you will more than
likely will need to update
and resolve any conflicts
local you have with that data.
So as I said, Save
conflicts can occur.
And this will happen where two
players who were basically going
to try to save data in
about the same time.
Since there's no real formal
turn passing it's very possible
that two players can be
taking a turn at the same time
if that's how you design
and implement your game.
So say we've got Players Two
and Three and they both try
to save at the same time.
Well, one of them is
going to win so I'm going
to say it's Player Two.
That means when Player Three
tries to save they're going
to get an error and that
conflicted data will
be returned.
Now you are going to
need to figure out how
to resolve this conflict.
Since we have no
specific formalities
for what this data is we also
don't know what the data means.
And so it's going to be up
to you to architect your data
in such a way that it's going
to be easy for you to figure
out what those conflicts
are, resolve those conflicts,
and recall saved data in order
for that data to
actually be saved.
If you do not recall saved data,
your data will not be saved
and you need to continue
to call saved data
until you return
without a conflict.
And then everything
will be up to date.
Everything will be the
same for all your users
and you can continue forward.
And then everything
will be grand.
We've talked about
having multiplayers, well,
how do you get additional
players into your session?
Any player that's in a session
can invite other players
to join.
Basically you're going
to be provided with a URL
that you need to
get to someone else.
You can send this via iMessage,
email, Twitter, Facebook,
print it out, paste
it on a tree --
that's probably not
the best way.
But as long as you can get
this URL to other people
and they can click on
it, then it will be able
to be added to that session.
The easiest way to do this
is through the share sheet
because it just pops
up right there
and you can send off a message.
And that's probably the
easiest way to do that.
So if like the Player One, if
they pull the URL from their,
from the session, they set up an
iMessage with that share sheet
to send to Player Two.
They've added a little
bit of text, "Hey,
want you want to play with me?"
It'll come out as
this iCloud URL.
It will be sent to Player
Two, they will click on it,
and as soon as they click
on it Player Two is added.
So in order to get the URL
you just call getShareURLWith
CompletionHandler.
It will give you the URL
that you can then do
whatever you want with.
And then anytime
a player is added
to a session the Event Listener
didAddPlayer will be called.
And that will let you know
that someone else has joined
your session and be able
to proceed with your
game accordingly.
So we've been talking
about players
so what exactly are they?
Well, we've got GKCloudPlayer.
This is different
than the GK Players
that you've been
dealing with before.
GKCloudPlayer is only for,
to be used for Sessions.
It basically has two pieces of
data, a player ID that is unique
to your app as well
as the display name,
that is what the user will have
as what they want they
name to be displayed.
This is not a GKPlayer
object at all.
If you try to use this for a
leaderboard, for achievements,
for other multiplayer, for
anything else, it will not work.
So please don't do that.
Everyone will be
very disappointed.
So how do we get
our Cloud Players?
Basically you can get your
current signed in player.
Most of the things in Sessions
basically are going to be called
from your current player though
there's not a whole lot of need
to make sure that
you have the player,
that you are then saying, "Oh,
this player is saving
this data."
All that's handled for
you in the background.
But you might be
interested to know basically
like who owns this session?
So you might want to know if
the session is being deleted,
if other player owns it,
then that will delete the
data for everyone else.
And you also might want to
be able to clear your badges,
send messages, be a
little more aware of that.
You can also get any of
the other players that are
in the session, it's just
a property on that session.
And that's the best way that
you're going to need to be able
to send those messages
to those other players,
especially setting
and clearing badges.
So speaking of messages and
badges, let's talk about that.
These messages, we say
messages but they're coming
in as Game Center notifications.
As I said before, all
players can send messages
at any time to any other player.
Those messages are
easily localizable.
You can also send a little bit
of data along with that message
if there's any sort of relevant
information that you might want
to pass to the other players
about what this message is about
or what they might want to
be looking at specifically.
And you can also optionally
badge the message recipient
so anyone that gets this
message can also receive a badge
as well as that message.
So what does the code look like?
sendMessageWithLocalizedKey.
You've got all these arguments,
who to send it to, whether
or not you would like
to badge those players.
And the Event Listener
that is called is session
didReceiveMessage fromPlayer.
And that will be called any
time a notification comes
in to let the player know
that something has come
in that they might
want to be aware of
or might want to deal with.
And badges.
So I've said badges can be
included with these messages.
So basically anytime you send a
message you can basically turn
that badge state
on for that player.
You've got one badge per
session so basically it means
like there's something you need
to deal with or there's not.
And these badges can be set
and cleared at any time.
So if you send a message
and then you're like, "Hey,
I need some help with this thing
that we're doing in the game,"
and then no one shows
up you can, you know,
clear those badges and
be like, "Never mind.
I didn't want to
talk to you anyway."
And so that you can keep all
of that badge data
relevant and up to date.
The app icon will
show the overall tally
so if you've got three sessions
and all of them are badges,
that app icon will say three.
If you have one, you know,
only one of them is
badge, it will say one.
We could aggregate that for
you but based off of the,
what is set in that session
it should be very clear
where that badge
number is coming from.
So let's talk about
managing these sessions.
So we've made a session.
We've saved it.
We've loaded it.
We've loaded the data.
We've sent it to some players.
Your user has turned
off your app.
They've done some other things.
You've come back.
You want to load those
sessions and make sure
that you've got all
the relevant data
so that they can
start playing again.
So the first thing you'll
want to call is Load Sessions.
loadSessionsInContainer,
that container,
that same app container
from the beginning
that you made the session in.
This will load the bare bones
information for all the sessions
that your local player
is a part of.
Then based off of that data
you're going to want to look
and figure out which session
you're going to want to load.
That session has two main
pieces to identify it.
One is that title that you gave
us but the title is not unique.
You can make it anything
that you want.
And so that's not enough to be
able to just load a session.
Upon creation of a session we
will give you an identifier
and that is what you will
need to use in order to load
that specific session.
Call loadSessionWithIdentifier
and that will give you
all the information
for the session including
everything that you will need
to do in order to start loading
that data, sending messages
to other players, and
continuing on with your game.
You also might want
to delete a session.
If you call
removeSessionWithIdentifier,
that's the same identifier
that we just talked about,
if the player does
not own the session,
it will merely remove
them from the session.
It will not actually
delete any of that data.
However, if you're
deleting a session
that that player created,
then it will delete that data,
not only for that player,
but for everyone
else in that session.
And that may be one
of those times
that who your local player is,
figure out if they are going
to be doing that to
everyone, and maybe send,
alert the user that,
"Hey, you're deleting this
for everyone," so that they
know what they're doing.
At any time a player is removed
the Event Listener will be
called didRemovePlayer
so that you'll know
that someone has left
and that you can continue
to update your game accordingly.
So let's talk about
Game Session Streams.
So this is the real-time
element of Sessions.
Everything else up until
this point has kind
of sound pretty turn-based.
You're saving.
You're passing messages.
We also have the ability to have
real-time elements to your game.
So Game Session Streams, you are
going to be able to connect any
of the players that are
currently in that session.
So everyone who is in that
session, if they would
like to start sending
data to each other,
that is how you're
going to do it.
You can basically see the
status of any other players
that are in the session.
You can send data to
all the players that are
in the connection
that you've set up.
And you will be able to add
and drop players at any time
without having to
restart that connection.
So you can someone join in and
like two people can be playing,
third person wants to come
in and join, you don't have
to reset everything up.
As soon as they start
they'll start receiving data.
They can start sending data.
You don't have to do any
handshakes for handling all
of that in the background
for you.
So how do we set
these connections up?
Basically you just need
to set the connection
state for that player.
So you would just call
setConnectionState
with completionHandler.
This can fail for a
number of reasons but one
of the reasons could
be if the max players
for that session has
already been reached.
So if this is the 17th
player who is trying to join
that stream and you've
got that max 17 set,
then this will actually fail
and they won't actually be able
to join into the stream.
You can see whether the players
are set with a specific state,
basically the states are
connected and disconnected
so you can see how many other
players are currently connected
and who they are.
And anytime a player either
changes that connection state,
either connects or disconnects,
the Event Listener session
player didChangeConnectionState
will be called.
And so you can know whether
or not that is changed
and how many people you
are currently playing with.
Once you set up the connection
then you're going to want
to probably start sending data.
So all of the data is
going to be sent to all
of the connected players.
You can send this either
reliably or unreliably,
just the same as our
real-time API now.
Whether or not it's more
important to make sure
that those players get that data
or more important to make sure
that they're getting the
data as fast as possible.
And any time data is
sent the Event Listener
didReceiveDataFromPlayer will be
called and you'll be able to get
that data and update your
game locally, and continue
on with playing your game.
So that's all like the basic
bones of what makes up sessions.
So let's talk about
some examples
of what this actually
really looks
like when you're
actually making a game.
So first basically
you've got, you know,
your basic turn-based game.
So you've set up your session.
You've got your game data.
You've added a few players.
Maybe it's Player One's turn.
They're going to start by
figuring out what their turn is
and they're going
to save that data.
That data can then be loaded by
Players Two, Three, and Four.
Message Player One can then
send a message to Player Two,
sending it that badge
and saying,
"Hey, it's your turn now."
Maybe you would like to do that.
Player Two can load up
their game, start playing,
figure out what they would
want to do with that new data,
take their turn, save that data,
and then pass the turn
on to Player Four.
Since there is no specified way
in which these turns can
be passed that's up to you.
You can pass it from One
to Two, Two to Three,
Four to One, whatever you want.
There is no specified way
in which these turns can
be passed and, frankly,
we don't know what you're doing.
So you pass the game
on to Player Four.
They get to take their
turn and continue on.
So you've got all the
elements that you need
for a really basic
turn-based game.
You can also do a
real-time game.
So you've got all of
your players set up.
You can then basically
have everyone turn
on their connection states.
As soon as these connection
states are turned on we will set
up the pipes in the
background to allow them
to communicate with each other.
And as soon as all
of those are set
up then your players can start
sending data to everyone else.
And then this data will
be just sent as long
as these connections
are available.
And then with sessions,
if there's any sort
of information you would like
to be able to store at the end,
such as, you know,
who won, or rankings,
or anything for this
particular real-time game,
you do have that ability
to have a little bit more
of a persistent data
that you might want
to save with that session.
So those are your
real basic examples.
But the real power session
comes in in being able
to do much more complicated
games.
So say you've got
a game session.
It's a turn-based game but you
want to do a little bit more
of a complicated turn.
They've got a game.
It's got some trading
card elements
so when it's the player's
turn you might be able
to trade cards, maybe brick
for sheep or something.
And so the things that you
might be able to accomplish
with table talk on an actual
board game you can now more
easily accomplish with sessions.
So say it's Player One's
turn and they want to trade
with the other players and so
they send out a message and say,
"Hey, I'd like trade
brick for sheep.
Anyone interested?"
So you can send that message.
You can send a little bit
of data with that message
to let the users know,
"Hey, this is what I want,"
and send it out to everyone.
Say Player Four is
like, "Oh, yeah.
That sounds really good.
You know, I'll take that trade,"
or, "Yeah, well, you know,
that doesn't work for me.
How about wheat for sheep?"
or something else.
So they can send a message back
to Player One, badging them
and saying, "Hey, this is, I
either, I'll accept your trade
or I have a different trade."
You can send that
message back and forth,
figure out what you want to do.
As soon as Player
One decides, "Okay.
Well, I'll take that trade,"
or, "I won't take that trade,"
they can their turn,
unbadge everyone else,
and save their data,
unbadge themselves,
and then pass the
turn on to Player Two.
We also have the ability
to more easily join
into multiplayer games
that might be a little
bit more complicated.
So say you've got a multiplayer
game that's a little bit more
like a King of the
Hill type stuff.
You've got all these people in
session but you only want two
of them to be able
to play at a time.
So you're going to
start up your session.
You've got Players One and Two.
They're going to turn on
their connection state.
They're going to join into
a game and they're going
to pass their data
back and forth.
They're going to have
a little head-to-head,
a little one-on-one, and fight.
And one of those players
will be eliminated.
In this case let's
say Player One.
And then Player Two
will go on and then play
with the next person in line.
You don't have to stop
your game in any way.
You don't have to set up any
sort of connection screen.
As soon as Player Three sets
their connection state then you
can start sending that data
back and forth to Players Two
and Three immediately
and they will be able
to have their little
bout, see who wins.
This time [inaudible] and
then Player Four can then come
in and join in the fray.
They can make that
connection and continue on.
And you can continue
on with this,
continuing to do any
sort of round-robin.
If you've got like 100 players,
you can go through
all 100 players.
And just continue to
have a little King
of the Hill style fight.
And then you can store
that data to your game data
that will allow to have a little
bit more persistent rankings
and a little bit more persistent
[inaudible] among the people
that are in this session.
Another situation
that we might run
into is assisted single player.
So say you've got a
single player game.
You're using Sessions to
basically store your data
which is totally fine.
You can absolutely do a single
player game with Sessions
and basically use this as
a way to store your data
and send your data so that all
of your data can be updated
across all of your
devices very easily.
But say your player is having
a little bit of a hard time.
They've been playing this
game for a little while.
Then they can't get
passed this level.
They're having a
really hard time.
Well, if you implement
your game as such,
then Player One can then share
their game with another player.
And so they can bring
in Player Two.
And then you can
either add some elements
that will allow Player
Two to help Player One
through that level,
through some co-op methods,
or you could even just allow
Player Two to just play
that level for Player One
so that they can get past
that really sticky point in
your game, allowing Player One
to have a little
bit more enjoyment.
So Player Two can come in, say,
do whatever you would
like to let them do.
Save that data, so
the game data.
And then they can lead
themselves, removing themselves
from that game and Player
One can continue on playing
that game just as if Player
Two had never actually even
been there.
So that is Game Sessions.
This is going to allow you
to be able to basically play
with anyone, anyone that has
an iCloud account you can
play with.
You don't need to be their
friend in any sense of the word.
So much more flexible game
structure that is going
to allow you, as developers,
to be able to set up your games
in whatever manner
you would like.
We have really, really simple
multiplayer connections.
They are really easy to
set up, really stable.
They allow for lots of data
to be passed back and forth.
And we're really excited
to see what new possible game
styles you're going to come
up with because of
the power of Sessions.
Because of this mixing
of turn-based
and real-time elements for
these games we're really excited
to see what you're
going to come up with.
So that's what's new in
Game Center this year.
We had our new message-based
multiplayer invite
which are now going
to allow you to play
with anyone that
you can message.
We have removed the
Game Center app.
We have those persistent
game sessions
that we just talked about.
And we have also announced
Apple Watch support.
If you would like any more
information on this session,
you can go to this link.
We are session number 611.
And we have a few
related sessions
that you might be interested in.
We have the "Game Technologies
for Apple Watch" later
on in this afternoon.
We've also had several
sessions earlier this week
that you can go and watch the
videos for, and several others,
even more than what's
listed here.
Thank you for coming
and have a great WWDC.
[ Applause ]