[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Hello everybody.
Hello again if you just came
from the previous session,
thanks for staying.
And hello if you're new.
Hello to everyone downstairs,
and hello to everyone
watching online.
My name is Nick, I'm joined
today by my colleague, Leo,
and we're going to
talk about what's new
with Wallet and Apple Pay.
First of all, we're going to
have an update for Wallet.
We're going to talk
about passes.
about some new features
for banks and for retailers.
And then we're going
to talk about WatchKit,
now you can use Apple Pay
not just to pay in-store
on Apple Watch, but also
inside WatchKit Apps.
We'll also talk about something
I'm really excited about
and that's the new extensions on
iOS, Siri, maps, and messages.
All of these new
extension points
that can be enabled
with Apple Pay.
And finally we'll talk about
something exciting and new,
I think you're all going
to love, testing Apple Pay
and the new Sandbox environment.
Let's get started.
What's new with PassKit.
So, hopefully you'll be aware
that Wallet isn't just Apple
Pay, it's passes as well.
And there's no better
time to start using passes
because more users are
engaging with Wallet
than ever, due to Apple Pay.
More people are opening
the Wallet App,
more people are using it.
Now, we don't have time today to
run through the pass ecosystem,
but we do have some
resources for you.
I'll tell you a little bit
about them just to remind you,
don't worry, not too much.
Passes enable you to get
gift cards, boarding passes,
rewards cards, event
tickets, membership cards,
and more directly into the
user's iPhone or Apple Watch.
And you can distribute
these passes in many ways,
through an app, through email,
SMS or iMessage,
web link or QR code.
And these passes can
be updated remotely.
And these updates show up
on a user's lock screen.
Things like date changes, for
an airline ticket, or relevancy.
Your passes can be relevant,
if you're near the store,
they'll show up on
the lock screen.
We have a session that talks
a little bit about some
of these passes and provides
you some more resources.
It's the home for
Apple Pay and more,
it was last year's session.
And there's plenty
of great resources
at developer.apple.com.
Let me talk now about
a few new changes.
Some things we've
changed over the past year
that maybe you didn't notice.
One of them was app placement.
We've actually changed the
pass design a little bit,
this happened in iOS 9.3.
Apps are now placed
on the front of passes
and these app icons
can deep link directly
into your applications.
So these are great for
things like gift card top-up,
if you're a gift card pass
and you want and easy way
for the user to quickly
top it off, or an airline,
you want to go to the app
for more information
about the flight.
And it's very easy to add this,
you just need to add the pass
to your pass, the apps ID,
it's Adam ID from iTunes,
and also its URL scheme to deep
link in if you want to do that.
Last year we also
introduced a new type of pass,
the value-added services pass.
So passes can now transmit
information securely over NFC.
Things like loyalty
card information,
if you're in the US you might
have used the Walgreens Pass,
which lets you transmit
over NFC.
And support for value-added
passes has grown
over the past year for many
points of sale systems.
Verifone, Ingenico and
many other manufacturers
of payment terminals now
support this protocol.
There's some things
you may not know
about value-added
service passes,
they also support what we
call a one tap experience.
It looks a little like this.
It's where you actually
place the phone
on the payment terminal
and you'll transmit both
your payment information
and your loyalty
information in a single tap.
So it's deeply integrated
into the purchase process.
This also works with
Apple Watch as well.
Now these value-added service
passes can also be distributed
over NFC, and you can even
sign up for loyalty programs
from these NFC distributed
passes directly from Wallet,
to be shared and personalized.
You can actually sign up for
a loyalty program right there.
Now, there are a few caveats to
the value-added service passes.
One of them you might be
aware is that passes need
to be signed using a
different certificate.
Regular passes are signed
with a certificate you create
at the developer portal, but
value-added service passes need
to be signed with an
NFC signing certificate.
Now, you need to request
these certificates.
You can contact us
to find out more.
I'm actually going
to have a link
at the end of this presentation.
So you can go and
request more information
about using value-added
service passes.
And we're also going to have
some engineers in the labs.
We got a lab right
after this session,
so if you have any
questions please come down,
we'd love to talk to you.
Let's talk about a few other
new features in PassKit.
Now these are specific
to card issuers,
but I think they're
pretty interesting,
even if you're not
a card issuer,
you might be interested
to know about them.
We offer some unique features
for card issuers
who use Apple Pay.
We also now support store
credit and debit cards.
Here's a Kohl's card.
So if you have a store
card you can add them.
So these aren't just for banks,
they're for retailers as well.
One really great feature
is app provisioning.
Now, we added this
last year and a couple
of apps have already adopted
it, Discover is one of them.
This lets you set up cards
in Apple Pay directly
from your own app.
You never need to leave you app,
to open Wallet, to
open preferences.
And it's available to any
existing Apple Pay issuer.
Now the API is documented
on developers.apple.com.
But you can also contact
us for more information.
We actually have an email
address, which I'll show
at the end, and we're going to
have people in the labs to help.
We also have this
great new button style,
which you can use
both for adding cards,
but also for adding
regular passes.
So if you're just
a pass developer,
you can use the new
PKPaymentButton style I'm
showing you here.
I'll have some codes to show
you how to do that in a minute.
Now something that's new
in iOS 10 is specifically
for card issuers and retailers
who might have partnerships,
either co-branded cards, or
they've got a partnership
with a bank, we now
let you enable a new
in-store experience.
You can present your cards
directly from your apps.
A really good use case of
this, you can redeem a coupon
from your app and immediately
present a payment method.
So maybe your app is
enabled with iBeacons,
it's got a great
in-store experience.
So you go into the store, you
redeem a coupon in the app,
you just press a button
and you can immediately pay
with Apple Pay.
The card could be right
there in your app.
It's a really easy API to use.
It's just on the Pass Library.
And you can use the new
PKPaymentButton style
for some consistent branding.
And this is the style .inStore.
We have another style I
just showed you to add it
to different class actually,
it's an Add to Pass Button,
but take a look
at the documentation
for more information.
Another feature that's pretty
interesting is associating your
applications with your cards.
Again, this is great
if you're a retailer
and you have a co-branded
card or you have a partnership
with an issuing bank, you
can associate your app
with your store or
program cards,
which means it can default,
if the user wants to do that.
Here's the screen you'll
get for a VAS pass,
but it's the same
for payment passes.
You can default your card
when paying over NFC,
or new in iOS 10
you can also default
when paying with an application.
And also a website if
you're taking advantage
of the new Apple Pay
on the web stuff.
Now the great thing about most
of this is that no API required.
It's actually built
into the card itself.
All you need to do is get
your app, and its Adam ID
and URL scheme into the pass
when it's added to device.
Now to do that you can
talk to your issuing bank,
or if you're an issuing
bank, you can come talk
to us using the contact
information at the end
of the session, or come
and see us in the labs.
So that's some of the
new stuff in PassKit.
I want to talk now about Apple
Pay and what's new in Apple Pay.
And I also want to tell you
how Apple Pay has been doing.
So Apple Pay is an easy,
secure and private way
to pay both in-store
and within applications.
And it's got amazing
customer satisfaction.
It has one of the highest
customer satisfaction rates
of any payment method.
And Apple Pay is usable
today within applications.
You can pay using Apple
Pay directly from apps.
And thousands of apps have
already adopted worldwide
in the US, in China,
an example here.
We've recently announced
we're launching
in France, also Australia.
We've got many countries
that support Apple Pay.
And millions of users are
enjoying using Apple Pay.
And we've seen incredible growth
of Apple Pay, both in-store
and within applications.
And developers such as
yourselves have seen some great
results too.
Here's two apps that
I want to talk about.
One of them is Chairish.
Now the Chairish app, they found
that when they used Apple Pay
their conversion rate tripled
from other payment methods.
That's a huge increase.
I can't think of
another payment method
that has such great results.
And StubHub in their
iOS application found
that Apple Pay was driving
twice as many new users
than any other payment method.
So this isn't just for
your existing customers,
Apple Pay can bring you
new customers as well.
Apple Pay apps are often
highlighted on the app store
in their own sections.
We often run promotions
of Apple Pay apps.
We've also seen some
great results in some
of the new countries
we've launched in.
One country I want to
briefly talk about is China.
We've seen some great
applications in China.
I was so lucky to go to
Beijing a few months ago
and taught some developers
using Apple Pay
and they've seen some
great results too.
Apple Pay in China
offers full support
for China UnionPay
credit and debit cards.
And the Apple Pay API
is accepted by CUP,
that's China Union Pay, PayEase,
Lianlian Pay, YeePay, and UMS.
These are major Chinese
payment processes.
We also have documentation
both interface guidelines
and our Getting Started Guide
are available in Chinese,
they're also now
available in French as well,
now that we're launching
in France.
You can check out our developer
site for links to those.
Now I want to talk about some
new API and if you're developing
for Apple Pay already,
you're probably really
going to love this.
One of the problems with
Apple Pay has been the need
to set your networks upfront.
You need to tell us the
networks you want to use
in your payment request.
So that's hard coded
into your application.
And adding new networks
is difficult.
You either have to perform SDK
availability checks to tell
if the constants are
available, or you have to try
to hack something
together, it's not ideal.
And for those of you who
have Apple Pay apps maybe you
remember when we launched
Discover on Apple Pay,
last year, unless you
went and updated your app,
you probably weren't
able to accept them even
if your payment processor could.
So we're introducing something
new in iOS 10 to help with that,
it's dynamic networks
and proxies.
Firstly, we're adding
a new class method
onto PKPaymentRequest.
It's going to tell you
all of the networks
that are available
on that device.
There's PKPaymentRequest
available networks.
We're also going to
enable something else.
You're going to be able
to set payment process
as supported networks.
And these proxy down
to other networks.
So for example, if my payment
processes supports Visa,
MasterCard, AmEx and it's
enabled here, I just put them
in as the supported
network and I'll get all
of the networks automatically.
And perhaps most importantly,
I'll get new networks
as they're added to Apple Pay
without needing to do anything.
So you can check our
developer site for information
about payment processes that are
going to participate in this.
It's a really cool feature,
it's going to save a lot
of pain I think for writing
Apple Pay applications.
One other thing we've changed, I
just want to touch on, Swift 3,
maybe you've already seen some
of the big changes in Swift 3.
We have improved our
API for Swift users.
We've actually completely
rewritten our sample code,
talk about that later.
One change that's coming,
didn't make seed one,
but it will be in seed two.
PassKit now uses stringly
typed enumerations.
If you're not sure what those
are, they're a very cool way
in Swift to take string
constants and turn them
into enums, which is
going to make developing
for Apple Pay a lot easier.
Now let's talk about
Apple Pay in general.
This year we've got
three big new places
where we're adding
support for Apple Pay.
We're adding support to
WatchKit for WatchKit apps.
And we're adding support to
new extension points on iOS.
And finally we're
adding support to Safari,
both on MacOS Sierra
and on iOS 10.
Now we just talked about
Safari in the previous session.
It's online right now.
You can check it out.
Let's focus today, right
now WatchKit and extensions.
I'm going to start
off with WatchKit.
And to talk more about WatchKit
and to show you how easy it is
to integrate Apple Pay on to
Apple Watch, I'd like to ask Leo
from the WatchKit
team to come up.
Leo.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Nick.
Hello everyone.
My name is Leo and I'm
a software engineer
on the Apple Watch team.
I'm really excited to tell
you about what we are doing
with Apple Pay on
the watch this year.
We're adding support for making
payments within WatchKit apps.
We think this is going to
enable a whole new category
of apps on the watch.
And the great news
for you developers,
if you have implemented
Apple Pay on your iOS app,
the same code with
work on watchOS,
with very minimal changes.
So let's take a look at what
we're going to be covering.
First we're going
to do a quick recap
on how payments work
on the platform.
I'm going to show you how to
create a payment request and how
to present a payment sheet.
And then we're going
to do a quick demo.
So you get an idea of how
easy it is to get started
with Apple Pay on the Watch.
Finally, we're going
to talk about some
of the design considerations
that you should keep in mind
when designing specifically
for the watch.
This is the Apply Pay experience
that your users are
familiar with in iOS.
Now let's bring up the watch.
The first thing you notice is
that the UI is very simple.
We only display the total amount
and the merchant
name at the top.
And users can simply
double press the side button
to pay at any time.
If they want to make
any changes,
or review their information,
they can scroll down.
And they can have access to
their different payment cards,
as well as shipping, billing
and contact information.
And they can see a detail
of what they are paying for.
When they're ready to pay,
they simply double click the
side button and it's done.
It is that simple.
Now let's take a look
at how payments work
from a developer's
point of view.
We follow the same flow that
we have on iOS right now.
First you create a payment
request and you pass that in
to a payment authorization
controller.
This is the object that
drives the payment sheet
on our platform.
As the user interact
with the UI,
we're going to call
your delegate,
for example in the payment
method, or the shipping address.
And you may use this opportunity
to perform some validations.
For example, you may not
ship certain products
to some countries.
Or you may want to
update the shipping cost
and the total amount on the UI.
When the user confirms
the payment,
we talk to the secure
element in our Apple servers
and we issue a payment
token that you can use
to process the payment.
Now refer everyone to
the code, a quick note,
there is some setup
that you need to do
to enable Apple Pay
on your apps.
First, you want to go
to the Developer Portal
and register a merchant
identifier and a certificate.
You may have done this
already for your iOS app.
And then you want
to enable Apple Pay
for your WatchKit
extension separately.
And there are step
by step instructions
on our website on
how to do this.
Now let's take a
look at the code.
This is how you create
a payment request.
We use the same PKPaymentRequest
object that we have on iOS.
You create one of this and
you set it up with a country
and currency code, your
merchant identifier,
and the payment network sync
capabilities that you support.
And then you specify a
list of summary items
that describe what the
user is paying for.
Always remember that
the last item
on the list represents
a total amount.
And we recommend that you use
your merchant name as the label,
since we display that at the
top of the payment sheet.
When you want to
present a payment sheet,
you create a PKPayment
AuthorizationController
and you pass in the request
that we just created.
Then you designate yourself or
some other object as a delegate,
and you simply code present.
Now, since you're
presenting the payment sheet,
you're also responsible
for dismissing it.
So make sure to do
that when we go
to payment authorization
controller DidFinish
in your delegate.
So PKPayment
AuthorizationController.
This is a new controller
class provided
in the PassKit.framework.
It is responsible
for controlling the
payment authorization flow.
And it has the same
API semantics
as of PKPaymentAuthorization
ViewController.
But since it's not
view controller based,
it allows for presentation
of the payment sheet
from your WatchKit extension.
It is supported across
watchOS and iOS,
so you can share your user
code across different apps
and across different platforms.
Now, let's put all of this
together and see a quick demo.
So I have been working on
this app for a coffee shop,
so that users can order and
pay for their drinks right
on their watch and have it
ready when they get to the shop.
Let's take a look at
my interface so far.
Great. So we have a product view
almost done, now we just need
to add a way for
users to pay for this.
I'm going to go to
the Option Library
in the bottom right corner and
search for a payment button.
We provide you with this object
that you can use when you want
to present the payment sheet.
We just need to drag and
drop this into our view.
And now let's add some code.
I'm going to bring up
the assistant editor
so I can have the code
and the UI side by side.
I'm going to control drag from
my button to my interface.
And create a new action
that I'm going to name Buy.
Now let's just focus
on the code.
First of all, since we're going
to be using the PassKit
framework,
let's make sure we import that.
And now we're going to implement
the buy method and it's going
to be pretty similar to what
we saw on the slides before.
First, we're going to
create a payment request.
In this case we're
setting it up for the US,
we're going to be charging
this in US dollars.
We specify the merchant
identifier
that we registered
is available portal,
and the payment networks
sync capabilities list
that we support.
And finally a list
of summary items,
in this case we're just using
the total for the coffee.
Now, if you want to
present the payment sheet,
we create a PK Payment
Authorization Controller.
We pass in the request,
we set our self
as a delegate, and
we call present.
Now for seed one we
ask you that you keep
around Payment Controller while
the payment sheet is visible.
Let's define the state
that we're using here.
And then since we're
implementing the delegate
protocol let's conform to that.
And we only have
to implement two
of the required methods
for this to work.
The first one,
PaymentAuthorizationController,
these authorize payment.
It's going to be called when
the user confirms the payment.
And we provide you with all
the information that you need
to send to your payment
processor
and to confirm calling
the completion handler
with a status.
The second one, as
I mentioned earlier,
PaymentAuthorizationController
DidFinish.
It's another opportunity for
you to dismiss the payment sheet
and perhaps present an
order status at the end.
This is all we have to do.
So let's try bill and run this.
Okay, there's our app.
I'm just going to click the
Buy with Apple Pay Button,
and there we have
the payment sheet.
It's very simple, we have
different payment cards
that we can try.
And if you went to simulator,
user action of double
clicking the side button,
there's a new option on the
simulator menu, under Hardware,
and it's called Authorize
Apple Pay.
We just click on
this and it's done.
Our payment is confirmed and
the coffee should be ready
pretty soon.
So that's our demo.
[ Applause ]
As you can see it's very
simple to implement Apple Pay.
It only took us just
a few minutes and less
than 50 lines of code.
Now, before we finish
this section,
I want to talk about design.
How do we make something easy
for users of Apple Watch?
Perhaps the most important thing
here is to consider what kind
of experience you want
to bring to the watch.
Users are not going
to spend more
than just a few seconds
interacting with your app.
So try to offer them
something they want,
and direct them quickly
to the payment sheet.
Remember that the interactions
are short and screens are small.
Next, don't request
information that you don't need.
This could be, for example,
a contact email address.
While we offer users the same
options that they have available
for billing and shipping on
the iPhone, there's no way
to enter a new one right on the
watch, so keep that in mind.
And then as we said in the demo,
use the Payment Button
that we provide.
If it's available on
the WatchKit framework,
it is supported on
Interface Builder,
so it is super easy to add.
And please follow the guidelines
that we have on our website.
This is probably more detail
how the Payment Button should be
used in the context of your app.
So to summarize, if
you have an iOS hub
that implements Apple Pay most
of the same code will work.
You just need to make sure
to implement PKPayment
AuthorizationController
and use the present and dismiss
methods that it provides.
When you're designing
apps for the Watch,
remember that the
interactions are short,
and the screens are small.
And use the Payment Button
that we provide following
our guidelines.
If you haven't done so already,
I highly recommend you checking
out last year's session
on Apple Pay We Announce,
which goes into a lot
more detail on how
to create this kind
of experiences,
and how to customize the
payment sheet in different ways.
I'm really excited to
see what you'll create
with Apply Pay on the Watch.
And now I'm going to turn
it back to Nick who's going
to tell you more
about extensions.
Thank you very much.
[ Applause ]
Thank you Leo.
Okay. Extensions.
In previous releases, Apple
Pay hasn't really played
that well with extensions.
It's been difficult to
support in extensions,
probably because we've always
needed a view controller
to present from, and not
all extensions are UI based.
Frankly, there also weren't
that many interesting
places to use it.
There weren't that many
extension points on iOS 9
and iOS 8 that really lend
themselves to Apple Pay.
But that's changing in iOS 10.
We've got some new
opportunities.
The new extensions, in iOS 10
work really well with Apple Pay
and they have built-in
support for Apple Pay.
And we've solved the
problem of not being able
to display in a non-UI context.
The PKPayment
AuthorizationController API
that Leo showed you on watchOS,
is also available on iOS.
You can actually use it anywhere
in an app, or an extension.
I want to show you some
extensions that use Apple Pay.
We gave the extension's API the
iMessage app API to Fandango
and they use it to
purchase movie tickets.
There's some other
things you can use it for.
You can use it to split
items and purchases,
send gifts to friends,
organize outings.
So here you can see,
Fandango you picked a movie,
suggest with your friends,
bought the tickets,
we never leave messages,
we're still in messages.
And you're done.
It's really easy.
I want to show you
another use of Apple Pay.
It's Apple Pay in Siri and
Maps in the Intents framework.
So there's a new ride
sharing extension point
that works both in
Siri and in Maps.
And you can use Apple Pay
within that extension point,
it's actually built in.
So you can pay directly
from the extension.
I'll show you a short
video of that.
The sample code that
we've developed this year,
actually has a ride
sharing intent.
So here we're asking Siri
to book a ride using
our sample app.
Siri asks us if we want
to get a ride, we say yes.
The Apple Pay sheet's
immediately displayed.
I can touch ID, and
then I can be on my way.
It's that easy.
I never have to leave
Siri, I stayed right there,
never have to go to another app,
never have to put any
payment information in.
This is great if the user
never has a relationship
with your app, if they've
never used your app before,
they can still pay for things.
They don't need to
have an account.
And so requesting and
presenting payment
in these extension points
is identical to WatchKit.
There's no difference.
You can use this new PKPayment
AuthorizationController
in both your UI and
your non UI extensions.
And I actually recommend that
you share your payment code.
You can have a centralized
payment class,
and you could share
that between Watch,
iOS app, and iOS extension.
That's actually what we've
done with our sample code.
So we've rewritten the Emporium
sample app we released last
year, it's been rewritten
in Swift 3.
It's been simplified.
So it's a lot easier
to understand.
And it shows a shared
Apple Pay model,
where the actual payment
logic is the same,
regardless of the
platform that you're on.
So, download that
and try it out.
Of course, you might have a
little problem trying it out,
and that brings me on
to testing Apple Pay.
I saved the best
until last for you.
Testing Apple Pay today
if you've developed
an Apple Pay app,
you'll notice it's
a little tricky.
You can test on the simulator.
And we've actually got
some great new support
in the simulator.
You saw the new authorized Apple
Pay Button on the simulator
for Watch, we're also bringing
that to iPhone in seed two.
And you can test your iOS,
your WatchKit, even Apple Pay
on the web, you can test
on the simulator in Safari.
Now the simulator returns
dummy payment data.
Its payment data
is completely fake.
It's not real and it's
not useable for anything.
So it's really useful for UI
development and quick testing.
But it's not particularly
useful for end-to-end testing.
It's not real card data, and
the simulator is just not
representative of
device behavior.
You know we always tell you,
please don't use the simulator
of your sole way of developing,
you have to test on hardware.
But with Apple Pay that's
not always feasible.
Apple Pay is available
in many countries,
but not all countries.
Maybe your developers
work abroad,
or you don't have a
card that's eligible.
Okay, we're going
to solve that today.
We're going to introduce the
Apple Pay Sandbox environment.
The Sandbox is a brand
new testing environment
for Apple Pay and it lets you
provision test cards directly
onto real devices and the data
that it returns is real payment
data using these test cards.
So it's just like paying for
something with a real credit
or debit card in Apple Pay.
It's really easy to use and
it's really easy to set up.
And you can integrate it
into your QA environments,
where previously perhaps you
couldn't due to restrictions
on production financial data.
Getting set up with the Sandbox
is really straightforward.
All you need to do is create
a testing iCloud account
at iTunes Connect.
Now you can already do this
for various other features,
so this already exists today.
You then just log into that
account on your device.
If you're not in a region
that supports Apple Pay you
can change your region to,
say the US, or to Canada.
And then you just use the
test cards that are published
at developer.apple.com.
We have a list of test
numbers that you can input.
There will be provisions
to Apple Wallet just
like regular cards.
There's no developer
setting or switch.
Environment's a switch
automatically,
where you sign in
and out of iCloud.
Now you should still
validate your apps
with production cards
before you launch.
You still should do an
end-to-end transaction.
I think this is going to be
a really great environment,
a really great feature
to help you test.
And actually if you're
using Apple Pay on the web,
which we talked about
in previous session,
initially you're only able
to test it in the Sandbox,
because we're not going to
roll out production support
until later, nearer the
time we actually GM iOS 10.
So the Apple Pay Sandbox
today supports three networks,
it supports American
Express, MasterCard and Visa.
And more networks will be
coming on board overtime.
We're also hoping that the
Sandbox can be integrated
in various payment processes.
So you can do that,
it's available today
if you're on iOS 10.
So let's have a quick
look at some
of the stuff we talked
about today.
We talked about some new Wallet
and Apple Pay API and features.
Some of the new things
that we've introduced
over the past year and in iOS
10 that help host developers,
card issuers and retailers.
And we talked about
Apple Pay and WatchKit.
I think Apple Pay
WatchKit is really great.
I can't wait to hail a ride
directly from my Apple Watch
without ever needing
to pull out my phone.
We also talked about
Apple Pay in extensions.
I think there's so
much opportunity here
to enable really compelling
experiences, where users can pay
for things without having to go
into an app, straight from Siri,
straight from maps,
straight from messages.
And then we talked about testing
in the Sandbox and
the simulator.
There's one thing we didn't talk
about that's very big this year,
that's Apple Pay on the Web.
So, you can use Apple
Pay as well as in apps,
as well as in extensions,
as well as in WebKit,
you can now use it on mobile
websites and you can use it
on the desktop, on MacOS Sierra.
You can authorize payment
in Safari using your
Apple Pay device,
both iPhone and Apple Watch.
Now, we talked about this
in the previous session.
So if you're interested
you can go
to the website, check
it out now.
And if you want more information
about anything we talked
about today you can check
our sessions microsite.
Now I did promise some
contact information,
and some other things.
I promised you bank and co-brand
private label inquiries.
If you're interested in taking
advantage of in-app provisioning
or any of the features I
talked about for co-brands
and card issuers, you
can email us here.
And if you're interested in
value-added service passes,
you can visit our website,
the links up here,
developer.apple.com/
contact/passkit.
And you can put in a request
to use the value-added
service signing certificates.
We have some related
sessions, like I said,
we just covered Apple
Pay on the web.
There's also a WatchKit session
tomorrow, upstairs in Presidio,
Designing Great Apple
Watch Experiences.
I think you should
definitely go to that
if you're interested
in WatchKit.
See how you can really enable
WatchKit apps especially
with the new changes
on watchOS3.
So thank you so much for coming.
Thank you for making
Apple Pay great
with your own applications.
And I can't wait to see some
of the amazing things
you're going to build.
And hopefully I'll see you
back here next year to talk
about even more cool
things in Apple Pay.
Have a great WWDC.