[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Hello, everyone.
Thank you for coming.
Welcome. My name is Dennis
Matthews, and I'm part
of the HomeKit engineering
team here at Apple.
So before we get started
with what's new in HomeKit,
we'll spend the first couple of
minutes and talk about HomeKit,
and I want to highlight
some of the key features
of what makes HomeKit.
HomeKit is a framework which
provides a rich set of API's
that allow your applications
to talk to different classes
of HomeKit enabled accessories.
Your applications can use
the same API's to talk
with accessories from
different manufacturers.
HomeKit maintains the user's
home data in a common database.
Now this is great
because all applications
in the system have access
to this exact same home data
and configuration
of the user's home.
And if the user has multiple
devices, all of them signed
in to the same iCloud
account, HomeKit takes care
of synchronizing this home data
over to the different devices
that the user may have.
Now this is great because
without any additional set
up on the user's part, the
user can just pick up any
of their devices and
start communicating
with the HomeKit accessories.
HomeKit also supports for
sharing of a user's home.
So a user can share their
home and allow their family
and friends also to
control the accessories
that the user has
set up in their home.
Sharing is very simple.
All that a user has to do is
invite additional users using
their iCloud account, and once
the user accepts the invitation,
HomeKit automatically takes
care of sharing the home data
across to additional
devices as well
as configuring all the
accessories in the home
so that now the shared
users can have access
and control these accessories.
The owner, of course, can
also revoke this control
at any point in time.
HomeKit supports a common
protocol for all the accessories
to securely communicate
with the Apple device.
So all HomeKit accessories,
irrespective
of their underlying
medium of communication,
use the same common protocol.
Now all this protocol Apple
has also defined a rich set
of profiles which describe
many of the common accessories.
Now with this profiles,
Siri support is built in.
This is great and it provides
a very natural way for users
to communicate and control their
accessories just using Siri.
When the user is at
home, communication
between their Apple device
and their HomeKit enabled
accessories is direct.
So all that a user need is their
HomeKit enabled accessories
and their Apple device to
talk to their accessories.
This communication
is either using Wi-Fi
or Bluetooth low energy.
When the user is away from
their home, remote access
to their accessories at home
is provided via the Apple TV,
which acts as a remote
access gateway.
And Apple TV then securely
channels the communication
between the user's device
and their accessories,
which are at home.
Security. We have built
HomeKit with security
in mind right from day one.
All HomeKit communications
are end-to-end secure.
What this means is
the keys that are used
to secure this communication
reside only
on the user's devices.
So even if the communication
flows
through intermediate
devices or services,
they cannot be decrypted.
Not even by Apple.
HomeKit provides for
what's known in the industry
as perfect forward secrecy.
What this means is every
communication session
between an Apple user's device
and their HomeKit
enabled accessory,
user's new session keys
which are generated just
for that session, and after
the session is completed,
these keys are then discarded.
Now this is great because
even if in the future any
of the device is compromised and
a long-term key is compromised,
that then cannot be used to
decrypt any communication
that would have happened
in the past.
Home data is private.
We take care of privacy
in our API's as well
as applications have to
explicitly ask user's permission
to get access to
their home data.
HomeKit supports a
variety of accessories.
Working with our accessory
partners, we have a variety
of accessories in
the market today,
and many of our partners
are bringing new
and exciting classes
of accessories
to the HomeKit ecosystem.
So that was a very
high-level overview of HomeKit.
With that background,
let's get started
with what's new in HomeKit.
So we're going to cover
three major areas.
First, platform.
We are expanding
HomeKit capabilities
through Apple's platform
for iOS, watchOS, and tvOS.
We are introducing support
for new and exciting classes
of accessories in this release.
And all this new
functionality as well
as several enhancements
are available
to your applications via
updates to the framework,
and we will cover
the details there.
First, on platform,
we are really thrilled
to deliver an Apple app
for HomeKit this year.
The home app provides a very
simple interface for users
to control their
accessories as well
as configure their
accessories in their home.
It also enables users
to set up automations
that they have in their home.
Home app is supported on all
iOS devices, iPod Touch, iPhone,
looks beautiful on an iPad,
and, yes, with watchOS 3,
home app is also supported
on the Apple Watch.
We think this is going to be a
great experience for our users.
Not only that, we are also
integrating HomeKit deep
into the system.
Now HomeKit is also available
directly on the control center.
So the user can configure
their favorite accessories
and can have control of the
accessories as well as control
to [inaudible] directly
from the control center.
Second on platform is remote
access and automation.
With tvOS 10, we are extending
the cable, capabilities
on the Apple TV so that in
addition to remote access,
now the Apple TV runs
all the automations
that the user has set
up for their home.
[ Applause ]
Yeah, that's great because now
no matter where the user is,
the virtual part of the world,
they can be rest assured
that all the automations now run
from their Apple
TV at their homes.
Apple TV also enables
for additional controls
for shared users.
Now it is also possible now
to grant administrative
access to a shared user.
So a shared user with an
administrative access can change
configurations in the home.
So they can add or remove
accessories in the home,
or they, in turn, can also
invite additional users
to the home and give
them control
of the accessories at home.
Now it is also possible to
control per user remote access.
So it is possible to grant or
deny remote access capabilities
to your accessories at home
using this functionality.
It's the same set
of functionality is now
also supported by the iPad.
Not only that, if
the user has multiple
of these remote access
capability devices
in their home, like in this
example, an Apple TV and an iPad
or any combination
of these devices,
they will automatically
work together
and extend the HomeKit
network within the home.
And to communicate
with the accessories,
they will automatically select
the part to communicate.
No additional configuration
from the user's part.
This is all just
automatic from HomeKit.
Third update on platform
is on tvOS 10.
We are thrilled to bring the
HomeKit framework to the tvOS.
[ Applause ]
Now with the HomeKit
framework on the tvOS,
your applications can
view home configurations,
control the accessories
in the home as well
as execute scenes
directly from the Apple TV.
This also means that
now Siri is available
for HomeKit on the Apple TV.
[ Applause ]
So directly from your
convenience of your Siri remote,
you can control your
HomeKit accessories at home.
So those were the major
updates on the platform front.
Let's just quickly recap.
First, home app.
An Apple-designed app for
HomeKit that makes setting
up of accessories as well as
controlling common functions
of the accessories very easy.
Second, remote access
and automation.
We're extending the capabilities
provided by the Apple TV
so that it now runs automation,
and it also enables additional
controls for shared users.
And the same capability is
now also extended to the iPad.
And, third, on tvOS, we're
bringing the HomeKit framework.
So we are really thrilled
to bring these capabilities
to the platform.
The second area we will
cover is new accessories.
First on new accessories, we
are introducing popular class
of air treatment accessories
to HomeKit this year.
So now HomeKit can support
air conditioners and heaters,
air purifiers as
well as humidifiers.
This is great because our users
can now have these accessories
which are also HomeKit enabled
part of their HomeKit ecosystem
in their home and add it
to their automations
and other things.
Next, we are really thrilled to
bring, to bring a powerful class
of camera accessories
to HomeKit this year.
[ Applause ]
Now with camera accessories,
your applications can
display live video streams
from the camera.
Display take and display
still images from the camera.
Control all the settings
on the camera as well
as control the speaker
and microphone settings.
Third, doorbells.
Now doorbell is a
very simple accessory.
It generates and events once
the doorbell is pressed.
Also the doorbell has control
where it can control the volume
settings of the doorbell chime,
and also if the doorbell has
a visual indicator settings,
those can also be controlled
by the doorbell accessory.
Now doorbells we are
seeing are also integrated
with other kinds of accessories.
So doorbell camera
is popular category.
Now this configuration is
also supported by HomeKit.
Not only are these powerful
accessories supported
by HomeKit, we are also tightly
integrating the experience
into the system.
So now, for example, if you
have a doorbell, a door lock,
and a camera which are
all configured by the user
to be part of a room, maybe
the user called the room an
entryway, HomeKit will
automatically associate services
from these different
accessories,
and they can provide
contact-sensitive controls
to the user.
This enables for some
magical experiences
like rich notifications.
So, for example, now here,
when the doorbell rings,
HomeKit will automatically take
a snapshot from the camera,
and the user is presented
with a rich notification.
Also, there are controls
directly on the notification
where the user can press,
touch on the intercom
and start an audio session
with the camera, or if the user
so chooses, unlock the door,
and the notification
displays live video streaming
from the camera.
And, yes, the same
functionality is also available
on the Apple Watch.
And, yes, touching on the,
on the picture there will
start a live video stream
from your HomeKit camera
to your Apple Watch.
And, yeah, you can unlock
your door, if you so choose,
directly from the Apple Watch.
Next, let's look at the updates
to the HomeKit framework.
So we'll start off first
with a, with few simple
but very powerful
enhancements that we have added
to the framework that
gives more context
about the accessory
to your applications.
First up is primary service.
Now this is an example
of an accessory
which has two services - a fan
service and a light service.
So this is what your
application today gets.
Now just by looking
at these services,
it is not clear what the user
perceives this accessory as.
Is this a light with an
exhaust fan, or is this a fan
which also has a light?
Now, with update to
the HomeKit protocol,
the accessory can mark
its primary service,
and this is available back
to your application using
the isPrimaryService property
on the HMService class.
Now this will be great for you
because now you can show
content-sensitive controls
about the accessory
to your users.
Second example is
on linked services.
Here's another example where
an accessory has three outlet
services and a switch service.
Now, again, by just
looking at these services,
it is not clear what
the switch controls.
Does the switch control
one of the outlet
or any other combination
of these outlets?
When a user looks
at the accessory,
it is clear that that switch
controls all the three outlets.
Now with linked services,
services can link
with each other and communicate
back their relationship
to HomeKit, and this is
available back to you.
So in this case, the
switch is linking
to these three outlets
communicating a logical
relationship that the switch has
in controlling these
three outlets.
So now for your users, when
they, when they are looking
at your UI, which is
showing the outlet,
you can now additionally
show the state of the outlet,
whether it is powered on
or off based on the fact
that it is linked
to, from a switch.
Third is valid values.
To explain valid values, let's
take an example where we want
to build an accessory.
Let's say we're building an
air conditioner accessory,
and as we're building
this accessory,
we want to incorporate the
Apple-defined characteristics
for this accessory.
So we will pick a target and
cooling state for our accessory.
So this is how it is
defined in the specification.
Now the air conditioner that we
are building doesn't support,
let's say, heating.
So the heat and the auto
state here is not valid
for my configuration.
Now it is possible for
accessories to mark enumerations
in Apple-defined characteristics
which are not valid
for its configuration.
So in this case, the accessory
marks the heat and auto
as not supported, and this
information is then, again,
available back to
your applications
through the
HMCharacteristicMetadata valid
values property.
Now you can show controls
that are only valid
to that particular
configuration of the accessory.
Next, setting up of
HomeKit accessories.
Today, to set up a
HomeKit accessories,
which is probably the first
step that your user will do,
involves a few different steps.
First, you will start
browsing for the accessories,
and once a new accessory is
found, which is already part
of your Wi-Fi network, or if
it is a Bluetooth accessory,
which is in range,
this is informed back
to you via the accessory
browser's didFindNewAccessory
delegate callback.
And once you have
that accessory,
you can then call the add
accessory method on HMHome
to start adding this
accessory to the home.
But for Wi-Fi accessories
that are not already part
of the user's Wi-Fi
home network,
you need to do some
additional steps
to get these accessories
added and configured
into the user's Wi-Fi network.
You do that today using
the [inaudible] framework.
So there are some additional
steps required for that.
We thought we can do better.
So now in iOS 10, we
have one simple API,
add and set up accessories
that completely takes care
of all the steps
that are required
to configure the accessory
and add it to the user's home.
So on calling this method,
addAndSetupAccessories,
the user is guided
directly using this UI
to select the accessory.
So in this case here, it's
showing all the configured
as well as accessory,
new accessories
that are part of
the Wi-Fi network.
The user can select the
accessories they want to add,
and once it is selected,
if it was not already part
of the user's Wi-Fi network,
it is added to the user's
Wi-Fi network securely.
Then the HomeKit
scan code is scanned,
and HomeKit pairing is
performed on the accessory,
and then the user is prompted
to name the accessory,
select a room for the accessory.
And also in this case,
since it's an outlet
which is generally
kind of an accessory,
the user is also prompt
to associate what kind
of accessory is connected
to this outlet.
So in our example here,
this outlet, let's say,
is being connected to a fan.
So we select the fan as
the associated service
for this accessory,
and, finally,
the user can also choose to
show this accessory as part
of their favorites, and using,
doing that enables this
accessory to appear as part
of their control
center controls.
So that's it.
Just one simple API,
and user is guided
through this complete
set up flow.
And now all applications
then will also have this
consistent experience.
We think this is going to
be great for our users,
and we really encourage all of
you to start using this API.
[ Applause ]
Next, let's talk about
camera accessories.
So a camera is a rich
and complex accessories.
It has many different
controls and configurations.
So rather than exposing all the
raw services and characteristics
to your app, we are providing
a very easy way for you
to take advantage of
this powerful accessory
with cameraProfile objects.
A profile is nothing but a
collection of related services
that describe a general
behavior for an accessory.
So cameraProfile objects
provides you all the interfaces
that is needed for you to
control the camera accessories.
So on an accessory, you can
get to the cameraProfile
from the cameraProfile
property on the HM accessory.
An accessory can
support multiple cameras,
and those are all
supported by HomeKit.
So it will be one
of the elements
in this cameraProfile array.
Let's look at what a
cameraProfile provides.
A cameraProfile provides
additional interfaces
that allow you to control
different aspects of the camera.
So you can display and
control the camera stream,
which is both the audio and
video stream from the camera;
display, take and display
still images from the camera;
control all the settings
on the camera as well
as control the speaker
and microphone settings
on the camera.
Let's look at the
HMCameraProfileClass
that provides these interfaces.
First is stream control.
Let's look at HMStreamControl.
So HMStreamControl provides
some few simple methods
that allow you to start
and stop streams directly
from the camera.
So you call the startStream
method on the HMCameraStream
to start a live stream
from the camera.
Once the stream starts,
it is informed back
to you using the
StreamControl delegate callback.
So once a stream starts,
the camera stream control
didStartStream informs you back
that the stream has started.
Similarly, to stop the stream,
you call the stopStream method,
and, again, using the same
mechanism it is informed back
to you via the camera
stream control didStopStream
with error delegate callback.
Once the stream is started,
your application has a reference
to the stream using via
the cameraStream property.
Let's look at what the
cameraStream looks like.
The cameraStream
represents both the audio
and the video parts
of the stream.
So on the cameraStream class,
you have additional controls
whereby you can control the
audio settings from
the camera stream.
So using this, you can
either mute the stream
or fully allow incoming audio
or allow bidirectional
audio from the camera.
Now that you have a stream,
what do you want to do with it?
Well, you would like to
display it in your app.
How do you do that?
It's simple.
On iOS 10 and tvOS
10, all that you need
to do is create a HMCameraView.
And to the view and on the
view we have a single property,
the camera source, and you
need to just assign the stream
that you just got when
you started the stream
to this property.
That's it.
All that is needed for your app
to show live stream
from the camera.
It's very similar on watch OS.
You just create an
HM WKInterface camera
and call the setCameraSource
method
to show live stream
directly on your Apple Watch.
So those were a few different
objects for you to look
to control your camera
accessory,
but in reality, it's
pretty simple.
Let's look at an example call.
So first we get to our
cameraProfile on our accessory,
and in this case, we're just
picking the first cameraProfile
that is there, and on the
cameraProfile's stream.Control,
we call the startStream method
which will start
a camera stream.
And to display our stream,
we'll create a HMCameraView,
and once our stream is started,
it's informed back via
this delegate callback
cameraStreamControl
didStartStream,
and all that we need to do here
is assign the camera stream
to the camera source
property on the view.
That's it.
Now your view in your
application is showing live
stream from the camera.
Next, let's look
at snapshotControl.
Snapshot control interfaces
are also very similar
to what we saw with
streamControl.
So for snapshotControl we
have one method, takeSnapshot,
which once a snapshot
is taken informed back
to you via the
cameraSnapshotControl didTake
snapshot method callback.
And the most recent snapshot
reference is available to you
in this most recent
snapshot property.
Let's look at the
SnapshotControl.
The SnapshotControl has
just one additional thing
which will show you
the capture date
of when this snapshot
was captured.
It has both the time and date.
And, again, similarly,
to display your snapshot
into a view, all that you
need to do is create a view
and assign it to this snapshot.
So here's an example to take
and display a snapshot
from the camera.
It's very similar, core
structure is very similar.
First we get to our
cameraProfile.
On this cameraProfile's
snapshotControl,
we call the takeSnapshot method.
We create a view to
display our snapshot,
and once a delegate is
called back, it comes back
with a reference
of our snapshot.
We just take that and assign it
to the camera's source
property on our view.
That's it.
That's all you need to show
the snapshot from the camera.
Next, let's look
at settingControls.
So settingControl gives you HM
characteristics which allow you
to control all the settings that
are supported by the camera.
So you have interfaces to
control night vision, tilt,
zoom, rotation, and
mirroring on the camera.
So if the cameraSupport does
not support any one of this,
then that property will be nil.
Otherwise, you have full access
to control all the settings
of this camera from your app.
Last, we'll look at camera
audio control, which allows you
to control both the speaker
and microphone settings
on the camera.
Again, these are also
HM characteristic
which will allow you to
change the mute settings
on the microphone, change the
mute settings of the speaker,
control the gain
on the microphone,
or control the speaker volume.
So those are all the key API's
that is available for you
to take advantage of
this powerful accessory.
So let's summarize.
We covered three major areas.
First, platform.
We're bringing the home app, an
Apple-designed app for HomeKit.
For remote access
and automation.
We're extending the capabilities
of the Apple TV as well
as adding iPad to
have the remote access
and automation capability
for users' home.
We're bringing HomeKit
to the tvOS framework.
Next area on accessories,
we're adding the popular class
of air treatment accessories.
We're adding powerful
camera accessories
to the HomeKit ecosystem.
And we're also adding doorbells
and combination accessories,
which are doorbell cameras.
On the framework
updates, we covered simple
but powerful capabilities that
allow you to get more context
about your accessory
in your app.
So you can show rich
and context-sensitive
UI to your users.
We have greatly simplified
the accessory setup flow.
Now with just one API call,
all apps get the consistent
experience of guiding the user
through the complete setup for,
for their HomeKit accessories.
And we introduced cam,
camera profile objects
that allow your applications
to take advantage
of this powerful
class of accessories.
Now before I conclude, I want
to leave you with this thought.
HomeKit accessories and your
applications are changing the
way that our users
interact with their homes.
With system features like Siri,
automations, and notifications,
also combined with the rich
set of accessibility features
on Apple platforms like
voiceover and others,
these accessories are,
for the very first time,
becoming accessible to users
with various kinds
of disabilities.
This is powerful, and it is
a life-changing experience
for many of our users.
So I encourage you to check out
all these different capabilities
that are available to
you on Apple platforms,
and take full advantage
and make your accessories
and applications
accessible to everyone.
For our MFi program members,
a preview of the updated
specifications will become
available to you soon, and for
new accessory manufacturers
who'd like to join the program,
this URL gives you more
information, or please come
and talk to one of us.
More information about this
session as well as HomeKit
and references are
available via this URL.
These are some related sessions
I'll encourage you to watch
on video if you have
missed them.
The first one is
really inspiring.
Thank you very much.
Have a great conference.
[ Applause ]