[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Good morning everyone.
Wow it's loud.
Thank you all for coming.
We're really excited to be here.
My name is Ryan Olshavsky.
And with me down
there is Jonathan Cho.
We're designers on an
iWork team at Apple
where we make the Numbers,
Pages, and Keynote apps
for Mac, iOS, and iCloud.
Jon and I have been
designing software interfaces
for quite a while both
at Apple and elsewhere.
And if there's one thing
that we've learned on all
of our years of experience, it's
that good design is not easy.
And I know that sounds like
something a designer would say
because it's good
for our job security
if everybody believes this.
And maybe some of you have seen
what designers do and thought,
well that doesn't look too hard.
And you're right a lot of times
great design can see obvious
or effortless.
But what makes design difficult
are the questions you have
to answer to do it well.
Questions like, what
are we making?
Who is it for?
Does it actually work?
And did we get it right?
These questions do not
have obvious answers.
And they're always
challenging even
for the most experienced
designers.
And if you're a solo developer,
or you're the only designer
on your team, or if you just
never really designed anything
before, trying to answer
these questions can be a
daunting task.
But we do it anyway, because
as you know design matters,
it's important and it can have
a profound impact on the quality
of your app and on
the people who use it.
A poorly thought out design
can turn the most basic
and obvious interaction
into a frustrating
and potentially embarrassing
experience.
A great design, on
the other hand,
can transform an
intimidating and difficult task
into something simple,
approachable, and elegant.
Even when it's based
on something extraordinarily
complex under the hood.
Now unfortunately there are
no shortcuts to great design.
There's no magic button you
can press to turn a bunch
of disparate features
into a compelling
and successful product.
Design is not effortless.
It takes time, commitment,
concentration and rigor.
But the good news is there are
ways to make design easier.
There are tools, techniques
and methods you can use
to mitigate uncertainty
and help you get
to a great design sooner.
So today, Jon and I are going to
share with you a few techniques
and methods that we use on our
team, in our own design work
to help you find answers
to a few common questions.
Specifically, what
are we making?
Where do we start?
And what's the right design.
So first, what are we making?
We're going to start
with this one
because if you can answer this
question it makes all the other
questions a lot easier.
So maybe you have a bunch
of amazing features,
but can't decide which
ones are worth building.
Or maybe you've identified a
potentially lucrative audience,
but don't know exactly what
functionality the people
in that audience want or need.
Or maybe you've built a
really awesome map already,
but don't know who
exactly it's for.
A powerful way to answer those
questions is to define your app.
That is, take all the things you
can imagine your app could do.
Identify the features that
matter most to the people
who will use your
app, and the features
that serve your own
goals for the app itself,
in order to determine
what your app should do.
So as an example, throughout
this session Jon and I are going
to pretend to design an app.
And how many of you here
have been to Caffé Macs?
Great. Well, if you haven't
Caffé Macs is the cafeteria
down in Apple Headquarters
in Cupertino.
It has a rotating menu
of freshly prepared food
and most Apply employees
eat there every day.
But a lot of people walk down
to the café, stand in line,
order their food, pay for their
food and then just take it back
to their desk and eat there.
So to make it a little
easier for those people,
we're going to design
an app for a new service
that lets employees order a meal
and have it delivered
directly to their office.
Which is pretty cool.
So, fair warning, you're
going to see a lot of pictures
of food coming up, so if you
weren't able to get breakfast
or a snack before the
session, I apologize for that.
So, let's go through the
process of defining this app.
So like I said first,
we need to identify,
and collect all the features
we think our app could have.
So you want to include
anything that's obvious.
So we're pretty sure we'll
need a menu of entrees,
details about those entrees
and a way to place an order.
But you also, and include
basically anything else.
Capture all the features
you think you
and your audience might
like to see in your app.
So in our case we might want
a way to schedule delivery,
see ratings, quickly
reorder meals.
Maybe we could offer
a catering service.
And so on.
There aren't any good or bad
ideas at this stage so feel free
to include anything you want.
And then once you have
your list you actually want
to set it aside for a little bit
because the next thing you need
to do is figure out
who you're designing
for and what they need.
Now this can often be
one of the hardest steps,
because it's not uncommon
for people on the same team
to have completely
different ideas in their mind
about who is going
to be using your app.
But without a shared
understanding
of who your user is, and what
their goals are you might end
up with a hodgepodge of features
that nobody needs, or worse,
you might spend a lot of time
and effort building an app
that nobody knows about because
you targeted the wrong audience.
So let's start with a
couple of simple tips.
First, you are not the user.
You might be a user of your app,
but if you design for yourself,
you risk building in
preconceptions and biases
about the user experience
that might be completely
wrong for everyone else.
For example, I'm an Apple
employee and I'll be a user
of the Caffé Macs app
that we're going to design,
but I almost exclusively
eat cheeseburgers.
And if I were to design the
app for my interest alone,
I'd put the burger of the
day at the top of the screen,
and that would be it because
that's all I really care about.
And that would be great for me,
but maybe not so much for people
who prefer salad, or who like
fish, or whatever else it is
that normal people eat.
Designing for yourself
distracts you
from what matters
most to everyone else.
But the opposite is also true.
Your audience should
not be everyone,
because this is too
vague, it doesn't allow you
to draw any meaningful
conclusions
about what would be most
important, or most valuable
to the real people
who will use your app.
Instead you need to focus on
the essential characteristics
of your target audience.
And one way to do that is
to image you're interviewing
someone who's going
to use your app to
find out what they like
and what they don't like,
and what they care about.
In our case, we might ask our
customer do they prefer a fresh
meal, or something
off the shelf?
Do they like to take
a leisurely lunch,
or just grab something
between meetings?
Do they get the same
thing every day?
Or do they like to try
something new and different?
And do they prefer
to eat healthy food?
Or do they just pickup
whatever looks good?
Try to capture a range
of characteristics
in a few questions like these.
And then pick the answers that
best reflect the people you want
to serve with your app.
You can use your instinct
and expertise to do this,
and if you have user
research or marketing data,
you can use that to
inform your choices too.
In our case, it's already pretty
easy to walk down to the Caffé
and get a premade
salad or sandwich.
So, instead, we want to focus
on the people who are looking
for a quick interesting, fresh,
and healthy meal every day.
Once you know the
characteristics
of your customer, you
can rephrase those
as a set of goals.
So, our customer goals
are to eat a fresh meal,
eat quickly, or sorry.
Enjoy a fresh meal, eat
quickly, try something new,
and make healthy choices.
Articulating your
audiences' goals
like this will help you focus
on their needs throughout
the design process.
But what about you?
What about your goals as an app
developer, or a product owner?
Maybe you want people to
rely on your app every day.
Or maybe you want it to be a
super fun app to play with.
Or maybe you want it
to be blazing fast.
You want to capture those
characteristics too,
as app goals that describe what
you think your app should be
like, how it should feel
and what makes it
memorable, or unique.
So our app goals might be
to provide a convenient
simple delivery service,
so people don't have to walk
all the way to the café.
We want to highlight
the daily entrees
so customers know
all the great options
that are available to them.
And we want Caffé Macs
diners to be happy, of course,
so they keep coming back.
Now, note that this list
does not include things like,
be profitable, or earn a
great return on investment,
or optimize food costs.
While those are important goals
from a business standpoint,
they don't really provide
any meaningful direction
for the design.
And that's because business
goals describe what you want
to get out of your app
after you release it.
App goals on the other
hand describe the qualities
of experience you want
your users to have.
You need to understand both
types of goals, of course.
But it's your app goals that
will inspire and motivate you
to design and build
a great product.
All right so finally, to figure
out what exactly
our app should do,
we need to consider all those
features we came up with
in step one from the perspective
of our customer goals
and our app goals.
So, here's our list again.
And by looking at each one
of these in the context
of our goals, you can pretty
quickly identify the ones
that are appropriate
for our app.
So, in addition to the
basic functionality,
we can also include an
entree rating system
that serves our customers'
goals, finding something new
and interesting to eat.
And a feedback link
serves our own app goals
of making diners happy
because it gives them a way
to let us know if
they're satisfied or not.
By the same method we
can also exclude features
that do not serve our goals.
Now this isn't to say
that these are bad ideas,
or that they're not
worth doing some day,
they just don't fit our
current definition of our app.
So we can set them aside
for now and maybe get back
to them in a future release.
All right, check this out.
Now that we actually
have a list of features
and we know what we're making.
We have a nice succinct
set of functionality based
on a solid understanding of
what's most important to us,
and what's going to matter to
the people who will use our app.
And so now to tell
you more about how
to actually start
designing your features,
I'm going to hand
things over to Jon.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you Ryan.
So now that know
what we're making,
let's start designing our app.
But where do we start?
Well what I like to do is I
like to start with what I know.
You might not know how all
of your app is going to look
or work yet, but
there's probably one
or two things you
do know you'll need
and you can start
by designing that.
For example, if you're designing
a messaging app, you might want
to start by designing
the conversation screen,
because you know that's where
a lot of people are going
to be spending their time.
Or, if you're designing a
dating app, you might start
by designing the profile
screen, because you know
that that's going to be a
big part of your experience.
In our case, I'm designing
a food delivery app.
So I don't know much
about what I need,
but I know at the very least,
I'm going to need a menu of food
so that people can
order from it.
So I'll start by
designing the menu screen.
So for this demo, I'm going
to design UI in Keynote.
You might already know Keynote
as a great presentation app,
but it's also a great
app to draw UI.
It creates layouts very easily,
you can try out different
animations.
You can even make
interactive prototypes
that you can load
onto your phone.
In our group, we like Keynote
so much that we design all
of our apps using Keynote.
In fact, even Keynote was
designed using Keynote.
Think about that.
[ Applause ]
That shouldn't even be possible.
But it is because
Keynote is awesome.
So, let's start drawing UI.
UI is made up of a
couple of simple elements.
It's made up of shapes and lines
and I can insert those
from my top here.
I can just tap to
insert a shape.
I can tap to insert a line.
UI also has text.
And I can insert
text by clicking
on this and get a textbox.
And UI also has images.
On my desktop I have
a folder of food
and I can just drag
it into Keynote.
And I can resize that.
Great. So to start, I'm just
going to start with a shape.
I'm going to copy
and paste a shape.
I'm going to change its
size to 375 by 667 points,
because this is the
resolution of an iPhone 6.
And I'm going to make it white
and put it right on the center.
So in just 30 seconds I've
already designed a simple
iPhone app.
It's a flashlight.
Ha,ha [laughter].
I'm just kidding.
So I'm going to draw a menu
screen, and one thing I
like to do is I like to take
screenshots of apps that I use
and use them as references.
So here I have a screenshot
that I took of my messages app.
So I'm just going
to drag that in.
It comes in a little large
because it's retina resolution.
So I'm just going to resize it.
And I'm going to put this next
to my screen that I'm drawing.
And now that I have
this screenshot next
to what I'm drawing, I
can use it as a reference.
So I'm going to start by
taking shapes and outlining
out the layout of my screen.
So I'm just going to resize
this box to be a header square.
I turned on my accessibility
zoom functionality
in system preferences so I
could zoom in really quickly
and make sure that
everything is pixel perfect.
Okay. I'm going to do
the same thing for lines.
I know that this
line is 1 point.
Again, I'm going to zoom
in to make sure it is
exactly where I want it.
Great and now I'm just going
to start duplicating this
line a bunch of times.
I don't really care where
it's positioned right now.
I can be a little bit sloppy,
because I'll clean
that up later.
The only one I do care
about is this last line.
I want to make sure that
this last line is exactly
where I want it.
Great, because now I can
just select all of my lines
and space them out evenly,
and the line then to the left.
So that was a really quick way
to just get all my lines
in place [applause].
Oh, okay. That was not
even the impressive part.
So now I want to change
the colors of my lines
and I can do that here.
I can make it gray.
Or if I wanted to
use a specific color,
I could use the system
color picker,
and use the eyedropper tool.
This turns my mouse
into a magnifying glass
and now I can click on a
specific color on my screen
and it will use that
color for the line.
And now I'll do the same
thing with my header bar.
I'll get this light gray.
So I've already got the outline
of the screen that
I want to draw.
So the next thing I want
to do is match the text.
So I'm going to take this
text box, and I can try
to match the style of the
text of the messages app.
So I can start by just typing in
the text that I want to match.
You can see that the font
and the size is incorrect.
I know that iPhone system
font is San Francisco.
So I can set it to
San Francisco.
And I'm just going to
make this font smaller.
It looks like what I'm trying
to match is actually semi-bold.
And I could actually
just zoom in there
and make sure that it is exact.
Great. So it looks like
a pretty close match.
I can do the same
thing for this subtext.
Close enough.
Okay. So now I've got my
text looking like the text
on my screenshot, and
this actually looks,
maybe like it's gray so I'm
going to drop the opacity a bit.
So now the next thing I want
to do is start putting
content into my UI.
I've got this text file
of different entree
names and descriptions.
So I'm just going to copy and
paste some of these in here.
Resize this.
Great. I also want to get
the title of my screen.
So I'll try to match that.
This looks like it's
actually the right size.
That's great.
Stick this in the center.
And I'll call this Caffé Macs.
Okay. So now I've got some
pretty good text in here.
The next thing I want to
do is put in some images.
I'm going to take my picture
of my mahi-mahi and resize it.
Now I want to get the
sizing and the shape exact.
So what I'm going
to do is I'm going
to use a shape and
use it as a mask.
So I'm going to just make this
square the exact size I want.
And now, if I select
both of them,
I can crop the image
using the shape.
Going to nudge it a bit.
Excellent.
And now my picture of fish
is the exact size I wanted.
I can mask images in other ways.
I want to get the status
bar of this screenshot.
I don't want to draw it.
So I'm just going to
duplicate this image,
double click the mask it
and just grab the bar
and stick it on top.
I saved myself a
couple minutes there.
And the last thing I want,
is I want this little arrow.
I've got this other trick.
I can actually take a
screenshot of any part
of my screen using the
keyboard shortcut command,
control, shift 4.
It's hard to remember,
but it's useful.
When I do that it turns my
mouse cursor into a camera.
And now I can just draw
a box around this arrow.
And it's copied to my clipboard
and now I can just paste that.
So that's a not well
known keyboard shortcut.
Great. So now I've got one row.
So I'm going to group
these together.
And again, I'm going to do the
same thing I did with my lines.
The only one I care about
getting right is this last one,
because I can just
select all of them,
space them out and align them.
Great. And now the
only thing I have
to do is replace these images
and copy paste some more content
in there to get it
looking like a real screen.
To save some time I've actually
drawn the screen beforehand.
So it looks something
like this once I swapped
out all of the content.
So in just I don't know, three
minutes, I drew the screen.
[ Applause ]
So I want to talk a little bit
about the exact steps I took
in the last couple minutes.
I started by using
screenshots as references
to match colors,
sizes and texts.
I also used screenshots
to collage bits
of UI that I wanted to use.
I drew a bunch of squares and
lines, and I resized them a bit
and I zoomed in and
out a lot to make sure
that they were pixel perfect.
And I used believable content
so that, I used realistic photos
and texts to make my UI
look more believable.
I think with a little
bit of practice
and effort these steps
are simple enough
that anyone here can
do what I just did.
So now I'll hand
things back to Ryan.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Jon.
Great work as always.
All right so here's our
awesome Caffé Macs menu design.
And we're done.
Right? This seems good enough.
Meets all the functional
criteria of a menu.
Looks great.
It's tempting to just
stop here and move
onto the next feature
or the next screen.
But how do we actually know
if this first design
is the right design?
Well, I can tell you from
experience it's probably not.
And that's because you can't
know if your design is right
if you try only one idea.
Instead you need to look at
the problem from other angles
and iterate on your design to
find new insights and approaches
that you might miss otherwise.
Basically, you want to look
at your app design and ask,
what could we do differently?
So here's our design again,
Well, in our case, it's based
on, our design is based on rows
so one thing you can do is just
change the size of the rows.
Here by making the rows taller,
we can't fit as many entrees,
but we can make the
photos larger.
And you can also increase
or decrease the amount
of information that's
on the screen,
so here we've added the prices.
You can consider different
layouts, and adjust the amount
of white space between
your content.
That's the space around
and between the things
that are on your screen.
So here we've added margins
around the photos which opens
up the UI a little bit.
You can also try
different topography styles.
For example, here we're using
a larger, lighter weight font
for the names, and we've
added some color to the prices
to make them stand out on
screen a little bit more.
You can also just go where
your curiosity takes you.
So, we wondered, what it the
menu didn't have pictures
of food, because why not?
It's worth a try.
But what we found is that
without a visual anchor
on each row, we needed to
make the entrée names bigger
and bolder, which gives
the menu a different feel.
And note that I'm not
actually judging any
of these designs yet.
We're just really brainstorming
with pictures to kind
of shake out new ideas.
So another technique you
can use is to do a 180.
So while this design
is very text oriented,
what about one that's
very image oriented?
So we have a grid
of photos here.
It kind of looks like a
totally different app right.
You can also think about the
proportions of your imagery
and what shapes suit
your content the best.
So while these photos
are square,
maybe wider landscape
photos work better.
You can also look at different
ways to contain your content.
Here each entrée is
on a tile or a card,
which helps them feel more like
distinct items on the screen.
Think about how you use
the space available to you,
these photos are edge-to-edge,
which makes the most
of the iPhone screen.
And in this layout to
fit the entree details,
we superimposed them
on the photos
to create a different
visual style.
And remember you
aren't restricted
to a uniform grid
of boxes or rows.
You can play with the size and
proportions of your content
to create completely
different effects.
You can combine ideas
to create new ones.
So, here we took the
edge-to-edge photo-style
and merged it with the list
view layout of our first design.
Think about how immersive you
want the experience to be.
These larger photos
dominate the screen,
which encourages the viewer to
spend more time with each one.
And if your text is critical
make sure you pay attention
to how readable it is.
Can somebody with
a vision impairment
or color blindness make
out the important details?
And finally what if we took this
large photo idea to an extreme
so that the image takes up
basically the whole screen.
Here scrolling vertically
might be a little strange,
so instead we're using a
swipe navigation scheme
so you just swipe
between the entrees.
So, consider how your
content could be served
by different navigation schemes.
All right so here
are 11 alternatives
to our original design.
These were all drawn
in Keynote as well.
And you want to basically
just keep asking what can we
do differently?
Until you've come
up and expressed
as many interesting alternatives
as you can come up with.
And again you can do that
by organizing your content
into different layouts,
playing with text size,
color, weight, and font.
Experimenting with proportions
of your content, increasing
and decreasing the amount
of information that's
on the screen.
Doing 180s and pushing
ideas to extremes.
And considering different ways
of navigating through
your content.
So the next question is,
will any of these designs
actually work for our app?
We don't know yet.
This is a step when
you and your team get
to actually judge your designs.
This can be the fun part.
So you want to set aside
your ego and your pride
and forget all the time you
spent drawing your mockups.
And instead pretend you're a
third party whose job it is
to evaluate and critique your
designs to find their strengths
and weaknesses, and
find the best one.
So to do that you have to
scrutinize each options
and ask some tricky questions.
Things like, how well
does the design serve your
audience's goals?
How well does it address
your own app goals?
And does it fit the
definition of your app?
Does the design provide people
with the right information?
Is there enough detail
to take action?
Is it readable?
Is the design intuitive?
Are you using interface controls
that people are familiar with?
And are you using terminology
your audience will understand
given their context
and experience.
And finally, does the
design feel right?
Even if it meets all
the other criteria,
and it's objectively
a good design,
does it feel the
way you want it to?
Does it have the personality and
the appearance that you want?
That's just as important
as everything else.
These questions are
all very subjective.
And you will most likely
get into disagreements
with your teammates and even
yourself about the answers.
But asking these
questions and trying
to answer them honestly
will really help lead you
to the right design.
So to demonstrate what
we're talking about Jon
and I are going to now critique
our own designs in front of all
of you, to find the one that
we thinks works the best.
So let's take a second
and just consider them.
All right what do you think Jon?
>> Looking at them side by
side, it's a little bit obvious
that some are better than others
so I think we can just go ahead
and eliminate a couple
right now.
>> Okay.
>> Let's get rid of A,
you know the first one.
It's pretty good, but it's
not as good as the other ones.
>> All right.
>> Let's get rid of D,
it doesn't have any photos,
that's wort of weird.
>> Yeah.
>> A food app, we need photos.
Let's also get rid of E.
Yeah that one has
too many photos.
It feels so crowded
and you can't even see
that much information.
>> True. I think we
can get rid of F also.
It has a little bit
more information,
but I think the visual layout
is maybe a little too busy
and the entree names are getting
cut off that's not great.
>> That's a good point.
>> I think we can get rid
of option I, the proportions
of those photos are
kind of interesting,
but you can't really see
enough of the food to know
if it looks good or not.
>> Okay.
>> And then option L, even
though I love the big photo,
I think paging through 12
or 15 different entrees
is probably just going
to be too tedious so I think we
should get rid of that one too.
>> I agree.
>> All right now we're down
to six, that's good progress.
All right [laughter].
Didn't take very long at all.
All right so let's look
at the rest of them
in a little more detail.
So between these two,
they're actually very similar,
they're very functionally
similar.
I would say that maybe option B
is a little more conventional,
maybe more what people expect
from a menu on an iPhone.
And I actually like the
edge-to-edge photos.
I think that's a nice look.
>> You know I actually
like option C.
It's a little bit
more interesting.
I like how the topography
is really thin.
I think that's really hip now.
It's also cool how all
of the information is
aligned on the left.
It's really each to just scan
down and see names and prices.
And I sort of like the
feel of it being more open
and feeling a little
bit more fresh.
>> Yeah. I think, yeah
those are good points.
Thank you.
>> Thank you.
>> You've convinced me.
All right let's get
rid of option B.
This is totally ad lib
by the way [laughter].
>> Okay these two look
pretty similar as well,
they both have edge-to-edge
photos.
G has more of a grid layout,
while H looks more
like a bento box.
I really like, I really like H.
You know there's a lot of
different sizes and variety.
It feels really fun.
>> [Sigh] Yeah H looks cool,
but I think it has a fatal slaw,
which is that some of these
entrees look more important
than others.
Like, we really want you
to buy grilled mahi-mahi
with this design.
And that's not really the case.
These should all
be equal options.
I think if we like this style,
I think G does a better job
with balancing this
edge-to-edge look
with the actual functional
intent of the app.
>> I still really like
H though [laughter],
but I think you make
good points.
>> Yeah.
>> I think we should go with G.
>> All right fair enough.
All right so between these
two, I actually really like J,
like I've said the edge-to-edge
photo thing is doing it for me.
And I love that this reminds
me of like a food magazine,
which I think is a
really cool style.
>> Ryan, we are not designing
a food magazine here,
we are designing a delivery app.
You can't even see
the words in J.
I like how K has a better
balance of photos and text.
Because it just seems more
relevant, and more appetizing.
>> All right I see
what you mean.
You gave me H, so
I'll give you K.
All right.
>> Okay, good.
>> Compromise.
[ Applause ]
>> All right now we're
down to our top three,
what do you think?
>> They look pretty good,
but you know seeing them side
by side, I think it's
sort of obvious now
that G is not that great.
These descriptions are
actually really useful to sort
of tell people what the food is.
And G just seems really
lacking in that regard.
>> Yeah. Seeing them all
together, I think you're right.
Even though I love the
edge-to-edge photo I think
having the descriptions,
the more information really
makes a better experience
so I guess we'll get rid of G.
>> Okay.
>> All right now
we're down to C and K
in just a few minutes
we've gotten
down to just two options
which is pretty cool.
These two are also very
functionally similar.
They both look great I think.
They do have pretty
different feel between them.
I don't actually, I
don't have a favorite
of these two, how about you?
>> Well [laughter], oh
I can't tell either.
They both look pretty good.
>> All right.
Well we were actually
worried it might come to this.
And so maybe all
of you can help us.
So given all of the, now you've
seen us critique our own designs
and given the goals and the
criteria we've been considering,
by round of applause, please
who thinks option C
is the better design?
[ Applause ]
Okay now, who thinks option
K is the better design?
[ Cheering ]
All right well I think
K pretty clearly won,
which is pretty convenient
for us [laughter].
All right so our
congratulations, option K.
Good job. So we've determined
as a large design team here
that option K is the
best combination maybe
of functionality, efficiency,
and the general feel we'd
like the app to have.
So now have we actually
found the right design?
Well, we're on our way, right,
but one screen is not an app.
We now actually have to figure
out how this thing works.
So to tell you more about that,
I'm going to give
this back to Jon.
>> Thank you [applause].
We need to design a workflow.
A workflow is a set of steps
it takes to complete a task.
In my case the task
is to order food.
So let's go back to the
design we just choose.
I think I'll take my
advice from before and start
with what I know here.
I don't know much about
what this is supposed to do,
but I do one thing,
that if I tap on one
of those entrees I probably
should see more information
about that.
So I'll go ahead and I'll
design a detail screen.
And maybe it looks
something like this.
Okay. So now that I'm here,
I probably need a
way to order food.
So I'll put in an Order button.
And maybe it will just go on the
bottom of the screen for now.
Excellent.
And now what happens if I
tap on this Order button?
Well, I don't know.
Maybe I'll just finish the order
and let the user know
that they're done.
So, I've designed a workflow.
It looks pretty good.
I think it gets the job
done of ordering food.
But you know now
that I look at it,
I think there's some problems.
It's actually missing a
little bit of functionality
that we talked about before.
You can't actually change order
details, where it's going to,
or when it's going to come,
so that's a little bit weird.
And now that I look at it, the
commitment is really abrupt.
After I hit the order button,
I've already spent $10.
There's probably
a rule somewhere
that says you shouldn't do that.
So I think there's
a lot of things
that maybe this workflow
could do better
so let's try that again.
So, in a couple apps I've
seen the shopping cart model.
So I think I'm going to
borrow that for this one.
So in the upper right hand
corner now there's a shopping
cart icon.
And now if I tap in food
there's an Add to Cart button.
And now I could tap that,
the button will say it's
been added to the cart.
And my icon will
change to let me know
that there's something in it.
It seems like a pretty
conventional behavior,
so that's really nice.
I think people will
know how to use that.
And now if I tap on the shopping
cart icon I can show the user a
summary of their order.
And from here they could maybe
change the options as well as,
to get a confirmation
that they're
about to spend 11.68 for food.
And now if they tap Place
Order, I can show them
that the orders complete and
give them information about it.
So, now my work flow
looks something like this.
It addresses the problems
I mentioned before.
It lets me know the
details of my order,
and it does not make the
ordering feel too abrupt.
It lets the user know
what's happening,
so I think that's really nice.
But you know I don't think this
workflow is that good either,
it's actually a whole lot of
steps for something as simple
as ordering a sandwich.
So I think we can
make it a lot shorter.
And I actually noticed,
having done this twice now
that the menu screen
does a pretty good job
of giving people
information about the food,
and they might not have
to go to the detail screen
to actually figure out
if they want to order it.
So maybe the user can determine
to order the food right
from the menu screen.
So let's try this again,
let's try to make
this workflow shorter.
So here, I put the Buy buttons
right on the menu screen,
because that seems like
enough information.
And now if the user taps
on one of those buttons,
maybe we keep the shopping cart
model, but instead of an icon
in the corner, it's
now this little tray
that comes up on bottom.
Here, I could actually show
information about the order,
and even let them
finish ordering it right
from the menu screen.
If they want to I guess, they
could just still swipe it up
and see the full
details of their orders
and the different options.
But I think for the most part,
this might be enough information
for someone to figure
out if they want
to complete this order.
And I could actually extend
this further, if the user taps
on the Order button, I could
use the same little tray
and show the confirmation
status.
So now, the workflow
looks something like this.
It's three steps, but
it feels a lot shorter
because all that's
happening on the menu screen.
And it still has all
of the functionality
as the previous design, but
now all of that's optional
under the tray rather
than forcing it
to be a mandatory
step for the user.
So that's really nice.
So I think this workflow
is pretty good.
I think it gets the job
done of ordering food
and I think it does
it very quickly.
Notice how to design this,
I used the same principles
that we talked about before.
I started with what I knew and
then I evaluated and iterated
on all my designs until I ended
up with something
I was happy with.
So now to wrap things up, let
me give this back to Ryan.
[ Applause ]
Thank you, Jon.
I can't wait to use
our pretend app.
All right so to wrap up, we
only have a couple minutes.
I hope we've been able to convey
a few key points to you today.
First, good design is not easy.
It can be a lot of fun,
but it takes time, energy,
and thoughtful deliberation.
But by using the methods
we've shared with you today,
it can be a little bit easier.
If you're trying to figure out
what the heck are we making?
Define your audience's goals
and your own app goals.
And then use those to
choose the features
that best serve everyone's
needs.
If you know what
you want to make,
but don't know what
the UI should look
or feel like, just
start drawing.
Start with what you do
know and build from there.
It's okay if you don't have
the whole system figured
out ahead of time.
And it's our completely unbiased
opinion, but try using Keynote,
we think you might like it.
And finally to find the right
design, try lots of ideas.
Don't settle for
your first concept,
or what might be good enough.
Then critique your
designs to determine
which options best suits
your customer goals
and your app goals.
Keep iterating and evaluating
until the design feels right.
So, we hope you'll
take these techniques
and methods back
to your own work.
Give yourself the time
to explore, iterate
and critique your designs.
We think you'll find
it was worth it.
You can find more information
about our session here.
Please also check out
these related sessions.
They're all awesome.
I think they're all online now.
Thank you everyone for coming.
[ Applause ]