[ Music ]
>> Ladies and gentlemen, please
welcome Vice President of
Software, Sebastian
Marineau-Mes.
[ Applause ]
>> Good afternoon, everyone.
Welcome to the afternoon session
of WWDC 2018.
Now, we had a really, really
great session this morning.
I think you all enjoyed the
keynote?
Lots of great things were
presented.
And I think you saw that 2018 is
a year with a strong focus on
the fundamentals across our
entire ecosystem where we pushed
the boundaries in key technology
areas.
We're introducing numerous APIs
and capabilities that enable new
experiences covering a broad
spectrum that ranges from
machine learning, augmented
reality, high performance
graphics and of course, new
development tools.
Now, many of the improvements in
the APIs apply to all of our
operating systems so they all
move forward together.
And iCloud provides the fabric
that enables a unified and
consistent experience across all
of our devices.
In iOS 12, we've seen a huge
number of incredible new
features including these great
new capabilities in AR, the
camera effects in Messages,
multi-way FaceTime, usage data
with Screen Time, richer photos
and of course, a great focus on
performance.
And with macOS, we're really
excited to introduce Dark Mode,
New Finder on desktop features,
new apps like news and stocks, a
redesigned Mac App Store, and a
strong focus on security and
privacy, watchOS 5 brings
customizable interactive
notifications, support for your
app content and shortcuts on the
Siri Watch face, background
audio mode and improved workout
API.
And in tvOS, we're adding Dolby
Atmos support so that video apps
can deliver immersive audio
experiences.
We heard that this morning,
really amazing.
Secure password sharing from iOS
devices so it makes it really
easy to slide into through Apple
TV apps, VPP support and
enhancements to UIKit and TV ML
Kit to make it even easier for
you to build native apps that
look and feel great.
Now our great products are
platforms and all of your apps
truly impact the world.
And when you think of the
breadth and the scale of our
ecosystem, it really makes us an
essential part of our users'
life.
Be it helping them explore their
creativity, connecting with the
people they care most about or
transforming the way that
healthcare is delivered, we
together focus on what's most
important to our users and we
deliver these great experiences.
Now we think technology is most
powerful when it empowers
everyone.
And so we work to make every
Apple product accessible from
the very start.
We provide great capabilities
that make our platforms and all
of your apps accessible and we
want to encourage you to take,
keep taking advantage of these
because it's really important to
those users.
Now, our users also entrust us
with their most precious data.
And so at Apple, we think deeply
about privacy and security.
And I'd like to invite Katie up
on stage to tell you more about
this.
Katie?
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Sebastian.
When we think about privacy, we
think about how to build privacy
into all their products and
services.
And there could be a lot of
details to think about.
But it's important to think of
the big picture, trust.
Now it's up to all of us to
ensure that users can protect,
can trust us to protect their
most sensitive data.
From financial data to
communications to location and
photos, trust is crucial as
technology becomes more and more
integrated into our lives.
So how can you build trust with
your users?
We focus on four key pillars and
let me show you an example of
each.
Now, we don't require users to
sign into Maps but instead we
use rotating random identifiers
that can't be tied to an Apple
ID to enable relevant results.
We use on-device intelligence to
enable powerful features like
search and memories in photos
without analyzing photos in the
cloud.
We designed Face ID so all Face
ID data is encrypted, protected
by the Secure Enclave and
doesn't ever leave your device.
And when we collect users' data
or allow a third party to
collect data like photos, we
make sure we do so with the
user's consent.
So let's dive a little bit
deeper into transparency and
control.
You have all seen these alerts
when you request access to
location or photos.
And this alert includes a
purpose string.
Now this is what you provide in
order to explain why you're
requesting data and how you will
use that data.
Now a good string includes a
clear explanation of what
features it will enable and what
functionality it will improve.
Now, the more specific you are
with your users, the more likely
they are to grant you access.
We think it's critically
important to understand and for
users to understand how their
data will be used.
So app review is paying closer
attention to these purpose
strings.
So if you have a purpose string
like this, which you know, it's
clearly not valid, you may get
dinged by app review.
Now this string technically
explains how data will be used.
But it lacks detail so it's
really hard for your user to
make a decision.
Now some users may have concerns
about granting your app
microphone access but it may be
key to your app's functionality.
So that's why it's important to
have a clear purpose string like
this one that explains exactly
how you are going to use the
data.
Now great features don't have to
be at the expense of privacy.
But instead can support them by
making it clear to users how
you're going to protect their
data and how it's being used.
Now, we care deeply about
security.
And in order to protect all the
sensitive data that resides on
the device in apps and in the
cloud, we think about security
holistically.
And we provide technologies to
make it easy for you to build
secure apps.
Here's a few examples of the
technologies that we provide.
On iOS, we automatically encrypt
app data by default.
Over the network, App Transport
Security means you never have to
patch client networking
libraries again.
Now in CloudKit in the cloud,
CloudKit securely stores and
syncs data across devices.
Letting you focus on building a
great experience for your users
without having to worry about
managing account state or your
cloud credentials.
And it enables you to take the
best, advantage the best
in-class security including
built-in two-factor
authentication.
Since its launch three years
ago, more than two-thirds of
Apple ID accounts have adopted
two-factor authentication.
This is a huge success compared
to the rest of the industry
where we see less than 10% of
accounts protected by two-factor
authentication.
But this is very important to
us.
And we work continuously to make
our users' accounts more secure
so you're the only person who
can access your account even if
someone else knows your
password.
And new in iOS 12, we're making
using passwords more convenient
and more secure for you and your
users.
We all know that a secure
password is critically important
to keeping your information and
your identity secure.
But they can be hard to remember
and it's tempting to use weak or
reuse passwords.
And this creates problems for
you as a developer as well.
Now, users may abandon account
sign up and you have to deal
with password reset requests.
But worst of all, is the
potential for compromised
accounts due to weak passwords.
So we have a solution -- iOS 12
makes it easy for you and your
users to always use a strong
unique password by creating,
storing and AutoFilling the
password.
But the really great thing is it
will also work automatically in
your iOS app too so they always
get a strong password no matter
where they create an account and
it syncs to all of their
devices.
Now it couldn't be easier to
offer automatic strong
passwords.
In fact, you may not need to
make any changes within your
app.
So to ensure it just works, you
need to associate your app with
the domain.
You may have already done this
if you have adopted universal
links.
Then you need to label your user
name and password fields.
And if the passwords don't meet
your app requirements, now you
can even customize them.
We've also made it easier for
your users to get to their
passwords.
They can just ask Siri and once
they've authenticated, they're
taken right to their password
list.
And on top of that, to help
clear up old password since,
we're making it really easy to
tell if any of your passwords
have been reused across your
existing accounts.
Your iPhone would flag these
passwords and take you right to
the website where you'll be able
to replace it with a strong
password.
We're also make it easier to
deal with those one-time
passcodes that are texted to you
and your users much more
convenient.
They'll automatically appear
right in the click tap bar and
you can fill them in with just a
tap.
[ Applause ]
We're also creating a new
extension point for third-party
password managers to enable them
to supply passwords for AutoFill
and apps in Safari.
[ Applause ]
Now these features work across
iOS, the Mac and even Apple TV
for a great experience across
your Apple devices.
We care deeply about privacy and
security.
And they're foundational to all
of our products.
So we provide the ability for
you to build on this foundation
to protect, secure and earn your
users' trust.
And now, handing it back to
Sebastian.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Katie.
Isn't -- aren't these new
password features amazing?
Really, really great.
That was great.
Thank you.
Now, ultimately, we also promise
our users great experiences.
And we usually think about great
experiences as being great
innovative features.
But equally important is not to
compromise that delight with
unpredictable and slow software.
This is top of mind for the
Apple Engineering Team.
We develop tools and practices
that help us with this.
And then we work to bring these
same tools to all of you so that
you can apply them through
applications.
Available to you are a number of
tools and techniques to help you
make your code more reliable and
robust.
It's important for your app to
be predictable.
And of course, making your app
run fast is critical.
And for that, we have a number
of performance tools at your
disposal.
Now we understand that
optimizing performance across
complex systems and applications
is challenging.
And this year, we worked a lot
on this.
We've developed a lot of new
tools and techniques and want to
bring you some of these powerful
new capabilities.
So in Xcode 10, we've extended
instruments capabilities and
enabled you to take it even
further with your own custom
tools and work flows.
Now this all starts from a
legacy API.
Some of you may know this and
have used it.
I know I'm guilty of it --
printf, it's like the Swiss Army
knife of APIs.
We use it to debug and trace
through our code but we all know
that it's slow.
And so two years ago, we brought
you this new API called os log.
It's an efficient and performant
API that captures logs and
tracepoints across all levels of
the system.
It's fast and lightweight and if
you've not adopted it already,
you really should.
It's great.
And our newest addition this
year builds on top of os log and
it's called os signpost.
It's a powerful technique that
provides rich, contextual data
for your application in a format
that instruments can interpret.
So you could use signpost to
trace through your code and you
can also use it to bookend
critical sections of your
functions.
And once you have the data, the
real power comes in the built-in
custom instruments
visualization.
Now, we have this new Custom
Instruments support and the best
way to convey the full power of
this, I think, is through demo
so Ken will show us what our
tools can do.
Ken?
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Sebastian.
So I'm working on my Solar
System Exploration app here.
And I've noticed I've got a
little bit of a performance
problem.
So every time the app goes to
update its data, you know, when
it launches or when I press
command R like that, you can see
the UI, it gets really choppy.
The planets, they kind of
stutter as they move around
their orbits.
And then once the update
completes, well, it's pretty
smooth.
So I want to figure out what's
going on here.
Now back over in my code,
PlanetUpdateService.swift --
this is the file that handles
that planetary update.
So I want to add some logs, some
signposts to help me understand
what's going on in my code.
So I'm going to start by adding
a log handle.
So I'm going to use the new
pointsOfInterest category.
Now this is a special new
category.
Anything that I log with it is
automatically going to show up
right inside instruments.
Now, the first thing I want to
see is when we kick off this
update.
And that happens in this method.
So I'm going to add my first log
statement here.
I'm going to say requesting
planet data so that we could see
that.
And then what I really want to
know is how long is it taking to
process and parse all the data
that I'm doing here?
So right here is where that
happens.
And to help me visualize this,
I'm going to add a couple of
signposts.
So the first signpost is going
to be a begin-type signpost
here, just before I start doing
the work.
Then I'm going to add another
signpost right here after I
finish doing the work.
That's an end-type signpost.
So this is going to create a
time interval for me,
automatically calculate the
delta and surface that right up
through instruments.
So let's profile this in
Instruments and see what kind of
data we get.
So I go to Product, select
Profile.
Xcode's going to build my app,
launch Instruments and then
we'll start to see, well, we'll
start seeing data stream in
here.
Now right here, you can see the
pointsOfInterest track.
So everything that I was logging
with the pointsOfInterest
category, that shows up here so
this is my data.
I want to zoom in.
So I'm going to hold on Option
and click and drag so we can get
a closer look.
And we can see this little flag
right here that says requesting
planet data.
So that's a result of the first
log I added in my code.
Then these blue bars right here,
this is where I'm processing and
parsing data.
So those are the results of the
signpost I added.
Now, as I look at this, I think
I see what the problem might be
right away.
So every time I go to process
data and parse it here, I can
see a corresponding spike in the
CPU use on the main thread.
And to me, that is a bright red
flag that I'm probably parsing
and processing this on the main
thread.
Not a recipe for a smooth UI.
So with just a log statement, a
couple of signposts, you could
see I can start to get some
really great insight into the
performance of my app.
Now the new tools, they let you
do way more than that.
So with Xcode 10, there's a new
template that lets you create a
fully customized Instruments
package.
Now, one of my team mates, he's
gone ahead and built one based
on some network, some signposts
that he added to our networking
framework.
And I've got the latest version
he sent me here in my downloads.
So let me open that up and when
I do, Instruments offers to
install it for me.
So I'll say install.
And now you'll see, I've got a
new template.
Here are my templates.
These are called Solar Systems.
I'm going to double click that.
And then we'll start recording
data again.
Now, just like before, I have
the pointsOfInterest tracked so
that is on the data that I
wanted to see.
But now, I've got much more
detailed information about the
networking request that I'm
making here.
So again, let me zoom in so we
can get a closer look.
Now, this custom Instruments
package here is giving me a
great visualization into how I'm
using this framework.
So it's showing me things like
for example here, how many
network requests am I making on
average every 10th of a second.
Then down here, this track is
showing me detailed information
about each and every network
request.
How long did it take?
It's even highlighting duplicate
requests in red.
So these are places where I'm
asking for the exact same data
more than once.
It looks like I'm doing that
maybe even more than 50% of the
time.
So I'm just leaving a ton of
performance on the table and
it's exactly these kinds of
insights that I need to help me
use this framework more
effectively.
So signposts, Custom Instruments
packages, two really great new
ways for you to visualize your
data right in Instruments.
And that's a look at the new
performance tools.
Sebastian?
[ Applause ]
>> All right.
Thank you, Ken.
That's a really, really amazing
demo.
Really great tools that all of
you can use to make your apps
run even faster.
Now, to recap, we just reviewed
a lot of great tools and best
practices that we can use to
ensure that we delight our users
and keep their trust.
Now, I'd like to turn our
attention to the Mac.
OS X was launched 17 years ago
and we've constantly pushed the
platform forward.
64-bit support in Leopard, MacOS
Mountain Lion introduced
Gatekeeper, a key step forward
in Mac security.
And one of our key missions is
to always push the Mac forward
by extending its capabilities to
take advantage of the latest
technologies.
But as we push the platform
forward, we sometimes have to
deprecate legacy functionality
to ensure that we're not holding
it back.
Last year, we announced that
High Sierra was the last MacOS
release to fully support 32-bit
apps without compromise.
And this year, we're announcing
that MacOS Mojave is the last
release to support 32-bit at
all.
So as we remove 32-bit support
next year, these 32-bit only
frameworks will also be removed
such as the QuickTime framework
and the Apple Java framework.
Next, let's look at security on
the Mac.
Gatekeeper has done a great job
at avoiding large-scale malware
attacks and this year, we want
to push it even further.
We're extending user consent,
enhancing run time security and
we're launching a new Notary
Service.
So let's look at these in more
detail.
As you heard this morning, we're
extending the protections
afforded to sensitive system
resources.
We've added camera and
microphone and we now require
user consent for API and direct
access to all these resources.
What does it mean in practice?
Well, it means that your
application has to gracefully
handle those calls potentially
blocking or failing as the user
provides consent.
It's also a really great idea,
as Katie has pointed out, to
provide meaningful purpose
strings so when the user is
faced with one of these
dialogues, they understand why
your app needs access.
We're also going further in
protecting sensitive user data.
And only specialized apps like
backup tools require access to
this kind of data.
And so we'll protect these
locations by requiring user
consent directly in the security
and privacy preference pane.
Next, we're introducing
enhancements to run time
protections.
Now, a number of you have
requested a way to extend the
zip protections to your own
apps.
And our new enhanced run times,
there's a new security baseline
that requires risky capabilities
to be opted in.
So beyond strong code
validation, if for example also
protects your apps from code
injection.
The enhanced run time is fully
backwards compatible.
It's opt in through a simple
switch in Xcode.
And finally, we're introducing
the concept of notarized apps.
This is an extension to the
Developer ID program for apps
that are distributed outside of
the Mac App Store.
And it has two main goals.
The first is to detect malware
even faster than today before it
gets distributed to our users.
And second, provide a
finer-grained revocation
capability so that we can revoke
a specific version of a
compromised app as opposed to
revoking the entire signing
certificate.
Now here's how it works.
You develop the bug and build
your app as before.
And you sign it with your
Developer ID Certificate.
But before distributing it to
your users, you submit to the
Developer ID Notary Service.
Once notarized, you distribute
the app through your existing
channel.
Once your user runs the app on
their system, MacOS Mojave will
check with the Notary Service to
make sure the app is properly
notarized and is not known to be
malicious.
Now, the service is not app
review.
There are no new guidelines
being imposed on Developer ID
apps as a result of the Notary
Service.
It is used exclusively to
analyze apps for security
purposes.
A future version of MacOS will
require all Developer ID apps to
be notarized by the service
before they can be installed so
we want you to get ready.
It's available in beta today.
We encourage you to try it out
and give us feedback.
And those are the enhancements
to Gatekeeper in MacOS Mojave.
Let's now switch gears and talk
about the MacOS user experience.
And to do that, I'd like to
invite Kristen up on stage.
Kristen?
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Sebastian.
I'm excited to be here.
We have a lot of great features
in MacOS Mojave including
improvements to Finder,
SnapShots and desktops docs.
I'd like to focus on one in
particular that you, as
developers, can take advantage
of.
And that's Quick Actions.
With Finder Quick Actions, we've
embedded the tools you need
right where you need them in the
Finder preview pane.
You can perform common actions
on your files without ever
leaving Finder.
And there's different actions
for different file types.
As you can see here with video
and here, with a PDF.
And it's not just built-in
actions.
We know pro users especially
like to create their own.
And those actions are shown here
in Finder as well.
New developers will be able to
provide custom actions from your
applications using app
extensions.
And as an end-user, you can also
combine shell scripts,
AppleScripts and Automator
Actions in Automator to create
an action bundle.
And these action bundles will be
shown here in Finder as well
based on file type.
These Custom Actions get some
prime real estate in Finder and
even more so in Touch Bar.
Touch Bar is great when
customized.
And you can customize Touch Bar
to show these actions all the
time or on the tap of a button.
Moving on, in the keynote this
morning, you got a sneak peek at
another technology we are really
excited about.
An easy way to bring iOS apps to
the Mac.
We are in the midst of
developing this technology in
the context of these four apps,
News, Stocks, Voice Memos and
Home.
These apps utilize UIKit and
this is a new way to delivery
great Mac apps.
Of course, AppKit is our primary
native framework and it takes
full advantage of all the Mac
has to offer.
And in no way are we
de-emphasizing that.
However, we note that a lot of
you have iOS apps and you don't
have a native Mac experience.
And for these cases, we want you
to -- we want to give you an
easy way to bring your apps to
the Mac as well.
So how are we doing this?
These UIKit apps are running in
a native environment on top of a
native stack.
And if you look closely, you'll
see that the stack below the
UIKit app has a lot in common
with the stack below the AppKit
app.
In fact, these environments were
built on a common foundation
which in some cases has drifted
apart over time.
So we're taking this opportunity
to rationalize the substrate
which is great news for you
developers independent of this
technology because it makes it
easier for you to write portable
code.
These apps get all the typical
Mac features and I'd like to
show that to you now.
You've seen the new Stocks app
for iPad.
I'm running a Mac version of
this app built from the same
sources.
Mouse events are mapped to UI
events so I can click on a
ticker symbol in the watchlist
to see more information.
I can move my mouse over the
interactive chart to see the
price at a point in time and I
can click and drag to see the
price change over a period of
time.
I'm going to click on an article
to open it right here in app.
Now since this is a Mac window,
I can resize it as I would like
and I can also take it full
screen.
I can navigate using two-finger
scroll which is another example
of event mapping.
And if I want to copy some text,
I can select it, pick it up and
drag it and drop it in my Notes
app.
Now in this Note, I have a link
to a news article so I'm going
to click that to open it
directly in News.
And we've populated the menu
with items for this application.
So for example, I can go to the
file menu and I can follow this
channel.
And notice how ESPN appears
directly in my transition
sidebar.
Another Mac touch can be seen in
the toolbar here where there's a
red color contribution coming
from the content underneath it.
Now we have controls for the
window in the toolbar including
the share button so I can click
on the share button to show this
article with a friend.
So that's a quick look at UIKit
apps on the Mac.
[ Applause ]
Now, thank you.
We are continuing to develop
this technology and we are
working to fully vet it before
making it available to you and
your applications which we are
planning to do next year.
Next, Dark Mode -- you've seen
that Dark Mode is a big thing
for MacOS Mojave and we think it
looks stunning.
Let's take a quick tour.
The window background is dark
making the content pop.
The sidebar is translucent and
the content is blended vibrantly
which preserves contrast with
whatever may be underneath the
window.
And in a few cases, we found it
valuable to change the icons
slightly so you can see a slight
darkening of this photo icon and
a new dark trash can.
But there's something very
subtle here.
The window background is
actually picking up a slight
hint of color from the desktop.
To show you what I mean, here is
a window on top of two very
different desktop pictures.
On the left side, there's a
slight blue tint in the window
from that slightly blue desktop
picture.
And on the right side, there's a
slight orange tint from the
predominantly orange desktop
picture.
This is not translucency.
We're actually picking up our
average color from the desktop
and blending it into an opaque
background.
And we do this so that your
window looks harmonious with a
variety of desktop pictures.
Let's look at what you need to
do in your apps to support Dark
Mode.
Because we want to make sure to
preserve compatibility with your
applications, we are not
automatically opting you in.
You need to build against the
MacOS Mojave STKit.
For example, this is how Keynote
looked when we first ran it
after building on Mojave.
It got a dark toolbar but it
didn't otherwise adopt to Dark
Mode the way we wished.
The [inaudible] part is drawing
too light of a background.
The toolbar controls are faint
and hard to read.
The sidebar is the wrong
material so it's too
translucent.
And in the selected segment in
control, we have a white glyph
on a white background.
The good news is these issues
were all easy to fix.
We have simple API that support
all the needs of Dark Mode.
And in fact, most of these have
existed for years and we just
had to augment them a tiny bit.
There's NSColor.
There's Container Views with
background color properties.
There's Visual Effect View in
materials.
There's Template Images and a
new way to colorize your
content.
So we updated Keynote with these
APIs and this is the result.
It looks great.
These were pretty simple
changes.
We invite you to try this today.
If you're already following the
best practices of using asset
catalogs in system colors, you
could be pleasantly surprised at
how close you already are.
And since these techniques are
available on previous releases,
you can adopt and easily
back-deploy.
It, of course, depends on how
many custom controls you have in
your applications but for a few
of our apps, it was as little as
a day of work.
We give you some useful tools
for it as well.
Well, I'd like to welcome
Matthew to the stage to show you
how Xcode 10 supports adoption
of Dark Mode and much more.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Kristen.
Our Xcode release this year is
focused on the productivity.
Work flow improvements,
performance improvements and new
feature support in all of our
STKits.
And of course, when running on
MacOS Mojave, Xcode has a whole
new look and feel.
So let's start by taking a sneak
peek at how Xcode can make your
Mac apps look great in Dark Mode
too.
So here we are back in our solar
system application.
We've been converting it over to
Dark Mode and we've made great
progress so far.
There's a couple of items left I
need to finish here.
There's a darker version of this
globe my designers have provided
to us.
And there's these two hard-coded
boxes that have colors that I
need to change.
Xcode's asset catalogs makes
this easy.
Let's start with this image.
I'll change over to the tab with
my assets and we can see, I've
already defined dark variance
for all of my colors.
I'll select the group with all
of my images and here's the
planet image I'd like to add a
dark variant for.
That's easy.
I'll select it.
Go in the Inspector and add a
dark variant.
And my designers have sent me
the assets here so I can just
pull them out of my downloads
folder and put them into the
catalog.
That's it.
You'll see when I go back to my
interface now, the globe is
updated to match the appearance
of the interface builder canvas.
Now, I've already specified all
the color variants that I need.
So to update these boxes, I'll
just select both of them, go to
the Inspector and change the
fill color to one of my catalog
colors.
We'll take the badge background
color.
Great, so now my interface is
looking pretty good.
Now when designing interfaces, I
often like to check the other
appearance as I'm going along to
evaluate my progress.
Interface Builder makes this
easy.
Down the bottom here, there's a
new appearance bar that allows
me to toggle between
appearances.
I'll just select the appearance
on the left and now I'm seeing
my application in the light
appearance as well.
So I can easily evaluate my
progress.
Let's run our application and
see how we've done.
We'll update our assets and
we'll launch our application.
And we'll see here that the
application launches.
And great, it's looking pretty
good.
Now the application launched in
the dark mode to match my
system.
But while I'm developing, I can
change the appearance.
Down here in the debug bar is a
new appearance toggle that's
also in Touch Bar, and it gives
me access to all the
appearances.
I can select the light mode, the
dark mode, even high-contrast
modes to evaluate accessibility.
So I'll select the light mode.
We'll load those assets, and
there's my application in light
mode as well.
So very simply, with asset
catalogs, interface builder, and
our debugging tools, it's really
easy to make your apps look
great in Dark Mode, too.
[ Applause ]
Now I know many of you have
wanted a dark mode appearance in
Xcode for a long time.
It's been one of our most
popular requests.
In fact, just a couple weeks
ago, there was a posting in the
App Store about this feature.
It was from a user name Ronnie
Bo Bonnie.
This is true -- I'm not making
this up.
But I just wanted to take a
moment and say Ronnie, if you
are out there, no charge.
[ Laughter ]
[ Applause ]
Now we also have some other
improvements to our design tools
to share with you today.
Form-based UIs like preferences
and inspectors are common in Mac
apps.
And Cocoa's NSGridView is the
perfect system for laying them
out.
So we're bringing the power of
NSGridView right into Interface
Builder where you can now design
your column- and row-based UIs
just like working with tables in
a spreadsheet.
Drag-and-drop content [applause]
-- yes.
Yeah, you can clap for that.
Spreadsheets can be cool.
You can drag-and-drop content,
use contextual actions, and you
get system access to things like
right-to-left layout.
Now when designing your
interfaces, the library is an
important tool, and we have a
whole new workflow for you
because the library is now
separate from the inspectors.
You can now take the library and
reposition it wherever you want.
you can adjust the size to match
your layout.
And you can keep the library up
while working or have it
automatically dismiss when you
are done.
[ Applause ]
And the library works great with
all of our content types,
including media and code
snippets.
And finally, with our design
tools, you'll notice they're
just snappier, with faster
document loading and more
responsive canvas interactions.
Now we've also spent time
focusing on our source editing
tools, keeping them fast, fluid,
and informative.
We started with performance,
where you'll now see the editor
loads large documents much
faster, all while keeping smooth
scrolling at 60 frames a second.
Next, we double down on
stability in SourceKit and
enhance the robustness of our
language integration.
So now more of your colorful
comments will stay inside of the
editor rather than being about
it.
[ Applause ]
Co-completion and navigation are
two essential workflows, and
we've improved on both.
Co-completion now provides more
targeted results and limits
completions to high-confidence
matches.
And when navigating, with jump
to definition, the destination
list will now provide contextual
details like file and line
information to help you easily
get to where you need to go.
[ Applause ]
And you'll see the same
contextual information in the
new callers option in the action
menu, which is a seamless way to
move throughout your projects.
Now last year, we introduced
refactoring for all languages,
including Swift.
And you, the Swift community,
embraced the opportunity and
added a number of new actions.
These actions all streamline
common programming scenarios and
are built right into Xcode now,
just a click away.
Now refactoring is just one of
many ways you can modify the
source in your project.
And to make it easier to keep
track of your changes, we're
introducing a source control
change bar.
The change bar is on the left
side of the editor and
highlights lines of code which
have changed since your last
checkout.
The style and color of the
indicator reveal the type of
change, making it easy for you
to see at a glance changes you
have made, your team members
have made, and those which might
be in conflict.
Now this feature is -- yes.
[ Applause ]
I agree. I think this feature is
pretty awesome.
And I'd actually like to show it
to you in a demo now.
So we're going to go back to our
solar system application, and I
have some changes I'd like to
make in one of our source files.
It's our scene view controller
here.
So I'll scroll down in the
editor to the place I'd like to
make changes.
And here we can see on the left
-- just to the left of the line
numbers -- the source control
change bar is indicating there's
some upstream changes a team
member has made.
In fact, if I had already made
the changes to this line, you'd
see the indicator turns red,
highlighting a conflict.
If I put my cursor over the
indicator, you'll see it
highlights the ranges of
characters which have changed
and are in conflict.
And if I click on the indicator,
it brings up an action menu with
both a description of the
changes and some actions I can
take I see my team member has
added more descriptive comments
here.
I think we'll take his change,
so I'll use the action menu to
discard my change, and go up
under the source control menu to
pull his changes in.
So here's his changes -- very
descriptive comments.
I can scroll to the bottom of
the editor, see if there's
anything else I'd like to look
at here.
Here's another new feature of
Xcode 10 -- our editor supports
overscroll now.
[ Applause ]
So going back to the lines of
code I'd like to change, I'd
like to convert these hard-coded
functions into properties that
pull the colors from the asset
catalog.
Now there are three of them that
I'd like to change, and they're
a bit spread out now because of
all these comments.
Well, no matter, with Xcode 10,
we've improved code folding.
Basically, you can now code fold
anything you want.
And we've brought back the code
folding ribbon.
So just to the right of the line
numbers, I can click --
[ Applause ]
-- to collapse the code away.
And we have this nice, svelte
presentation of the collapsing
now.
Now this is the first function
I'd like to change, and I see
that all of these functions are
very similar, and it would be
great if I could make all of
these changes all at the same
time.
Well, I can do that now, too,
with multi-cursor editing.
[ Applause ]
The key to multi-cursor editing
is two fingers, control and
shift.
So I'll hold down those two keys
and just click at the beginning
of each of the other functions.
We'll use range selection, and
we'll just change that to VAR.
We'll change those into colons.
And we're pretty good so far.
Now I happen to know that I've
named my colors in the catalog
the same name as my properties
here.
So we'll just select those names
and copy them.
And now let's go to the
implementation and change that.
So we'll drop three more
cursors, and we'll just select
all of this, type in named,
paste in those colors, and we've
made all those changes.
It's like three times faster.
[ Applause ]
Now multi-cursor editing also
works great with column
selection.
So here I have all of my
IBOutlets defined with week.
If I hold down the option key
and I select all of these in
here [cheering] -- oh, yeah.
Oh, yeah, so let's just convert
those into [applause] unowned.
And just like that, I can make
my changes, and then use the
source control bar to make sure
that I got the changes I want.
So those are some of the great
new editing features you'll find
in Xcode 10.
[ Applause ]
So additions like the source
control change bar and
multi-cursor editing alongside
performance and stability
improvements.
Xcode 10 continues to raise the
bar on our source editing
experience.
Now in addition to the source
control change bar, we are also
extending our source control
integration.
We started first by unifying our
conflict resolution system with
Git, making the results more
accurate, more predictable, and
significantly faster.
Next, we've enhanced the pull
action to support rebase.
So you can replay changes
between branches [applause] --
yes, it's okay to clap for that.
[ Applause ]
You can replay changes easily
between branches without the
unnecessary merge commits.
And to keep your connections
secure, Xcode will help you
create SSH keys and upload them
directly to your service
accounts.
[ Applause ]
And this is the perfect
accompaniment for our service
integrations, because in
addition to GitHub, we're adding
two new services this year,
support for Atlassian's
Bitbucket cloud and Bitbucket
server --
[ Applause ]
-- and support for GitLab.com
and self-hosting.
[ Applause ]
There's a lot of source control
love here.
And both of these work great
because their web interfaces
will check out directly into
Xcode.
Now as Sebastian mentioned
earlier, we are passionate about
giving you great tools to debug
and optimize your apps.
And this year, we focused on the
usability and performance of our
tools.
We started with LLDB, our
lower-level debugger.
Which now has faster startup and
more precise access to your
variables in the console and
Xcode's variables view.
Next, we've made downloading
debug symbols five-times faster.
So now it's more like seconds
rather than minutes.
[ Applause ]
We've enhanced our memory
debugging tools to have faster
loading, and saving of
documents, and a new compact
layout to help you visualize
even more of your application at
once.
And earlier this spring, we
introduced energy diagnostic
reports.
They're like crash logs, but for
energy usage.
These reports are automatically
collected on iOS for test flight
in App Store apps and surface
details for foreground and
background usage.
These reports show up in the
organizer and include stack
frames to illustrate the issue.
And just like with crash logs,
you can open these reports in
your project to navigate your
code and find and fix the
issues.
Oh, and to go alongside these,
we also have some improvements
in testing.
Earlier this spring, we enhanced
code coverage, adding a command
line tool to access coverage
data, and giving you the ability
to select individual targets to
collect coverage for.
This means your coverage reports
can now be actively focused on
the areas you are coding and
testing.
In addition to these, we're
adding two new testing workflows
this year -- actually, three.
The first is that you can now
automatically include or exclude
new tests in your test bundles.
Next, you can randomize the
order that your tests are
executed in to minimize
accidental dependencies.
And our biggest change for this
year is you can now execute your
tests in parallel inside of
Xcode.
[ Applause ]
Now last year, you could use
Xcodebuild to test on many
devices in parallel, sending all
the same tests to each device.
Now this is perfect for use with
continuous integration where you
want the broadest scale of
testing.
When you're working in Xcode,
you're more often focused on a
single configuration.
And once you're testing, to
finish as quickly as possible.
This is the configuration Xcode
10 dramatically improves with
parallel testing.
Behind the scenes, Xcode will
create copies of your Mac app or
clones of your iOS simulator and
then fan your tests suites out
to them.
This means you continue to test
a single configuration, but your
tests finish in a fraction of
the time.
And parallel testing
automatically scales to the
capacity of your machine, which
means on an iMac Pro, it can be
pretty awesome.
How awesome, you might ask?
Well, let's see in another demo.
So we're going to go back to our
solar system project one more
time.
And here we see the testing log
for our Mac tests that we ran
before.
Took about 14 seconds.
Let's run it with parallel
testing now.
I'll click and hold on the
toolbar and select the test
action.
And we'll bring up the scheme
sheet.
In the options, I'll just click
execute in parallel and click
test, and we're going to build
our tests for parallelization.
And if you watch the doc in the
lower right, you'll see that we
launch the tests, we now launch
many different processes -- this
is one for each of our test
suites -- and collect the
results.
And if we look at our testing
log, it finished almost four
times faster.
[ Applause ]
So where parallel testing works
great for unit tests, it works
awesomely for UI tests.
So I will select the iOS version
of our application, and we'll
kick off testing.
So behind the scenes, we're
going to go and clone the active
simulator, and then set up a
number of debug sessions for
each one of these, and then
switch over to a space with all
of those simulators running.
So you'll see we'll install
different test suites on each of
these simulators and kick off a
different set of tests on each.
So I can run all of my same
tests faster on all these
devices, which gives me the
ability to add more tests and
make a much better app.
This is ludicrously awesome
parallel testing in Xcode 10.
[ Applause ]
Last year, we introduced a
preview of our new build system
written in Swift.
Many of you tried it out with
your projects and provided great
feedback.
And so I'm happy to say our
modern build system is now on
for all projects.
In addition to greater
reliability and stability, we
also focused on overall build
performance.
You'll find the build system now
has faster rebuilds, better task
parallelization, and uses less
memory.
And the build system now
includes new richer diagnostics
to help you tune your project
configuration to achieve the
best build performance.
Now staying on build performance
for a second, I'd like to talk
up another core component of our
release, Swift 4.2.
Over the last year, we have made
steady improvements to compile
times with Swift projects.
We've sampled a number of open
source iOS applications, and
compared to our previous
release, debug build performance
with Xcode 10 is often twice as
fast.
And for release builds, code
size is up to 30% smaller using
the new size optimization, which
is a great win for cellular
downloads.
Now in addition to these, Swift
also adds a number of additions
and runtime language
improvements.
Some of these are
tongue-twisting APIs like
synthesized hashtable
conformance.
A perfect place to try out these
APIs is in Xcode Playgrounds
because Xcode Playgrounds now
include new [inaudible]-like
interaction that allows you to
evaluate new lines of code
without restarting the
Playground session.
[ Applause ]
Here's a Playground of our solar
system view.
And the new lines of code added
to move to the next planet are
evaluated and return results all
while the Playground continues
to run.
So all of these additions to the
runtime language and tools
continue Swift's great momentum
as part of Xcode 10.
And we also have another release
coming up for you in the
language, Swift 5.
The focus of Swift 5 is greater
adoption by delivering Swift as
part of the OS.
Apps will no longer need to
include the Swift runtime when
delivering on our newer OS
releases, resulting in smaller
downloads [applause] and faster
launches.
[ Applause ]
We're very excited about this,
too, and we have made great
progress toward this goal.
And you'll see it in a release
coming early next year.
So Xcode 10 includes a number of
great productivity improvements,
alongside deep investments in
performance, robustness, and
stability throughout our tools.
And all of this to help you do
your best work now faster than
ever.
And that is Xcode 10.
[ Applause ]
Next, I'd like to invite up John
to tell you what's new in
Machine Learning.
John?
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Matthew.
Machine Learning is at the
foundation of our operating
systems and many of our
applications.
But our goal has been to provide
simple and easy-to-use API to
make Machine Learning accessible
to everyone.
And you've all done a fantastic
job brining so many innovative
features and intelligence to
your applications.
Last year we introduced Core ML
with its base performance
frameworks as well as Vision and
Natural Language at a high
level.
And I'd like to start by showing
you some improvements we're
making with Vision and Natural
Language.
If we take Vision and, of
course, a photo that we want to
have depth, we now have APIs
that support object detection
and bounding boxes like this
sign being held in the picture.
We can do face detect, facial
landmark detection.
And also, barcode like this QR
code can be detected in your
image.
Now in addition to the APIs we
previously provided for depth,
we now support people
segmentation, so you can remove
a person from a photo and
separate them from the
background or substitute in the
background for something a
little different.
For Natural Language, we have a
brand-new, easy-to-use,
Swift-focused API.
So you can take simple sentences
like this one and automatically
identify it as the English
language.
You can tokenize the sentence
and convert it into its speech
parts all with simple API.
And as one other option, you can
do named-entity recognition.
Here, determining that the
sentence is talking about Apple
as the organization and a
location in San Jose.
Now you might think this is easy
in languages like English, but
we support many more, including
French, German, Japanese, and
this Simplified Chinese example.
now let's look at Core ML.
This is our foundation of our
Machine Learning technologies.
And just one year ago, we
introduced Core ML here.
And since then, we've got
adoption of every major Machine
Learning training framework and
format.
This is just incredible to have
achieved in only one year.
But we didn't want to stop
there.
We're introducing Core ML 2.
And we focused on making the
models execute faster, those
models smaller, and making it
far more customizable.
And we know these are the
features that were most
recommended -- requested.
To look at performance
improvements, we've added a new
batch API.
Where previously you needed to
do inference on each image,
passing them between the CPU and
GPU, you can now bundle those
inference requests together and
exploit the full performance of
the CPU and GPU.
Through this technique and
enhancements to the Metal
Performance Shaders underneath,
we now have up to 30%
performance improvement on large
networks like Resnet.
But if you're using a smaller
network like the kind you're
going to be using on iOS, we see
up to four times improvement
when running with MobileNet.
Now we didn't stop there.
We wanted to look at making the
model smaller, so we now support
quantization.
So we can take a model that
previously had shipped in 4.3 --
such as this example again from
MobileNet -- and reduce it down
to Int 8, and take its size from
17 megabytes to less than 5.
This is a huge saving for the
models that you bundle with your
applications.
Now you can do further reduction
through features like table
lookup quantization.
And we support many other
features, including support for
custom models now and, a very
popular feature, flexible
shapes.
So you no longer need to ship a
model for each shape that you
want to do inference on.
You ship one model, and our
simple API takes care of
everything for you.
now let's talk about Create ML,
our brand-new, easy-to-use
machine learning training
framework.
It brings together the power of
Machine Learning, Swift, and
Xcode, and Xcode Playgrounds.
No more downloading packages
from the Internet and going
through long, complicated
tutorials to portray a model.
We support feature-level
training such as image
classification and natural
language.
And if you do want to go deeper
in machine learning, we support
traditional types of algorithms
such as linear regression and
boosted trees as well as
traditional data processing.
But we think people will want to
use these feature type of
training far more, so let's look
at those examples.
For Natural Language, you can
now have your own custom Natural
Language model that does text
classification, word tagging,
and of course, we support
multiple languages.
So you could train a model with
very small datasets to do
sentiment analysis such as these
reviews for a movie where you
just train with positive and
negative in strings, and you
build your own custom image --
custom text classifier.
And then you could do the same
for domain analysis, being able
to train a model to understand
whether you're talking about a
hotel or a restaurant in a given
sentence.
Now we think, by far, image
classification will be the most
popular kind of training that
people want to do, and so we've
put a real focus on this.
Traditionally, if you were
training a very large model with
what might only be a small
dataset because as a developer
that's all you have access to,
your model wouldn't train well,
and it over-fed, and you get
poor predictions.
Now Apple has extensive
experience in training very
large models with datasets of
photos say in the -- with many
millions.
And we want to bring all that
experience to all of you.
And through a technique called
transfer learning, you can train
your own custom image
classifier.
So we'll bundle our model into
our OS, so there's no need for
you to ship that.
You take your data, and use
transfer learning with Create
ML, and augment our model.
That means you only need to ship
the part of the model that
you've augmented, bringing a
huge saving to your
applications.
So we've worked with a number of
developers who already have
models in the around
100-megabyte range, just to add
one intelligent feature to their
application.
And now, through transfer
learning, they can take that
model size down to three
megabytes.
[ Applause ]
Now this is far cooler to see if
you see how it's all done inside
Xcode and Xcode Playgrounds, so
I'd like to invite Lizzie up to
give you a demo of that now.
[ Applause ]
Lizzie?
>> Thank you, John.
Let's take a look at how to
create an app to classify
different types of flowers.
Now I've started by using a
state-of-the-art image
classifier model called
Inception B3, but there are two
problems with this approach.
One, this model is quite large.
It's taking up 100 megabytes in
our app.
And the second is even though
this model has support for 1000
classifications, it can't
correctly classify a rose.
Now normally what I'd have to do
is switch to a new development
environment, download an open
source machine learning library
and spend hours training a new
model.
But now with the power of Create
ML, you can do this in minutes
and in Xcode.
Now I'll switch to a new
Playground and import Create ML
UI.
The next step is to define a
builder that can build image
classifier models.
Then to enable drag-and-drop
interaction with this model, we
can show the builder in the live
view.
And see, on the side we get a
prompt to drag in images to
begin training.
Now over on my desktop, I happen
to have a bunch of different
images of flowers organized into
folders with the name of the
particular one that they are.
So we have some daisies,
hibiscuses, and of course, some
roses.
Now what I'll do is I'll take
this folder and drag it into the
UI.
And instantly, an image
classifier model begins training
on the Mac, accelerated by the
GPU.
And right away, I can see what
the accuracy was on this
training dataset.
But what I'd really like to know
is how it performs on new types
of flowers that it hasn't seen.
And I've set some of those aside
here, and I can just drag them
in to let the model begin
evaluating on these new ones.
And if I scroll, you can see
what the actual label was for
each type of flower and what the
model predicted.
Now 95% is pretty decent on this
dataset.
So what I'd like to do is add it
into my app.
And you can do so just by
dragging and dropping it.
I'll then add it.
And if we take a look at this
new model, we can see it's only
50 kilobytes.
That's a huge savings.
So I'll go ahead and delete --
[ Applause ]
-- I'll delete the 100-megabyte
model and initialize the new
image classifier.
Now if I rerun the app, it's
bundling this new model into the
application.
We can go ahead and test it to
see if it can correctly predict
on the images that we've trained
it on, or new images of the same
types of flowers.
And indeed, it can correctly
classify a rose.
Let's try it on a hibiscus.
And it can correctly predict on
those, too, since we've trained
it and incorporated it into our
app.
So as you've seen, we've been
able to train our own classifier
models using Create ML in a
fraction of the amount of time
to produce models a fraction of
the size, all using Swift and
Xcode.
Back over to you, John.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Lizzie.
Isn't that cool, a custom image
classifier trained with three
lines of Swift, in seconds,
right there on a Mac?
So we've looked at new Vision
and Natural Language APIs and
the enhancements we've made
there; our improvements with
Core ML 2 with smaller, faster
models and even more
customization; and Create ML,
our brand-new machine learning
training framework for the Mac.
Now I'd like to talk about
another area of intelligence
that we've built into the OS,
and that's shortcuts, a powerful
new way for you to expose key
capabilities of your
applications through Siri.
And you can even expose these
key capabilities using voice
commands.
Previously, sections of the OS
that had suggested features and
actions for Apple's software are
now accessible to you through
shortcuts.
We do all this prediction on
device using machine learning
that preserves your users'
privacy.
So you're probably asking how do
you adopt shortcuts?
Well, many of you have already
adopted NSUserActivity for
features such as Spotlight
search and Handoff.
And if you have -- and it's as
simple as adding this one line
of code making them eligible to
prediction for the system.
[ Applause ]
Yeah, one line of code.
But if you want the full, rich
experience of shortcuts, then
you want to adopt the new Siri
kit Intense API.
That allows rich, inline
capabilities of your application
to be exposed in Siri, custom
voice triggers and responses,
and more importantly, more
targeted predictions of when
those shortcuts will be
interesting to your users in the
future.
Now a great shortcut is one that
accelerates engagement with your
application, and increases
engagement, too.
It's one that's likely to be
repeated more often.
So in the TeamSnap example you
want to be able to check your
kid's soccer game schedule every
Saturday morning.
And ideally, it's one that can
be engaged right there in the
Siri UI and handled without the
need to punch out to your app.
But you do have the option if
that's something that you want
to do.
Now when creating a shortcut,
you need to do three simple
things.
You obviously need to define the
shortcut and do it for those
actions that really are
interesting to the users.
You need to donate when those
shortcuts occur, even if that's
in your application, because we
need that signal to be able to
predict those shortcuts in the
future.
And of course, you want to
handle those shortcuts when they
occur.
Now if you've done all this, you
get something pretty cool in
that you can interact with your
shortcut directly from home pod.
So now without picking up your
phone, you can just ask Siri
from your home pod for your
kid's soccer roster, and it will
respond using the app.
Now if you also want your
shortcuts to be exposed through
the Siri Watch Face, you can
just adopt this new Relevant
API.
So that's shortcuts, a powerful
new way to expose key
capabilities of your application
and increase engagement through
Siri.
Now I'd like to hand it over to
Jeremy to talk to you about
what's new in Metal.
Jeremy?
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, John.
So Metal is Apple's modern,
high-performance,
high-efficiency programming
interface to the awesome power
of the GPU at the heart of each
of Apple's platforms.
It accelerates both advanced 3D
graphics and general purpose
data parallel computations.
And since we introduced Metal in
2014, we've seen it used for
everything from smooth,
high-performance UI to modern 3D
games, advanced computational
photography, and the latest in
AR and VR experiences.
And when we introduced our
latest iPhones last fall, we
were incredibly excited to
reveal the next chapter in the
Metal story with the A11 Bionic
chip where Apple harnessed many
years of deep expertise in
hardware and software design to
bring the Apple-designed GPU,
optimized for Metal 2 with such
innovative new features as tile
shading and image blocks, and
advancing the state of the art
of GPU programming with both
faster performance and lower
power.
Now your applications can use
Metal directly for 3D graphics
and GPU Compute.
And Metal powers many of Apple's
system frameworks for graphics,
media, and data processing.
Let me give you just one
example.
Our iOS camera framework uses
Metal to calculate depth
information, identify people in
photos, and generate this
depth-of-field effect in this
gorgeous portrait image.
And developers like Epic Games
are using Metal's broad support
across all of our platforms to
bring their smash-hit game
Fortnight to iPhone, iPad, and
Mac.
AMB's metal-accelerated radion
[assumed spelling] pro-ender
plugins, are now driving high
performance, 3D contact creation
and professional editing in
Maxon Cinema4D and Autodesk
Maya.
And apps like Gravity Sketch are
using Metal to power the next
generations of artists in
immersive professional VR
editing.
Metal's machine learning
acceleration empowers iOS apps
like BeCasso to transform your
photos into beautiful paintings.
And drives automatic,
intelligent image editing in
Pixelmator Pro for macOS.
And those are just a few
examples as the developer
adoption of metal has been truly
astounding, with more than
400,000 apps now using the Metal
API.
And all systems running an iOS
12 and macOS Mojave support
Metal, which includes all iOS
devices and all Macs released in
at least the last five years,
which means there are now well
over 1 billion Metal systems for
your applications and games.
So with Metal's deep and broad
support across all of Apple's
desktop and mobile platforms, we
are now deprecating the legacy
OpenGL and OpenCL GPU framework,
starting in macOS Mojave, iOS
12, and tvOS 12.
Now apps using these legacy APIs
will still continue to work in
these releases, but deprecation
is a first step as we wind down
legacy technologies.
So if you've not already done
so, you should begin
transitioning your apps to
Metal.
And we'll communicate more
details about this transition in
the near future.
Now as you bring your apps to
metal, we are here to help.
The Metal API is dramatically
easier to use and much more
approachable than these other
GPU programming APIs.
It contains a familiar, yet
powerful, C++ GPU shading
language.
And we provide a full suite of
advanced debugging and
performance profiling tools for
using Metal, all built right
into Xcode.
We have GPU performance counters
with advanced profiling to
identify your most expensive
lines of shader code and a
visual API debugger for
navigating your Metal function
calls, a Metal System Trace to
put your Metal commands in the
context of everything else
happening on the system.
And we're really excited to
announce two new powerful tools
this year, a new Metal
Dependency Viewer where you can
investigate your complex,
multipass rendering and command
encoders, and an all-new,
interactive GPU source code
shader debugger where you can
actually explore your Metal code
right down to the pixel level.
Now you have to see these new
tools in action, so I'd like to
invite Seth to give you a
demonstration.
Seth?
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, John.
Xcode's GP debugger is the tool
for developing your Metal
applications.
In the Debug Navigator on the
left, you can see all the Metal
API codes and [inaudible] codes
used in your frame.
And on the right, you can see
the results of the selected
[inaudible].
The main editor shows you the --
all the buffers, textures, and
other resources that were used
for that [inaudible].
Well, new in Xcode 10, we're
introducing the Dependency
Viewer, a powerful way to
understand how complex render
passes combine to form your
scene.
This gives you a blueprint of
your frame in explaining and
understanding how the complex
render graphs at one application
such as Unity's breathtaking
"Book of the Dead" demo shown
here.
I can zoom out to see more
detail.
Earlier render passes are shown
at the top, with the later
render passes shown at the
bottom.
The lines indicate the
dependencies between passes,
with those for the selected pass
highlighted in blue.
As you can see, with more than
100 render passes, there's
clearly a lot going on in this
scene.
Now as good as this scene looks,
there's always room for more
flair.
So I did an additional render
pass, the lens flare.
But as you can see, something
didn't [inaudible] quite right
-- far, far to green.
Well, let's zoom in, select a
pixel, and launch the new Shader
Debugger, a powerful interactive
tool to let you visually debug
shaders [inaudible].
In the main editor, I can see my
source code.
And in the sidebar to its right,
I can see variables touched by
each line of code.
Additionally, I can expand any
of these to see more details in
line.
These two views visualize the
area around the selected pixel,
corresponding to the highlighted
region in the frame attachment.
The view on the left visualizes
the variable value.
And the one on the right, the
pixel -- the execution mask.
This indicates which pixels
executed this line of code.
This is an incredibly powerful
way to debug the massively
[inaudible] execution of shaders
on the GPU.
Now you can see here that the
shape of the execution mask
matches that of the visual
aberration, telling me that the
issue exists on this line of
code.
Well, now that I know where the
issue is, I can see what I've
done wrong, using the vector
length of the lens flare rather
than the color of the lens
flare.
That will be easy to fix.
I can now hit the update shaders
button to quickly apply the fix,
recompiling the shader and
deploying it to the GPU.
And here we can see that my lens
flare is fixed, and the scene
looks cool.
[ Applause ]
So that's the new Dependency
Viewer and GP Shader Debugger in
Xcode 10, giving you powerful
new tools to build your Metal
applications.
Jeremy?
>> All right, [applause] thank
you, Seth.
So in addition to these amazing
new tools, we're continuing to
advance Metal with a fantastic
set of new features in iOS 12
and macOS Mojave.
Now I'm going to highlight just
three of them today --
GPU-driven command encoding,
machine learning training
acceleration, and ray tracing.
So first, GPU-driven command
encoding.
Now historically, your app would
encode its GPU commands using
the CPU and then subsequently
execute those commands on the
GPU.
And while Metal enabled this
encoding to be very fast, it
could still become bottlenecked
by the synchronization between
the CPU and the GPU.
Well, now in iOS 12 and macOS
Mojave, you can actually encode
those commands right on the GPU
itself, freeing up precious CPU
time for other use by your games
and apps.
And because you issue these
commands right on the GPU using
a compute shader, you can
actually officially construct
massive numbers of commands in
parallel as well, unlocking
completely new levels of
rendering performance and
sophistication.
Next, I'd like to share the
latest advances in Metal's
support for machine learning.
In iOS 12 and macOS Mojave, we
have augmented our existing
library of Metal performance
shaders with an enormous array
of all-new compute kernels,
optimized to support machine
learning training right on the
local GPU on your iOS and Mac
devices.
And the performance improvements
we are seeing from these new
Metal performance shaders on
training are truly stunning,
with an order of magnitude
faster training times.
We're also really excited to
announce we've been working with
Google to bring Metal
acceleration to TensorFlow later
this year, and the early
performance results are showing
an astonishing improvement of 20
times the previous
implementation.
[Applause] Yeah, it's awesome.
[ Applause ]
And last, ray tracing.
Now this is a time-honored
technique to achieve incredibly
realistic scenes, often used for
high-end rendering and 3D
product design.
However, it traditionally had to
be done offline because it was
so computationally expensive.
Now let me describe why very
quickly.
First, you would need to
mathematically model the rays
from a light source as they
bounce off of objects through
the scene, toward the screen,
and into your eye.
And to achieve higher and higher
resolutions, you would need to
add more, and more, and more
rays until you could reach the
desired resolution.
And this simple 1k-by-1k image
would take nearly 6 million rays
to generate.
Now each of those rays also must
be processed with at least two
sets of expensive mathematical
calculations.
First, you had to determine if a
given ray intersects a
particular triangle in your
scene.
And second, you must apply a
material-specific shader
necessary to generate the pixel.
Now originally, both of these
operations would have been
performed by the CPU.
But while the GPU can easily
handle the pixel shading, the
ray-triangle intersection itself
could remain an expensive CPU
bottleneck, and it would be
incredibly difficult to move
this to the GPU efficiently.
But the new Metal Ray-Triangle
Intersector solves this problem
for you.
And with this new API, you get a
dramatic increase in performance
of up to 10x in a very
simple-to-use package, all
pre-optimized for use with our
iOS and macOS GPUs.
And it really is that simple,
just a few lines of code.
And the ray tracing, like many
GPU compute operations, is
exactly the kind of operation
that can efficiently scale with
the available GPU horsepower.
So we can actually get even more
performance by using Metal 2
support for external GPUs.
Now you really have to see this
in action.
And I'd like to invite Rav to
give a quick demonstration.
Rav?
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Jeremy.
All right, let's bring up this
ray trace rendering of the
Amazon Lumberyard Bistro scene
using the CPU to perform the
intersection calculations.
And this implementation is
optimized to run on all 10 cores
in our iMac Pro.
We've also added a little
benchmark mode that times how
long it takes to do 80
iterations of our ray-tracing
algorithm.
And for context, that requires
performing over 6 billion
intersection tests.
And as you can see, we need
about 12 seconds to do that on
the CPU.
So let's compare that to using
the new ray -- the new Metal
Ray-Triangle Intersector on the
built-in GPU in the iMac Pro.
And you can immediately see that
it's much faster, and we only
need about 1.3 seconds to do the
same amount of work.
It's so good, I'm going to do it
again.
Here we go.
And it's done.
So getting an almost 10-times
performance increase is
fantastic.
But of course, we didn't just
stop there.
As Jeremy noted, ray tracing is
well-suited for parallelization
across multiple GPUs, so I can
enable an external GPU that I
previously attached to this iMac
Pro and get the render time cut
in half.
So you'll note the green line
that we've added to help
visualize how we're splitting
this workload across the two
GPUs, with each GPU rendering
half the frame in this case.
So this is a great improvement,
but as Jeremy says, you can
never have too many GPUs.
So let's add another two for a
total of four GPUs now rendering
the scene.
So that's over 40 teraflops of
compute capability with our iMac
Pro, and we're rendering the
scene 30 times faster than the
CPU.
We think that's pretty amazing,
yep.
[ Applause ]
And since ray tracing is so
great for rendering shadows, I'm
just going to turn off a couple
lights here to get them to pop.
And you can really appreciate
how much faster the image
converges on the GPUs.
So the new Metal Ray-Triangle
Intersector and external GPU
support on macOS we believe is
going to enable some great new
workflows on apps that are
taking advantage of ray tracing
techniques.
Thank you.
Back to you, Jeremy [applause].
>> All right, that is really
stunning.
Thanks, Rav.
So that's Metal 2 in iOS 12 and
macOS Mojave, an easy-to-use,
unified 3D graphics and GPU
compute API with broad support
across all of Apple's products,
including the A11 Bionic and the
Apple-designed GPU.
GPU developer tools integrated
right into Xcode and all-new
features to support the latest
advancements in machine learning
training and ray tracing.
There's never been a better time
to move your app to Metal, and
we can't wait to see what you'll
create next.
Thank you.
And now, I would like to hand it
over to Mike Rockwell to talk
about what's the latest news in
AR?
Thanks.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Jeremy.
So last year has been an amazing
year for AR at Apple.
With the debut of ARKit at last
WWDC, iOS became the world's
largest AR platform by a lot.
There are hundreds of millions
of AR-enabled iOS devices, and
that number is growing rapidly.
As Craig showed you this
morning, with iOS 12, we're
taking things further by making
AR ubiquitous across the
operating system.
We can now experience AR content
via the new QuickLook Viewer in
Messages, News, Safari, and
more.
To do that, we had to work on
and create a file format that we
optimized for AR.
And we worked with Pixar and
Adobe to create a new mobile AR
format called USDZ.
It's based on the universal
scene description format that's
used across the industry for
professional content creation.
It's optimized for mobile
devices, and it supports Rich 3D
assets and animation.
It's incredibly easy to use
USDZ.
On the web, it just takes a
couple of lines of HTML, and
it's also natively supported in
SceneKit using Model I/O, so you
can easily use it in your
applications.
We've also been working closely
with industry leaders in content
creation tools to provide native
support for USDZ.
And as you heard this morning,
Abhay said this morning that he
had a sneak peek for you about
what they're doing at Adobe.
So I'd like to invite him to the
stage to give that to you right
now.
Abhay?
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Mike.
It's great to be back onstage.
So as you heard in this
morning's keynote, Adobe's
Creative Cloud and ARKit will be
able to reimagine and blend the
digital and the physical worlds.
Now this will require a complete
reimagination of new design
interaction models.
So earlier today, we announced a
new system for creating AR
experiences called Project Aero
that infused ARKit with the
power of familiar Creative Cloud
applications like Photoshop and
Dimension.
So in fact, for the first time,
with Creative Cloud and iOS, you
will now have a
what-you-see-is-what-you-get
editing in AR.
So as you think about this --
and we looked at it -- ARKit is
absolutely the leading platform
for AR.
And so we're really excited to
partner closely with Apple as we
go jointly explore and push the
boundaries of immersive design.
But to fully realize the
potential of AR, you really have
to work across the entire
ecosystem.
And so today, we are also
announcing that Adobe will
natively support USDZ format,
along with Apple and Pixar
[applause].
Now AR is a unique medium in
that it allows interactive
content to go extend well beyond
the screen, where physical
spaces around us literally
become a creative canvas.
So let's take a look.
[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
That's pretty cool.
So at its core, Project Aero is
part of Adobe's vision and
mission to truly democratize
creation of immersive content.
As you hopefully saw in that
video, creators and developers
will be able to collaborate
seamlessly to deliver a wide
range of AR experiences using
these tools.
Stay tuned for more updates on
Project Aero at our upcoming
conference, AdobeMax.
Personally, I couldn't be more
excited about our partnership
with Apple, as we go together
jointly explore the limits of
this emerging and powerful new
storytelling medium.
Thank you.
Back to you, Mike.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Abhay.
Isn't that awesome?
Amazing stuff.
Of course, the foundation of AR
at Apple is ARKit.
With robust device position
localization, accurate lighting
and size estimation, ARKit has
made it easy to create AR
applications.
The iPhone X has provided
groundbreaking face tracking
that used to require custom
hardware.
After the initial release, we
quickly followed up with ARKit
1.5, adding 2D image triggers, a
high-resolution background
camera, and the ability to
suspend and resume tracking so
that you don't have to restart
an AR session if you get a phone
call.
Well, I'm incredibly excited to
tell you about our next big jump
forward, ARKit 2.
ARKit 2 delivers a big set of
advances, including improved
face tracking, with a new
ability to track your gaze and
tongue.
These highly-requested features
allow you to take facial
animation to a new level of
realism.
Turns out that the first thing
kids do when they play with
animojis is stick their tongue
out.
And I think a lot of you do,
too.
That's why we had to put that in
there.
To more accurately integrate
objects into a scene, we've
added environment texturing.
ARKit creates textures based on
what the camera sees in the real
world -- notice that the globe
is reflecting the real picture
on the table below.
But what about what the camera
can't see?
While using machine learning, we
trained a neural network on
thousands of typical
environments.
And this enables ARKit to
hallucinate the rest of the
scene.
This means that you'll get
plausible reflections of things
like overhead lighting -- you
can see that in the globe --
even though it's never seen the
lighting in the environment at
all.
We've extended the 2D image
detection to provide support for
those -- tracking those images
in three dimensions.
So you can now have 3D objects
that stick to images in the real
world when they're moved around
-- and not only in 2D, but also
in 3D.
[ Applause ]
ARKit can now detect 3D objects.
You can scan objects via an API,
or a simple developer tool we
provide, and then later, these
maps can be used to recognize
those objects and their
locations and trigger a
contextually-relevant AR
experience.
[ Applause ]
An incredibly important feature
of ARKit 2 is support for
persistent experiences.
You can see here in the video
that we've mapped an environment
and then placed a 3D object.
This map can be saved and then
later used to recognize the
space and relocalize to that
same coordinate system -- and
not only on that device.
You can share these maps to
other devices to allow them to
have the exact same experience.
This makes it possible to create
apps that provide persistent
experiences you can go back to
again and again.
You could, for example, have an
augmented reality pinboard in
your home with pictures and
artwork.
And you can share these maps
without having to go to the
cloud.
These can be done peer-to-peer
locally on your devices.
One other thing that we've done
is we've allowed you to have the
ability to share these maps in
real time.
And this lets you create
multiplayer AR games.
So to experiment with this, we
created a new game called
SwiftShot.
And I'll show you the video that
-- of it that we did.
[ Music ]
So SwiftShot is a blast to play,
and we actually have it here at
the show.
If you haven't had a chance to
go by, we have an AR game area.
We wanted to share it with you,
so we've actually made the full
source code available for you to
download under an open license.
You can play with it and modify
it as you like.
We can't wait to see the
creative things you'll do with
SwiftShot.
So that is ARKit 2, improved
face tracking, environment
texturing, image detection and
tracking, 3D object detection,
and persistent experiences as
well as multi-user experiences.
That combined with USDZ across
the operating system makes iOS
12 by far the most powerful
platform for AR.
And we're really excited to be
giving that to you today, and
can't wait to see what you'll do
with it.
So with that, I'll hand it back
to Sebastian.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Mike.
Wow, I think we've seen a ton of
exciting new technologies today,
and I hope you're really,
really, really excited about
this.
We make it easy to leverage
machine learning, build great
new experiences with ARKit,
high-performance graphics with
Metal, a huge step forward on
the Mac with Dark Mode.
I know you all love this.
And it's all backed by great
advances in our development
tools that are really critical
to make the most of these
super-powerful technologies.
And we've also covered how we,
together, can focus on what's
most important to our users.
All these great technologies and
tools are available today as a
developer preview from the WWDC
attendee portal.
Who here has started downloading
them?
Few people?
Okay, you've got to hurry up.
Distribution is limited.
Please make sure to download it
right away.
And also, make the most of your
week.
There are more than 100 sessions
here at the conference that go
deep in all of these topics.
Really, really great sessions.
We also recommend that you make
good use of all of the labs that
we have, because you can get
help from the many Apple
engineers that are here onsite
to answer all of your questions.
So with that, I hope you have a
great conference, and I'm
looking forward to seeing you
around this week.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]