[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you all for coming.
And welcome to the session,
Advances in Rresearch and Care
Frameworks.
My name is Srinath and I'm a
software engineer.
Now, if you're familiar with our
WW talks in the past, you might
remember that our sessions have
focused primarily on our two
open source health frameworks.
ResearchKit and CareKit.
This year, although we'll still
be talking a lot about these
frameworks, we'll also be
covering some new APIs and
features that we've been working
on in the larger health space.
But for those of you who are
somewhat new to these
frameworks, I highly recommend
checking out our two sessions
from last year.
What's new in CareKit and
ResearchKit was hosted by Sam
Mravca.
Where she gives a really good
overview of both ResearchKit and
CareKit.
The other session, Connecting
CareKit to the Cloud was by
Kelsey Dedoshka, where we
introduced a new CareKit bridge
API that allows developers to
sync care plans between patients
and providers using any HIPAA
compliant backend.
And on that note, I'm really
excited to show you all some of
the amazing work that's been
happening at Penn Medicine.
The Penn Life Gained Appl
utilizes CareKit and the CareKit
bridge API to help patients
through both pre and
post-bariatric surgery at Penn
Medicine.
The app leverages care plans,
healthcare data and other
interactive components to help
patients go through their weight
loss journey.
Data is constantly being synced
between the iOS apps used by the
patients, and the iPad apps used
by care providers in order to
closely monitor and interact
with their patients in real
time.
The team has received extremely
positive feedback from both
patients as well as clinicians
with regards to the impact that
these apps have had on their
bariatric program.
And now that we have touched
upon where we have come since
last year, I would like to take
a quick step-out to all of our
health frameworks as a whole.
The creation of these frameworks
stems from our overarching
desire to improve the world of
health, through technology.
And in that process, we really
want to empower our users and
provide more tools to developers
and researchers, so at the end
of the day, you and all of us
can help improve and advance two
core areas of interest, research
and care.
This year, I'm really excited to
be talking to you about some of
these topics which we care so
deeply about in a variety of
ways.
Starting with the framework
focus, where I'll talk to you
about updates we have made to
our ResearchKit framework.
From there, we'll move on to a
more condition focused approach,
specifically around movement
disorders like Parkinson's,
where Gabriel will come on stage
and talk to you about this
brand-new API.
And finally, we'll bring it all
together with a demo where we
will showcase how you can
utilize these new APIs and
features directly in code.
Now let's get started with
ResearchKit.
Over the past year, we have been
putting in a lot of effort to
improve out openness and
engagement with our community.
Some updates to our ResearchKit
UI and modules, as well as some
new additions to our existing
library of Active Tasks.
Now, let's get started with
community updates.
I want to cover two main topics,
repository privileges and
schedule updates.
Over the past few months, we
have been expanding our access
rights and providing write
privileges to members of our
community.
In fact, we've chosen five
all-star contributors and given
them direct access to the
ResearchKit repository that also
allows them to merge MPRs.
A huge thank you and
congratulations to Erin,
Fernando, Nino, Ricardo, and
Shannon.
Next, I want to touch on our
schedule updates.
Historically, we've been pushing
to master and stable at the same
time.
Now, we realize that this
inhibits the ability for
developers, like you, to
leverage some of our in-house
features like localization,
accessibility, and QA, which is
why this year we will be pushing
to stable two to three months
after our push to master.
We hope that you can use this
time to check out our latest
updates, provide feedback and
submit PRs.
And the changes that you make,
will make it soon into our
stable, tagged release branch as
opposed to you having to wait
for an entire release cycle.
And now that we have touched
upon community updates, I would
like to dive a little bit deeper
and talk about updates we have
made to the ResearchKit
framework itself, starting with
UI updates.
Now, for comparison, this is
what our Mini Form step looks
like in ResearchKit 1.5, as
taken from our ORK test app.
And here is the same Mini Form
step as it will be available in
ResearchKit 2.0.
As you can see, we have worked
very hard to update the overall
look and feel of ResearchKit UI
to closely resemble the latest
iOS style guidelines.
Let's take a closer look.
We've moved the progress label
from the center of the
navigation bar to the right side
and applied some styling.
This allows us to leverage the
large titles feature in nav bars
and apply it to all of our step
titles.
Now, to keep the consistent
styling, we are also adding a
new card view in order to
improve the overall user
experience for those who are
answering multiple questions and
surveys, as it now provides a
clear break in action that
you're requested to perform.
Now, this card view is applied
by default to all our steps and
forms.
But we are also exposing a
Boolean property that you can
set to falls for backwards
compatibility.
And finally, we are also adding
a footer container view, to
improve the navigation flow.
The cancel button is now part of
the footer view, which is always
sticky to the bottom.
What this means is that your
users will no longer have to
scroll all the way to the bottom
of the step, in order to access
forward navigation options.
And having all these controls in
one place makes it much more
intuitive.
And now, moving on, one of the
most commonly used modules in
ResearchKit is informed consent,
which is used to generate a PDF
and attach a user signature to
it.
Now, we realized how important
it is to be able to survey some
of these confidential documents
to your users within the context
of your app.
Which is why we are adding a new
ORK PDF viewer step.
This is built on top of the PDF
Kit framework that came to iOS
just last year.
Let's take a closer look at some
of the functionalities that this
step provides.
Quick navigation to easily
switch between pages.
Real-time annotations to mark up
the document if necessary.
Search functionality for your
users to query the entire
document for keywords or
phrases.
And the ability to share this
PDF or save it using the
standard iOS share sheet.
And what's even better is how
easy it is to incorporate this
in your app.
You create an instance of ORK
PDF viewer step with a unique
identifier, and simply provide
us the file path to the PDF
document that you wish to
display.
And now, I'd actually like to
switch gears and talk about one
of the core components of
ResearchKit.
Active Tasks.
For those of you who are
unfamiliar, Active Tasks are
prepackaged modules that allows
users to perform certain tasks
or take certain tests in a given
amount of time.
When the user completes the
step, the developer receives a
delegate call back with an ORK
resolved object.
Now, this object consists of a
variety of data points, which
include things like user
responses, timing information
and data recorded from different
sources like Accelerometer,
Gyroscope, healthcare data, and
even from your microphone.
And this year, we are also
adding support for health
records.
Now, let's take a look at how
you can utilize this in your
app.
Now, your objective here is to
create a recorder configuration
that can query health clinical
data types.
And you need to provide us with
two important parameters.
First is of HKClinicalType, and
a second is an optional of type
HKFIRResourceType.
And once you have created this
record of configuration, you
attach it to the step.
So, now when the user is about
to perform the task, they will
be prompted with HealthKits new
authorization UI.
And only if they grant access
will we be able to run the
query.
And once the user completes the
task as part of the delegate
call back in your ORK result
object, you will also have
information that you requested
for from health records.
Now, to understand and leaner
more about these different
health records types, I highly
recommend everyone here, to also
visit the session, Accessing
Health Records with HealthKit,
that is happening right here at
3 p.m., where they will talk
about everything related to
health records in great detail,
including some very important
best practices.
And now that we have covered
updates to the Active Task
module as a whole, let's talk
about the Active Tasks
themselves.
This year, we are adding new
modules focusing on three main
areas of health; hearing,
speech, and vision.
Let's get started with hearing.
We are adding a new dBHL tone
audiometry step.
This implements the
Hughson-Westlake Method and
allows you to determine the
hearing threshold level of a
user in the dBHL scale.
And to facilitate this, and
ensure that you get the most
accurate results.
I'm really excited to say that
for the very first time we are
open sourcing calibration data
for our AirPods.
Now, this comes with three
tables.
The first one is a volume curve
for AirPods on all iOS devices.
The second one is the
sensitivity per frequency.
Where sensitivity is measured in
decibels sound pressure level.
And finally, we are also
providing the reference
equivalent threshold sound
pressure level tables or RETSPL.
Now, it's really important to
note that the RETSPL table is
still in beta.
This means that we are actively
running internal validations and
tests.
And over the next few weeks, we
will be updating these tables as
we start converging on accurate
data.
Now let's take a look at how
this Active Task actually works.
The user is required to hear
tones at a particular frequency
at varying levels of dBHL value.
When the user hears a tone, they
are expected to tap the button
to indicate that they have heard
it.
And at that point we will start
decreasing the dBHL value as
indicated here by the green
dots.
Now, when the user fails to tap
the button after a given timeout
period, we will start increasing
the dBHL values as indicated by
the red dots.
And over time we will feed these
data points to the
Hughson-Westlake Method in order
to determine the hearing
threshold level of the user in
the dBHL scale.
Now, from a developer
perspective, the entirety of
tone generation occurs in three
phases.
The first one, is a pre-stimulus
delay, which is a
developer-specified maximum
number in seconds that we use to
generate a random delay between
one and that value before we
start playing the tone to the
user.
This is to ensure that the user
cannot cheat the test by just
randomly tapping on the button.
Next, we are also providing a
property for tone duration,
which governs the actual
duration for which the tone will
be played.
And finally, is the post
stimulus delay, which is the
amount of time allocated to the
user to respond for that
specific tone.
To incorporate this in your app,
you create an instance of
ORKdBHL tone audiometry step
with a unique identifier and
provide us values for some of
the parameters, including a
frequency list, which is an
array of frequency that you wish
to be played back to your user.
We're also exposing more
properties that you can further
customize for your specific use
case.
Now, when the user completes
this task as part of the
delegate call-back, the ORK
result object will be returned
to you.
Let's take a look at what that
object looks like for this
particular task.
So, at the top level you get a
variety of information that
includes things like output
volume, and also includes an
array of sample objects.
These objects in turn
encapsulate things like
channels, which refers to
whether the tone was being
played in the left or right
channel to the user, as well as
the threshold value, as
determined by the
Hughson-Westlake Method.
This also consists of an array
of unit objects.
And the unit objects in turn,
provide details like the dBHl
value at which that particular
tone was being played, and a
variety of timestamps, which
also includes when exactly did
the user tap the button.
So, now let's move on to our
next task that falls under the
hearing category.
We are adding an environment SPL
meter.
This implements an A-weighted
filter, in order to measure the
environmental sound pressure
level in DBA, or in other words,
it tells you how noisy it is.
Now, this step also accepts a
threshold value, and this makes
things interesting, because now
you can use the step as a gating
step.
So, for example, if you want
your users to perform the tone
audiometry task, you can add
this task before that to ensure
that your users are not in an
environment that is too noisy to
accurately perform the task.
To add this you create an
instance of ORK environment,
SPLMeterStep with a unique
identifier and provide us the
threshold value.
We're also exposing additional
properties that you can further
customize.
And now, let's take a quick
detour and move on to our next
category, speech.
We're adding a speech
recognition module, which
leverages the speech recognition
framework on iOS, now, this
gives us direct access to a
real-time speech recognizers
that supports over 50 different
languages, or locales.
As part of this task, the user
is asked to either repeat a
sentence, or describe an image.
And once they are done speaking,
the users will be automatically
taken to a next step, where they
can edit the generated
transcript.
So, for example in this case
quick and fox were incorrectly
interpreted as quite and box.
Your users can just tap on these
words an edit them if necessary.
Now, it's important to note,
that as part of this task, we
are returning to you a very,
very rich dataset that consists
of three main things.
A direct audio recording to what
the user said, the transcription
generated by the speech
recognition engine, and the
edited transcript by the user.
To add this to your app, you
create an instance of ORK
speechRecognitionStep, and
provide us with either a UI
image, or a string.
You can also customize the
locale for this recognition.
And also, you can surface
real-time transcription as the
user is speaking.
Now, let's take a closer look at
one of the subsets of our result
object.
This is of type FS transcription
as surface by the speech
recognition framework.
The formattedString provides the
transcript, and the array of
segment objects, essentially
breakdown the transcript into
substrings, as well as provide a
confidence letter for each
substring.
On top of this, they also
provide an array of alternative
string, as you can see here in
this illustrative example.
Now, these results can be used
to derive syntactic, semantic
and linguistic features, as well
as speaking rate in order to
evaluate the speech patterns for
various medical conditions,
including cognition and mood.
Our next task, Interestingly, is
a combination of speech and
hearing.
The speech and noise Active
Task.
This allows you to perform fully
automated speech audiometry.
And conventional tone audiometry
uses pure tones, which are
essentially sign waves.
Now, there have been recorded
instances, where users are able
to clearly distinguish pure
tones, but find it extremely
difficult to distinguish words
when they are intermixed with
noise.
And this closely reflects
real-world examples of
early-stage hearing loss.
For example, when you are unable
to understand what the person
sitting in front of you is
telling you in a noisy
restaurant.
Now, before I go into further
details let's take a look at how
this task actually works.
>> The actor tried three green
pictures.
>> Now, as you notice an audio
file was played to the user, and
once it completes, they are
immediately requested to repeat
what they have just heard.
Now, the speech and noise Active
Task uses audio files generated
by combining five words from a
close-set matrix, that was
validated internally for things
like word familiarity,
uniformity, difficulty, and also
to ensure that the sentences
generated by the synthesizer
were phonetically balanced and
more importantly, consistent.
These files are then
programmatically mixed with
background noise at varying
levels of signal to noise ratio,
or SNR.
And developers will also have
the option to set the value for
the gain for all of the noise
signals.
Now, speech reception threshold,
is defined as the minimum value
in SNR at which a user can
understand only 50% of the
spoken words.
Now, our vision for this test is
over the next few weeks, we'll
be uploading over 175 different
files that corresponds to 25
lists, each with 7 sentences.
And in the long-run, we want to
be able to support this test for
multiple languages, especially
ones where currently speech and
noise is not possible due to a
lack of speech database or other
testing resources.
So, if you are a researcher in
this particular field and if you
have a request for specific
locale, I highly encourage you
to reach out to us and we'll do
our best to accommodate your
request.
To add this to your app, you
create an instance of
ORKSpeechInNoiseStep, and point
us to the audio file that you
wish to play.
You can also specify the gain
applied to the noise signal.
And lastly, let's touch on
vision.
the Amsler grid is a tool that
is used to detect problems in a
user's vision that can be caused
due to conditions like macular
degeneration.
Now, this test is conventionally
performed in a doctor's office
on a traditional piece of paper,
displaying a graphic like the
one you see right here.
Users with perfect vision would
see exactly this, whereas users
who suffer from some conditions
would start seeing distortions
on this graph.
Now, please don't panic if
you're seeing distortions right
now.
That was intentional and it was
added for dramatic effect.
Now, users simply have to point
to places on the grid where they
see distortions.
By replicating this grid, we are
able to bring the functionality
of this task to the users at
home on their device.
Users simply have to annotate
areas on the grid where they see
distortions.
And we believe that developers
can leverage some exciting iOS
features like [inaudible] or the
depth sensing camera to increase
the experience of a user who is
taking this particular task.
Now, all of these Active Tasks
are really great for data
collection and analysis.
But they are designed to be
performed at a specified time
for a given period.
And as we start to dig into
specific conditions, we have
realized that some of the more
complex problems in health
require constant monitoring, and
therefore, introduce the need
for passive, noninvasive data
collection.
And to talk more about that I
would like to introduce Gabriel
up on stage.
[ Applause ]
>> Hello. My name is Gabriel and
I'm here on behalf of the core
motion team to introduce a new
research API.
The movement disorder API.
As Srinath was mentioning, this
is a passive, all-day monitoring
API, available on Apple Watch,
which will allow you to monitor
the symptoms of movement
disorders.
Specifically, two movements
disorders which are relevant to
the study of Parkinson's
disease.
Now, because of the targeted use
case as a research API, you will
need to apply for a special code
signing entitlement in order to
use this API.
This application process will be
done through the Apple developer
web portal, starting in seed
two, though if you just can't
wait and I don't blame you,
there will be sample data sets
as well as demo code available
in the research kit, GitHub
repository for this talk.
So, let's start talking about
those two movement disorder
symptoms.
As some of you may know,
Parkinson's is a degenerative
neurological disorder which can
affect the motor functions of
those with the disease.
One of the identifiable symptoms
of Parkinson's is a tremor.
And this API monitors for tremor
at rest, characterized by a
shaking, or a trembling of the
body when somebody is not
intending to move.
Now, there are treatments
including medications, which can
help suppress and control the
symptoms of Parkinson's.
However, these very same
treatments can often have
negative side effects.
Side effects such as
dyskinesias.
And one dyskinetic symptom that
this API is able to monitor for
is a fidgeting or swaying of the
body known as choreiform
movement.
So, to recap, you have tremor, a
symptom of the disease as well
as dyskinesia, a side effect of
the treatment.
Let's take a quick look at what
tools researchers and clinicians
currently have in order to
assess these symptoms.
Typically, these types of
assessments are done in clinic.
A clinician will ask a patient
with Parkinson's disease to
perform physical diagnostic
tests in order to rate and
evaluate the severity of their
condition.
These ratings provide a
quantitative, though subjected
to the rater, measurement of
their condition at that point in
time, when they're in the
clinic.
In order to get a broader and
more complete picture, patients
are also encouraged to keep
diaries where they log their
symptoms manually.
However, this can be cumbersome
for patients and some will
understandably forget or be
unable to describe the full
extent of their symptoms every
single day.
Wouldn't it be great if there
was a passive, unobtrusive way
to monitor for these symptoms.
Well, by using the movement
disorder API, researchers and
developers like yourselves, will
be able to build apps which
collect these types of the
metrics, continuously whenever a
patient is wearing their Apple
Watch.
Not only does this give you a
quantitative measurement of
those symptoms, displayed here
as the percentage of the time
observed.
But it also gives you a
longitudinal analysis, where you
can track changes to those
symptoms over time.
These algorithms were designed
and piloted using data collected
from Parkinson's patients in
internal clinical studies.
And we hope that you can use
these tools and these learnings
to build new care experiences
that improve the quality of life
of people with Parkinson's.
But before you can do any of
that, you're going to need to
know how to use the API, right?
All right.
Well, let's take a look at some
code.
The first thing you're going to
want to do is request motion
authorization from the user in
order to use their movement
disorder data.
Once you've done that, you'll
want to call the monitorKinesias
function in order to enable
symptom monitoring.
Now, this symptom monitoring
does turn on additional Apple
Watch sensors, so this will have
an impact on the battery life of
your users, though they should
still be able to have a days'
worth of data collection on a
single charge.
As you can see, the maximum
recording duration is seven
days.
I know that many of you are
going to be conducting studies
that are longer than seven days,
and if that's the case, simply
call the monitorKinesias
function again in order to
extend your data collection
interval.
This will begin to store tremor
and dyskinesia results on the
user's device, on your behalf.
At a certain point afterwards,
you're going to want to return
to that application so you can
query for those records.
Let's take a look at what the
query function looks like.
As you can see, in this line,
recording for any new tremor
records that were stored on the
device since our last query
date.
These records are stored on
device by the API, but they also
will expire after seven days.
And so, before it expires,
you're going to want to take
ownership of those records
either by serializing them and
storing them on this device
yourself, or transferring it to
a different platform so you can
visualize it and analyze it.
The data will be returned to you
as an array of minute long
object results.
So, one hour's worth of data, 60
result objects.
Let's take a look at what one of
those result objects will look
like.
As you can see, the result
objects return the percentage of
the time the percentage of that
one minute that the algorithm
was able to observe the
presence, or the absence of the
symptom.
For dyskinesia, here on the
right, you can see that that's
pretty simple; unlikely or
likely.
tremor gives you a few more
options.
Let's go through them.
Since this is a tremor at rest
any active or chaotic motion
will simply be returned as
percent unknown.
And this is the same category
that we use for low signal
levels we're unable to make a
determination.
However, if the algorithm is
able to make a determination, it
will also return the severity of
the tremor, ranging from slight
up until strong.
Now, to show you just how well
the passive monitoring of the
movement disorder API is able to
work in conjunction with the
active monitoring of a
ResearchKit Active Task, I would
like to invite up to the stage
Akshay, who is going to
integrate both into one stellar
research application.
[ Applause ]
>> Hello, everyone.
And welcome to the Advances in
Research in Care demo.
In this demo, we'll see some
research get update and also
implement the movement disorder
API.
As part of our research kit
repository on GitHub, we have
already added an ORK Parkinson's
study app.
This app implements the movement
disorder API and also visualizes
the tremor and dyskinesia
symptom data points that we just
saw.
Let's go ahead and see what this
app looks like right now.
We have an Apple Watch app where
we implement the movement
disorder API, collect the tremor
and dyskinesia symptom data
points and send them to our
phone app.
In our iPhone app, we have a
questionnaire, a few Active
Tasks, and also visualize these
tremor and dyskinesia symptom
data points.
Let's look at what the code
looks like, and for this demo,
we'll start with the basic bald
plate application and try to
recreate this app.
Here's my Xcode workspace, and
as you can see, in my
ResearchKit, I now have ORK
Parkinson's Study App.
We have a task list
viewController, where we'll be
adding all our Active Tasks and
questionnaires.
A graphviewController, where
we'll be visualizing these
tremor and dyskinesia symptom
data points.
And an assessment manager, where
we will be implementing the
movement disorder API.
When a Parkinson's disease
patient, or a PD patient visits
their doctor, they're asked a
certain set of questions, and
these questions include
questions about their activities
of daily life, something for
example on a scale of 0 to 10,
how is your pain level today.
Or, what kind of non-motor
symptoms are you feeling?
We have already added a subset
of such questions in our app.
Now, these questionnaires are
usually followed by seven
physical tests.
And one of the physical tests is
assessing the clarity of speech.
So, let's go ahead and add the
speech recognition Active Task.
In my task list view controller,
I'll go ahead and add the speech
recognition Active Task.
And as you can see, we just
added an ORK ordered task of
type speech recognition.
And if you notice, one of the
parameters is the speech
recognizer locale, which is an
item provided by ResearchKit
that represent all the locales
that are supported by speech
recognition API, so that you, as
developers don't have to worry
about conforming if your locale
is supported by these speech
recognition API.
Now, let's move on to our
assessment manager.
As Gabriel mentioned, we have a
variable call manager, which is
of type see and movement
disorder manager.
And if you notice, we have a
function that calls the
monitorKinesias method for the
maximum duration of seven days.
Let's call this matter in our
initializer.
Now, whoever creates an object
of a type assessment manager
will simply start the tremor and
dyskinesia symptom query.
Once we have collected these
data, we need a way to query
these data points also.
So, let's go ahead and add a
method that record these data.
I add a new, query new
assessments method, where I'm
calling the query tremor method
for a given start date and an
end date, and the query
dyskinesia symptoms method, for
the same start date and the end
date.
For this demo, we have already
ran this query and collected the
tremor and dyskinesia symptom
data points and saved them as
part of JSON file.
Let's go ahead, use those JSON
files and create ResearchKit
graphs on them.
I'll move over to my graph view
controller, and here, as you can
see, I have a create graph
method, which reads the JSON
files and creates ResearchKit
graphs from them.
Let's call these methods in our
view data log.
Perfect. Now, let's run this.
As you can see, we added this
speech recognition Active Task,
and added the movement disorder
API.
Here's what our Parkinson's
study app looks like.
We have the questionnaire on
top.
Let's quickly go ahead and run
through one questionnaire.
As Srinath mentioned earlier, we
now have a card view for all
these survey items.
And also, all these steps in
ResearchKit adhere to the iOS
paradigm.
Let's quickly finish this
questionnaire, and that's it.
Now, let's move on to the speech
recognition Active Task.
The first two steps talk about
how to use the speech
recognition step.
And as soon as I press the start
recording button, I would be
repeating the text that I see.
A quick brown fox jumps over the
lazy dog.
I am directed to the next step,
which is the other transcription
step.
And as Srinath mentioned, this
step is optional and could be
replaced from the task by
setting the property allow edit
transcript to no.
Perfect. Now, let's look at the
graphs that we created off of
tremor and dyskinesia symptom
data points.
Since the ResearchKit graphs
look really nice in the
landscape mode, I'll quickly
turn my phone, and let's look at
the graphs.
Here as we can see, we have all
the tremor and dyskinesia
symptom data points for a
particular day starting from 7
a.m. to 6 p.m. We can see tremor
slight, mild, moderate, and
strong.
And also, dyskinesia likely.
Perfect. With this, I would like
to call Srinath back up on stage
and continue with the session.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks for that great demo.
So, now let's take a look at a
quick recap of what we went over
today.
We started off by talking about
updates that we have made to our
community by expanding
privileges and also updating our
release schedule.
We showcased the look and feel
of ResearchKits new UI, and we
also added some new Active Tasks
focusing on three main areas of
health.
Hearing, speech and vision.
Gabriel spoke to you about the
new movement disorder API that's
available on the Apple Watch
from WatchOS 5.
And now, we'll look to all of
you as current or new members of
the community to continue to
engage with us and provide
feedback.
We also encourage you to take
advantage of our new release
schedule so that way you'll be
able to leverage some of our
in-house features like
accessibility, localization and
QA.
And on that note, as we continue
to expand on our library of
Active Tasks, we look to all of
our developers, researchers and
health professionals to help us
improve on these.
These Active Tasks are just
building blocks, which we hope
you can utilize to create much
bigger research studies, care
plans and treatment mechanisms.
And as you do, we encourage you
to contribute back to
ResearchKit, so we can continue
to improve our foundation and
expand on the breadth of Active
Task that's available for
everyone to use.
For more information about
ResearchKit, please visit our
website researchkit.org.
For additional information about
the talk, you can visit the
following URL.
I also encourage you to stop by
our lab session today.
Our teams will be down there and
will be really excited to answer
any questions you have, as well
as discuss more about some of
our new updates.
And finally, we really look
forward to seeing what you all
do with some of these new
updates in the coming days.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]