[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Welcome to CarPlay Audio and
Navigation Apps.
I'm Jonathan, an engineer on the
iOS Car Experience Team.
We are so excited to share some
updates with you today to help
you build a great experience in
CarPlay.
We'll start by reviewing CarPlay
Audio apps.
Then, we'll introduce the brand
new CarPlay framework for your
navigation apps.
And we'll drive a quick detour
to show you how easy it is to
build a great navigation
experience in CarPlay.
Let's start with a quick review
of CarPlay.
CarPlay is a smarter safer way
to use iPhone in the car.
You can seamlessly perform
common scenarios while driving
using your car's built-in
display.
You can make calls, send and
receive messages, listen to
audio, podcasts, and radio, and
now, get directions with your
navigation apps, all while
staying focused on the road.
You can think of the car screen
like a second external display
for your phone.
Your app can present a version
of itself on the car screen with
UI and features optimized for
use in the car.
There are some special design
considerations for your app when
presented in CarPlay.
CarPlay vehicles have a wide
variety of input styles.
Some cars have touchscreens.
Others have a rotary knob that
lets you move focus around and
select elements.
And some have a touchpad that
allows for swipe gestures, and
you can even do character entry
by tracing with your finger.
In a right-hand drive vehicle,
the CarPlay status bar and app
content will automatically
switch sides to be closest to
the driver.
Some cars, also, inform iOS when
to transition to a dark
interface mode.
Usually, when it's nighttime or
when the vehicle's headlights
are turned on.
Your app can use this as a
signal to, for example, update
your map tile display style.
CarPlay vehicles, also, support
a wide variety of screen sizes
and aspect ratios.
iOS handles all of these input
methods for you, so you can
write your app just once for
CarPlay and rest assured it'll
be supported on all of these
configurations.
So, what kind of apps can you
build in CarPlay?
These are the five categories of
CarPlay apps.
The car is a special place and
if you have an app in one of
these five categories you'll
need to apply for an entitlement
for your app to work in CarPlay.
If you're unsure whether your
app fits into these categories
and you're here at the
conference, please come talk to
us in our lab, later today.
More details on that, soon.
You can, also, go to this URL to
request an entitlement for your
app.
Let's quickly review these
categories of CarPlay apps.
Auto maker apps are a special
category of CarPlay app.
These apps are built by the auto
maker and work only in vehicles
from that manufacturer.
They can display fully
customized UIs for scenarios
like heating and cooling, seat
controls, and other direct
integrations with the vehicle.
SiriKit integration into these
apps allows you to change all of
these settings with just your
voice.
Last year, we introduced
messaging and VoIP apps to
CarPlay.
Your messaging and VoIP app can
tap into SiriKit.
So, your users can perform many
common messaging tasks while
connected to CarPlay, again,
while staying focused on the
road.
Check out SiriKit for more
details and see our session from
last year, Enabling Your App for
CarPlay.
In a prior release of iOS, we
introduced third party audio
apps to CarPlay.
Audio apps use a template
interface optimized for the car,
where your app provides data and
metadata for the car's screen.
We have some exciting new
performance improvements and
optimizations to share with you
today for audio apps.
And last but not least, today
we're introducing the CarPlay
framework, a brand new iOS
framework for your navigation
apps in CarPlay.
[ Applause ]
Just like with audio apps, iOS
displays your app on the car's
screen and handles the interface
with the car.
Your app doesn't need to worry
about input hardware or many
vehicle specific considerations.
You only need to update your map
tile experience to be
appropriate for the car.
The CarPlay framework provides a
fixed set of UI templates that
iOS renders on the car screen.
Your app decides how to create
and configure these templates
and what actions to take in
response to the user interacting
with your app's templates.
We'll hear much more about the
CarPlay framework, soon.
Back to our CarPlay app
categories, today we'll be
focusing on two of these
categories; audio and
navigation.
Let's start with audio apps.
Albert.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Jonathan.
I'm super stoked to talk to you
all today about CarPlay audio
apps.
We're going to go through a
brief overview of how to get
your audio app set up for
CarPlay.
Some performance improvements
and optimizations we've made for
iOS 12, and some best practices
to make.
And some common scenarios to
account for when developing your
audio app for CarPlay.
Now, driving and audio go hand
in hand.
It's very clear that when you're
driving you want to listen to
your favorite hits, your
classics, or even stream some
podcast episodes, or listen to
the latest news on radio.
We want to make sure that if
you're developing an audio app
that you want to provide the
best experience to your drivers.
Now, to illustrate this, I want
to let you guys in on a little
side project that I've been
working on.
It's a little app that I think
will be a great hit.
My app is called Srirocka.
It combines two of my most
favorite things; hot sauce and
hot tracks.
And with these synergies I think
it'll be one of the top audio
apps on the App Store when it
launches.
Now, Srirocka is already a fully
functioning audio app and we'll
need to add CarPlay support to
it.
So, let me illustrate how
this'll be done.
Like Jonathan mentioned, CarPlay
uses templates that will
abstract away many of the
different complexities CarPlay
has, such as input methods and
screen sizes, and so on.
So, your audio app just needs to
be able to display information
onto the CarPlay display and
provide the best content.
This is, usually, done by using
a table view or tabs, depending
on how you want to present your
data.
You'll need to focus on
delivering the appropriate
content to a CarPlay user.
And if you're already developing
an audio app, it uses existing
APIs you may be already familiar
with.
So, let's take a look at this in
detail.
So, these are the three APIs
that you'll need to know to
launch your app in CarPlay.
If you want to learn more about
this in detail, we had a session
last year that goes through the
details of each single API.
But I'll go through a brief
summary of every single one of
these.
To browse your content on the
CarPlay display, you'll need to
use MPPlayableContent.
MPPlayableContent has a data
source and a delegate, so that
you or your audio app can
populate your app's information
onto the CarPlay display.
As well as a delegate to receive
callbacks whenever the user
selects something on the CarPlay
display.
Now, if you already set Now
Playing metadata to Control
Center or Lock Screen, or you're
already working on this on your
existing audio app, you're
already familiar with these two
APIs.
MPNowPlayingInfo Center allows
you to populate your now playing
metadata and things such as
title and album artwork and
etcetera onto the CarPlay's now
playing screen.
As well as Control Center and
Lock Screen if you've already
been doing so.
MPRemoteCommandCenter allows
your app to respond to remote
command events, such as the Play
command, Next Track, and so on.
We want to allow your CarPlay
app for a seamless Now Playing
experience.
Now, let's take a look at how
this is done in code.
So, when Srirocka is launched,
I'm going to use Srirocka as an
example, here.
This is what is needed at a
minimum to support CarPlay audio
apps.
Srirocka will provide a data
source and a delegate to
MPPlayableContentManager, so
that Srirocka can provide
information to the CarPlay
display and respond when
absolutely necessary.
Next, I've set
NowPlayingInfoCenter to let
MPNowPlayingInfoCenter know that
my app will be providing
NowPlaying metadata when it
becomes a Now Playing app.
And finally, I've responded to
MPRemoteCommandCenter events.
Specifically, just a Play
command in this case, so that
when Srirocka becomes the Now
Playing app it can respond to
these events.
So, we can see here that the one
API that was needed for CarPlay
is MPPlayableContent.
And for iOS 12, we took a good
look at how to better optimize
this and we can safely say, for
iOS 12, we've remastered
MPPlayableContent.
[ Applause ]
We took a deep dive into
MPPlayableContent and we pushed
for performance improvements in
how the data source and delegate
calls are made.
Without changing your current
audio app's implementation in
CarPlay, we sped up the startup
sequence and provided much
smoother animations whenever
content is changed on the
CarPlay display.
We've also provided much better
communication to your app to
anticipate whatever the user may
want to play or to browse on the
CarPlay display.
Now, there's lots of room to
improve on your audio app.
And let's see how we can do
this.
The first of which, is that we
looked into the implementation
of reloadData.
Which, is a call in
MPPlayableContent, and figured
out how to better optimize this
for your audio app.
What we found is that you should
really only call reloadData when
absolutely needed.
What it does is that it
deconstructs the entire apps'
hierarchy on the CarPlay display
and asks your audio app to
reconstruct everything again.
And this can be a very expensive
operation, leaving your app not
very responsive.
Instead, if you just have
content that just needs to be
updated, you should wrap them
together inside of a
beginUpdates and an endUpdates
call, so then that content can
be updated, appropriately.
Now, these calls that
MPPlayableContent has are
asynchronous operations when we
ask you app for your data.
So, keep an internal
representation or a cache of
your information on somewhere in
your app.
So, then that when we ask for
your content information you're
able to provide us information
quickly and makes your app
responsive.
Next, let's discuss some ways to
further optimize your audio
app's performance in CarPlay.
So, Srirocka, already, has a bit
of an implementation and is
partially implemented.
And the user has decided to make
a selection on the Heating
Habaneros playlist.
It is one of the top playlists
that's super-hot.
But it seems to be stuck
loading.
We're not entirely sure what's
going on, here.
And CarPlay, actually, will
timeout if the app doesn't
provide content in time.
Because it doesn't call
completion handlers or just
simply isn't returning its
information.
But what's going on, on the
phone, here?
So, CarPlay users are, usually,
driving in areas where there's
not a speedy connection or their
screen is locked.
A vast majority of CarPlay users
are driving with the screen
locked and with a passcode.
After all, they're driving.
If your app has data protection
policies that are dependent on
the phone being unlocked, you
won't be able to access your
app's information and,
ultimately, CarPlay will
timeout.
So, if your data needs to be
accessed while the phone is
unlocked, you'll need to audit
your app's data intergradation
policies.
The other issue is that you may
be driving in areas, or CarPlay
users are driving in areas with
little to no cellular
network-tivity [phonetic].
Drivers are driving everywhere,
from the country roads and rural
areas, to big cities.
And these are very varied areas
with different CarPlay,
different data service.
And you need to test for
situations that are not just the
constant WIFI network
connection.
Now, Srirocka does account for
all of this, as well.
But it uses some very advanced
machine learning to see what are
the hottest tracks.
And after all, all of this
happens on device, since privacy
is a very important issue.
And this just takes some time to
process.
Well, what happens in this case?
We have an API called
beginLoadingChildItems at
indexPath to initiate fetching
content.
This API will be called whenever
any of your index paths are
visible on the CarPlay display.
So, when the user is scrolling
through table cells or selecting
different tabs,
beginLoadingChildItems will be
called for every single index
path that shows on the display.
This gives your app a chance to
start loading before the user,
actually, selects the content.
And here's a code example inside
of Srirocka, where when the user
sees that the Heating Habaneros
playlist is visible on the
CarPlay display, we start
processing that playlist.
And when the user makes a
selection, will have either been
midway through the network
request or ready to go and able
to provide content.
So, let's take a look at some
app scenarios that may occur
when developing your app for
CarPlay.
Now, Srirocka provides a very
rich user experience when logged
out.
It's very clear here, with
beautiful typography and great
graphic design, that the user is
logged out and will need to log
in.
But how does this look on
CarPlay?
Well, Srirocka, actually,
doesn't provide data when logged
out.
And this leads to a very poor
user experience.
The user doesn't really know
what's going on here and isn't
able to interact with your app.
You should make sure that you
should provide some type of
experience, so that the user can
at least interact with your app,
even if your app is logged out.
So, this leads to a very good
user experience for your audio
app.
So, wrapping all this up, we can
say that CarPlay audio apps have
its greatest hits.
MPPlayableContent allows your
app to provide templates to the
CarPlay display so that your app
can provide users a good user
experience to the CarPlay
display.
You should account for real
world scenarios, such as when
your app is logged out or your
screen is locked, so then that
your app can still function
beautifully in CarPlay.
And with iOS 12, we made some
great optimizations and
performance improvements to make
your app even better in CarPlay.
So, you should run your app
again and see if there's any
performance improvements you can
make to your app, to make it
even better.
Now, to make us sure that we're
steering in the right direction,
I'd like to invite my colleague,
Mike, to talk about navigating
with the CarPlay framework.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> All right.
Thank you, Albert.
I am thrilled to share with you,
today, how to add CarPlay
support to your navigation apps.
Navigation is such a huge part
of the CarPlay experience and
your users will be so happy to
see their favorite apps on the
car screen.
As Jonathan and Albert have
previously mentioned, we've
employed a template based
approach for previous app
categories.
Your apps have been able to
provide data and metadata that
iOS will display on the car
screen and manage these
interactions on your app's
behalf.
And this has worked extremely
well.
But, we realize that navigation
apps are a little bit different.
Your apps have beautiful maps.
And such incredible and
immersive navigation
experiences.
And your users will expect to
see that on the car screen.
So, new in iOS 12, we're
introducing the CarPlay
framework.
The CarPlay framework is your
toolkit for building great
interactive experiences on the
car screen.
It uses a fixed set of template
objects that your apps can build
and use, and that iOS will
translate into a UI presented on
top of your app.
With this and a little bit of
effort on your part, your apps
will support all CarPlay
systems.
So, let's take a look at an app
in CarPlay.
We've been building our own
navigation app that we call
Country Roads.
It takes us to our favorite
destinations using the scenic
route.
And let's see what it looks like
on CarPlay.
We're looking at the CarPlay
home screen and you can see our
Country Roads app icon right
there with the rest of the apps
on iOS.
As we launch it, the first thing
you'll be greeted with is our
beautiful map tiles.
When connected to CarPlay, a
navigation app will be given a
window to draw content on the
car screen.
This window is your canvas for
displaying all that beautiful
noninteractive mapping and
navigation related content.
Then, as the app used templates
iOS will take those templates
and translate it into a UI
presented on top of your app.
So, let's take a look at the
code on what happens when your
app is connected to CarPlay.
The first thing you'll need to
note is that your application
delegate will need to conform to
the CarPlay application delegate
protocol, CP Application
Delegate.
One function in that protocol is
application didConnectCar
InterfaceController to window.
This function will provide two
very important objects to your
apps.
The first is an instance of
CPInterfaceController.
CPInterfaceController is your
connection to the template world
and what your apps will use to
manage what is displaying on the
car screen.
Additionally, you're given the
window I just mentioned, which
is where you can draw all your
mapping content.
You want to be sure to keep a
reference to both of these
objects throughout the duration
of the CarPlay session.
Next, you can create a new view
controller to populate that
window with content and assign
it to windows review controller.
And then, create a root
template.
And using that interface
controller object, you can
setRootTemplate on the car
screen.
So, let's talk about some of
these templates that are
available in the CarPlay
framework.
And we'll start with one you've
already seen and where your
users will spend a majority of
their time.
And that is on the map template.
The map template is unique from
all the other templates in that
it is transparent to your app
window.
So, the content that you draw on
that window will be displayed
underneath the content provided
by the map template.
The map template can be
configured in a few different
places.
You can place buttons in the
navigation bar.
You can place up to four; two on
the leading side and two on the
trailing side.
These are instances of
CPBarButton and are created
either with text or images and
are automatically sized and
styled by the system.
There's no notion of predefined
button actions in the CarPlay
framework.
But when you create a button,
you provide a custom action
handler.
And when the user interacts with
your button on the car screen
your custom action handler will
be called in your app.
You may also place up to four
buttons that appear above your
map window.
And these are map buttons.
You can create them with an
image, and unlike the bar
buttons, these are not styled by
the system.
The map template is also home to
a lot of other mapping and
navigational related
functionality.
Such as panning the map,
providing important contextual
information to your users using
navigation alerts.
And of course, turn by turn
guidance.
We're going to talk about
guidance in a little bit.
So, let's get started by going
over panning and navigation
alerts.
If your app supports panning the
map, we require that you present
a button on the map template,
either in the navigation bar or
as a map button that enters pan
mode.
When a map template enters pan
mode it will display four
directional buttons that your
users can interact with and are
translated into an API, where
your app only needs to know
which direction to pan the map.
This is an example of how the
CarPlay framework has abstracted
away a lot of the complexities
of all the various CarPlay
systems.
These buttons can be interacted
with using touch, both high
latency and low latency
touchscreens.
Using a rotary knob or touchpad
to select one of these buttons.
And additionally, for CarPlay
systems that have a rotary knob
that also supports joystick of
directional movement, those same
movements will be translated
into this API.
Your app does not need to worry
about where it came from.
While your users are driving,
you may want to present
information to them, such as a
road closure ahead or maybe, a
better route is available.
For this, you can use navigation
alerts.
Navigation alerts present on the
map template and can be
configured with a title,
subtitle, image, primary and
secondary action, and if it
makes sense, you can use a
dismiss interval after which the
alert will self-dismiss.
Let's take a look at some code
on how we built our root
template.
And let's add a new button for a
missing feature on our Country
Roads app.
Since this was our function that
created out root template, the
first thing we're going to do is
create an instance of
CPMapTemplate.
We will then create a new button
for a missing feature.
One of the great things about
Country Roads is that our users
can search for their favorite
categories.
And we'll add a new button for
that.
So, let's create a CPBarButton
of type Image.
And in its custom action handler
we will call a function of our
own that is display our favorite
categories.
We'll then retrieve an image and
assign it to the button.
And we want this button to
appear in the trailing space
alongside our traffic button.
So, we'll assign those two
buttons to the trailing
navigation bar buttons on our
map template.
And then, return our map
template.
Great. Now, that we have a
button on our map template, we
want a way to display those
favorite categories to our
users.
The CarPlay framework has a
great template for this.
And that is the grid template.
The grid template will display
an array of up to eight buttons
in a grid format.
These buttons appear here and
can be configured with an image
and a title.
The grid template also has a
navigation bar, where you can
place the same leading and
trailing buttons.
But you can also create a grid
template with a title that will
appear in the navigation bar.
Let's jump over the code and
let's create a grid template.
We'll start by retrieving an
image for our grid button.
We're going to add a Parks
button.
We'll then create an instance of
CPGridButton with a title of
Parks and the image we just
retrieved.
That, with the other buttons,
we'll assign to an array.
And then, create an instance of
CPGridTemplate with a title of
Favorites, since these are our
favorite categories, and the
array of grid buttons we've
created in code.
And this is where we jump back
to that interface controller
object I mentioned earlier.
That is how we manage what is
presenting on the car screen.
So, we would use that interface
controller to push this new grid
template onto the car screen.
Now, that we have a way to
search for our favorite
categories and our favorite
items, we need a way to display
the search results to our users.
For that, we can use a list
template.
The list template will display a
list of CPList items.
They can be configured with
text, detailed text, an image,
and a disclosure indicator.
You can provide multiple
sections.
And you also, have a navigation
bar where you can provide a
title and those same leading and
trailing buttons.
One of the nice things about the
CarPlay framework is that, when
appropriate, it will also
display a nice scroll bar on the
side that helps your users page
through their search results
while driving.
Let's build a list template.
The first thing we're going to
need to do is take that array of
our own search results and
translate them into an array of
CPListItems.
So, we'll do that by using some
of the properties on our search
result class.
We will then initialize a new
CPListTemplate with one section
of those items, assign a title
of Parks, and also, assign a
delegate to manage interaction
from the user.
We, again, use the interface
controller to push our new
template onto the car screen.
When the user interacts with an
item on the screen listTemplate
didSelect item completion
handler will be called on your
list template delegate.
There are a few other items
available in the CarPlay
framework that I'd like to go
over, briefly.
The first is a great example of
how complex CarPlay can be and
how the CarPlay framework helps
you not have to worry about
that.
What we're looking at, right
now, is the search template
available in the CarPlay
framework presenting a
touchscreen keyboard.
But one thing we've learned is
that not all CarPlay systems
have a touchscreen.
Many only have a rotary knob or
touchpad for user interaction.
On those systems, when
appropriate, the CarPlay
framework will display a linear
style keyboard.
And of course, for those
touchpads that do support
character recognition, through
the same search template API
your app will receive those
characters as entered for free.
You may, also, want to present
information to your users in a
way that demands a little bit
more of their attention.
For that, you can present a
CPAlert in ActionSheetStyle or
for information that truly
commands their attention, you
can use a full screen template.
And lastly, since voice is such
a huge part of your apps, we'll
be providing a template that
will help you manage voice
control.
And with that, I'd like to
invite Jonathan back up to give
you a demo of our Country Roads
app.
Jonathan.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Mike.
Let's take a quick look at
Country Roads.
This is the CarPlay simulator.
It's included with Xcode.
Let's start on the CarPlay home
screen, where we can see our
custom navigation app enabled
for CarPlay.
Let's tap the icon to launch our
app.
When our app launches, we start
on the map template.
Here, the app overlay that Mike
mentioned is fully transparent
and it allows our app's
beautiful map tiles to show
through.
This map is really out of this
world.
I have some basic controls on
this map, like zooming in and
out with ECP Map buttons.
I can, also, switch in and out
of pan mode using this pan
button.
All of these buttons are simple
configurable template objects.
CarPlay tells my app when the
user has interacted with a
button and my app can zoom in or
out or take any other
appropriate action in response.
That new Favorites button that
Mike just added shows up in the
navigation bar on the trailing
side.
When we tap it our app has
created, configured, and pushed
a grid template that lets us
navigate to certain very
important destinations.
If we select Parks our app
creates, configures, and pushes
a list template where we can
visualize search results for
interesting nearby parks.
We'll revisit Country Roads,
shortly.
But for now, back to Mike.
[ Applause ]
>> All right.
Thanks, Jonathan.
So, let's talk about one of the
most important functions that
your apps will provide to your
users while driving.
And that, of course, is
turn-by-turn guidance.
Let's start by walking through a
typical flow your users may see
while beginning a navigation
session.
The first thing they need is a
destination.
This could be something that is
surfaced by your app through a
navigation alert.
Or perhaps, they've done a
search and found a destination
they want to travel to.
They may want to, then, preview
the route and see important
information about it, such as
how long it might take to get
there and what their estimated
arrival time is.
If there are multiple route
choices for the trip they're
about to take they'll probably
want to preview each of those
routes and make a choice that
suits them best.
They'll then select a route and
begin navigation.
This is when your app will begin
providing turn by turn updates
to the user.
Eventually, they'll arrive at
their destination or cancel
navigation.
And let's take a look at how you
can accomplish this same flow
using the CarPlay framework.
Let's start by talking about
Route Preview.
Your app can provide data that
will appear in a way that the
user can see and visualize all
the important details about
their upcoming trip.
You can provide destination
names, information that is
pertinent to the route, such as
advisory notices.
You can, also, provide estimates
to let them know when they'll
arrive.
And if the trip has multiple
routes the CarPlay framework
will automatically display a
more routes button.
This will allow your users to
toggle between individual routes
and select the one that they
want to take.
Let's look at the classes and
methods you'll want to be
familiar with to build an
experience in the CarPlay
framework route preview.
The first is CPTrip.
This is a representation of the
upcoming trip for your users.
It includes items such as the
origin and destination, as well
as multiple CPRouteChoices for
each route that they may take.
CPTravelEstimates describes how
long it will take for an entire
trip, as well as for individual
maneuvers.
On your map template, when you
are ready to show a route
preview to your users, you call
ShowTripPreviews on your map
template with the CPTrip object
you've created.
As the user toggles through
individual routes you have an
opportunity to update the
content that is being displayed
in your window.
MapTemplate selectedPreviewFor
trip using routeChoice will be
called and you can change what
is being displayed.
This is a great opportunity to
mention how the map template is
drawing content that covers up
your window.
And you'll want to make sure
that the content you're drawing
is visible to your users.
For this, we've leveraged the
existing safeArea API you may
already be familiar with.
As the content changes from the
map template it will update the
safeArea insets on your window
to let you know where it is safe
to draw.
You'll just want to implement
safeAreaInsetsDidChange and pay
close attention to those insets
and make sure your content is
drawn within them.
Now, let's talk about turn by
turn guidance.
Similar to our preview, your app
can provide data to the CarPlay
framework that will cause it to
draw a guidance card populated
with information, such as an
image representing the maneuver.
How much farther it is until you
arrive there.
And of course, instructions on
what to do when you get there,
such as turn left or continue
straight.
Let's take a look at what you'll
need to learn to use turn by
turn guidance in the CarPlay
framework.
The CPMapTemplateDelegate and
the mapTemplate are two places
you'll need to start.
First, when the user hits that
go button from Route Preview
mapTemplate startedTrip using
routeChoice will be called on
your template delegate.
This is your indication to begin
navigation to that destination
using the route choice the user
has selected.
This is when you would begin
navigation in your app, and
also, begin providing turn by
turn updates to the CarPlay
framework.
You'll want to call
startNavigationSession for trip
on your map template.
And this will provide you with
an instance of
CPNavigationSession.
And this is where you manage
those upcoming maneuvers.
Using CPNavigationSession and
CPManeuver you will set upcoming
maneuvers and the system will
automatically display a primary
maneuver.
And if you provide a second
maneuver it can display a
secondary maneuver on that
guidance card.
You will then use update
estimates for maneuver to
continually update what is being
shown in that guidance card.
And let your users know when
their maneuver is approaching.
And most likely, your app will
be playing back audio prompts to
let them know, as well.
For this, you'll want to make
sure that your audio session is
configured appropriately for
CarPlay.
We have to remember that when in
the car your users may be
listening to an audio source
from iOS or they may be
from the car, such as FM radio.
You want to configure your audio
session with
AVAudioSessionModeVoicePrompt as
this will let the CarPlay system
know when to appropriately duck
the audio source, regardless of
where it's coming from.
You can, also, configure your
session with the category
options duckOthers and
interruptSpokenAudio
AndMixWithOthers.
And this will help ensure that
your audio plays well with other
iOS audio sources.
So, what happens next?
Well, your users will continue
to drive.
You'll want to continue to
provide updated maneuvers and
estimates and help them make
those turns when they need to.
What happens if they veer off
route?
Well, you might want to
calculate a new route.
You can set a pause reason which
will display a rerouting status
to the user.
Perhaps, a new route is
available or something has
occurred along the route.
And you can use a navigation
alert to present that
information to them, right there
on the map template.
And ultimately, they'll arrive
at their destination, thanks to
your app.
So, we've talked a lot about
what your apps can look like
while frontmost on the car
screen.
But we know that our users in
CarPlay often switch between
their mapping app and an audio
app, like our favorite audio app
Srirocka.
What happens when your app is
backgrounded and you need to
present important information to
your users?
You will have an opportunity to
provide banner notifications
that will display when the user
is away from your app.
And this will work for maneuver
updates, as well as navigation
alerts.
On your map template delegate
there are three methods you'll
want to implement.
The first is mapTemplate,
ShouldShowNotificationFor
maneuver.
When you set a new maneuver and
your app is backgrounded this
method will be called.
And if you return true, the
system will take that maneuver
and translate it into a banner
notification.
If you're already presenting a
banner notification for a
maneuver, and simply are
updating the travel estimates,
mapTemplate
shouldUpdateNotificationFor
maneuver with travelEstimates
will be called.
Allowing you to update the
content that appears in that
banner.
So, instead of rolling a new
notification, you can simply
update the contents that are
already there.
And for navigation alerts, you
will have an opportunity to
display those, as well, using
mapTemplate
shouldShowNotificationFor
navigationAlert.
With that, I'd like to invite
Jonathan up one more time to
give you a demo of how we've
integrated our Country Roads app
with the CarPlay framework to do
route preview and turn-by-turn
guidance.
Jonathan.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Mike.
Let's take a quick look at some
code for how your navigation
apps can provide guidance in
CarPlay using our sample Country
Roads app.
When the user selects a
destination, we're going to grab
that placemark and hand the
current location and destination
to our navigation engine to
calculate some route choices.
For our purposes here, we have
only a single route choice, but
your navigation engine can
provide multiple alternative
routing options when available.
Plus, we can include some extra
details to help the user make an
informed decision about a route.
We'll create a CPTrip and call
showTripPreviews to inform
CarPlay that we're starting
navigation guidance.
Lastly, we'll update the
estimates to provide our user an
ETA for this trip.
Let's take a quick look at how
we can provide the maneuvers
that CarPlay needs for
navigation.
When our user has selected a
route and started navigation,
first we can hide the route
previews that our user was
browsing.
We'll tell our map template to
start a navigation session.
And we can move the session to
the loading state while we're
calculating maneuvers.
We'll build a list of CP
maneuver objects from our
navigation engine.
And last but not least, we'll
provide the first instruction to
our navigation session.
And now, we're ready to drive.
Let's see it in action.
All right.
Let's browse to our Favorites
list and choose Parks.
When we tap one of these
locations we'll see our app pops
back to the map template and
presents a route guidance card.
If we choose to start guidance
by tapping on the Go button
here, we'll see the app enter
navigation mode.
Your app can also update the Nav
bar if needed to show custom
buttons for navigation mode,
like a Cancel button or a toggle
for voice prompts.
Looks like we're making pretty
good time, here.
When we arrive at our
destination our app transitions
back out of navigation mode.
That's it for maps with the
CarPlay framework.
Let's review the roads that
we've driven together today.
We've shown you some big CarPlay
audio performance improvements
and optimizations for a better
experience for your users.
We introduced the brand new
CarPlay framework for navigation
and guidance apps in CarPlay.
Your app can work seamlessly on
different strings and input
devices.
You're the navigation experts
and you only have to do what you
do best; draw beautiful maps in
your beautiful apps.
And we'll take care of the rest.
You can draw your map template,
use CPMapTemplate and
CPNavigationSession to manage
navigation.
And show other templates as
needed to present information
and handle user interactions.
If you have any questions for
us, please come meet our team at
the CarPlay lab, later today, in
Lab 11 at 2 p.m.
You can, also, check out
developer.apple.com/carplay for
more details.
Otherwise, you have everything
you need to build a great
CarPlay app.
And we are so excited to see
what you create.
Thank you so much.
[ Applause ]