[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Good afternoon.
Welcome. My name is Ken Ferry.
Today Kasia Wawer and I are
going to talk to you about
performance in Auto Layout.
Last time I was up here talking
about Auto Layout was in 2011
when we first introduced it.
So it's really great to be back
up here chatting with you all
today.
OK, so Auto Layout.
This is how we position content
on iOS on the Mac.
The main object involved as we
know are views and constraints,
constraints giving the
relationships between views.
When it comes to performance, I
think the challenge here is that
if all you've said is the
distance between these two
buttons should be 20, it can be
hard to understand the
step-by-step process that the
machine goes through to do that
and that means it can be hard to
understand the expectations
around performance and
understand what's fast and
what's not and generally how
things are working.
So that's our goal for this
talk.
It's to really understand that,
to have a good feel for how
things are going to work.
So we're going to start things
off by first showing some of the
work that we've been doing in
this release for iOS 12 around
performance.
We've been doing a lot of work,
that's we get to give this talk.
When that's done we're going to
move on to trying to build that
step-by-step understanding that
I was talking about.
So we have good intuition and
good expectations around
performance.
To do that we're going to do
something very unusual for us,
which is to go into internals.
So enjoy that please.
Last, if you only ever rely on
our intuition for performance,
it's not going to work out very
well.
So we will then look -- Kasia
will take over and we'll analyze
code and we'll sort of show how
to merge your intuition with,
you know, practice.
But let's get to it.
So first as is traditional for
an Apple presentation, we're
going to look at a bunch of
numbers and brag.
[ Laughter ]
Here we have, what we're looking
at here is a benchmark.
So the way we approached this
work is we went out and looked a
bunch of third party apps as
well as our own apps and we
tried to isolate what we saw
happening into test cases that
we could then benchmark.
So this one here, what we're
looking at, is UICollectionView
with self-sizing cells and on
the whichever side looks bad is
iOS 11, which hopefully looked
janky and bad.
And on iOS 12 it's perfect.
It's hitting full frame rate.
So that's just one of the cases
we looked at.
Here are some more, just another
sampling.
We have a lot.
These ones are all time.
So what you're looking at is
that the gray bars are iOS 11.
How much time it took on iOS 11
and the blue are iOS12.
So what you take from this is
that we found a lot of places
where we could make things
really a lot better.
And that will only improve your
apps.
That will make things quite a
bit better for you I hope.
This is going all the way up and
down the stack.
So some of it is in the real
guts that affect just absolutely
everything.
Some of it's moving into UI
kits.
Some of it's up in the client
layer so for in how people use
Auto Layout.
So if you look at for example
that UICollectionView benchmark
that we were looking at that's
all of those.
It does include stuff that's in
the real guts but it also
includes a lot of really
important changes in just how
UICollectionView uses Auto
Layout and is more performance
due to it.
Which is a good segue to the
rest of the talk, which is how
you can do that too.
So how to use it properly.
When we were going through these
I think a lot of the time the
reason why we were able to make
all these improvements is that
we have a good mental model for
how things are put together and
how it performs, how it works.
We want to help you develop that
model as well.
So to frame this we're going to
go through an example case, some
client code, that is not -- that
has some issues and we're going
to discuss why.
So your code may or may not have
this particular issue, but we
did choose what we thought was
the most common thing that we
saw when we went through all
these client apps.
But even if you don't have this
particular issue, the work we do
to go through what's happening
should be meaningful to
everybody and probably new to
almost everybody.
So let's do it.
This is the case we're going to
go through so we're going to
produce this layout, obviously
very simple.
Oftentimes I think you would
build this in interface builder.
That's a great idea.
It is such a good idea that it
would completely prevent the
performance issues that we'd
like to go through.
So let's say we didn't do that.
Let's say that we built it like
this.
First let's just walk through --
before we try to analyze it,
let's walk through what this
code is doing.
First, we are overriding the
UIView method updateConstraints,
whatever that does.
So we'll talk about it.
Next, we have an Ivar called
myConstraints.
And we are taking everything in
that variable and we are
deactivating all those
constraints.
We are then creating
constraints, which implement the
layout that we were just looking
at.
That's fairly straightforward.
It's using visual format
language here.
We're then activating those
constraints, installing them,
and last we're calling
super.updateConstraints was an
important thing to do because
the UIView level implementation
that this method does do work.
OK, that's the basic structure
of what it's doing and it does
work, it's functions.
But let's talk about what it's
doing more concretely now so
that we can understand the
performance.
So the first thing to understand
is what exactly is
updateConstraints, this method
we're overriding.
Well, it's one component of the
Render Loop.
The Render Loop is the process
that runs potentially at 120
times every second.
That makes sure that all the
content is ready to go for each
frame.
OK, so it consists of three
phases -- Update Constraints,
Layout, and Display.
First every view that needs it
will receive updateConstraints.
And that runs from the leaf most
views up to the view hierarchy
towards the window.
Next, every view receives layout
sub views.
This runs the opposite direction
starting from the window going
down towards the leaves.
Last, every view gets draw if it
needs it, that kind of thing.
OK, what are these for?
Why do they exist?
Well, they all have the exact
same purpose and they have exact
parallel sets of methods.
And that purpose is to avoid
wasted work, which I can explain
by example.
So a label, a UI label needs to
have constraints that describe
the size of its text, OK?
But there are many properties
that contribute to that size.
There's the text property
itself, there's the font, and
the text size, etcetera.
One way to do this would be that
every time one of those
properties changes go re-measure
your text.
However, that would often be
pretty inefficient because you
usually change a bunch of these
right in a row.
When you're first setting up a
label, you're probably going to
call a bunch of these property
setters and if you're
re-measuring text on each one,
all the intermediate ones are
wasted, you really just want to
measure at the end.
And that's what the Render Loop
gives you.
Because what you can do instead
is that inside a set font you
can just call
setNeedsUpdateConstraints and
then you're guaranteed to get
update constraints at the end
before the frame goes to the
screen.
And that's what it's for.
So the couple things to
understand from this before we
move on is number one it runs a
lot, 120 frames a second.
Number two they're parallel.
So you can use that for
intuition as well.
If you feel like you understand
the layout pass or have some
feel for that, same deal when
you're thinking about
UpdateConstraints or you're
thinking about display.
And then the last thing being
that the whole reason it's there
is to avoid wasted work, to
defer work and possibly skip it
entirely.
All right, so having looked at
that we are now in position to
analyze the rest of this method.
See how we are -- every time
it's called we're deactivating
constraints and then activating
them again new ones.
We are saying this is analogous
to layoutSubviews.
So if we wrote the exact same
code in layout Subviews that is
the analog, that would be as if
you -- every time layoutSubviews
was called you destroyed all
your Subviews, created them from
scratch and then added them
again.
And I think a lot of people have
the completely accurate
intuition that that's not going
to perform very well.
So the thing to really get is
that it's the same.
Whatever intuition you take from
that apply it to
updateConstraints as well.
When you are ripping down
constraints like that you're
doing a lot of extra work.
So how do you fix it?
Well, you need to use -- as we
were saying, you need to make
sure that you're not doing it
more than once.
It's for deferring work.
So it should be something like
this, we say did we already do
this work?
If we did then just don't do
anything at all.
If we haven't done it yet, then
sure set up those constraints
once.
And that will perform well, OK?
So this is again, this is
actually the most common error
that we see in client code,
which is we call it churning the
constraints.
Unnecessarily ripping them down
and putting them back up.
OK, great.
We are going to do more but
stepping back for a second now
to think about the Render Loop
for a little bit.
The Render Loop is great if you
actually need it.
The purpose again, it's really
useful for avoiding that
redundant work.
But it's also dangerous because
it runs to often.
It's very sensitive code.
So in a case like this usually
what you want to do about
sensitive code is not -- like,
you should take care if you're
writing it but you should also
try to minimize how often you
write sensitive code because,
you know, you're probably going
to screw it up.
We all do.
So in this case, in fact you
might be, you should really
think again like could I just do
it once and not put it in
updateConstraints?
And a good way to do that is use
Interface Builder.
If you can use Interface Builder
you should.
It's great for all sorts of
reasons.
It puts you on a good path.
OK, so that's great.
We've now talked about that.
I think we have a better
understanding for why that's
problematic, at least somewhat
by analogy sub use.
But for the purposes of this
talk we want to do better than
that.
We don't just want to say this
is bad.
We want to really understand it
and understand the process.
So to do that we're now going to
peel back the covers and start
to really see what really
happens.
So when we activate these
constraints, when we add the
constraints, what is the process
that occurs?
Let's diagram it out at a high
level.
So if this is the view that
we're adding the constraints to,
this view is in a window.
Hanging off the window is an
internal object called the
engine.
And the engine is the
computational core of Auto
Layout.
When the constraint is added
what will happen is that we make
an equation, which corresponds
to the constraints, and we add
that equation to the engine.
The last object to understand in
the diagram is that the equation
is in terms of variables where a
variable is like, you know, if I
hand you an equation and I say
solve for X, X is a variable.
The things that we need to solve
for in this case is the frame
data of a view.
So there will be four variables
for every view, which is the min
X, the min Y, the width, and the
height.
OK, so let's go into this
process.
So this was the layout we were
going to do.
We're going to focus just on the
horizontal constraints for
simplicity, but we're going to
follow through the process.
So the first thing that happens,
as we said, is we make these
equations, which look like this.
These are pretty straight
forward.
The most interesting one is I
think the space between the two
text fields, which looks like
we're saying it looks very, very
similar to what you say with the
constraint but it's somewhat
lower level because it's in
terms of these variables.
OK, then each of those equations
needs to get added to the
engine.
And we're actually going to
follow along that process again
with the goal being to have a
good feel for the performance
characteristics.
What is happening when we do
this?
So the engine is trying to solve
for these variables, which is
something you may have done in
algebra and it actually looks
exactly the same.
So let's follow it.
So first equation comes in, says
the first fields minX is 8.
Cool. Its width is 100, fine.
OK, when this one comes in we
say the second field's minX is
equal to the first minX plus the
width plus 20.
What would you do in algebra if
somebody asked you to solve for
these variables?
You would substitute out for the
ones that you already had in
there.
And that's exactly what's going
to happen.
If you are profiling, you'll see
there is a genuine method in the
engine that contains the word
substitute as well as another
140 characters because we are
Cocoa Code Programmers.
But and that's what it will do.
And then, you know, and the last
equation comes in and this looks
done.
it looks like that was all the
work that had to happen at least
in this case to solve for those
variables and that's true.
That's what I want to understand
at this point is that the work
that happens is both not very
complicated.
It corresponds very, very, very
closely to what you would do if
you were doing it by hand.
And it's also not very
expensive.
It's just sort of substituting
out like this.
That's the work it does.
OK, so now we have sort of
solved for these variables in
the engine but that's not
layout.
So let's finish the process.
What happens for the rest of the
process is that whenever the
engine sort of assigns a value
to one of these variables, it's
going to inform the view that
the variable came from and say,
this thing changed.
What will the view do in
response to that?
Well, if you think about it for
a minute it will call it
Superview and say hey,
setNeedsLayout because it needs
to move.
OK, that was all happening as
part of the update constraints
phase.
We now just receive
setNeedsLayout, so at some point
it will move on to the layout
phase.
Then, OK, so the last piece of
the puzzle is that we'll
receive, UIView will receive
layout Subviews will do is it
will copy that data from the
engine into the frame.
So it will just say engine, what
are the values for those
variables?
Engine will tell it and it will
just call set Superview of that
view we'll call setBounds at
setCenter on that Subview.
And that is the entire process.
So just step back and think for
a second.
Like, that is the step-by-step
process of Layout.
If you can try to internalize
that and get a feel for it,
you're going to have a much,
much, much better feel for
performance expectations around
this stuff.
In fact, let's see how that's
going right now, because now
when we look at this and we look
at this method that we were
looking at that where we're
deactivating constraints and
we're reactivating constraints,
think about what we just did and
think about what the engine is
going to be doing.
It's going to look like this.
Which we call churning [laughs].
So each operation it's doing is
not super expensive, but it's
doing a lot of them and it's
just completely unnecessary.
This work is wasted.
So if you can feel this in your
heart, if you can really feel
that this is what is happening
when you do this, then you're
going to be in good shape.
Then that's -- you're going to
be in the same position we are
to go through and really get a
good feel for this.
OK, so I hope that's great.
There's one other big topic that
we want to cover though.
If we want to really have a good
performance model is this idea
that you only pay for what you
use with Auto Layout.
And having looked at this, I
think we're in a good position
to understand what that means,
OK?
To do this, let's say we double
the situation we had before.
So we have four text fields in
two sort of independent
hierarchies.
Now something you can do is you
can make a constraint that
crosses the hierarchy like this.
That goes -- that you can say,
well text field one should be
aligned with text field three
even though they don't have the
same Superview.
I think sometimes people have
the impression that because this
possible, it means that things
are going to be generally quite
slow because anything could
affect anything at any time and
so it's just sort of a giant
ball of mud and performance
probably sucks.
OK, but having looked at what
we've looked at, let's see what
happens in the common case where
you don't have this because most
of the time you don't.
Most of the time views are only
constrained to their parent and
to their siblings.
What you'll see there is that
since we have these two
independent blocks, that will
give, if you look inside the
engine it will be two
independent blocks of equations
that completely don't interact
with each other, that don't have
any overlapping variables.
What that will do, is that
because they completely don' t
overlap, they just don't
interact.
And if we have one of these it
will take some amount of time to
deal with.
If we have two of them it will
just take twice the time because
they have nothing to do with
each other.
Three of them, three times,
etcetera, the point is you're
going to see a line.
You're going to see linear
performance, which is the best
you can get.
That's perfect marks for this
kind of thing.
So I want to stress this again,
the reason why it's linear is
because there aren't any
dependencies between these
pieces.
If you do have a dependency,
then it will tie those blocks of
equations together and that will
be somewhat more, you know, more
computation to deal with but
that's only if you use it.
And of course if you do have
something like that, you know,
if you're doing it by hand of
course it's going to be a little
bit more expensive that's what
you expect.
You're doing something more
complicated.
So it's kind of this usual thing
that we often aim for in Cocoa,
which is that the simple things
are simple and the complex
things are possible.
In this case it's more like they
cost a little more.
But you're not paying for it if
you're not using it, which is
actually the right way to think
of the whole engine in terms of
intuition again, you can think
of it as a cache for layout and
as a dependency tracker.
It's very, very targeted.
It understands which constraints
affect which views, and when you
change things it just updates
exactly the things that are
needed.
And this has implications on how
you write code too.
Sometimes we see -- one issue we
sometimes see is people taking
great pains to avoid making
constraints because they have
the impression it's going to be
expensive.
But actually, it's very, very
targeted.
As long as the constraints that
you're making correspond closely
to the problem that's being
solved, it's pretty unlikely
that whatever you do, if you
tried to dodge it, it's going to
be more performance.
Oftentimes we'll see people
doing very complicated
measurement and adding things up
and sort of trying to pull
information out and then push it
back in and that's almost always
more expensive than just
directly expressing as a
constraint what you're after.
Now the converse side of that is
that sometimes we see
hierarchies that look like
something like this where we see
lots and lots of constraints and
lots of priority and it's really
not clear what's happening and
this is a -- usually this is a
telltale sign of this being the
situation that there's actually
just two completely separate
layouts that someone has in mind
and we're trying to sort of pack
them together into one set of
constraints and do it all in
one.
And that's also not a real good
idea.
So that will -- that creates a
lot of false dependencies,
places where it seems like
things interact that they really
don't.
It's also nearly impossible to
Debug, if you haven't noticed.
So the overall advice is try to
model the problem as directly as
possible.
Kasia is going to walk through
this kind of case where you're
switching between different
layouts and show that a little
more explicitly.
But that's the general advice.
Just use it in a natural way.
It's better for both performance
and for understandability.
OK, so that most of what we have
to say.
But since we're trying to build
an overall mental model of the
performance characteristics of
Layout, I want to at least make
sure we touch on all of the
major features.
So there are some other things
you can do.
And let's discuss.
So you can say that some
particular view should be at
least 100 points wide.
You can use inequalities.
What does that cost?
Very, very, very little.
Compared to just saying it's
equal to hundred points wide.
Since we went internals a little
bit, it's going to coast exactly
one more variable.
That's it.
You can also call set constant.
The example use case for this is
something like I have a gesture
recognizer and I'm kind of
trying to drag a view around and
what I'm going to do is every
time I receive a call from the
gesture recognizer I'm going to
take its translation and I'm
going to pump it into a
constraint by calling set
constant on that constraint with
that translation value.
OK, what that's going to do is
we talked about how the engine
is a dependency tracker.
This exploits that to the
maximal degree.
So that's sort of a very, very,
very fast one step update of
just exactly what has to change
due to this one constraint
changing.
So that's a performance
optimization.
That's why we even have this
method set constant.
Last to talk about it priority.
So here you can say, you know,
you can say this view should
ideally be 100 points wide, but
if something else prevents that
just please be as close as
possible.
This does incur some more work,
some amount of work.
So let's talk about that a
little bit more.
Another way to think about that
is to say that the width of that
field is going to be equal to
100 plus some error and please
minimize the error.
That's what you're asking for.
So there is an error
minimization phase I didn't
discuss before.
So when the view asks the engine
as part of layout subviews and
says, hey what's the value for
these variables?
The engine needs to make sure
that all of those error terms
have been minimized first.
And this is actually, this is --
I'm not going to go into how
this works but I am going to
talk a little bit about
performance characteristics and
I'm also going to say that's
super neat.
So you might want to look this
up.
This is the simple X algorithm.
This is what we're really doing.
It's super old.
It was developed during World
War II.
What you might note is before
computers.
In fact, the people who used to
be called computers, before
there were machines that were
called computers, this is kind
of what they're doing.
They're doing it by hand, which
does give you some feel for the
performance characteristics.
It must be pretty fast if you do
it by hand.
And it is.
It's pretty much the same stuff
we've been doing.
It's more substitutions.
That's how you should think of
it.
Anyway, but it does -- you know,
when you use priority it does
cost at this level so that's
just something to be aware of.
OK, and other than that it's
just same as before.
So that's what I wanted to talk
about.
So that is our attempt to build
this intuitive understanding of
the performance characteristics
around Auto Layout.
So quick review of what we
talked about.
Try not to churn your
constraints.
That's when you're doing all
this work that just doesn't
matter.
So don't do it.
When you do work with
constraints it's basic algebra
and that algebra is happening
when you add constraints, when
you remove constraints, when you
call set constant, that's the
primary times.
And then also, you know, when we
have this error minimization
phase.
The way to think about what Auto
Layout does is that it's a cash
for your layout, we saw the
engine sort of contains all
those solved values and it's a
dependency tracker so that when
things change we can update
those values in a super, super
targeted way.
Which leads to our last point,
which is that you only pay for
the features that you're using.
That's what we talked about.
You know, that's your intuition.
And for the rest of the talk I'm
going to turn it over to Kasia
because if you, again, if you
only rely on intuition, things
are not going to go well.
So she's now going to go into
some analysis, avoid we talked
about and putting that intuition
into practice.
So please enjoy.
[ Applause ]
>> Ok let me get to my slide
here.
Thank you, Ken.
Hi everybody.
My name is Kasia Wawer.
I am a member of the iOS
Keyboards Team and we use Auto
Layout and we love it.
So I get to talk to all of you
about building efficient
layouts.
All right, let's go back to
Constraint Churn real quick
here.
Constraint churn as we heard
happens when you change your
constraints but the actual views
don't need to move so you're
sending extra work to the engine
and enough of that can affect
your performance.
So you tend to want to avoid it.
So let's talk about how you
might run into this problem and
how you might get out of it.
So we're going to work with a
spec here.
This is for a social media type
app.
There's an avatar view that
shows you who is sharing.
There's a title, a date, and a
log entry view and for that
you're going to need some
spacing, you're going to need
some sizing and you're probably
going to need some alignment
too.
But this is actually not a pure
social media app.
It is a semi social media app,
where you can choose whether you
want to share things.
So there's also optionally a
view that says that you've
shared and who you've shared
with.
And no social media app would be
complete without the ability to
share cat pictures.
So that's another layout that
you might have to put in.
And maybe you don't even want to
share that cat picture because
it's just too good, you want to
keep it to yourself.
So we have four very similar
layouts.
They're not the same and there's
going to need to be some
adjustment when these table view
cells come on to the screen.
If I didn't mention it these are
in table view cells.
And let's say that you are
working on performance in this
app and you ran it for the first
time and this is the scrolling
performance you got.
And there are a lot of hiccups
there, especially on the scroll
back to top.
So you're like, OK, how do I
improve this app?
What's going on?
So I get to introduce something
new today, a sneak peek into
something we're working on.
This is not actually available
in the beta but stay tuned
because we're going to be
introducing an instrument for
layout.
And, OK.
[ Applause ]
I'm glad you are excited.
That's good motivation.
Anyway, let's take a look at
what's here.
The top track is your standard
how much CPU is being used.
And this is sort of your canary
in the coalmine view.
If there are a lot of peaks here
you have an indication that you
might have something you need to
look at in your layout.
And if it's pretty flat,
probably your performance
problems are originating
somewhere else.
Below that we will be
specifically tracking constraint
churn.
The height of the bars in this
instance correspond to the
number of views that are
experiencing constraint churn.
So when you see a big piece
there you know a lot of views
are affected.
We're also going to show you how
to remove and change constraint
instances and finally sizing for
UILabel and other text views.
This one says UILabel because
that's what's in this app.
It's also going to track other
types of text views as well.
So this was taken with that app
scrolling, so what do we look at
here?
There are several peaks in the
CPU view but let's zoom in on
this one because right below it
I see a big jump in constraint
churn and that's a little
concerning.
So if you highlight this view
and go down to the detailed view
in instruments, what you'll see
is a list of the views that are
affected by churn by view
description.
And we are grouping them by
Superview so that in an instance
of say Table View Cells, it's
easier to see that it's
happening over and over in a
specific context and not
different ones.
So in this instance we see that
the avatar view and three labels
are experiencing churn.
And since I am the one who ran
this through the instrument, I
know that these labels
correspond to the Title Label,
Date Label, and our Log Entry
Label.
That's almost all of our views
in this cell.
That's a little concerning.
Let's see what happened.
All right, back to our spec
here.
So look into the code and find
that UpdateConstraints is being
overridden.
And in that method when anything
changes or when
UpdateConstraints runs at all,
we're removing all of the
constraints and then adding back
the ones that we think we still
need.
Well, everything landed back in
the same place where it started.
So that removal just is
contributing to performance
issues.
So in the instance of the social
label here, social avatar thing,
being added and removed, we
don't actually need to pull it
all the way out.
When you look at the constraints
around this view, you'll see
that they don't actually
interact with anything else,
just that particular view.
So here you can use, you know,
this neat little feature called
setHidden, maybe you've heard of
it.
And because it's not affecting
any of the views around it, it's
just going to disappear, it's
constraints stay in place and
this is a very, very, very cheap
way to hide and show views,
rather than removing them from
the hierarchy.
So that's fine.
But this is a really simple
example.
What about the image view?
All right, so for the image
view, again we might we might
want to try removing all
constraints and then adding back
the ones we already had plus the
image view ones.
And again, everything is landing
in the same place so we're
experiencing churn.
Well, in a situation like this
how I want you to think about it
is to look at groups of
constraints.
So let's start with this group
that I'm highlighting here in
green.
These constraints stay the same
in every one of our layouts.
Once we're doing the hide and
show on the sharing view that
doesn't need to change, the
avatar view never moves, and the
labels never move other than the
log entry label being able to
get longer.
So those green constraints
should be added when you create
the views and then left in
place.
Don't touch them.
They want to stay where they
are.
But now we have the four
constraints that are controlling
the image view.
So what do we do with those?
Well, let's stick them in an
array and let's also take the
constraints that are going to be
there when there's no image.
And I very creatively named
these imageConstraints and
noImageConstraints so you can
keep them apart.
And let's, when we're getting to
the point where we're going to
be putting in this image view or
taking it away, let's see what
layout we're currently in.
Deactivate the
noImageConstraints if we need to
and activate the ones for the
image.
If we don't have an image coming
in, you know, all of our other
constraints are already
activated, we just have the one
that we're adding.
Now I put these both in arrays
despite the fact that this is a
single constraint because it
simplifies things in my code.
I don't need to check and see
whether I'm dealing with an
array or a single constraint,
I'm always dealing with an array
of constraints.
Your mileage may vary though.
So the nice thing about this is
that if you are tracking your
constraints properly like this
and you know that you want to
add this image view live in
front of the user, you can
deactivate these
noImageConstraints, activate the
ImageConstraints and call Layout
in needed inside a View
Animation block and it's going
to animate nicely into your
view.
If you tried to do this with
deactivating all of your
constraints and putting them
back in, it would look very
interesting.
Let's say it that way.
All right, so now that we've
debugged this and we're working
with groups of constraints
instead of throwing everything
at it, let's look at what it
will look like.
This is what it looked like
originally just to remind you.
Let's scroll to the top.
It's very bad.
And this is what it looks like
after we've debugged it.
And that is much smoother.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
But wait there's more!
I actually took this video on
iOS 11.
This is not taking advantage of
any of our performance
improvements in iOS 12.
This is just the client code
doing things more efficiently.
In iOS12 it also looks great.
And of course fabulous
[laughing].
[ Applause ]
Yes, it's great.
So how do we avoid constraint
churn?
Well, avoid removing all of your
constraints.
That's usually going to put you
into a situation where you have
to put a bunch of them back and
that's going to land you in a
position where you're relaying
out frames that don't need to --
or relaying out views that don't
need to be laid out again.
If you have a set of constraints
that going to be common to all
of the potential layouts in your
app, add them one and then leave
them alone.
This is a good use for Interface
Builder and the initial layout
of your app.
Changes to the constraints that
need changing but don't change
the ones that don't need
changing.
Kind of tautological but it
seems good.
And then you have a neat trick
now for hiding views instead of
removing them when that makes
sense.
All right, so that was
constraint churn in the
instrument.
We also have that view at the
bottom that said UILabel sizing.
UILabel sizing is tracking the
amount of time it takes for the
label to calculate its size.
So let's talk about intrinsic
content size.
I'm going to take a walk over
here.
OK, not all views actually need
intrinsic content size.
Some views do.
Views with non-view content like
to return a size for their
intrinsic content size based on
that non-view content.
Two examples of this are
UIImageView, which uses the size
of its image to calculate its
intrinsic content size and
UILabel, which measures its text
and uses that to return its
intrinsic content size.
There's nothing really magical
about intrinsic content size,
it's used to create constraints
by UIView.
It makes sizing constraints for
you and that's it.
You can define all of your
sizing in constraints yourself
and skip this whole thing.
There are a few circumstances
where it needs to be overridden,
that's what it's there, as we
saw there are these couple of
things plus some other examples
in UIView subclasses.
But a lot of the times it gets
overridden because the
assumption that it's either
faster or more exact and it is
neither of those things.
However, there is a circumstance
where overriding it might help
your performance.
Text measurement can be
expensive.
In our app here the UILabel
sizing did not take very long.
It was very short durations.
So messing around with that is
not going to improve the
performance of that that much.
But if you have a text intensive
app and you're seeing a lot of
time happening in the UILabel
text measurement or you have
text view text measurement or
whatever else you're using, you
might be able to help it along
if you have some additional
information.
If you know the size that the
text needs to be without doing
all that text measurement, you
can return that size and
intrinsic content size, or if
when you're going to be putting
this view on the screen the
constraints are going to be
fully defining the size
regardless of the size of the
text inside of it.
For instance, the constraints
are always going to make it
larger than the amount of text
you have.
Then you can go ahead and return
no intrinsic metric for the
width and height in intrinsic
content size.
And what this will do is tell
the parent, hey I already have
my size, don't bother to do the
text measurement.
So obviously this only works if
you're not trying to detect
measurement yourself, but it can
help some apps improve their
performance.
So I wanted you to know that
this little trick exists.
And we can't talk about
intrinsic content size without
talking about system layout size
fitting size because people
often conflate the two even
though they're kind of
opposites, so that's kind of
unfortunate.
Intrinsic content size is a way
that you communicate size
information to be put into the
engine.
System Layout Size Fitting Size
is a way that you get sizing
information back out of the
engine.
They're actually kind of
opposites.
So this is used in sort of mixed
layouts where there's some
reason that you need frame
information from a view that
manages its subviews using Auto
Layout.
Not very frequent usage but is
there and can be used.
I want to tell you how this
method works because it might be
a little more expensive than you
think.
When you call System Layout Size
Fitting Size an engine is
created.
Constraints are added to this
engine, the layout is solved,
and then the size of the top
views frame is returned, and
then the engine gets discarded.
So each time you call this
method an engine is being
created and discarded.
While this is fine for small
uses, if you're doing it a lot
you can see how it might start
to build up over time.
So be cautious when calling
System Layout Size Fitting Size.
One of the uses that we
sometimes see people do is
forwarding that call from their
self-sizing collection or table
view cell to a content view.
And when you do that you're
actually overriding some
optimizations we've made to make
that scrolling, scrolling in
that view faster and you're
adding extra engines.
So if you're currently doing
that and your scrolling is no
good, maybe look into that.
All right, now we come to my
very favorite topic in the
world.
Unsatisfiable Constraints.
OK, so what are unsatisfiable
constraints?
If you haven't run into this
before, this is what happens
when you do something like, hey
this view should be 50 points
wide, also it should be 200
points wide.
Well, that's not really going to
work.
These are not actually quantum
phones.
You know, I can't speak to the
future but so the engine has to
kind of calculate the fact that
there's no layout available and
break a constraint in order to
generate some sort of layout for
you.
When it breaks that constraint
it sends a very detailed log to
your debugger, possibly you've
seen it, that says, hey
unsatisfiable constraints.
Here's the constraint that I
broke and here's all the other
ones that affected, that caused
me to have to break it.
So this can sometimes affect
performance directly and it can
also mask other issues.
So it's a good idea to get them
debugged.
And Mysteries of Auto Layout,
Part 2, had some good debugging
information so you might be
interested in checking that out
if you have been having trouble
with your unsatisfiable
constraints.
OK, guys you've graduated.
Congratulations.
You are all Auto Layout experts
and, you know, I hope that you
really enjoyed learning about
the internals of how it works.
Now you know better how to think
before you update constraints
and understand the process they
go through, you've got some
tuning information with size and
priority and inequality, and you
have faster layouts in iOS 12 so
that's awesome.
We're going to be in the Labs
tomorrow if anybody has
questions.
And we've got the link here for
information in related sessions.
Enjoy the rest of your week.
[ Applause ]