[ Music ]
>> Good afternoon, everyone.
[ Applause ]
Welcome to Core Data Best
Practices.
My name is Scott Perry.
I work on Core Data.
And we'll be joined later by my
teammate, Nick Gillett.
The plan for today, first, we'll
talk a bit about how the process
of getting started with Core
Data has evolved over time.
Then, we will cover ways we can
evolve our application more
easily by taking advantage of
extension points in the
persistent container.
We'll follow that with how we
can evolve our model as our apps
requirements change and our data
grows.
Then, Nick is going to talk
about a few ways our app can
maintain its performance, even
as it scales beyond our wildest
dreams, and we'll wrap up with
some good stuff about
transformers, debugging, and
testing.
But first, let's build an app.
I like to take photos, so we're
going to build something that
allows me to share photos with
friends and get comments from
them, even if it's just Nick
asking how my slides are going.
Where should we keep our app's
data?
Well, we could keep it all
online, but I usually take
photos when I'm traveling, and
the connection can be kind of
spotty, so we should keep it
locally, organized into some
kind of store.
So, we have posts and comments
and their instances and the
relationships between them form
an object graph and we've
decided we need to persist these
things on disk, so that's what
Core Data is for.
So, we'll use that and we'll
start by translating our mock
here into something a store can
understand, a managed object
model.
We'll need fields for
everything, with attributes for
things like the image's data as
well as the time it was posted,
and we'll need relationships for
posts and comments.
We've also defined a need for a
store, but there's a lot
involved in maintaining data on
disk over time.
Luckily, Core Data provides a
persistent store coordinator to
manage that.
The coordinator can do things
like compare the app's model
with the store's version and
automatically migrate it forward
as our app evolves.
Finally, managed object context
provide safe, fast, and
predictable access to our data,
even when we're using many at
the same time through features
like query generations,
connection pooling, and history
tracking.
Setting this all up requires
finding the model and loading it
and deciding where to keep the
store, but a lot of these error
paths can't actually fail once
you've shipped your app, so Core
Data provides a container type
that dramatically reduces the
amount of boilerplate required
to set up your stack, just refer
to the model by name, and the
persistent container will load
it out of the main bundle and
keep a stored in a consistent
location.
This persistent container type
encapsulates a whole stack and
includes conveniences for a
shared main queue view context
as well as factory methods for
generating background contexts
as well as performing background
work.
It's also designed to be easy to
work with as our app grows.
For example, let's say we want
to factor our model layer into
its own framework.
We can do that by creating a new
framework target in Xcode and
moving our code into it.
It's all super easy, but when we
move our model into the new
target, in the built product,
targets move from the app into
the new framework, which is
what's supposed to happen, but
now NSPersistentContainer
doesn't know where to find our
model anymore.
This is because it only checks
the main bundle by default.
Why stop there?
Well, searching all of the app's
bundles could get really slow
for a complicated app and it's
not a cost you want to pay every
time you spin up a stack.
How do we fix this?
Well, we could resuscitate the
model out of the framework
bundle ourselves and use one of
the container's other
initializers, like one that
takes an explicit managed object
model, but NSPersistentContainer
actually has a way for you to
change which bundle it searches.
See, NSPersistentContainer knows
when it's been subclassed and
will use the type of the
subclass as a hint when it looks
for the model.
All we need to do to take
advantage of this is to create a
subclass.
It doesn't even need to have
anything in it.
Then, any code setting up
through the container that wants
to use our model can just adopt
that subclass and the persistent
container will check in our
frameworks bundle for our model
instead.
So, that's fun, but since we're
going through the effort of
factoring our app's resources,
wouldn't it be nice if we also
improved the organization of our
data on disk?
By default, new persistent
containers come with a store
description for an SQLite store
with automatic migration that on
iOS lives in our app's documents
directory.
That was great when our model
code was part of the app, but we
should try to keep our new
frameworks files from mingling
too much with the apps.
Since we already subclassed
NSPersistentContainer to make
finding the model easier, let's
build on that to improve this.
The brute force way to change a
store's location is to directly
modify the URL in the
persistentStoreDescription
before loading the store.
Sometimes that's what you want
and we could use that pattern
here, but we don't have to
because NSPersistentContainer
calls its own default directory
URL method when creating
persistent store descriptions.
And it's made to be overridden.
In this case, we can just append
a path component, but this is
also a good way to set up
containers for caches or other
kinds of stacks that need to
keep their stores in different
locations, like your tasks.
So, now that we've got our Core
Data stock all figured out,
let's have a look at our app and
some of the view controllers
that we've written.
It looks like we've got some
pretty specialized view
controllers here.
Here's one that shows all of my
posts as well as another that
shows all posts by all authors.
Even the detail views are
duplicated.
It feels a lot like we could
have written half the code.
All we should really need is one
view controller for displaying a
list of posts and another for
displaying a single post.
We can accomplish this by
defining good boundaries in
between our view controllers in
the form of interfaces that take
model objects.
Each controller gets configured
by its model parameters and then
they can customize their views
in cells based on whether
they're showing my posts or
someone else's.
When drafting view controllers
using Core Data, list views
should get fetch requests and
detail views should get managed
objects.
View controllers also need a
managed object context, either
the container's view context or
some other main queue context.
And this pattern for
generalizing view controllers
with Core Data isn't just for
UIs; it works really well for
utility types as well.
Instead of passing Core Data
types for presentation, we can
pass things like URLs or
serialized data into background
work controllers and turn those
into new and updated managed
objects using a background
context instead of a view
context to do our work.
Adopting this kind of interface
and utility type is super easy
since we own the initializer, so
we can just require the
parameters to create the
controller.
But how do we get our boundary
variables into our view
controllers?
Well, if we're using segues, we
can override the prepare method
and get a reference to the
destinationViewController and
then configure it there.
If we're using storyboards or
nibs, then we already have code
that has to cons up a
destinationViewController, so
all we need to do is set the
properties before presentation.
And, if we're driving stick, we
can just write an initializer
that explicitly defines the
boundary conditions, just like
we do with our utility types.
OK. So, now we've got a fetch
request and a context for our
view controller, but before we
smash them together to get our
results, we should configure the
fetch request a little bit more
to make sure that our controller
will have great performance.
Sometimes it makes sense to set
a fetch limit, but in the case
of our list view, batching makes
more sense because we want to
show all the data and we know
exactly how many cells our view
controller can fit on the screen
at once.
In general, at least one of
these options should always be
set for fetch requests that
might return an unbounded number
of results.
So, at this point, we could turn
our fetch request into objects
and populate a list view with
the results, but what if we want
to keep the UI up to date with
changes as they happen?
Core Data has us covered here as
well with the fetched results
controller.
Available on all platforms since
Sierra, adopting the fetched
results controller just requires
writing an adaptor between the
delegate protocol and the view
it's driving.
And to create one, all we need
is a fetch request and a
context.
The fetched results controller
even supports driving more
advanced list view concepts such
as sections.
If we wanted to group posts into
sections by the day they were
posted, we could do it by
extending the post type that's
generated by Xcode with the
computed property and passing
the name of it to the fetched
results controller's
initializer.
This works well, but what if we
have a view controller more
complicated than just a list of
our objects?
What if we want to show
something like a chart of the
posts per day on our app?
Well, the first thing we should
do is not underestimate the
power of fetched requests.
I'm just one person, so in the
last month, I haven't managed to
post more than 40 pictures per
day.
Over the course of 30 days,
that's still a fairly reasonable
amount of data to pull out of
the store at once.
If the day property that we
defined earlier was actually
part of the entity in the model,
then we could write a fetch
request that counts up the
number of posts grouped by the
day they were posted.
There's three parts to this
request.
The first one is just setting
the range.
We want the last 30 days of
data.
Next, we want to group together
all results whose day attributes
share the same value.
Since we're now fetching
aggregates instead of individual
objects, we have to change the
result type to something more
sensible as well, in this case,
a dictionary.
Finally, we define an expression
that represents the number of
objects in each group and tell
the fetch requests to return
that count along with the day it
represents.
This fetch request returns 30
results, each of which is one
point on our chart.
If you're into databases, this
is the SQLite query that Core
Data generates from that fetch
request.
It's exactly what you do if
you're writing the query
yourself.
Core Data understands how to
convert many expression
functions into optimal database
queries.
A group by query can use
aggregate functions such as
average and sum and scalar
queries, like a normal fetch
request, can use scalar math and
date functions, like abs for the
absolute value and now for the
current time.
If you want to know more about
what you can do with
NSExpression, check out the
documentation for its list of
functions.
Many of them are supported by
fetch requests in Core Data.
OK. So, fetch requests can
accomplish a lot through the use
of expressions, but SQLite still
reads every one of our posts
through memory when computing
the counts for our graph here.
That works fine for charts
showing the amount of posts
generated by one human in a
month, but what if we want to
chart something bigger?
What if we want to show a whole
year or what if our little app
starts handling orders of
magnitude more data?
Now the fetch request would be
counting at least 50,000 posts
one by one just to show 30 data
points and that's not going to
be fast enough.
The mismatch between our views
and our model has gotten to the
point where we need to start
doing some denormalization.
Denormalization is when we add
redundant copies of data or
metadata to improve read
performance at the expense of
some additional bookkeeping.
Database indexes are a good
example of this.
Adding count metadata to our
store is exactly the kind of
compromise we need to get our
chart's performance again.
So, let's look at how our model
can group posts into counts by
day.
We'll need a new entity with two
attributes, plus a bit of extra
maintenance to keep them
accurate.
Grouping by day improves our
fetch request so much that it
guarantees good performance for
charts covering years of data,
so we only have to create this
one level of denormalization and
the fetch request that we passed
to the chart view controller?
It's super simple.
It's really not that much
different than the fetch request
that we'd pass off to any other
list view, which is actually
kind of sort of what a chart
view is if you squint hard
enough.
But what about that extra
maintenance?
We've got to increment the count
whenever a post gets published
and decrement it whenever a post
is removed.
We could do this in the methods
that change the post object's
relevant state, but a more
foolproof solution is to update
our counts in response to the
context saving.
We could just register for the
managed object contextWillSave
notification with a function
that goes through all of the
posts that have been inserted,
incrementing the count for each
day that's relevant, and another
loop going through all of the
deleted objects, decrementing
the count for each day.
And that affects the state of
the context before it commits to
the database, so it all winds up
happening in one transaction, so
this scales really well, which
is useful because my teammate
Nick Gillett is here to talk
about how Core Data can help us
as our little app scales beyond
our wildest dreams.
Nick.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Scott.
So, as Scott said, as your
applications grow, they get more
and more complex and at Core
Data it's really important to us
that your applications do grow.
In fact, we want this.
That's the whole reason we exist
is to help you manage this
growth, make it efficient for
you to work with, and help you
give more value to your
customers.
But this happens in ways that
are very specific to your
application.
It's also highly aligned with
your customer experience or the
way that you want them to
experience your application.
Unfortunately, like all complex
systems, as it grows and becomes
more complex, it also tends
toward chaos.
So, today we're going to talk
about ways that Core Data can
help you manage this chaos and
give it some structure.
We'll talk about building
predictable behaviors and
helping you build tunable
containers that you can align
with your experience metrics.
What does that mean?
Well, when we think of metrics,
there's a couple of different
ways that we can think about
them.
The first is in alignment with
our customers.
And usually we define these as
things that they experience,
like having a consistent user
interface or a responsive scroll
view, and also as delight.
But those are really hard for us
to capture as engineers.
So, we translate them into
engineering metrics, things like
peak memory consumption, how
much battery drains during a
given task or how much CPU time
is burned during a given task.
And, finally, how much IO we do
during a given task.
To make this a little more
concrete, we'll use this
application.
Some of you may remember the
history demo application that
was introduced last year at WWDC
and I've modified it for the
purposes of this talk.
There are a few actions here
that a customer can take while
using our application.
The first is they can add a
single post to our database by
hitting the + button.
They can also download any
pending data from the server by
tapping Download.
And, finally, for anything that
hasn't yet been uploaded to a
server, they can tap Post All.
Now, this application has a
fairly small set of interactions
that a customer can take, and
yet, as these happen
concurrently, it tends towards
chaos.
So, we can see that even with
this small set of actions,
things that go on concurrently
could cause a number of
different state changes in the
application and the worst thing
for us is to end up with a user
experience that looks like this.
This notion of partial
completeness doesn't make sense
to our customers.
In fact, it doesn't make sense
to us either.
Core Data is here to help with
that with query generations.
Query generations were
introduced in 2016 in our What's
New in Core Data session.
So, if you're not yet familiar
with them, I highly recommend
that you check out that session
for more information about how
they work.
What you do need to know is that
they require wall journal mode
and only work with SQLite.
The goal of query generations is
to isolate your managed object
contexts from competing work.
This could be rights to the
background or actions that the
user is taking that you're not
yet ready to manifest in a given
context.
Query generations provide a
consistent, durable view of the
database that will return the
same results for fetches
regardless of what other
contexts are writing to the
database at a given time.
The best part is we can adopt
them in one line of code.
This is a typical change for
reloading a table view.
We would just have to insert a
call to NSManagedObjectContext
setQueryGenerationFrom token
with the current query
generation.
And when it comes time to update
them, we can update them as we
normally do by using
NSMangedObjectContextDidSave
notification.
And this allows us to manifest
changes to the application's
data in the UI at the right
time.
But what if the data that we're
writing isn't related to the UI,
such as downloading some
comments that Scott mentioned
earlier?
In this case, we don't want that
data to manifest in the user
interface or cause changes to it
because none of the change will
be visible to the user.
So, we can actually filter out
these updates by using history
tracking.
Persistent history tracking was
new in iOS 11 and macOS 10.13.
We introduced it in our session,
What's New in Core Data, last
year at WWDC, and for more
information about how it works
and what the underlying features
are of it, you can use that
session as a reference.
Persistent history tracking is a
great way to get a persistent
record of each transaction that
connects to the database and
this is useful to us for a
couple of different reasons.
For the purposes of this talk,
though, we'll be considering
NSPersistentHistoryChange, which
gives us a changedObjectID and a
set of updatedProperties.
And
NSPersistentHistoryTransaction
which gives us a set of changes
and an objectIDNotification.
So, let's consider the following
set of changes.
As you can see, these are posts
that are being inserted to our
database and when this happens,
given our table view, we would
want to refresh the UI, which we
can do by using the
objectIDNotification.
These are analogous to
NSManageObjectContextDidSave
notifications and can be merged
in using the same API.
But if we downloaded a list of
comments that we don't want to
manifest in a user update for,
we can filter them.
Using this small amount of code,
we can filter out the changes
from a given transaction to
decide if any of them were
relevant to the post entity and
in that way we won't refresh the
UI and cause an unnecessary blip
or stutter to the user.
But as you can see here, we're
actually only using a small
amount of the post content.
In fact, we're only using two
properties, the image and the
title.
And so we can do better than
just filtering out by entity.
We can actually filter out by
updated properties using the
history changes and in this way
we can create highly-targeted
updates to our user experience
that align with changes that
will be visible to them.
But Core Data can also help you
support new interactions for
your users.
As your data becomes more
complex and grows in scale, some
editing operations can get more
expensive.
For example, consider a simple
photos browser.
Typically, when our applications
grow, we want to -- we want to
introduce new functionality that
makes it easier to perform
repetitive tasks, such as
multiple selection.
And Core Data can support this
by using batch operations.
In fact, in just a couple lines
of code we can mark an entire
set of photos as a favorite or
not.
And in just one line of code, we
can purge or delete a set of
records from the database using
a batch delete operation.
And these operations scale in
ways that aren't possible by
faulting the objects into
memory.
For example, during a delete, a
traditional delete by calling
NSManagedObject.delete will grow
with the size of the records in
the database.
And as you delete objects and
their memory gets faulted into
the context, this gets more and
more expensive the larger your
database gets.
But with batch operations, we
can perform the same mutations
in just a fraction of the
memory.
And this has the curve that we
want as data increases, where
the larger the data set is, the
less memory we use, using up to
about 7% of the memory of a
traditional delete at 10 million
rows.
So, this is a very powerful way
to save resources on your
customer's device.
But one of the traditional
problems with batch operations
is that they were difficult to
work with because they don't
generate save notifications.
That's where history tracking
comes back in.
With persistent history
tracking, we can fetch out the
transactions from the database
that occurred as part of the
batch delete or update and we
can use the objectIDNotification
method to generate a
notification that works like a
save notification.
In this way, the fetched results
controller or any other context
in your application can update
to those notifications
incrementally.
And so those are some ways you
can manage growing data with
Core Data, but how about your
workflow itself?
What can Core Data do for you as
a developer and engineer to make
it easier to build and test your
applications?
The first thing is that we can
help future you today.
As you may know, NSKeyedArchiver
is changing.
We're adopting secure coding
across the entire platform and
the KeyedArchiver API has
changed significantly this year
in support of that.
For Core Data, this means that
value transformers are changing,
so if you have a transformable
property in your managed object
model and you're not sending a
value transformer today, you
used to be getting
NSKeyedUnarchive
FromDataTransformer as your
default value transformer.
In the future, you'll be getting
NSSecureUnarchive
FromDataTransformer and this
implements secure coding under
the covers and you should adopt
it today.
There was a great talk this
morning about exactly this topic
called the Data You Can Trust
and I highly recommend that you
view it to get more information
about secure coding and how to
make your applications more
resilient.
You can specify this in the
model editor with a
transformable property by the
value transformer name field.
And today, we want you to
implement this on your own.
This will become the default in
a future release and in a future
release Xcode will also start
emitting a warning for anyone
that's using the default value
transformer name.
If you're building your models
in code, you can set it by using
the valueTransformerName
property on NSAttribute
description.
This should be transparent for
you if you're not encoding
custom class types.
So, for plist types, this is a
no op.
You simply change the value
transformer name and you'll get
the new secure coding behavior.
However, if you are implementing
custom classes, those classes
need to adopt secure coding and
you can come see us in the labs
for help with that.
But we can help you more.
At Core Data, we've spent time
building in new debugging tools
over the years that can help you
understand what's going on under
the stack.
So, this is a picture of our
preferred default scheme
configuration.
We have a couple of process
arguments that we have that can
help you get more debugging
information about SQLite, but
the big one you should always
run with is com.apple.Core
Data.ConcurrencyDebug.
And this will catch any queue
exceptions in your applications,
so areas that you may be
transferring objects between
main and background queue
contexts or areas that you may
not be obeying a managed
object's actual context.
SQLite also has a number of
interesting environment
variables, so their threading
and file assertions are a great
way to ensure you have
correctness in your application
around their API as well as the
file system.
And auto tracing is a great way
for you to see what's going on
under the covers, an additional
tour on debug logging.
com.apple.Core Data.SQLDebug has
four levels.
The first level is the most
interesting and the least of a
performance hit.
The fourth level is the most
verbose, but does cause
significant performance hit when
you run with it.
When you enable SQL debugging
and our multi-threading
assertions, you'll see a couple
of logs in the console and these
are the indication that the
assertions are enabled and
running correctly.
With our SQL debugging on,
you'll be able to see things
like select statements for our
fetch requests as well as how
long they took.
And, if you're set to level
four, you'll even get explain,
which will show you the query
plan for a given select
statement.
And here we can see that our
table view is selected via table
scan and then using a temporary
B-tree in memory for the order
by, which is on the timestamp.
This is a potential performance
problem and as you're running
your application you can use
messages like this to see where
you may be doing more work than
you need to.
So, how would we fix this?
Well, turns out SQLite 3 can
actually tell us.
If we open a database and hand
it the select query from our SQL
logs, we can enable a mode
called Expert, which will
analyze the query and give us
the ideal solution of optimizing
it by creating a covering index.
And we can do this in the model
editor by adding a fetch index
to our post entity.
Here I've configured it to run
on the timestamp and fetch them
out in descending order because
we're showing the most recent
posts at the top of the table
view.
When we run the application
again, we see the same select
logs.
Except that this time we see
that the select query hits the
covering index during the query.
Explain shows us that the query
will use the covering index for
its order by.
Core Data supports many types of
indexing, including compound
indexes using R-trees.
And these are great for creating
any kind of query or optimizing
a query that uses a bounding box
in its select statement.
This is most commonly done with
locations and we can set this up
by adding another index to our
post entity, which works in the
latitude and longitude property
that I added for the purposes of
this slide.
We change the query type in this
box by selecting R-tree.
And then we can set up our
predicate on the fetch request
to say get all of the posts that
happen inside of continental
China.
This predicate is a little more
advanced because it uses
functions inside the actual
select statement to hit the
index that we created in the
managed object model.
When we run our application
without this predicate and
without this index, we see the
same results that we saw before
where we're hitting only the
timestamp index.
But when we run it with our new
index and predicate, we see that
SQLite is using the index to
generate faster results for both
of the between statements.
Unfortunately, because our
timestamp index doesn't have any
bounding predicates on it,
SQLite can't use it for the
sort.
So, the optimization that we've
chosen here is to use a compound
index to first filter out the
result set to a smaller set of
objects and then we'll do an
in-memory B-tree sort for the
order by.
As you can see, this index
increases the performance of our
fetch by about 25%.
In this case, my performance
test was run over a size of
about 100,000 rows and we saw
around 130 milliseconds of
improvement for just the fetch.
Which brings me to my next topic
of testing with Core Data.
As you may know, we really like
tests.
Tests are awesome.
And, at Core Data, we use them
internally for both correctness
as well as learning.
They're a great way to learn
about the functionality of Core
Data and how our API behaves
under a given set of conditions.
They're also a great way to
verify your assumptions about
how Core Data works and how it's
going to help your customers
have a better experience with
your application.
As you saw in the previous
example, we can verify that our
R-tree index actually does give
us a performance benefit even
though it's using an in-memory
B-tree sort.
They also capture your product
requirements, and this is really
important to us at Core Data
because it helps us communicate
around your expectations.
With tests, we can see what
you're doing in code and how you
expect those lines of code to
behave for your customers.
There are some important things
that you can set up to make this
easy for yourself, such as a
base class that generates a
persistent container.
This base class on the screen
happens to use a file URL of
/dev/null for the persistent
store and this is a great way of
making tests that operate on a
small set of managed objects run
very, very quickly because
they'll run entirely in memory.
When you do this, SQLite
materializes an in-memory store
for you that can be very
efficient, but because it's in
memory, if you have a lot of
data, this will cause a lot of
memory growth in your test
suite.
You should have at least one
test, though, that actually
materializes your store file on
disk.
And this is because if you can't
open your store for your test
suite, it's highly likely that
your customer can't either.
If your persistent container is
in the application delegate, you
can have a test base class that
grabs the container out and
writes directly to that store.
But I must caution you to take
care when you do this, because
that means that you're writing
to the store file that's in use
by the application, so if you
run your test on a personal
device, you'll see the effects
of the unit test when you open
your application the next time.
What if I told you I could
insert 100,000 records in just
seven lines of code?
I'm cheating a little bit.
I was going to leave this as an
exercise to the reader, but this
type of scaffolding is a great
way to help you build a test
suite that evaluates your
invariance around your data.
By building these methods ahead
of time, as your data changes or
you become aware of new use
cases for your application, you
can iterate on these to build
new edge cases, build new
structures for your object
graph, or evaluate the behavior
of certain functionality under
the covers, such as performance.
This is the unit test scaffold
that I used to build a
performance test for the R-tree
query.
In just a handful of lines of
code, we get high confidence on
the performance of our fetch.
And these types of tests are
very informative when you're
trying to evaluate tradeoffs
between different features and
functionality in Core Data.
These three lines of code
generate a new managed object
context and container for us for
our test to use.
Now, this is important primarily
because the setup and teardown
logic in tests can sometimes
affect their performance.
So, you'll need to take care to
analyze whether or not you're
actually testing the teardown
performance or the setup
performance or the actual
runtime performance of the
queries you're evaluating.
And after you've run these
tests, you can file good bugs.
We love bugs, especially from
you guys because we're building
a product to help you build your
applications.
But, bug reports without tests
or without a sample application
are very hard for us to
communicate around because, as I
mentioned earlier, they don't
capture your product
requirements and expectations in
the same way that
well-structured tests do.
In fact, in an application
attached to our radar that has a
test suite or even just a bare
sample application with some UI
that explains your constraints
and concerns to us, we can get
back to you much more rapidly
about what's going on and what
you should do about it.
They also help us verify the
correctness of our fixes later.
So, if you're going to file a
bug, please take some time and
write a test for us.
That's all I have today.
Come see us at lab tomorrow.
We are here from 1:30 on in
Technology Lab 7 and I highly
recommend that you check out
Testing Tips and Tricks tomorrow
in Hall 2 at 3:20.
Thanks.
[ Applause ]