[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Well, good afternoon and
welcome to a tour of
UICollectionView.
My name is Steve Breen-- I'll
set this over here-- and I'm a
frameworks engineer on the UIKit
team.
And I'm joined on stage today
with my colleague, Mohammed
Jisrawi, also on the UIKit team.
So today we're going to do
something a little bit
different.
We're going to build an app from
some specs we receive from our
designer, Breanka [phonetic],
and this is going to leverage
many of the capabilities of
UICollectionView.
Now, while we work through all
the tasks required to build our
app, we're going to touch on a
wide range of topics regarding
UICollectionView including
layouts, updates, and
animations.
So we've got a ton of ground to
cover, so let's jump right in.
All right, so here's the first
spec we got from our designer.
It looks like a friends feed,
imagine that.
A great little columnar layout.
It looks pretty straightforward,
okay.
Okay, this looks great.
So here we've got this really
fancy looking mosaic layout,
which is the contents of our
friends feed.
Okay, so Mohammed, since you're
going to be writing all the code
for us and walking us through
how to use these features, what
are your thoughts on these
designs?
>> Well, you know, I'm seeing
these for the first time, but
they seem like great candidates
for collection view.
I think we can have a lot of fun
with this one, especially.
>> Yeah, this one looks great.
All right.
So before we dive into code, and
Mohammed starts walking us
through this, we need to cover
three core concepts we need to
understand about CollectionView
before we dive right into that
code.
So let's do these now, and we're
going to talk about the layout,
data source, and the delegate.
Okay. So, first of all, let's
chat a little bit about the
layout.
So if you open up the definition
for UICollectionView for the
very first time, and you're
familiar with UITableView, you
notice right away that there's a
lot of familiarity in the API.
You got a delegate and a data
source.
All these things look pretty
familiar, but the layout
concept, that's pretty unique
and distinct to
UICollectionView.
You can really think of it as
UICollectionView's super power.
It allows CollectionView to
abstract away the visual
arrangement from your content
separate from the content
itself.
Layout is all about the where
content is displayed.
Now, each individual item is
specified by the
UICollectionView layout
attributes, for attributes like
such as bound, center, and
frame, things like that.
You can think of it as a set of
properties you can use to define
these items that are displayed.
You can even customize these by
printing your own subclasses of
UICollectionView layout
attributes and include these in
your designs.
Okay. So as the user is
scrolling through the content on
screen, the layout is considered
to be immutable.
Now if you need to change this,
like for example you're going to
change the appearance of the
layout, you would use the
invalidation mechanism, which
Mohammed will walk us through in
a little bit.
Okay. Now, one great thing about
layout being a separate
abstraction is we can transition
from one layout to another
layout and get a great animated
effect when you move between
layouts, and layout A doesn't
need to know anything about
layout B.
They just declare what the
layout is going to be, and the
transitions occur.
Okay. So CollectionViewLayout is
an abstract class, and as such,
it's not meant to be used
directly, but rather subclasses
of CollectionViewLayout are
meant to be used.
Fortunately, we provide one.
UICollectionViewFlowLayout, and
you're probably familiar with
this class if you used
CollectionView before.
Now there's a lot of
customization points on
CollectionViewLayout including
some properties that we'll talk
about in a little bit, but you
can also customize it using a
delegate, and we'll talk about
the CollectionViewDelegate in a
moment, but
CollectionViewFlowLayout will
specify additional things that
extend that
CollectionViewDelegate.
Okay, so what's Flow all about?
Well it's a line-based layout
system, and because of this, it
can cover a wide range of
different designs that you might
receive.
All right, so what does line
base mean?
Well let's go through this.
So the best way to explain what
a line based system is like is
to give an example, so let's do
that.
Okay. So here we see, we've got
a vertical scrolling collection
view, and we're going to mimic
what flow layout does when it
lays out this content.
All right.
So here's our first item, and we
start at the top leading edge,
and we start laying out our
items along a line.
Now look at this line.
This line is orthogonal to the
scroll axis.
We're scrolling vertically, so
the line is horizontal.
Okay, now notice here, we filled
up the available space for items
on that line, so now we're going
to drop to the next line and
continue laying out our content.
And finally, we drop to that
last line, and bingo, we got all
our content.
Now if I dropped some guides on
here to show highlight where
those lines are horizontal,
let's talk about some
definitions that we have for
ways to customize flow.
First up is the notion of line
spacing.
And as you see the arrows here,
the line spacing is going to be
the space between these
horizontal lines.
Similarly, inter-item spacing is
the space between the items
along the layout line.
And we have two properties on
flow layout that let you specify
the minimums for both of these.
Okay. So let's cement our
intuition a little bit and
rotate the whole thing, pi over
2, and let's start over at the
top leading edge.
Now, this one is scrolling
horizontally, right, so we're
going to have a vertical layout
line, and when we get to the
bottom of this area, we filled
out that line, back up to the
top.
Okay. This pattern is pretty
familiar now, right.
There we go.
There's all our content.
Now we have our vertical layout
lines.
So now in this orientation, our
line spacing is this.
And our inter-item spacing is
this.
It's key to remember when you're
working with flow layout.
Okay, so that's layout.
Let's talk a little bit about
the data source, and if you work
with TableView, this should look
very familiar.
It's a very similar pattern.
They share very similar APIs.
Okay, so if the layout is all
about the where content goes,
the data source is the what.
The content itself.
Three core methods to think
about here.
The first one is optional,
number of sections in
CollectionView, and this one if
you don't provide it, we'll just
assume you mean one.
Similarly, we have number of
items in section, and this is
going to tell you the number of
items in each individual
section, because they can all
have different numbers of items.
And then the last one, sell for
item index path is where you
provide the actually content
you're going to display to your
users.
Okay. So that's the data source.
Okay, the final of our three
topics we're going to talk about
before we dive into code with
Mohammed is the Delegate.
Okay. So use of the Delegate is
optional.
Now, CollectionView is a
subclass of UIScrollView.
So we use the same Delegate
that's provided by the
ScrollView superclass, but we
extend it.
So if you need to modify
scrolling behavior, you can do
it also against this same
Delegate and also work with some
of the UICollectionViewDelegate
methods that provide things like
fine-grained control over
highlighting and selection as
the user interacts with your
content.
And we also got an API that
let's you know, hey, something
came on screen.
WillDisplayItem and
DidEndDisplayingItem.
Okay. So those are the three
core concepts we really need to
talk about before we dive into
code to get started with
UICollectionView.
So let's switch over to the dev
box with Mohammed and have him
show us how it works.
Mohammed.
>> All right, so the first of
our two screens that column
layout is a great use case for
using CollectionViewFlowLayout.
We can probably accomplish
everything we need there, and it
would be a great way to get us
started using UICollectionView.
So now while we could accomplish
the entire goal of our design
with a flow layout, I'm actually
going to subclass
CollectionViewFlowLayout because
we're going to do a little bit
of extra customization.
So I'm going to start out by
creating an instance of my
ColumnFlowLayout class, which
I've already prepared.
I'm going to use that instance
to create my CollectionView.
I'm going to take that
CollectionView, and I'm going to
set some view properties, like
auto resizing mask, background
color, and since it's the
ScrollView, I can set some of
it's ScrollView properties as
well.
This is all just to get it to
look and feel the way I want it
to look in our app.
After adding the CollectionView
to my view hierarchy, I'm going
to register my PersonCell class
using its unique identifier with
CollectionView so we can get our
cell design to app.
And then I'm going to set the
view controller as the
CollectionView's data source so
we can give it some information
about how many cells it's going
to display and what sort of data
it's going to display in it's
cells.
And then I'm going to set it as
it's delegate as well, so we can
handle cell selection.
So now that we've gotten set up,
we need to actually conform to
these two protocols.
So let's start out by conforming
to the data source, and we have
two required methods we need to
implement here.
The first of these is number of
items in section where we can
just return the number of people
or the number of items in our
people array to get our data
model objects displayed.
The second method we'll need to
implement is
CellForItemAtIndexPath where
we'll dequeue a cell from the
CollectionView using our unique
identifier, pass a person and
object that we get out of our
people array, to the cell to
actually display our data, and
then return the cell.
And to wrap things up here,
we'll just need to implement one
optional method from the
Delegate protocol, so we can
handle selection.
So I'm just going to add
DidSelectItemAtIndexPath where
we'll just instantiate our
FeedView controller, which is
going to be our second screen if
we don't already have an
instance, and then we're going
to pass it a person object so we
know whose images to display,
and then we'll push it onto our
navigation controller.
Okay. So let's build this and
switch to the simulator to see.
All right.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
Okay. So we have our
CollectionView on screen here,
and we have some cells.
You can see them, though they're
kind of squished.
They're not the right size, so
we're going to have to do some
of that customization we thought
we might need to do.
So let's go back to Xcode, and
let's pop open our column of
class here, our ColumnFlowLayout
class that we've put together,
and let's take a look at what we
need to do here.
So I already have a stub
override of the layouts prepare
method.
Now,
UICollectionViewLayoutsPrepare
method is called whenever the
layout is invalidated, and in
the case of
UICollectionFlowLayout, our
layout is invalidated whenever
the CollectionView's bounds of
size changes.
So if our app rotates on a phone
or if our app is resized on an
iPad.
So this is a great place to do
any customization that takes the
size of the CollectionView into
account.
In our case, we want our cells
to be some function of the
CollectionView's width.
And we can let the
CollectionView know how big we
want our items to be by saying
it's item sized properties.
So I'm going to go ahead and do
that here.
So I'm just going to set my
CollectionView's item size to a
CG size with a width that is the
width of the CollectionView's
bounds, inset by its layout
margins, and then we're going to
give it a height of 70 points
just to match our design.
And since we're already here,
I'm going to do a couple of
other little things here just to
get things to look nice.
I'm going to apply a section
inset with some padding at the
top that matches our inter-item
spacing, and I'm going to set
the layout section inset
reference property to from safe
area so everything is neatly
tucked within the CollectionView
safe area insets.
Okay. So let's go back to the
simulator one more time and see
what our properly constructed
layout looks like.
All right.
That looks great.
That looks just like our spec. I
think our designer is going to
be really happy.
And if we rotate to landscape,
we see that our cell is a great
size, and so we know that our
invalidation code is getting
called again in prepare.
Now while this is okay, you
might be thinking, it's not the
best that we can do here.
It doesn't look as great as it
can.
We might want to do something
more interesting here like
display multiple columns since
we have the space available to
us.
Now flow layout makes it really
easy to do this.
If you remember during Steve's
explanation of how flow layout
performs it's layout earlier,
flow layout will automatically
try to fit in as many items as
it can within a line before it
wraps to the next one.
So using that, we can kind of
figure out that layout-- that we
can get multiple columns if we
change our item size.
So if we head back to Xcode, to
our layout here, and if we just
change how we're calculating our
item size here.
So I'm just going to remove this
fit here, and I'm going to
replace it with something that
does a little bit of extra math.
So I'm just starting out with
the same available width that I
had before.
This is the bounds inset by the
margins, and some arbitrary
definition of what a minimum
column width is, it's 300
points.
And then taking both of those
values and using them to
calculate a maximum number of
column that I think I can fit
within the available space, and
I'm taking that and dividing the
available width by it to
calculate an optimal cell width,
which might be more than our 300
points.
I'm then passing that to the CT
size that I'm using as my item
size.
Okay. So let's go back to our
simulator again and see what our
updated layout looks like.
Okay. So everything is the same
here.
We didn't break it.
It's a good start, and if we go
to portrait, there are our
multiple columns side by side,
just what we want.
What do you think, Steve?
>> That looks great.
We got a great adaptable
columnar base layout.
Not a lot of work.
>> No.
>> What's next in our design?
>> Well, now that we've eased
ourselves in with our friends
list, it's time to start
thinking about that fancy mosaic
layout for [inaudible].
>> Oh, yeah.
That's going to be great.
>> Yeah.
>> Let's switch back over
slides, and let's chat a little
bit about that.
Okay. So let's take a look at
this layout or design here and
see what we can do.
So our first inclination, I
don't know about yours, but mine
would be can I use Flow.
I've got it.
It's ready to go.
Let's try to use it.
So let's zero in on this design
a little bit and see if Flow is
going to make sense for us.
And this particular region where
these three photos are, I'm
going to zoom in on that real
quick.
All right.
So now in this instance we have
a very large photo on the left
and then a vertical stack on the
right.
So in the flow universe, since
it's line based, we're going to
lay out that large left item,
move over to the next item where
it's got room, try to lay out
another item, and then jump to
the next line.
But we're not done.
We've got that vertical stack to
contend with.
So this really is not going to
work for Flow because it turns
out it's not really a line-based
layout, this fancy layout of
ours.
But going through this exercise
is useful, so, you know, let's
start with flow first.
Okay. So in this instance, we're
going to create our own custom
layout.
Oh, no, we're scared, right.
Nope, it's not complicated.
We've got four basic methods to
deal with here, and I'm going to
bring up one additional method
that gets an honorable mention.
Okay. So four methods.
Here we go.
Our first method I want to talk
about is the CollectionView
Content Size.
Now, recall before we mentioned
CollectionView is a subclass of
UIScrollView, and one of the
features of UIScrollView is that
you have a visible region with a
large content area, and you get
that great iOS experience of
moving your content around
inside that, and so
CollectionView needs to know how
to tell the ScrollView, hey,
here's how big my content is.
Okay. So how do we get this
size?
Well, if you imagine a rectangle
that encompassed all the content
that the layout is going to
define for your CollectionView,
we want the size of that.
Okay, so that's CollectionView
Content Size.
Next up we have two methods that
are in the business of providing
layout attributes.
The first one is
LayoutAttributesForElements (in
Rect).
Now this is called periodically
by CollectionView when it needs
to know what is needed to
display on screen as the user
scrolls through your content or
displays for the first time.
So this query is by a geometric
region.
Okay. It's companion API,
LayoutAttributesForItem
AtIndexPath, as you can imagine,
it's just looking for a single
item.
Give me the attributes for that.
Okay, so we're going to see more
when Mohammed walks us through
this, but for these two APIs,
it's important to note that
performance matters.
Okay, so the fourth of our four
core custom layout subclass
items is going to be the Prepare
method.
Now Mohammed has already chatted
about this a little bit.
This is called every time the
layout is invalidated.
So this is a great time to
compute anything, such as your
layout attributes you might want
to cache and also your content
size, which is going to be asked
for pretty soon afterwards.
Okay. So our honorable mention
APIs, so let's talk about this
one.
This is a Should Invalidate
Layout For Bounds Change.
So this is called every time the
bounds in the CollectionView
changes.
Okay, so again, it's a
CollectionView is a UIScrollView
subclass.
So what do we mean by a bounds
change?
Well, when a ScrollView bounds
change, the origin can change
during a scrolling, and also the
size can change when the
application size changes or the
CollectionView size changes.
So this is going to be called
during scrolling.
Hence the oh yeah emoji.
This is called very often.
So making the right decision
here is important.
Okay, so the default
implementation in
UICollectionViewLayout returns
false.
So if you need this to do
something different, here's your
chance.
And as a way of an example,
UICollectionViewLayout will
return false if the origin
changes.
Okay, so if the user is just
scrolling through your content,
we won't invalidate.
Let it by default.
But if the iPad rotates, the
phone rotates, and your app
changes to a different size,
it'll return true.
Now a slight exception to this
is things like floating headers
and footers, right.
We have to recompute those while
you're scrolling your content.
That'll do a custom invalidation
to take care of those things.
Okay. So enough theory.
Let's switch back to our
development machine and have
Mohammed walk us through what
this is going to look like in
code building this fancy custom,
UICollectionViewLayout.
>> All right, let's dive right
in.
So I've already put together
another layout subclass that
we're going to use for this
layout, and you might notice
that it's a subclass of
UICollectionViewLayout directly,
not a subclass of
CollectionViewLayout, and this
is for the reasons that Steve
explained to us earlier are
UICollectionViewLayout doesn't
really meet the needs of our
custom mosaic design.
So the first thing I'm doing
here is I'm setting up a couple
of instance variables that I'm
going to use to hold onto some
key pieces of information that I
can refer to later.
The first of these is a content
bound CG rect, which I'm going
to use to keep a representative
bounds of all the items within
my CollectionView.
And the second is a cached
attributes array, which I'm
going to use to hold onto my
layout attributes so I can refer
to them quickly when performance
matters.
So we're going to start out by
implementing our prepare method
again for this layout.
Prepare is the ideal place to do
the bulk of our layout work
because it's getting called once
per invalidation.
We can set up our layout here
and then avoid having to do any
heavy layout work or any heavy
layout math in the methods that
are called much more frequently.
So we're doing a couple of
things here.
First, we're resetting our
cached attributes and our
content bounds just to clear out
any stale information from
previous invalidations.
Next, we're doing a few things
for every item in our
CollectionView.
The first of these is actually
preparing the attributes, and
now I'm not going to go too
deeply into what that entails
for our specific layout because
this is going to be different
for you.
This is where you are going to
calculate the sizes and
positions and transforms, etc.,
for your cells to match your
design needs.
But there are a couple of key
things that we're going to do
here after we are done with the
attributes.
The first is, we're going to
cache them.
We're going to put them in our
cached attributes array so we
can grab them quickly later on.
And the second is, we're going
to union their frame with our
content bounds rect so that our
content bounds are kept up to
date.
So now that our prepare is up
and running, we need to
implement the remaining methods
in our layout that we need to
get everything working.
So the first of these is
CollectionView Content Size
where if we had done our job
right in Prepare, we can just
return our Content Bounds as
size.
Next is should invalidate layout
for bounds change.
Now since our layout doesn't
have any elements that require
us to invalidate while we're
scrolling, so no floating
headers, no floating footers or
anything like that.
We only really want to
invalidate when our
CollectionView's bounds of size
changes.
So we'll just return true if our
new bounds of size is not equal
to our CollectionView's bounds
of size, our current bounds of
size.
After that, we'll implement
LayoutAttributesForItem
AtIndexPath where, again, since
we've prepared all the
attributes in our Prepare
method, we can just grab the
specific attributes that
correspond to the
RequestAtIndexPath from our
array.
And finally, we're going to
implement
LayoutAttributesForElements
InRect.
Now this method is called
periodically by the
CollectionView with different
query rects, which may be bigger
than our CollectionView.
Our CollectionView is just
asking for a set of attributes
that match a certain region.
It's our job to return an array
that contains all the attributes
that correspond to all the items
that are going to appear within
that rect in our CollectionView.
So we can answer that question
here simply by filtering our
cached attributes array on the
frame of the attributes.
So if our attributes have a
frame that intersects our query
rect, we can return them.
Okay. So let's switch back to
the sim and see what our layout
looks like.
So I'm going to select one of
these feeds, and there you go.
We have our layout.
Our images are nicely loaded in
this fancy mosaic configuration,
and if we rotate to landscape,
you can see that our cells have
resized so we've updated
everything correctly, we've
invalidated, which is great.
So this looks like our spec, but
that scrolling performance isn't
great, is it?
>> No.
>> No, it's pretty bad, huh.
So you might already have an
idea of what's going on here.
Let's switch back to the code
and see what might be happening.
So if we take a look at our
layout attributes or elements in
rect here, remember that this
method gets called frequently
during scrolling.
So this function here, which is
filtering our entire array, you
might imagine can get really
expensive as the number of items
in our CollectionView increases.
So the more photos we have in
our app, the slower our
scrolling performance is going
to be.
So if you find yourself in a
situation like this, it helps to
step back and think about the
nature of your layout and think
about whether you can find any
optimization opportunities.
So our layout kind of demands
that every cell apps next to or
below it's preceding cell.
So this means that our
attributes are already sorted
within our cached attributes
array by their frame's minimum y
value.
So we have a sorted array, so we
can speed up our search by doing
something like a binary search
as opposed to our linear filter
that we're doing now.
So let's remove our slow
implementation here, and let's
replace it with something that
should be much faster.
So I'm going to step through
this bit by bit, don't worry.
So the first thing we're doing
here is we're calling into
binary search function that
we've already prepared, which
takes in a range of indices
within our array and our query
rect.
If it finds a set of attributes
with a frame that sits within
our rect, it'll return the
attributes as index within our
array.
Then starting from that index,
we can build up the set of the
rest of attributes for our query
rect simply by looping up and
down in our array and picking up
attributes until we exit our
query rect, until we find
attributes that are outside our
rect.
And this should be much faster.
You have thousands of items in
your array.
You're not going to loop through
the array thousands of items,
thousands of times.
Okay, so let's go back to the
sim again and let's see what our
faster scrolling algorithm looks
like.
Let's pop this open and give it
a flick.
It's way faster.
What do you think, Steve?
>> Much better.
Okay, great.
So we've got these two great
layouts.
What's next?
>> So we have our two screens.
That just leaves our update
animations for our friends list
here.
>> Oh, great.
All right.
Well let's switch back over to
slides, and let's walk through
that totally cool update
animation I think our designer
called it.
All right, so we've got a video
here.
Let's run through this and see
what this totally cool update
animation looks like.
Okay. So we have some elements
here.
We see that last item is getting
refreshed.
I guess somebody posted a
picture, and then we got another
item there, it looks like, yeah,
that third item smears is not
going to be here.
Okay. So we've got three basic
operations happening, right.
We've got a reload, a move, and
a delete.
Why don't we switch back over to
the dev machine, and Mohammed,
why don't you show us how this
works?
>> Sure thing.
Okay, so we're doing multiple
animated updates at the same
time.
So you might be aware of a great
tool that UICollectionView and
UITableView provide us, and it's
the Perform Batch Updates API,
which basically allows us to
pass the collection view a set
of updates that can be performed
at the same time with animation.
So I'm going to add a call to
CollectionView
PerformBatchUpdates, and note
that I'm doing both my data
source updates and my
CollectionView updates in the
closure here.
This is really the best way that
I have of coordinating my
updates and keeping things
neatly in sync and avoiding
inconsistencies.
So, first I'm just updating my
last item in my data source.
I'm removing the second to last
item, picking up the last item,
moving it to the top, and then
I'm asking the CollectionView to
perform the animations that I
want.
Okay. Let's go back to the sim
again and see what our update
looks like.
So I have wired our update code
through this update button at
the top right corner, and uh oh.
>> What's going on?
>> Oh, that's embarrassing.
What's going on here.
>> You know, I've been writing
iOS for a long time.
I've seen this movie before.
>> Yeah, it sucks when it
happens on stage though.
You know, we're running out of
time here, so why don't we just
call reload data, and we can
come back and do the animations
for V2.
>> Really?
[ Applause ]
You know, we could do that, but
then we'd lose that totally cool
update animation, and our users
expect these lively interfaces,
right?
>> Yeah, yeah, you're right.
You know what?
They deserve better.
>> Ah, I like the way you think.
All right, let's switch back
over to slides real quick, and
let's see if we can save our
totally cool update animation.
You've seen this before.
All right.
So first of all, let's dig into
this debug exception and see
what it's trying to tell us.
All right.
So it's saying here we're
attempting to perform a delete
and a move from the same index
path, 0-3.
So if I remember right, that was
the fourth item.
We did a reload and a move on
that.
We didn't delete it, we deleted
the third item, 0-2, right.
>> I don't remember deleting
them.
>> So, yeah, what's up with
that?
All right, but before we do
this, let's go back and take a
peek at the PerformBatchUpdates
API and talk about some
high-level principles.
All right.
So as Mohammed mentioned earlier
when he introduced this API, the
purpose of this API is that we
can commit multiple updates at
the same time and have anything
animate together and get that
great experience.
And as he also mentioned, it's
super important to perform your
data source updates alongside
your CollectionView updates
inside that CollectionView
update closure.
Now, what I'm saying for
CollectionView also applies for
TableView.
So if you got TableViews in your
apps, all this information is
going the same direction.
Okay. So let's make some
observations here.
The CollectionView updates, when
you do inserts, moves, and
deletes, the ordering of those
do not matter in your update's
closure.
Put them anywhere you want.
Now however your data source
updates, when you're changing
the structure offer your data
source, which is backing that
data source, or does matter.
Okay, so this is best served by
showing an example, so I'm going
to take a example of two arrays
that have three elements in
them, and we're going to
strengthen our intuition on this
and show a delete and an insert,
but we're going to do the first
run through with the delete
first and the second delete
second.
We're going to reverse the
order, just to kind of
strengthen our intuition.
I do this all the time, draw
pictures, right.
All right.
So we deleted the first item,
and now we're going to insert at
index one.
Okay, on the second example, we
reverse the order and do the
insert first and then the
delete.
So our intuition holds, indeed
we get a different result.
This is probably not a good
thing, right.
So let's contrast this with the
CollectionView updates.
Now here I have two sets of
CollectionView updates on a
submit via batch updates, and
I've left out the data source
updates, just to keep the slide
tidy.
But I've got an insert and a
delete on the first one, and the
second one has a delete and a
insert, and the order is
different.
This will give you the exact
same result.
We're all engineers.
We want to know why, why is
that?
Well, let's talk about that.
How does this happen?
Why is the ordering not
important for the update sent to
the CollectionView, and of
course it is for your data
source.
Okay. So let's walk through
these operation by operation.
So the first one to delete, this
is process in descending index
path order.
Now let's talk about the index
paths.
So first of all, if you can
think about what's happening on
a PerformBatchUpdate, before the
batch update starts, your data
source is in a before state.
Now once everything is done in
the batch updates, you'll be an
after state.
Okay. So for delete, the index
paths always referred to the
before stage.
So that's delete.
So insert is processed in
ascending index path order
paths.
So the index paths refer to in
the insert are always referring
to the final state or the after
updates stage.
Okay, a move is this mixture of
the two, right.
You have a from and a to index
path, and the from is in the
before state, right, and the to
is in the after state.
Reload. Now reload is a little
bit of a super command if you
will, right.
It actually decomposes down into
a delete and an insert.
And the index path specified in
a reload is speaking about the
before state.
Okay. So this insight now that
we understand what reload is
really doing can kind of tell us
a little bit of what's going on
with our error in our app
because of the delete on the
reload on the last one is
conflicting internally with the
notion of moving that item,
okay.
So we can address this in a
minute when we get back to code.
Okay, so I'm not going to go
through these, but you can
reason about these later.
Just put it up here as reference
that these are the things
that'll cause CollectionView to
go bonkers.
Don't do it.
And how can we take all this
knowledge and simplify it,
distill it in such a way that we
can always apply our data source
updates from a given set of
CollectionView or TableView
updates and make sure everything
is in sync.
All right.
So these four basic rules.
So first of all you want to
decompose those moves and to
delete and inserts.
Easy. And then combine all your
deletes and inserts into two
separate lists, process the
deletes first in descending
order on the index paths, and
then finally apply those inserts
in the ascending index path
order.
Do this, and you're good to go.
What about reload data?
And I know Mohammed said we
could just hit that and we're
done, and everybody laughed so
I'm pretty sure I yelled and
that's the case, but the thing
about reloaded data is you don't
get those great animations, and
this is really a sledge hammer
approach.
So, and we really prefer the
apps to be lively and animated
and feel great for our
customers.
So, and this is used in special
cases.
Okay, Mohammed, let's switch
back over real quick and see if
we can get this fixed in code
and save that totally cool
update animation.
>> All right, time to redeem
myself.
>> Yes.
>> So let's use the guidelines
that Steve just shared with us
to fix our update animation.
So let's remove our existing
implementation here.
And if you recall, our update
consisted of a reload, a delete
and a move, and our reload and
the move were at the same index
path.
They started at the same one.
So that's really where our
conflict is.
So we'll need to start out by
separating those two.
So let's take our reload out
into its own call to perform
batch updates, and here I'm just
updating my data source, again,
same as before, and calling
reload items on the
CollectionView.
I'm just performing it in a UI
view performed without animation
closure because if you look
closely at our spec, it's
actually nonanimated, that
initial reload.
Okay. So next up, we have to
take care of our remaining
updates, that delete and the
move.
And let's reason about them for
a second.
We have a delete at index two,
and then we're moving the item
at index three to index zero.
So if we break down our move
using the guidelines that we
just learned about, that becomes
a delete at index 2, a delete at
index 3, and an insertion of the
item from index 3 at index 0.
So now we have two sets of
operations.
We have deletions and
insertions.
We can process them accordingly.
First, we'll perform our
deletions in descending order.
So we'll do our deletion at
index 3 first, and will hold
onto the person from there so we
can insert them later on.
And then we'll delete the item
at index 2.
Then we'll need to process our
insertions in ascending order.
We just have one, so we can just
go ahead and insert it.
And finally, we'll ask the
CollectionView to perform the
animations that we want.
Now, note, I'm still calling
move here.
I didn't break it down into it's
component actions because we
still want the collection view
to play the right animations,
and if we've done the right
thing with our data source, the
CollectionView will do the right
think in terms of animations.
All right.
Let's go back to the simulator
and see what our update looks
like when it works.
All right.
Here goes nothing.
>> Wow.
>> Great!
[ Applause ]
I'm going to reload and take a
slow-mo victory lap just to--
there we go.
That looks exactly like our
spec, doesn't it.
>> That's great, awesome.
All right.
Well let's wrap it up.
We covered a ton of content.
Can you switch it back to
slides?
And I'd like to issue a bit of a
call to action.
So if you've been nervous or
anxiety building that custom
layout, take the stuff we just
applied today and go back and
dive in and create those custom
layouts and build really great
CollectionView solutions.
And if you got a lot of reload
data sprinkled all throughout
your apps and you're losing out
on these gray animations.
They'll inspect those things and
see maybe why you didn't
understand or something wasn't
quite jived about why it was
happening and fix those spots.
Okay, so more information, you
can see the link on the slide
here.
And we also have a
CollectionView lab tomorrow
morning at 9.
If you have any questions or
comments about your
CollectionViews, please swing on
by and chat.
Mohammed and I will both be
there.
And thanks very much for coming
out, and I hope you enjoy the
rest of your conference.
[ Applause ]