[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Hello and welcome.
I'm James Vest, and I'm here to
teach you today how learning
VoiceOver can help make your app
more usable for everyone.
And here's how I'm going to do
that.
I'll tell you what VoiceOver is
and why you should support
VoiceOver and also how to use
VoiceOver if you have never done
it before and also how VoiceOver
benefits your app.
So what is VoiceOver?
I get some common answers like
well VoiceOver is a screen
reader.
That's true, but VoiceOver
doesn't just read the screen, or
VoiceOver is for the visually
impaired.
It's true, but it's not just for
the visually impaired.
So if VoiceOver is not just for
the visually impaired, and it's
not just a screen reader, what
is it?
VoiceOver is an alternative way
of using you app, and it uses
gestures, a keyboard, or a
Braille display to give a
variety of users equal access to
your experience, and it's built
in to every Apple device.
Now think about that last point.
It's kind of awesome.
I mean that means that every
person who uses your app has
access to VoiceOver.
But not every VoiceOver user has
access to every app.
And that's why you're here.
That's why you are such an
important role in this story
because you must update your app
for us to take advantage of
VoiceOver.
Now when I say updating your app
or supporting VoiceOver, I'm not
talking about creating or
maintaining a alternative or
simplified layout or tailored to
a subsection of users.
It's about allowing all users to
access the experience that you
created.
So why support VoiceOver?
Well, supporting VoiceOver makes
your app more inclusive.
VoiceOver users are more likely
to choose you app over other
apps that don't support
VoiceOver.
And this is a great community,
so they are more likely to in
turn recommend your app to other
VoiceOver users.
But sadly, for many developers,
those reasons are not enough,
and I get it.
There's only so much time.
There's only so many resources,
and you want to make the best
decisions to create the best
experience for the most of your
users.
So that's why it's so important
today that you realize that
learning VoiceOver can help make
your app more usable for
everyone, not just VoiceOver
users, for all users.
So I bet you're asking yourself,
right?
Can a screen reader do that?
Yeah, absolutely.
I mean look at some of the
latest apps coming out, those
larger texts.
Those cleaner layouts.
They're not just benefiting low
vision users or users with
cognitive needs.
They benefit us all, and the
same is true with VoiceOver.
So here's how VoiceOver could
help you with your app.
Well, testing with VoiceOver can
give you a new perspective.
Now it's easy to take for
granted your app because it's
your app.
You know exactly what it does,
what it's supposed to do, how
it's supposed to do it.
But we take a lot of those
things for granted, and when I
say testing with VoiceOver gives
you a new perspective, it's
getting a chance to experience
your app in a new way.
That's because VoiceOver goes
beyond the way your app location
looks.
I mean an app might look good,
but that doesn't make it usable.
So side-scrolling states, hover
states, they can all give the
allusion of straightforward,
clean, easy-to-use interface.
But testing with VoiceOver goes
beyond that, and so it allows
you to discover new challenges
and insights, and finally, I
believe VoiceOver gets really at
the heart of what we do.
As iOS developers, we pride
ourselves on creating
easy-to-use, easy-to-understand
apps.
Well those values are especially
apparent when using VoiceOver.
So my question to you today is
your app so easy to use you
could use it with your eyes
closed?
And that's not a question just
for testers.
That's a question for designers,
for developers.
Anyone responsible for creating
the best experience possible for
our users.
And the only way to answer that
question is to start testing
with VoiceOver, and that's what
I'm here for today.
I'm going to give you some ways
of being able to turn on
VoiceOver and start using it.
Figure out where you're at,
where you could improve, and
then I'll give you some things
else to watch out for that might
not only improve your VoiceOver
experience but possibly the
experience that all users get.
And here's where we're going to
start.
We need to know how to use
VoiceOver.
Now in the next slide, I'm going
to show you how to enable
VoiceOver in settings.
What I don't cover in the next
slide is how to navigate with
VoiceOver, activate with
VoiceOver, heck even turn
VoiceOver off using VoiceOver.
So if you're following along out
there on your iOS device, you
may want to wait.
But I promise you, everyone in
this room is going to have a
chance to turn on VoiceOver
before my presentation is done.
So how do we turn on VoiceOver?
Well, it starts in settings, and
we go to general.
In general, I can open up the
accessibility menu.
It's a great list of all the
features that we include on our
iOS devices so that we can have
equal access to our users.
And VoiceOver is right at the
top of that list, but I
discourage you from opening it
there.
I discourage you from going in
and enabling VoiceOver because,
again, we might not know enough
about VoiceOver to turn it back
off.
So when I teach people how to
use VoiceOver for the first
time, I encourage you to go to
the bottom of this list to the
accessibility shortcut.
It's here inside of a list of
options.
If I just check VoiceOver, that
means I can easily turn
VoiceOver on when I want to test
it and also turn VoiceOver back
off when I'm not ready to test
it or my phone goes to sleep or
I get a phone.
So just checking VoiceOver in
this box I can turn it on by
triple clicking the home button.
Click, click, click.
And if you have a brand new
device that doesn't have a home
button, well then you'd use the
side button, click, click,
click.
When VoiceOver is enabled, we
see the VoiceOver cursor.
It's a visual reinforcement of
what VoiceOver is trying to
describe, and that's the first
objective when testing
VoiceOver, is to make sure that
these descriptions are accurate
and complete.
And the only way you're going to
test every single element inside
of your app is to navigate with
VoiceOver, and here's how to do
it.
Navigating can be as easy as
just reaching out and touching
the screen.
Dragging your finger across the
screen, VoiceOver will just read
whatever is under your finger.
But that's actually not really
how a lot of people review their
apps.
I start at the top.
I work through everything in
read order to the very end.
VoiceOver users accomplish using
flick navigation, and that's
taking my finger and putting it
on the screen and then flicking
to the right, flicking to the
right.
Now if I went slow enough, it
would just read under my finger,
so you have to really give it a
quick flick until your finger
flies off the screen.
And conversely, I could go back
to the left, and I could go to
the previous item or the next
item.
And it's important that you also
want to keep in mind the
starting position of your
VoiceOver cursor, because if
will start in the middle of your
page.
Well, that would assume as a
user that there isn't anything
before it, and so you might be
leaving your users without all
the story.
So, we have two ways to
navigate, and we have no way to
control how a user navigates.
So you want to test both these
ways to make sure they work as
expected in your app.
Now while you're navigating your
app, you may need to pause that
output.
So, if you ever need to have so
stop speaking, just take two
fingers and tap the screen.
And if you make that peace sign
again and tap the screen,
VoiceOver will just pick up
right where you left off.
Now, if you accidentally enabled
VoiceOver earlier in settings
when I said not to, don't worry.
You're halfway to turning it
back off.
But there's one piece that's
still missing, and that's
activating.
You know, we take for granted
that if I see a button on the
screen I just tap it and it
opens, but with VoiceOver when I
tap an element, it describes it
to me, and it gives me the
choice to decide.
Do I want to open this element
or do I want to move to another?
So, when I reach out and I hear
a description of what I want to
open, then I follow that up with
a single finger, double tap,
tap, tap.
And the selected item will open.
So to illustrate how navigating
and activating with VoiceOver,
well, I'd like to welcome to my
stage my colleague, Ryan Dour,
to the stage.
[ Applause ]
Thanks James.
So you guys have all heard about
how VoiceOver is used, but in
order to really see this thing
in action, we got to turn it on.
So I'm going to go ahead here,
and on this phone, I have an
iPhone X, I'm going to triple
click the side button.
There we go.
>> Flash Thursday, June 7.
>> Excellent.
>> Heading not found.
[ Background Noise ]
Facetime.
>> There we go, okay.
Fantastic.
So we've started off here on the
home screen, and the first thing
I'd like to show you is that
we've got a VoiceOver cursor on
the Facetime icon.
It's a black cursor.
That's going to follow me
everywhere I go while I'm using
VoiceOver, and there's really
several different ways that we
can move the VoiceOver cursor
around.
The first is that I can reach
out and touch just about
anything on the screen, and the
VoiceOver cursor is going to
follow along, and it's also
going to speak that item.
So if I just reach out and
touch--
>> Reminders.
One task due today.
>> Excellent.
I can also just drag my finger
around the screen to move that
VoiceOver cursor, and it's going
to follow along, so I'll try
that.
>> No mail [inaudible] maps,
weather.
>> We also have flick
navigation.
If I flick left.
>> Maps.
>> I move back an item.
If I flick right.
>> Weather.
>> I move right an item.
And this reads left to right,
top to bottom.
>> Notes.
>> See how it wrapped to the
next line there?
So from here I can actually go
ahead and if I want flick my way
to an app and launch it.
>> Remind, news, stocks, TV,
stocks, weather.
>> Or I can find it this way,
and I can double tap.
>> Cupertino.
Cupertino.
No weather info-- San Jose,
[inaudible].
>> There we go, that's the right
location.
>> Seventy-three degrees.
>> Except I don't want to hear
the entire thing, so I paused it
with a two-finger tap, again,
using that peace sign, just
performed that two-finger tap,
and it paused the speech.
If I do it again.
>> Thursday, clear.
High 76.
>> This feature zooms.
>> Low 52.
>> And, again, I can pause it.
That way I can send it back to
James.
Thanks James.
[ Applause ]
Thanks Ryan.
Now I just want to stop here and
point out that using these steps
alone you can actually start
testing your app with VoiceOver.
You can turn it on.
You can navigate your app, and
you can see how well it works
but just with VoiceOver on.
So now the other side of testing
VoiceOver is about getting
familiar with the expected
result, and that means getting
outside your app and starting to
experience areas that already
have a good VoiceOver
experience.
So here's how we do that.
Now if I needed to go home,
well, I could press the home
button.
But on a new device, like iPhone
X, we need to go home by taking
our finger from the very bottom
edge of your device and starting
to slide it up.
The first vibration I feel will
go home, and if I keep dragging
up, the second vibration I feel
will open the app switcher.
I can also repeat this gesture
from the very top edge of my
display and open things like the
Navigation Center and the
Control Center.
And when you're not testing your
app, you can three-finger flick.
It's basically the same as a
one-finger flick to allow me to
scroll or move between my home
screens.
But in this case, I'm using
three fingers.
So using three fingers back and
forth, up and down, will allow
me to get to those areas.
So whether or not you're
exploring other apps or going
into Control Center or
Notification Center, these areas
are full of complex UI that's
waiting to teach you the
expected results when we focus
the VoiceOver cursor on them.
Now another gesture you may need
is called the two-finger scrub,
and that's where I take that
same two-finger tap from before,
but instead of letting go, I
scrub back and forth very
quickly, almost like in a fast Z
pattern, and that will allow me
to get out of a window without
having to navigate back to
cancel buttons or back buttons.
Or in the case of UI, where they
don't even have close buttons,
to quickly scrub back and forth
and dismiss the window.
So while we're busy navigating
and exploring and learning about
this great expected behavior, we
also kind of need to know what
we're listening for.
So when you open a newspaper,
you receive a lot more visual
information than just words on a
page.
Here's that same newspaper.
If we fail to infer all of that
additional information, like
headings or images, so we need
to explore and listen to
headings and images, tabs and
buttons, and make sure we're
honoring that experience.
Now to demonstrate these initial
gestures, here's Ryan Dour.
Cool. Thanks James.
So we're still here in our
weather app, and I would
actually like to go back to the
home screen.
This is an iPhone X, so in order
to do that, I need to use our
new home gesture, and that is
going to be again, touching my
finger at the bottom in the home
[inaudible], and then sliding my
finger up until I feel that
first vibration to go home.
VoiceOver will also tell me, if
I haven't let go of the screen
yet, that this is exactly what
I'm going to do if I let go.
Let's go ahead and check that
out.
>> Lift for home.
>> And I'm going to do that.
>> Weather.
>> Okay, so we're back on the
home screen.
Many of us have many pages of
apps, so in order to switch
between those with VoiceOver, we
use a three-finger swipe.
Actually it's a three-finger
flick, but, yeah, it's funny, we
actually interchange that a lot
here at Apple.
We say three-finger swipe or
three-finger flick, but they're
interchangeable.
I'm going to go ahead and
three-finger swipe left.
>> Page three of three.
>> There we go.
>> Utilities folder.
Four apps.
>> I'm going to go ahead and
double tap on this utilities
folder so that we can explore
the inside.
>> Utilities, heading.
>> Let's explore.
I'm going to go ahead and flick
right.
>> Voice memo, compass, measure,
calculate, calculator.
Hear that bonk?
I've reached the end.
If I flick left--
>> Measure, compass, voice,
utilities, heading.
>> Well, there's a lot of apps
and a great heading here.
However, there's no apparent way
to close this folder.
Without voiceover on, you would
just tap outside of the folder's
area in order to be able to
close it, but with VoiceOver, we
use the two-finger scrub.
Now, you can use it just as
James described it, like a Z
gesture, but I'm a DJ, and I
kind of think of it more like a
scrub, like you're scratching a
record.
So let's go ahead and take those
two fingers and--
>> Utilities folder.
>> Boom that folder's closed.
>> Four apps.
>> Cool. Thanks, James.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Ryan.
So when faced with a lot of
information, a sided user may
choose not to go through every
single object in read order to
the very end.
No, instead we choose to pay
attention to maybe a select
group of elements, like these
headings on this newspaper.
VoiceOver's users can also
navigate this way using the
Rotor.
And the Rotor is a VoiceOver
feature that dynamically
presents options that the user
can adjust or navigate by.
A VoiceOver user can set the
Rotor by making two fingers on
the screen and turning it around
a center point, almost like
you're turning an invisible knob
on screen.
And as we adjust the rotor,
it'll speak all the options that
are supported within the view
that we're focused in.
So in this case, we could turn
that rotor and switch it to
headings, and once it's set to
headings, I'd be able to go to
the next heading by taking a
single finger and flicking down.
Or, conversely, I could flick up
with one finger, and that would
go to the previous heading.
And here's why the Rotor matters
to you as a developer.
Because a Rotor only works if we
as developers remember to
include headings in our apps.
So when your app doesn't support
one of these rotor options, well
then we're kind of taking a tool
out of that user's toolbox to
have a great experience in their
app.
So I invite you to go back into
settings, general,
accessibility.
Inside of the VoiceOver menu is
a lot of great settings that
VoiceOver users customize, and
one of them is the Rotor
settings.
So review what we can support
and make sure that we are
honoring those in our apps.
So here's Ryan Dour to
demonstrate how the Rotor works.
>> Cook, thanks James.
So again we're back here on the
home screen.
We're on our second page of
apps, and I'm going to open the
App Store.
So I'm going to flick once,
right.
>> App Store.
>> There it is.
Image going to double tap again
to activate.
>> Apps, heading.
>> So I'm on the apps tab of the
App Store.
There are an awful lot of
fantastic apps here.
However, I don't want to have to
explore each and every one of
them to get to the various
categories.
So I can actually touch one of
them.
>> WWDC18, celebrating the Apple
design award winners.
>> And I'm pausing this speech
again with that two-finger tap.
Now, to do the Rotor gesture,
all I have to do is take two
fingers and turn either
clockwise or counterclockwise.
>> Characters, words, headings.
>> There's the one I want.
As soon as I let go, I am on
that rotor.
Now, if I flick down--
>> New apps we love, best new
updates, stream yourself selfie
with light skin tone, heading.
>> Now, if I flick up--
>> Best new updates, new apps we
love, heading.
>> I move back up that list, and
of course if I want, I can go
ahead and dive into a category,
but before I do, I want to tell
you guys about one more gesture,
one that is, at least for me,
extremely important.
So James started this whole
thing off with asking you a very
important question, which is, is
your app easy enough to use with
your eyes closed?
And I'm going to guess that for
a lot of you, you might say,
geez, I have no idea.
I'm going to find out, but for
me that is my experience.
I don't get to see your app.
I cants see your app.
So for me I really need that
question to actually be the most
serious one you ask yourself.
Now, keeping your eyes closed is
a challenge.
It's very difficult to keep it
up, and also you might want to
be looking at your computer,
taking notes, and doing other
things.
So in order to do this, the most
effective way I know possible, I
encourage you to use the screen
curtain.
The screen curtain blacks out
your entire screen and puts you
in my shoes.
You have a chance to use your
app the way I use it entirely,
and there's no cheating here.
That is the only interface
you're going to get.
Let's turn it on.
So three-finger triple tap.
Again, three fingers, three
times.
>> Screen curtain on.
>> There we go.
At this point, we're on the same
plane, and if I, again, flick
down--
>> Best new updates, heading.
>> And I flick right, let's
start exploring.
>> See all, button.
>> Of course now I know that's a
button, and I can activate that
button.
So I'm going to go ahead and do
a double tap.
>> See apps, back button.
>> I'm in the apps areas, I'm
going to start flicking through
to the right, let's explore.
>> Best new update, [inaudible]
get, but, world of dinosaurs,
$1.99, in-app purchases, button.
>> That's a lot of information
that you're getting that's
usually very visual.
>> Procreate pocket,
entertainment, button.
>> And of course, if I want to
go back, that two-finger scrub--
>> Apps, heading.
>> And we're back.
>> Screen curtain off.
>> So that is screen curtain,
and I can't encourage you enough
to use it because when you make
your app experience something
that you can take VoiceOver
through, both enjoy and make
sure that it's completely
amazing, then so can I.
I can enjoy your app in full if
you take this through as the
final step before you call it
done.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks Ryan.
So now it's time to talk about
how VoiceOver can benefit your
app.
Because you're ready.
Today you can leave this area
and go and test your app, and I
would encourage you to test it
like you normally would just
with VoiceOver on.
But I want you to pay attention
to these additional insights
that could make your app better
for all users.
So one, if something doesn't
sound right, it may not read
right either.
It's like when a writer reads
something aloud that they wrote.
It's just another way to check
that your message is coming
through, and it doesn't just
look right, it actually sounds
right as well.
Two, if navigating with
VoiceOver takes effort, it
probably takes a lot of effort
visually as well.
So maybe it's time to add
section headings or break up
your content to allow users of
your app to benefit from a
cleaner, more straightforward
visual and spoken experience.
Three, if your app sounds out of
order, your content may be too.
VoiceOver navigates your app in
read order.
So if you're navigating your app
wondering where's the login?
Well, likely is a lot of your
audience asking the same
question.
There it is.
So these issues can't hide from
VoiceOver and neither should
you.
So let's turn it on.
Are you guys ready?
Come on, do you remember how?
All right, let's review then,
all right.
So inside of settings, we're
going to go to general.
If you have an iOS device, feel
free to take it out.
Inside of general is
accessibility.
Accessibility, we're going to
ignore the very top of the
screen, and we're going to go
all the way to the bottom.
If we can enable today the
accessibility shortcut, not only
are we going to have a chance to
turn on VoiceOver, potentially
for the very first time, but
it's also a quick way to go back
and turn it on again, back to
show your colleagues.
Turn it on again when you go
back to your office or maybe
when you're trying to make a
case for trying to give more
resource time to focus on
VoiceOver.
So, if we've gone into settings,
general, accessibility, and gone
into the accessibility shortcut
and checked VoiceOver, now we'll
be able to turn on VoiceOver
quickly with the home button.
Click, click, click.
Three clicks of the home button
or on iPhone X, three clicks of
the side button, click, click,
click.
Ready to activate VoiceOver.
Let's do that now.
Yeah. And how does it feel,
right?
For a lot of us, it's brand new,
and so we could have mixed
feelings or uncertain feelings.
This could be challenging, but
I've never done anything
worthwhile in my life that
wasn't challenging.
All right.
So our next challenge will be
turn VoiceOver back off.
[laughter] Let's see if we can
do that now.
So with the home button, give it
a triple click, click, click,
click.
Or with the side button on an
iPhone X, click, click, click.
So, yes, I'm going to call you
out individually now, and, but
no, in review.
VoiceOver is an alternative way
of using your app.
And you can navigate and
activate elements based on just
how they're labeled.
And you can explore other apps
to learn expected behavior.
And then rediscover your app by
hearing it to help identify
other issues.
So here's some steps I want you
to do as soon as you leave
today.
Just like Ryan suggested, I want
you to close your eyes and test
your app.
So really experience this.
Start identify issues that
prevent users from getting the
most out of your app.
And then open your eyes and
confirm that experience, because
if you've ever wondered what a
VoiceOver experience should be,
just remember, the goal is just
to match the experience everyone
else gets.
So compare the two and improve
both based on what you learn.
And then make VoiceOver a part
of your regular testing.
Talk to your team.
Make VoiceOver a part of your
practice, not just so that you
can continue to improve your
experience with every release,
but also to avoid losing the
lessons that we gained here
today.
And lastly, go out there and
teach others what you know
because that's why I'm here
today, because teaching is the
best way I know how to master
any subject.
Now helping you become a master,
I also want to share these
resources.
Apple.com/accessibility is a
great resource to get to know
VoiceOver and other
accessibility features and also
have access to resources such as
the guides, not only to
reinforce what we learned today
but build on it.
And the same is true for
developer.apple.com/
accessibility/ios.
And for more information, feel
free to rewatch this video.
Anytime we do something for the
first time, it's hard to master,
so watch it again.
Practice with me until it feels
comfortable and you're ready to
share.
And also, take advantage of
these other opportunities.
For instance, tomorrow starting
at 7:00 in the morning until
7:30, you can sign up for
accessibility design by
appointment lab, and that will
allow you to talk to an engineer
like me, who can also help you
go through your app, identify
issues, and then you can take
those issues to the
accessibility lab and technology
lab nine tomorrow at 11 a.m. so
you can meet with other
engineers and say, how do I
start fixing some of these
issues?
How do I start improving that
experience?
And then, also go to deliver an
exceptional accessibility
experience.
That's the book and presentation
to the presentation that you
watch today.
We showed you how to start using
VoiceOvers to identify issues,
and tomorrow we'll take the
stage again, and we'll start
showing you how to resolve some
of those issues.
Thank you everyone.
[ Applause ]