[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Good afternoon, welcome to
Optimizing App Assets, my name
is Will, engineer on the Cocoa
Frameworks group and today make
my coworker Patrick and I are
going to go through some of the
best practices for optimizing
assets in your application.
In this day and age, many apps
and games offer great user
experience by incorporating high
fidelity artwork and other type
of assets in their application.
And by doing so they're able to
attract a large number of
audience, as well as they're
engaging.
We want this to be true for all
of your apps as well and that is
why we're here today to showcase
some of the best practices with
Asset Catalog and also more
importantly, on how you can
better deploy the assets in your
application to your users and
how to translate that to the
overall user experience.
And throughout this talk we're
going to touch on a variety of
different aspects through the
traditional, design, develop,
and deployment workflow.
But first I'd like to spend a
little bit of time to talk about
a topic and that is image
compression.
Image compression is at the
heart of the Asset Catalog
editor and is the last step in
the Asset Catalog compilation
pipeline.
And is greatly related to some
of the other optimizations that
happen throughout the pipeline.
By default Asset Catalog offers
a variety of different types of
compression types and is also by
default able to select the most
optimal compression type for
getting any given image or
texture asset.
While that may be sufficient for
most projects, it's still a good
idea to understand what are some
of the options offered and more
importantly, to understand what
are their trade-offs, as well as
what are the implications on
your project.
Now before I dive into the
specifics of any image
compression, I'd like to talk a
little bit about another
optimization in Asset Catalog
that has a huge implication on
all of the compression that we
do, and it's called automatic
image packing.
Traditionally, before the
inception of Asset Catalog, one
way to deploy assets in your
application is just to dump a
bunch of image files in the
application [inaudible] of your
project.
It's important to be aware that
there are many drawbacks, as
well as trade-offs when doing
this approach.
There are two sides of downsize
that you have to be aware of.
The first comes from the
additional disk storage that
comes with doing so.
Traditional image container
formats uses extra space to
store metadata, as well as other
attributes associated with the
underlying image.
Now if your application has a
huge number of assets, and if
they have similar metadata, the
same information gets duplicated
over and over on disk for no
real benefit.
Additionally, if most of your
assets are fairly small then you
do not get the full benefit of
most image compression.
The other type of drawback comes
mainly from the organizational
overhead that you have to pay
for.
It is very hard work with a
large cache of loose image files
and it's also much harder to
interact with them from the
NSImage and UIImage family of
APIs.
Last but not least, you also
have to deal with the
inconsistency in image format,
as well as other image
attributes as well.
For example, in your artwork
collection you can have a mix of
images but some of them support
transparency while the others do
not.
The same applies to other
attributes, such as color space
and color gamut.
As the catalog is able to
address all these problems by
identifying images that share a
similar color spectrum profile
and group them together to
generate larger image atlases.
This way you do not have to
store the same metadata over and
over for all of your image
artwork.
And you also benefit better from
all the underlying image
compression.
Now let's take a look at a
real-world example.
Here on the left-hand side of
the screen there are a dozen
image artwork.
These may look familiar to you
and that is because they are
taken directly from one of our
platforms.
Now these image artwork are all
fairly small, but still the
overall size add up to over 50
kilobytes.
This automatic image packing
Asset Catalog is able to
identify that all of these image
artwork share very similar color
spectrum and if so it'll group
them together to generate one
single larger image atlas.
This way the overall disk size
gets reduced to only 20% of the
original size.
That is an 80% size reduction
saving and that is huge.
It's also important to be aware
of these optimization scales
very well.
The larger the amount of our
asset in your application, the
more benefit you're going to get
out of this optimization.
So that's automatic image
packing.
Now let's talk a little bit
about lossy compression.
Lossy compression is all about
trading minor losses in vision
fidelity for the large savings
that you gain from the
underlying compression.
So it's really important to
understand what are the
scenarios in your application
where lossy compression is most
applicable to.
Typically we recommend you use
lossy compression for image
artwork that have fairly short
on-screen duration.
For example, that will be
artwork that is shown on the
splash screen of your
application or through
animations and effects.
Now it wouldn't be exciting for
me to just stand here to talk
about lossy compression without
introducing a new lossy
compression in the Asset
Catalog.
So I'm very happy to announce
that this year we're extending
support of high-efficiency image
file format in Asset Catalog.
If you followed our
announcements from last year,
you know that we introduced
high-efficiency file image
format on all of our platforms,
as well as in the Asset Catalog
editor.
This year we're taking it one
step further, we're making
high-efficiency image file
format with default lossy
compression in Asset Catalog.
[ Applause ]
Thank you.
Now let's have a quick recap of
some of the benefits that we get
from high-efficiency image file
format.
The most important thing to know
that it's able to offer much
better compression ratio than
compared to some of the existing
lossy compression that we
already offer.
One that you may be already
familiar with is JPEG.
There are many benefits that
come with this high-efficiency
image file format, such as
support for transparency out of
the box.
And more importantly, it's
important to be aware that Asset
Catalog is able to automatically
convert image files from other
formats to high-efficiency image
file formats, which means that
as long as your image assets are
tagged to this lossy compression
there are no extra required, no
extra action required on your
end.
This all happens automatically
in the Asset Catalog compilation
pipeline.
For more in-depth information on
high-efficiency image file
format, I suggest you refer to
our session from last year.
Now let's shift our focus to
lossless compression.
Lossless compression is the
default compression type and
it's used for the majority of
application assets.
Therefore, it is really
important to understand how you
can get the most benefit out of
lossy compression.
Typically image artwork can be
categorized into two groups
based on their color spectrum
profile, and they each benefit
differently from any lossless
compression.
Let's take a look at that.
The first category of images are
commonly referred as simple
artwork.
And they're referred this way
because they have a fairly
narrow color spectrum and a
fairly small number of discrete
color values and that is because
of the simplistic designs.
And they're best represented as
many application icons.
On the other hand, the other
type of image artwork are
referred as complex artwork.
Again, both these types of image
assets benefit differently from
lossless compression.
And generally speaking, any
lossless compression will do
really great to either one of
them because they're optimized
for it.
We realize that both of these
are really important in many
projects.
And we also want to have all of
your assets to be deployed
through the best lossless
compression possible.
So I'm very happy to announce
this year we're introducing a
new lossless compression in
Asset Catalog and it's called
Apple Deep Pixel Image
Compression.
[ Applause ]
Thank you again.
Apple Deep Pixel Image
Compression is a flexible
compression that is adapted to
the image color spectrum.
What that means is that it's
able to select the most optimal
compression algorithm based on
the color spectrum
characteristics of any image
artwork.
This year not only we're
extending this new compression
to all of you guys, we're also
enabling it on all of our
platforms, as well as first
party apps.
And by doing so we're able to
observe on average 20% size
reduction across all of our
built projects, which is a
pretty big deal.
[ Applause ]
Now let's look at some numbers.
Here's a chart that shows you
the overall size of all the
Asset Catalogs from some of our
select platforms.
And it is immediately obvious
that we're able to see about up
to 20% size reductions across
all of our platforms.
When it comes to lossless
compression, compression ratio
is only half the story.
Because of the fact that
lossless compression is used for
the majority of your application
artwork, decode time is just
important as well.
Apple Deep Pixel Image
Compression is also able to
offer up to 20% improvement in
decode time.
So that was lossless
compression.
Now I'd like to shift gears to
touch on two separate but
strongly connected subjects that
have a huge implication on all
the optimizations and
compressions that I just talked
about, and their deployment and
App Thinning.
Here's a quick recap of what App
Thinning is.
App thinning is a process that
takes place in the App Store
that generates all variants of
your project targeting all the
device models, as well as
versions of your deployment
target.
When we take advantage of App
Thinning is to have the
deployment target of your
application to a version that is
lower than the latest version of
the platform you're targeting.
This way you'll be able to reach
more audience.
App thinning is able to take
care of generating all the
variants of your project and
deploy the most optimal one
across all of your user base.
This year if you build your
project with Xcode 10 and the
iOS 12 family of SDKs, your
project is automatically going
to benefit from all the
optimizations and new
compressions that I just talked
about.
However, if you back deploy your
application to an earlier
version the new optimizations
are not preserved.
And that is because App Thinning
has to generate variants that
are compatible to the earlier
versions of the targeted
platform.
This isn't ideal and more
importantly, we really want all
of your assets to be deployed in
the most optimal manner.
So I'm happy to announce this
year we're introducing a new
version of App Thinning, called
OS Variant Thinning.
With OS Variant Thinning your
application can still target
those that are on earlier
versions of your target
platform, say in this case from
iOS 9 all the way to iOS 11.
And for those that are running
on the latest version of iOS, OS
Variant Thinning is able to
generate a special variant of
your project that has all the
latest optimizations and
compression types.
This way everybody is able to
get the most effective version
of your project and everybody's
happy.
[ Applause ]
So that was App Thinning and
backward deployment.
Now I'd like to walk you through
an example of how you can
exercise the same App Thinning
expert workflow locally within
Xcode.
It is a fairly simple process,
all you have to do is go to
Xcode archive button.
This will simply instruct Xcode
to generate all variants of your
project.
Once that is done simply click
on the Organizer button and that
will bring up a window that
shows all the variants generated
for your project.
And here's a window for the
garage band project that we took
to perform this exercise.
The first thing that Xcode is
going to ask is to select a type
of distribution method that you
can distribute all the variants
that it just generated.
For the purpose of this
exercise, simply select Ad Hoc
Distribution.
And on the next window, in the
App Thinning field, simply
select all compatible device
variants.
This will instruct Xcode to
export all the variants that are
targeting all the supported
device types.
Once this is done Xcode is able
to synthesize a report that
summarizes all the variants that
it just generated.
And there are a few key data
points that you can extract from
the report to help you better
understand the deployment of
your project and again help to
answer a few key questions such
as how many variants are
generated from my project, what
do their sizes look like, and
are there any rooms left for the
optimization and fine-tuning for
any particular variant.
And it turns out that actually
half the numbers generated for
the garage project that it just
exported and let's take a look
at that.
So here on this chart it's going
to show you the sizes of all the
variants generated for a select
set of device models.
And these are the sizes
generated for the iOS 11 and
earlier versions of the
variants.
Now because garage band is a
fairly large project, with tens
of thousands of image artwork
the sizes of the generated
variants range from 90 to over
100 megabytes.
And here are the numbers for the
iOS 12 variants.
And again from this graph it is
immediately obvious that we're
getting about from 10 to 20%
saving sizes in size reductions.
Now if this number looks
familiar to you by now all of
these optimizations are from all
the optimizations and
compressions that I just talked
about.
So that is image compression.
Now I'd like to hand it to my
colleague Patrick to talk about
design and production of your
application asset.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you Will.
So that's great, so you just
heard about some amazing ways
that you can get your assets
improved just by using Asset
Catalogs in Xcode.
I'm going to talk a little bit
more about a few other things
that you can do with just a
little bit of effort in Asset
Catalogs to really optimize your
application's assets.
So and I'd like to begin with
design and production because
this is really where it all
begins.
So assets as you know they come
from many tools, many different
workflows, many different
sources but they have one thing
in common, they ultimately all
came from humans at some point.
And it really pays to be
organized in terms of
understanding that process of
how those assets come into your
software workflow and to pay
attention to some of those
details that can really pay big
dividends in your application
efficacy.
So the topic I'd like to talk
about first is color management,
often overlooked but still quite
essential.
So on disk an image asset is
just a bunch of boring bytes
right, it doesn't really mean
anything until you apply color
to it.
How does it get the color, how
does the system even know what
each of the numbers on those
bytes means?
Well the answer is it comes from
the color profile, that is what
actually gives each one of those
color [inaudible] a value and an
absolute colorimetric value, it
tells the system how it should
look.
As such, I want to emphasize
that it's really important to
maintain those color profiles in
your assets as source artifacts.
These are vital pieces of
metadata that keep the designer
intent intact on how that asset
was delivered.
And resist the temptation to
strip those profiles out because
you think they're just extra
metadata that you know take up a
bunch of payload.
These are source artifacts that
are checking into your project,
let the tools worry about
optimization for deployment.
So why is any of this color
stuff important?
Well the answer is our devices
have a broad range of displays
with different characteristics
and something needs to make sure
that the actual colors in your
assets match appropriately and
look appropriate and get
reproduced appropriately on all
those different displays, that's
the job of color management.
This is a computational process,
it can be done either on a CPU
or at times on a GPU, but it is
some work.
Now Asset Catalogs come into
play here because what they will
do is at build time in the
compilation process they will
perform this color matching for
you.
And this is really great because
it means that computation is not
happening on device when it
really doesn't have to.
And your assets are ready to go
on device and ready to be loaded
and ready to be displayed
without any further ado.
And as a bonus this extra
processing we do to do this
color management at build time
eliminates the profile payload
that you might've intended to
strip earlier and replaces it
with an ultra-efficient way of
annotating exactly what color
space we now have and the pixels
on disk, so that's color
management.
A related topic I'd like to talk
about here is working space.
Now by working space I'm really
referring to the environment in
which these assets actually got
originated in the first place,
this is the designer or maybe as
an engineer are working on some
artwork yourself, you're working
in a design tool, you're
creating content.
It's important in these contexts
to use consistent color settings
for all the design files that
you have for your project.
This actually is a good practice
and it actually has positive
technical benefits because it
ensures a consistency between
how you organize everything
across your application.
There are two specific formats
that are most talked about and
most recommended for creating
working design files.
sRGB 8 bits is by far the most
common, a very popular choice
and it has broadest
applicability across all of our
devices and your content types
really.
However, if you're working on a
really killer take it up to the
next notch vibrant design like
this wonderful flower icon here
for example you may want to take
advantage of the wide color
characteristics, capabilities of
some of our devices and use the
wide color, use a generated wide
color asset.
For this we recommend you use
Display P3 as your working
profile and 16 bits per channel
to make sure you don't lose
anything in executing that
design.
Now Xcode and the platforms,
runtime platforms have a wide
range of processing and
management options to handle
this wide color asset.
I'm not going to go into too
much depth here, but I encourage
you to refer to and look at the
Working with Wide Color session
that I did two years ago where I
went into some depth on these
topics and it gives you some
more background for this.
Also, new since last year
there's a great treatment of
working with P3 assets up on the
iOS Design Resources section of
the developer.apple.com website.
Okay now let's get into some
actual software art here.
Okay so you may have, your UI
typically has to adapt to a lot
of different presentations and
layouts, this can commonly call
for artwork that actually needs
to stretch and grow to adapt to
those layout changes.
How do you accomplish this with
artwork?
Well the most common approach is
to identify a stretchable
portion of the image and the
unstretchable portions of the
image.
Why is there a difference?
Well considering, this is a
crude example here on the slide,
but imagine that we had a
beautiful shape to the overall
asset and like round corners
that you wanted to preserve at
all possible sizes like a frame.
You want to make sure that you
don't stretch those pieces, the
blue pieces in this slide but
you can stretch the yellow
pieces.
So traditionally the way this is
done is with the modern design
tools is to slice all these
items up, identify all these
regions, and distribute them as
individual assets.
Then the programmer would
reassemble these in the final
design size using a draw 3 or a
nine-part API for example.
Now this works fine and has been
a tried and true practice for
many years, but it does have a
downside.
Reassembling those images at a
final size is a pretty CPU
intensive task and it can be a
bit complex and inefficient and
it's not really a good fit for
modern GPU UI pipeline like core
animation.
What's a better approach?
A better approach is to take a
single image and just provide
the stretching metadata for it
that identifies what the
stretchable portion is.
And that really enables the most
optimal smooth GPU animation of
that resizable image.
And I'm happy to tell you that
Asset Catalogs makes this really
easy to do and it's called the
Show Slicing editor.
It's really easy to work with,
you just click the Start Slicing
button and then you start
manipulating the dividing lines
here which actually lets you
identify the stretchable
portions of the image and the
unstretchable portions of the
image.
In this example the left and
right end caps and then that
middle slice that's orange is
the one that's the stretchable
piece.
Now you may notice there's a big
piece of this image that has got
this white shading over it, what
is that all about?
Well that's actually a really
interesting thing, that part of
the asset is not actually going
to be needed anymore because we
can represent any possible size
with the three remaining pieces.
Okay why is this important?
Well the nice thing is now that
Xcode knows this at build time
we can actually just take the
pieces we need and leave the
rest behind.
So that large section we don't
have to include that in the
bytes on disk that we actually
ship in your app, that's great.
And it also means that it has a
secondary benefit and this is a
more subtle one, but I really
like this.
It means that you can tell your
designer to feel totally
comfortable delivering assets at
sort of their natural size and
don't have to worry about
pre-optimizing them to be the
smallest possible things so that
it's efficiently deployed right.
That shouldn't be the concern of
the designer it's actually much
more meaningful over the
long-term to put something in
the source code that's easy to
look at and obvious what it is
and let the tools worry about
these deployment details.
So in addition to the graphical
inspector and graphical way of
identifying the stretchable
portion there is of course also
the Show Slicing Inspector which
where you can have fine control
over these edge insets and also
control the behavior of the
centerpiece when it stretches or
tiles.
All this of course adds up to
keeping the stretching metadata
close to the artwork which will
then yield enormous benefits the
next time, which inevitably
happens, the designer comes up
with a new update to your
design.
Now you can update everything in
one place and don't have to
remember the five or six places
in code where you might have a
hang code of the edge insets
previously, now it's all tied
together in one place.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
Okay next up I'd like to talk
about vector assets.
So because our displays on all
of our products have a variety
of different resolutions you're
probably very used to delivering
1x, 2x, 3x depending on what
platform you're targeting,
distinct assets.
And that's fine and works really
well, but it's kind of a mess to
have to deliver three or two or
three assets every time for a
single design for no other
reason than just resolution.
What if you can actually get
away with this with just one
asset?
Well you can and we've been
supporting vector assets in
Asset Catalogs for a number of
years now in the PDF format.
And with Xcode Asset Catalogs
you can actually supply a PDF
and Xcode will generate and
rasterize that PDF into all of
the applicable scale factors
that your app is currently
targeting depending on platform.
And that's really great because
it means you don't have to worry
about paying any cost at runtime
on device to render an
arbitrary, potentially
arbitrarily complex PDF vector
asset.
So it gives you some peace of
mind about using vectors.
Now you may have a scenario
where actually you want to
present your assets in some
circumstances at a different
size or scale than the most
common natural size that the
asset was designed for.
Well new since last year in iOS
11 and Xcode 9 we now allow you
to preserve the vector data so
that when that image is put into
an image view that is larger
than the natural size of that
asset it'll go ahead and find
that original PDF vector data,
which by the way we've linked it
out and cleaned of any
extraneous metadata and profiles
as well so it's nice and tight
and it's slim as possible.
And we'll go ahead and
re-rasterize that at runtime but
only if you're going beyond the
natural size, otherwise we'll
use that optimized prerendered
bitmap.
So this is great because it
means your app might be able to
more flexibly respond to dynamic
type and automatically your
images will look more crisply
when you resize your UIImage
view.
That's vector assets.
Okay next, I'd like to talk a
bit about designing for 2x, 2x
commonly known as retina is the
most popular and common display
density that your apps are
probably being experienced on.
And it's great right, it was a
huge step forward, however,
there are still cases where you
can have designs where a stroke
or an edge might land on a
fractional pixel boundary and
result in a fuzzy edge.
It's still not high-resolution
enough that you won't notice a
difference between a sharp edge
and a fuzzy edge.
And this can still be a
challenge in designing assets at
times.
Well what are some techniques
that can be used to address
this?
One common design technique is
to turn on point boundary
snapping in your vector design
tool, set up a grid at one-point
intervals and turn on snapping
so that when you adjust your
shape or your control points
that you know that they can
snap, when they snap to a
boundary you know that that's
going to be a pixel boundary and
that's great.
But there's still some cases
that you might have with a
design where some of the edges
are still perhaps landing
somewhere in between one and two
and you're not sure, but you'd
really like to know, especially
on a retina 2x device what's
going to happen there and can I
optimize further for the actual
display density.
Well what you can do is you can
actually use a 2x grid, make
your asset twice as nominally
big in your vector design tool
and make that grid now be a
one-pixel grid where every two
points, every two units is going
to be one point for retina.
And then adjust your assets and
use the point snapping to adjust
your strokes and edges to fit
there.
Okay that's great, now what do
you do with this thing once
you've got it, it's too big
right, it doesn't work?
Yes it does, all you have to do
is just drop it into the 2x slot
in the Asset Catalog scales bins
and that will automatically
enable Xcode to process that
artwork, realize it's actually a
2x piece of artwork, it's
slightly too big, one point is
not equal to two pixels of
retina, but rather the other way
around.
We'll do all the math, we'll
render all the right rasterized
bitmaps for all the other scale
factors and handle that for you.
Freeing the designer to use that
2x grid which can be rather
helpful.
Of course, if the automatic
scaling that we do is
insufficient or still presents
problems in some areas, you can
have ultimate control of your
results as always by dropping in
hinted bitmaps into the
appropriate scale factor bins
and we'll go ahead and use that
and prefer that over the
generated PDF rasterizations.
Okay so that's a bit about
design and production ends of
things, now let's talk about
cataloging and sort of the
organizational aspects once
you're in Xcode.
So those of you who have played
around a little bit with Xcode
Asset Catalogs it can be a bit
overwhelming to see how many
things there are in front of you
there and what you're supposed
to use and how many options
there are.
Well I'm here to tell you, you
really should only use what
makes sense, what makes sense
for your project and what makes
sense for the content that
you're working with.
There's a lot of options here
and we've made a very powerful
engine and organizational scheme
here that has lots of
capabilities, but you really
need to fit it to the need that
you have and use the simple,
start with simple first and then
go from there.
So I'd like to talk about two
organizational techniques that
can help in this area.
The first is bundles, now why
would I be talking about bundles
in an asset talk that seems
rather incongruous?
Well I'm really trying to
address large projects.
So if you have a large project
where there are perhaps multiple
frameworks involved, maybe you
even work with multiple teams.
Dealing with assets can
sometimes be a pain if you have
to pour them all into the main
app bundle and have to manage
them all there and make sure
names don't conflict and
appropriately sourced to the
relevant parts of your
application.
One of the ways you can solve
this problem is by building
those assets into multiple
bundles because Xcode will
always generate a unique Asset
Catalog deployment artifact per
bundle or target.
So for example, consider
creating an artwork only bundle
as an example and this can be
for a good reuse strategy for
example to have a single
consolidated component that
contains all your artwork, that
has a consistent namespace, that
can provide images to the rest
-- to the other components of
your application.
How do you retrieve these?
It's simple, you just use the
image constructors like UIImage
named in bundle compatible with
trait collection that gives the
bundle argument.
On the macOS side of course
there's the NS bundle category
image for resource.
And keep in mind, that each of
these bundles provide a unique
namespace, so within them the
names have to be unique.
But across bundles you feel free
to use any naming convention you
like.
So speaking of namespaces,
there's another feature I'd like
to call attention to and another
challenge with large projects.
Now in this case the problem I'm
addressing is large collections
where they might have some
structure in them right.
So let's imagine you have an app
that deals with 50 different
rooms, each one of those rooms
has a table and a chair in it
and there's assets for each of
those.
In your code you'd really like
to refer to them as table and
chair, that seems like the most
natural thing but unfortunately
there's 50 of them what are you
going to do.
One alternative is to just
generate a naming convention of
some form and figure out how to
demux that in your code, that's
not ideal.
One solution that Asset Catalogs
can offer is to use the provide
namespace option.
By checking this box after
organizing your artwork into a
folder, we will automatically
prepend the folder name into
each image's record in the Asset
Catalog, which you then use to
retrieve it.
This can be a nice way to
organize large structure
collections of assets.
Okay so we talked about
cataloging, now let's talk about
some exciting stuff around
deployment which is really where
the exciting stuff starts to
kick in.
So Will talked about App
Thinning, I'd like to give some
overall perspective on what we
try to do with Asset Catalogs in
App Thinning.
So overall what you're trying to
do is you're providing all the
content variants for your
application, you're adapting
your content to the needs of the
various devices your app runs
on.
The most common technique for
doing this is you know split
across product family iPad or
iPhone, tv or watch or different
resolutions, 3x and 2x.
You provide all those content
variants to effectively adapt
your content and then App
Thinning is responsible for
making sure that we just select
the right subset of that content
that's appropriate for the
device that your customer is
running the application on.
Well I'd like to talk about a
different way you can approach
the same sort of content
adaptation and that is
performance classes.
It's a different way of looking
at the exact same problem.
What if the entire product mix
the way your application saw
that continuum was instead
segmented by performance
capability, not by other
characteristics?
Well this is what you can do
with Asset Catalogs.
There's such a broad range of
hardware capabilities between
the supported devices that we
have, even if you go back a few
iOS, I mean all the way from say
an iPhone 5 up to the latest
iPhone 10, that's a huge range
of performance capability.
Wouldn't it be nice to take
advantage of that and avoid the
needing to constrain your app to
the least capable device that
your application needs to
support?
That's the goal here to be able
to have your cake and eat it too
and to do that you can solve it
with adaptive resources.
I'm going to tell you how now.
So there are two main ways that
we divide the performance
continuum.
The first is memory classes and
this is perhaps the most
important one.
We have four memory tiers, 1 GB
through 4 GB and that
corresponds to the installed
memory on the various devices
and again this is across our
entire product mix, it doesn't
matter what it is, it's in one
of these bins.
The second access of collection
is graphics classes.
Now these actually correspond to
two things.
One, they correspond to Metal
feature family sets, which if
you're a Metal programmer you
may be familiar with, this is
the GPU family concept.
But they actually correspond
also exactly with a particular
processor revision in your
device.
So Metal 1 corresponds to Apple
A7 all the way through Metal 4
which is the Apple A11
processor.
And we allow you to catalog and
route assets to each of these
particular graphics classes.
That can be pretty powerful by
itself either one of those, but
where it gets really interesting
is when you can combine these
two traits together to form a
full capability matrix that you
can really finally calibrate how
you want to adapt your assets to
this hardware landscape.
Now how does this work?
I'd like to explain this to you
by walking through a simple
example and this is really key
to understand how we do things,
it helps you understand how you
might be able to use it.
So in this example, we've
provided three specialized
assets, one any any which is
just the backstop for the lower
capability devices.
And then we provide two
optimized assets, one for 3 GB
devices with Metal 3 or better
and one for 2 GB devices with
Metal 4.
So let's imagine that I'm
selecting the asset from the
context or the viewpoint of an
iPhone 8 Plus.
So I'm 4 GB, Metal 4, that's
where I'm starting and I'm
searching, I'm finding nothing
in 4 GB memory tier.
So next, I'm going to go drop
down a memory tier and look for
anything that can be found in 3
GB memory tier.
I do that and I find this asset
here and I'm going to select
that.
Now what's important here is
that I have selected this asset
at 3 gigabyte Metal 3 even
though there is an asset that
actually matches exactly to my
GPU class.
But because we prefer and scan
through things in memory
priority order before we do
graphics classes, we're going to
select this first.
This is really important because
we have decided that memory is
really the most important way
that you can characterize the
overall performance of a device,
so we're going to prefer that as
we go through the selection
matrix.
Okay that's how it works, how do
you think about using it.
Memory really represents the
overall headroom of your device
and is really the best aggregate
indicator of capability.
So it's a really good choice to
use with larger or richer
assets, more detailed stuff,
things that are bigger on disk,
things that are going to take a
little more memory when they're
expanded in in memory for
rendering.
Just a richer user experience is
usually associated with higher
memory.
Now higher graphics is a little
more subtle since that tracks
the raw processing capability,
both CPU and GPU, of the device
so it's better for more complex
assets.
Maybe you use a shader that
takes advantage of certain
features that are only available
on certain GPUs or not or you
put an asset that requires a
little more processing than
others.
I'd like to give two simple
examples as food for thought on
how this could work.
And the way I'm going to give
the example is by talking about
NSDataAsset.
NSDataAsset is a very simple
piece of Asset Catalog but it
can be very powerful.
All it is is a way to provide a
flexible container that you can
put in your Asset Catalog with
content variants around
arbitrary files.
This doesn't have to be an
image, it doesn't have to be a
very specific format, this can
be anything.
But you can use this with Asset
Catalogs in App Thinning to
route arbitrary data to these
different performance classes.
So that's an example, consider a
cut scene video in a game.
So you might provide, have a
nice video that you put in sort
of the mid-tier of the
performance spectrum and then
you might have a really awesome
high resolution, maybe it's even
HDR who knows video that you put
in the really capable quadrants
of that capability spectrum.
And then on the lower end you
put a still image or a very
simple image sequence that's not
going to take any time or
excessive resources on those
devices and still give those
customers running those older
devices a nice and responsive
user experience.
So that's one example.
Another more intriguing example
is plist, well why I put a plist
in an Asset Catalog, it seems
like there's much better ways to
deploy plists than Asset
Catalogs.
Well when you use it in
conjunction with NSDataAsset for
example you could consider using
a plist to tune your application
with different configuration
parameters that scale according
to the performance class that
you cataloged that plist in, in
your NSDataAsset.
So for example if you have an
app that renders a crowd for
example you could set the size
of the crowd based on the
capability of the underlying
hardware and your code would
automatically be self-tuned
based on what device it's
actually running on at the
moment.
So that's an interesting idea
about how to use performance
classes.
Next, I'd like to talk about
Sprite atlases.
So Sprite atlases were
introduced a few years ago in
support of SpriteKit
applications in SpriteKit games.
Now, but I'm not going to talk
about them in the context of
SpriteKit based games, I'm going
to talk about them in the
context of regular applications.
Now they have some attributes
that are very similar to what
Will talked about with automatic
image packing, you're taking all
of the related images in that
Sprite atlas and packing them
into a single unit, they get
loaded at once, and then all the
images that you reference that
are contained within that atlas
are just lightweight references
to locations within that atlas.
So that's great.
But the key thing is that you
don't really need to use
SpriteKit to access these, you
can just use this as a grouping
mechanism because the one
difference that Sprite atlases
have over automatic image
packing is you get to control
the grouping and you to assign a
name to it.
So you can deal with it, you can
have a little bit of control and
sort of organize things that
way.
But you can still access the
images contained within using
the standard UIImage and NSImage
APIs, and the names within that.
In addition, there is an
intriguing way that you can use
SpriteKit framework even though
you're not building a SpriteKit
application by taking advantage
of the SKTextureAtlas preload
texture atlas named API if you
have a case where you have a
large number of images that have
to be loaded fairly quickly and
have to be used right away.
So what this API will do is
it'll preload or load from disk,
decode, get ready and warmed up
in memory asynchronously with a
callback completion handler for
a set of named atlases.
So this is great, but I will
caution you, do not use this API
indiscriminately because it does
exactly what it says it's going
to do and that means it's going
to potentially consume a large
amount of I/O and memory to load
all those images.
So please be sure that you're
about to use them right away and
that it's the right choice,
otherwise a jetsam awaits you.
So another powerful thing about
Sprite atlases is that any image
within the Sprite atlas has all
of the regular features of any
other normal image set within
code Asset Catalogs, including
all the cataloging features, all
the compression settings, and
all the App Thinning features.
We will take care to
automatically split and collate
all of the images that you
provide appropriately, split
them by pixel formats, by
different device traits, and
different compression types.
And make sure everything gets
baked appropriately and then
thinned appropriately so that
the data gets routed to the
right device in the right way.
So those are some interesting
details about deployment, we're
in the homestretch here.
So I'd like to remind you of the
important things about
optimizing app assets here.
First and foremost, I think
Xcode Asset Catalogs are really
the best choice for managing the
image resources in your
application.
This year you get 10 to 20% less
space on disk just by using our
new compression algorithms.
No matter what deployment target
you have, your iOS 12 customers
will get those benefits thanks
to the improvements in App
Thinning, which now optimizes
for the latest OS going forward.
And we have a bunch of
cataloging features that you can
use to adapt the resources of
your app to the devices your
customers use.
For more information please look
at this link and hope you all
had a nice day.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]