[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Good morning.
My name is Keith Rauenbuehler,
and I'm from the HomeKit
Engineering team.
Now, today we're here to talk
about HomeKit with a focus on
three specific areas.
First, we'll give an overview of
HomeKit and the Home app.
Then, we'll outline what it
takes to build a HomeKit
accessory.
And finally, we'll look at some
HomeKit APIs and how to use
them.
So let's jump right in.
So the best way to really
understand the power of HomeKit
is to take a look at the Home
app.
It's a single app interface to
all of your HomeKit accessories.
Now, there are a ton of
capabilities packed into the
Home app, and we'll use this
session today to talk about some
of the most important ones.
And the Home app currently
exists on iPad, iPhone, and
Apple Watch.
And the Home app has three basic
tabs.
There's the Home tab, which is
where you'll find your favorite
HomeKit accessories and your
scenes.
There's the Rooms tab, which is
a great, it's a great tab to dig
into a specific room and view
all of the accessories
associated with that room.
And the Automations tab, which
is where you'll be able to set
up and manage your smart home
automations.
Now, controlling accessory in
the Home app is simple.
To toggle the state of it, just
tap on the tile.
So if you want to turn on a
light, all you need to do is tap
on the tile for it.
Now, if you want finer-grain
control, you can use 3D touch to
bring up our quick controls.
And so if we go back to that
same light and we want to adjust
the overall brightness -- say
it's a dimmer switch -- we can
3D press on the tile, and we can
bring up our quick controls.
Now, we've also added scenes to
the Home app, and scenes are a
great way to allow you control--
allow you to control multiple
accessories with a single tap.
A scene is our simple interface
for tying multiple accessories
together, whether it's kicking
off your morning routine or
setting up your living room to
the perfect movie-watching
environment.
Now, throughout the day, your
home is always changing.
People may come and go.
Lights might turn on or off.
Blinds can open and close.
And scenes allow you to
basically specify a desired
state for all these accessories.
So you can have a good night
scene that turns off the lights,
closes the blinds, locks the
door, and sets the thermostat.
Then, when you're ready for bed,
you simply tap on the tile for
"Good Night," and HomeKit
prepares your house for the
evening.
Now, in iOS, we also have quick
access to Home shortcuts via
Control Center.
This is a great way to view and
control your favorite HomeKit
accessories, and it even
provides access to your scenes.
Now, this is very-- really
convenient, but another great
way to control HomeKit
accessories is through Siri.
You can tell Siri good morning,
and that will kick off your good
morning scene.
You can also use Siri to control
individual HomeKit accessories.
So you can use Siri to turn on
your light in the kitchen or to
make sure your door is locked.
You could even use Siri to bring
up your favorite HomeKit camera
stream.
Now, up until now, HomeKit has
only existed on iOS, watchOS,
and tvOS.
But this year, we're excited to
announce that we're bringing the
Home app to the Mac.
[ Applause ]
Now, we're really excited about
this, as it's a great way to
control your home using your
computer, all without taking
your phone out of your pocket.
It's also a great way to monitor
your home because you'll get
your HomeKit notifications right
on your Mac.
And we've even built HomeKit
Siri integration on the Mac as
well, so you can use all of your
favorite Siri triggers to
control your accessories
directly from your computer.
Now, one of Apple's newest
products, the HomePod, is my
favorite way to control my
HomeKit accessories.
Not only is it a great music
speaker, it's also a great way
to control your HomeKit
accessories because anyone in
your house can use it using just
their voice.
This hands-free Siri interface
allows you to quickly and easily
control these accessories in
your home.
It's really simple to get
started, and I love using my
HomePod to control the lights in
my house.
It's especially convenient when
I walk into the kitchen with my
arms full of stuff, and I can
use my voice to tell Siri to
turn on the lights.
Now, we've also gotten a lot of
feedback from users saying they
love using their HomePod to
trigger their good night scene.
They simply tell Siri good night
as they head off to bed.
Now, the HomePod also plays a
much more powerful role in the
home, as it helps control remote
access and automations.
Now, remote access is one of my
favorite features in HomeKit, as
it allows you to monitor your
home when you're not there.
So you can have peace of mind,
and you can check to make sure
your garage door is closed or
make sure your thermostat's
turned off when you're not at
home.
And you can do this all while
being remote.
Now, this feature requires a
home hub, but HomePod, Apple TV,
and iPad have the home hub
functionality built right in.
So with remote access, you can
keep tabs on your home while
you're away.
And you may also want to share
some of this support from this
control with other users.
With HomeKit, you have control
over granting remote access to
some users and then specifying
other users to only control
accessories while locally.
So let's talk a little bit about
how remote access works.
So when you're in your home,
your Apple device communicates
directly with your accessories.
But when you leave your home,
you'll need a home hub -- again,
this is a HomePod, an Apple TV,
or an iPad -- and your iPhone
will communicate with your home
hub, and your home hub will talk
to your accessories directly.
You can look at the latest state
of these accessories.
You can view the stream from one
of your cameras.
You can even lock your door if
you've forgotten to secure your
house before you left for the
day.
Now, we saw earlier how easy it
to leverage scenes to get
devices to work together.
Now, scenes are great, but
automations allow you to run
scenes automatically.
So you can do so without
launching the Home app or using
your voice.
Automations allow you to control
individual accessories or entire
scenes based on some key
triggers -- things like someone
arriving home or having it run
at a specific time of the day.
You can even use other
accessories in the house to
trigger automations.
Automations can be as simple as
turning on the back porch light
when the back door opens or
turning down the air conditioner
when someone leaves.
Now, we also support more
complex automations so you can
open your garage door, turn on
your lights, open your shades,
and set your thermostat to just
the right temperature all as you
pull into your driveway.
Now, this is one of my favorite
automations, as I'm frequently
juggling groceries, or kids, or
even finishing up a phone call
as I get home.
This allows me to get in my
house without needing to fumble
with my keys as well.
Now, one of the key things that
HomeKit provides to the customer
is an incredibly easy way to add
an accessory to your home and to
your home network.
Other services often require
downloading an app, following
custom instructions, and jumping
through a lot of hoops to get an
accessory on your network.
Now, if you've ever set up a
non-HomeKit accessory, you know
just how frustrating of an
experience this can be.
With HomeKit, the add accessory
flow is really simple.
All you do is launch the Home
app and scan the accessory code.
HomeKit handles the rest.
It's really that easy.
And accessories can also use NFC
to make this setup even easier.
So you can launch the Home app,
tap on the accessory with your
phone, and you're done.
Now, the great thing about
HomeKit is that it's both secure
and private.
All accessory communication is
encrypted, and we create a new
shared secret for each session.
The data is also private, so
Apple doesn't have access to
your camera streams.
Apple can't listen in on your
conversations.
Apple can't even tell if you
have a light bulb turned on or
off.
We know your home is private,
and we want to keep it that way.
So you can monitor your home,
control accessories, execute
scenes, and even use full Siri
support all in a secure and
private way.
We want this communication to be
super secure, and so all
messaging is done directly
between the Apple device and the
accessory.
So your accessory never needs to
talk to the cloud.
In addition to this being
secure, it's also really fast
because all the messaging is
done locally and there's no need
to round trip to a server.
Now, our HomeKit Accessory
Protocol is the communication
channel for secure messaging
between an accessory and your
Apple device.
These messages are encrypted so
that only the trusted devices
can read them.
This means that if someone else,
something does intercept the
message, they can't decrypt it
and understand what it says.
And the HomeKit Accessory
Protocol works over Wi-Fi and
Bluetooth Low Energy.
And by IP, we mean Wi-Fi and
Ethernet.
And Wi-Fi's great because it
provides reliable, fast,
long-range support, so you can
position Wi-Fi accessories
anywhere in your house.
And we also support Bluetooth
Low Energy.
This is also great because --
especially for accessories that
are battery operated.
So for things like sensors, you
can use Bluetooth Low Energy,
and you can position these
sensors in convenient locations
because they don't require a
power cord.
Now, we want everyone to
experience home automation, and
so we provide lots of accessory
categories, and we have some of
the top manufacturers in each
category.
Now, we have an ever-growing
list of categories, and we
support multiple manufacturers
in these categories.
So you can find the one that's
right for you.
With HomeKit, you can even
combine accessories in the same
category from different
manufacturers and have them work
together.
HomeKit makes it easy for you to
choose the accessory that's
right for your home.
Now, with AirPlay 2, we've added
support for adding speakers to
the Home app.
And in iOS 12, we're also
releasing support for remote
control systems.
Now you can create a remote
control accessory that's able to
control your Apple TV, including
support for Siri.
Now that we've given a quick
recap of the benefits of using
HomeKit, let's dive in and see
what resources are available for
making a HomeKit accessory.
So the easiest way to get
started with HomeKit and
building an accessory is to
become an MFI licensee.
It's a great program with lots
of valuable tools that I can't
wait to tell you all about.
Now, if you just want to learn
about the HomeKit Accessory
Protocol, we also have that
available for developers.
Now, this is for noncommercial
use to explore and experiment
with the HomeKit Accessory
Protocol.
So this is great for learning
about the HomeKit Accessory
Protocol, but if you're serious
about building a HomeKit
accessory, we really encourage
you to join the MFI program
because it's the best way to get
off to a quick start.
So let's talk a little bit
about, what are the benefits of
being part of the MFI program?
So becoming an MFI is really
easy, and you'll get lots of
tools and resources.
And one of the newest tools that
we're really excited about is
the HomeKit Accessory
Development Kit.
This is an easy way to get
started on building a HomeKit
accessory.
Now, this Dis a set of code that
runs on the accessory to help
abstract away a lot of the
implementation details that you
previously have to worry about.
Now, we also have tools to help
with certification, and we also
provide access to documentation
to help you get off the ground.
You'll also get a copy of the
specification that has all the
commercial support, including
how to build authentication
right into your accessory.
Now, the ADK makes it easy than
ever to build a HomeKit
accessory.
Previously, you would need to
worry about building your
accessory logic, adopting the
protocol, implementing crypto,
adopting WAC, all these other
steps.
With the accessory development
kit, we've abstracted all this
away for you.
So we provide the platform logic
for your specific accessory, and
the HomeKit Accessory
Development Kit handles a lot of
the details.
This means you only need to
worry about that accessory
logic, which is the part that's
unique to your accessory and is
the part of the code that you
care about.
[ Applause ]
Now, the HomeKit ADK is new, but
we've already gotten a ton of
great feedback from our partners
on how simple it is to use.
MFI licensees are finding it
easier than ever to get started,
and we're seeing that the
ramp-up time for new partners is
faster than ever before.
And of course, the ADK is
reliable and secure, as we've
tested it thoroughly internally,
and it's been reviewed by our
security folks.
Now, the really nice thing about
the ADK is that we'll continue
to update it throughout the
year, so whenever there's an iOS
update that releases new support
for accessories or to the spec,
we'll also rev the ADK so that
it'll stay in sync.
So how much faster is it to use
the ADK?
Well, with the ADK, you can
build a functional prototype and
have it up and running within
just a week.
But let's look at how that
impacts the overall timeline.
So previously, our partners were
spending about 6 months for
development, and then they'd
have to do integration,
certification before they could
ship their product.
We were finding this would often
take about a year to complete.
So with the ADK, we're seeing
that timeline get dramatically
decreased.
Based on feedback from our
partners, it's now possible to
ship out HomeKit accessory
within just 3 months.
[ Applause ]
The ADK makes it easier than
ever to build a HomeKit
accessory.
To learn more about it, join the
MFI program.
You'll have access to all the
ADK information that our
licensees are already using
today to build great
accessories.
Now, I mentioned authentication
before, so let's talk a little
bit about that.
So this is an important part of
the MFI program.
Now, our customers trust when
they see that Apple logo.
They trust that they're buying a
high-quality product.
So when they buy an accessory
that works with Apple HomeKit,
they trust that their accessory
has been tested thoroughly and
reviewed by Apple.
Now, this process is similar to
the App Store review process, so
on the HomeKit side, we have a
way of reviewing accessories.
This is so they, we ensure that
they meet our high bar of
quality and that they're ready
to be shipped to customers.
Now, once an accessory is
certified, it uses our
authentication stack for
onboarding.
This helps guarantee that a
customer is getting that
high-quality product.
Now, the authentication itself
can be done using our hardware
chip or via our new
software-based authentication.
Now, as an MFI licensee, you'll
also have access to
manufacturing partners that can
help get your product to market.
So if you're sitting in the
crowd today with a great idea
for a HomeKit accessory, this is
your big opportunity to bring it
to the home.
Now, we've always supported
hardware-based authentication,
but we have also recently began
supporting software-based
authentication.
Now, customers can be guaranteed
the same level of quality and
trust, and the integration
support can be rolled out via a
firmware update.
Now, this is great because this
means you can roll out HomeKit
to accessories that are already
shipping to customers.
Now, there are three other great
tools that I want to talk about
this morning.
The first is a resource for
accessory developers, and this
is available for MFI licensees,
and this is the HomeKit
Accessory Tester.
Now, this is an app that allows
an easy interface for helping
you test your accessory.
This is a great way to validate
that your accessory is ready to
be submitted to the review
process.
Now, the second tool I want to
talk about is the HomeKit
Certification Assistant.
Now, this resource is also
available to MFI licensees,
which is another great benefit
of being part of the program.
And this is built on top of that
HomeKit Accessory Tester.
Now, this allows you to
self-certify your accessory and
even has support for automating
some of that testing process.
And the third tool I want to
talk about is the HomeKit
Accessory Simulator.
Now, this is a tool that's
created for app developers, and
so it will simulate various
accessories.
Now, this allows you to test
your app and make sure it plays
with all the HomeKit accessory
categories.
Now, the really nice thing about
this is it means you don't need
to go out and buy each one of
these accessories to do your
testing.
You can get this tool available
through Xcode and also through
the MFI program.
And this is actually one of the
tools that we use internally, as
it's a great way to quickly and
easily set up a complex home
with lots of accessories.
Now, of course, you'll also want
a test with real-world
accessories as well.
Now, we talked quite a bit about
making a HomeKit accessory, but
what about making a HomeKit app?
So let's switch gears and talk
about what it takes to build a
HomeKit application.
So there are lots of apps out
there on the App Store.
How do you make yours stand out?
Well, for HomeKit, it's
important to think about your
target audience.
So that might mean extending
custom functionality, like
tuning or calibrating an
accessory, or maybe it means you
live in a region where there's
some functionality that's
specific to your locale that
doesn't already exist in the App
Store.
And if you're an MFI licensee
writing an app for your
accessory, you may what to be
able to support custom services
and characteristics.
Now, with HomeKit, there's a lot
of APIs that I'm going to talk
about today, but before I get
into the details, I think it's
important to take a look at a
high level at the object
hierarchy.
So the first class that I want
to tell you about is this core
object, which is the HMHome.
Now, this is corresponds to the
overall home, and within the
HMHome,
you can also optionally have
HMZones.
Now, these are things like
upstairs and downstairs.
Now, you could also have
HMRooms, and these are the rooms
that are normally associated
with the home -- the kitchen,
the living room, the dining
room, the bedroom.
And within those rooms, you can
have HMAccessories.
And these are the lights, the
fans, the cameras, the locks,
all the normal accessories we
support.
So your home, the HMHome
contains HMZones.
The HMZone contains HMRooms.
And the HMRoom contains
HMAccessories.
Now, the home has a handful of
properties on it, but the home
is really used as the central
organizing object for HomeKit.
So the home is how you add
accessories, configure rooms,
create scenes, and build
automations.
But some users may have more
than one home, and so you'll
need to use the HMHomeManager to
help manage these homes.
So if you want to add a new home
or remove an existing home,
that's done through the
HMHomeManager APIs.
Now, the great thing about
HomeKit is you can extend home
control to other users.
We also have access control
capabilities so you can give a
spouse or a roommate full
administrative privileges.
Now, as an administrator, they,
these users can add accessories,
edit scenes.
They basically have full control
over the home.
But you may only want to give
some users normal access to the
home and only allow them to
control accessories and not edit
them.
And those are
non-administrators.
Now, the important take-away
here is that if you're building
an app, you want to make sure
that if your HM user is not an
administrator that you disable
some key functionality so that
it doesn't fail when they go try
and use it.
Again, all this user management
is done through the HMHome
object, and you'll quickly see
that this is a common design
pattern we use where the HMHome
exposes a lot of the basic
functionality.
So let's take a look at some
sample code and see what this
looks like.
So here we have a class where we
will instantiate an
HMHomeManager.
Now, we want to add a home to
that home manager, so we'll use
the addHome APIs and specify the
name of the home.
Now, we want to be sure to set
ourselves as the delegate, so
we'll get the appropriate
delegate callbacks.
And finally, if we want to
configure the users for the
home, we'll call manageUsers on
HMHome.
Now, I mentioned HMZones
earlier, so let's take a little
peek at that.
So this is a way of grouping
multiple rooms together, like
upstairs and downstairs, or you
can group all the bedrooms
together in a single zone.
So it has some basic properties
on it like name and access to
the rooms, but it also has this
unique identifier property.
And this could often be
overlooked, but this is a way
that you keep track of which
zone you're, you care about.
So when the name changes or the
rooms change, you still have an
access to that specific zone.
Now, on the HMRoom object, we
also support exposing the name
and the list of the accessories,
and it also contains this unique
identifier property so you can
keep track of rooms as well.
Again, the rooms and zones are
managed through the HMHome APIs,
so if you want to add or remove
a room or if you want to add or
remove a zone, you do through,
do that through the HMHome APIs.
So if we go back to some sample
code, let's take a look at this
[inaudible] in action.
So here we are adding a room to
the home with our roomName.
And then, we're adding a zone to
the home with a zoneName.
And then, we associate that room
to the zone.
Now, the next level of object
hierarchy that's important is
the relationship between
accessories, services, and
characteristics.
Now, this can sound confusing,
as accessories contain services
and services contain
characteristics.
So it's best to look at a
real-world example to give you
an idea how, really how this
fits together.
So let's say you have a ceiling
fan fixture.
Now, this is a single accessory,
and it has a light, and it has a
fan.
So this maps to a light service
and a fan service.
Now, these services have a set
of common characteristics that
are shared across all services,
but they also have
characteristics that are unique
to their service.
So the light service has
characteristics like power,
brightness, and saturation.
And the fan service has
characteristics like power,
rotation speed, and rotation
direction.
Now, some of these
characteristics are optional.
As you can imagine, not all
lights support saturation and
color.
But the HomeKit APIs expose
these as a way to elevate these
services to your user.
So we look back.
We have the ceiling fan fixture,
which is the HMAccessory.
We have the light service and
the fan service, which are the
HMServices.
And we have the corresponding
characteristics, which are the
HMCharacteristics.
So we look, if you look at the
API for some of this, you could
see we have HMAccessory, and
this allows you to learn about
the accessory that you're
controlling.
So this exposes properties like
the name, the list of services
it supports, and the firmware
version it's running.
Now, this is just a subsample of
all the properties on the
accessory.
I just wanted to give you an
idea of the sense of what types
of properties are on it.
So if we take a look at
HMService, we'll see that it
exposes the list of
characteristics, and there's a
setter method for updating the
name.
Now, updating the name is
actually pretty important.
So why is it important?
Well, it's important because
this is how Siri and the Home
app will interface with your
accessory.
So you'll want to choose a good
default name.
So we, you don't want to use
serial numbers, or MAC
addresses, or model numbers in
your service name because
that'll make it challenging for
the user to talk to your
accessory through Siri.
You also don't-- want to avoid
special characters and numbers,
emojis, punctuation, things like
that also because it gets
confusing to the user on how
they want, when they want to
address their accessory.
Now, we support over 40
predefined service types.
So things like light bulbs,
thermostats, garage door
openers, outlets, and all kinds
of sensors, to name a few.
We also allow the ability to
specify custom service types as
well.
Now, when it comes to adding the
accessory to the home, you'll
want to go back to the HMHome
helper methods.
These APIs are pretty simple to
use, but we'll walk through an
example shortly here anyway.
So the addAccessory API, this
API is what invokes the Home UI
view service, which is that
familiar addAccessory flow that
I mentioned earlier, which is
how you can do quick QR code
scanning or use NFC to add an
accessory to the home.
Now, I want to call special
attention to the last method
here, which is addAnd
SetupAccessories with payload.
Now, you can use that payload to
pass in a HomeKit accessory code
for in-field activation cases.
So this API is especially
valuable for software
authentication.
So this is the case where your
accessory has left the factory
without a HomeKit code on it.
So you've updated the accessory
via firmware update to provide
HomeKit support, and you don't
want the user to have to
memorize the HomeKit code or to
write it down.
And so this API allows you to
pass in that HomeKit code so
that this accessory can be
seamlessly added to the home.
Now, this API is available to
MFI licensees.
For more information, contact
your MFI representative.
So if we look at some sample
code on how we would add an
accessory to the home, you just
need to call addAnd
SetupAccessories on the home
object, and HomeKit takes care
of the rest.
Now, I mentioned scenes earlier,
but it's a pretty powerful
concept, so I want to go a bit
deeper.
Now, this is how you can
integrate different types of
accessories together to help
provide a cohesive experience.
We have some suggested scenes,
but we also allow full
customization by the user.
Now, one of the great things
about scenes is that Siri
understands what scenes are.
And so speaking the name to Siri
execute, speaking the name of a
scene to Siri will execute the
scene directly.
Now, we don't call them scenes
in HomeKit.
We call them HMActionSets.
So if you want to create an
HMActionSet -- for example,
arriving home -- you'll need to
create a list of HMActions, and
then you'll associate those with
the action set.
So the action set, the
HMActionSet contains all of the
individual HMActions.
Now, we support some predefined
scenes, like wake up, go to
sleep, leave the house, and
return home.
Now, this not only gives the
user some context about what
types of action sets are
possible, but this is also what
we've found to be some of the
most useful.
Now, of course, we also support
user-defined action sets, and
these are great for things like
creating your perfect movie
scene lighting.
So again, to add them to the
home, we go back to the HMHome
APIs because this allows you to
add these action sets, execute
the action sets, and the HMHome
APIs also expose the way of
accessing the built-in action
sets.
So if we look at some quick
sample code, we'll see that if
we want to create an action set,
we call addActionSet withName on
the home, we pass in the name of
the action set, then we'll want
to iterate through our list of
actions and add each one to the
action set.
Then, later, if we want to run
the scene, all you do is call
executeActionSet on the home.
Now, running scenes via the UI
or via Siri is great, but
sometimes you want things to
happen automatically.
Now, we have several options for
automatically triggering scenes
and automatically controlling
accessories.
These can be geofence based, so
you can turn on the lights as
you pull up to your house.
Or they can be time based, so
you can turn up the heat before
you get out of bed.
They can be accessory based, so
you can leverage a motion sensor
to turn on a light.
And they can be presence based,
so you could turn off your
lights when you leave for the
day.
Now, event triggers themselves
are comprised of action sets,
and the APIs on HMEvent or
HMTrigger are mostly around
naming, adding, and enabling.
Now, with automations, you can
set them up to run once ever, or
you can have them be recurring.
So you can them just be, happen
that one time, or you can have
them happen every day, or maybe
you want them just to happen
every weekday, or even just
every Friday.
So with automations, you have a
lot of control with the
frequency and how often you want
automations to run.
Now, let's take a look at the
creation of an HMTrigger and how
we add it to the home.
So let's say we want to create
an automation that will run
every night at 7 p.m.
So first, we create our date
components and we set the time
to be 7 p.m.
Then, we'll create a calendar
event using that component.
Then, we'll generate a trigger
using that time event.
Now, we need to add that trigger
to the home.
And we need to add the action
set to the trigger.
So this allows you to run an
automation every night at 7 p.m.
So let's say it's turning on a
light every night at 7 p.m.
Now, that's great, except for
sometimes, some parts of the
year, it's not dark at 7 p.m.,
or sometimes, parts of the year,
it gets dark before 7 p.m.
Sometimes it gets dark after 7
p.m.
So turning on the light at 7
p.m. every night isn't really
what you want.
So we also support what we call
significant time events.
And this is sunrise and sunset.
So if we look at that previous
example, we could change that to
say, turn on the light every
night at 7 p.m.
We also support relative time
offsets, so you can have the
light turn on, say, 30 minutes
prior to sunset.
So let's go back to the code we
had before and make some changes
so that we can have it run every
night at 30 minutes before
sunset.
So the first thing we need to do
is change our date components to
be 30 minutes.
Now, you'll see that it's
negative 30 here because we want
it to run 30 minutes prior to
sunset.
Then, we'll create a significant
time event for sunset and pass
in that offset.
Then, when we generate our
trigger, we pass in the sunset
event.
Then, we execute the code we had
before, which is adding the
trigger to the home and adding
the action set to the trigger.
But sometimes you don't want
these automations to run.
You probably don't want the heat
to turn on in the morning if no
one's home.
You probably don't want the
light to turn on when the door
opens if it's during the day.
So we also support what we call
conditions.
And these can be time based,
they can be presence based, they
can be accessory state based,
and they can be based on
significant events.
Now, I have an automation in my
house which turns off the lights
whenever someone leaves.
Now, that's great, except that I
live with my wife, and so
whenever she leaves the house,
all the lights turn off and I'm
left in the dark.
So with presence-based
conditions, you can update this
so that the lights only turn off
when the last person leaves.
Now, to set these conditions, we
use predicates.
So let's take a look at some
sample code.
So here we can see that we're
using our same sunset time
offset from before.
Now, we're going to create a
presence event that's when users
are at home.
We're going to use that presence
event to generate a predicate.
And we'll pass that predicate
into our trigger generation.
Then, we'll go back to the same
code we had before where we add
the trigger to the home and we
add the action set to the
trigger.
So now, we've gone from having
an automation that runs every
night at 7 p.m. to an automation
that runs every night 30 minutes
before sunset, only if someone's
home.
Now, we also have support for
HomeKit cameras.
And there are some HomeKit APIs
that allow you to show live
streams, show still images, and
to configure camera settings.
You-- this support also includes
the ability to control the
speaker volume and microphone.
So let's take a quick look at
some sample code for that as
well.
So here you could see we have a
function where we want to start
the camera stream for our
accessory.
Now, we want to be sure to set
ourselves as the delegate so we
can get the proper delegate
callbacks.
Now, we'll use this start stream
API to start the stream, and we
also want to be sure to create a
camera view and to add that view
to our view hierarchy.
This is so we can display that
camera stream in our app.
Then, later, we'll get the
delegate callback.
Again, this is the
HMCameraStream ControlDelegate.
And we'll receive this
cameraStreamControl
DidStartStream delegate
callback.
And all we need to do there is
set the camera source to be the
camera stream.
Now, this is the end of the
sample code for today, but
there's plenty of documentation
available for these APIs online.
So we hope that this gives you a
fresh look at learning what, how
HomeKit works.
We encourage you to join the MFI
program to take advantage of all
these great resources and
powerful tools.
It's amazingly easy to become an
MFI licensee.
Come visit us in the lab to
learn more about it.
If you're already an MFI
licensee, contact your MFI
representative to get access to
the latest tools.
With the new ADK, we've made it
easier than ever to bring a
HomeKit accessory to market.
Whether you're building HomeKit
through, [inaudible] your
accessory through a firmware
update or creating a new HomeKit
accessory for the first time,
use these tools to start
integrating with HomeKit so you
can get native series support
and to integrate with other
HomeKit accessories.
We can't wait to see the great
accessories we know that you'll
come up with.
We also encourage you to use
these APIs to provide a unique
experience for your customers
and to take full advantage of
all that HomeKit has to offer.
For more information or to learn
about anything we've discussed
today, check out this link or
come visit us in the lab.
We're going to be down in the
Technology Lab 12, which starts
shortly.
Thank you all for coming.
Hope you all had a great WWDC.
[ Applause ]