[ Music ]
>> Hey guys!
>> Good afternoon.
Welcome to Adding Delight to
your iOS App.
My name's Ben.
>> And, my name is Peter.
And, we're going to show you six
pro tips to make it magic.
>> We're going to start with
external display support,
bringing your app's experiences
to the big screen.
>> Next, we're going to go
through a brand-new programming
pattern for you, called
layout-driven UI.
>> Then, we're going to show you
how to get your customers to
your delightful experiences as
fast as possible, with
laser-fast launches.
>> We're going to focus hard on
smooth scrolling, and keeping
things feeling great.
>> Continuity is one of the most
magical experiences on iOS.
And, we're going to show you
just how easy it is to adopt
Handoff in your applications.
>> And, finally, we're going to
teach you some Matrix-level
debugging skills, in debugging
like a pro.
>> We have a lot to cover, so
let's get started.
iOS devices are defined by their
stunning, integrated displays.
And, you can bring your app's
experience even further, by
adding support for an external
display.
We've built a demo app to help
illustrate this.
Built right into iOS, is Display
Mirroring, which replicates the
entire system UI on the external
connected display.
Here's our demo app.
As you can see, it's a simple
photo viewer.
When you tap on a photo
thumbnail, the photo slides in,
and it's full screen.
And, this entire experience is
replicated on the external
display.
To take full advantage of the
size of the external display, we
can rotate the iPhone to
landscape to fill it up.
And, this is great, with no work
on our part, we were able to get
this experience.
But, we can do better than this.
Built right into iOS, are APIs
that allow you to create an
entirely custom, second user
interface on this externally
connected display.
Let's take a look at a couple of
examples of apps that have done
this.
Keynote is a great example.
On the external display, you
remain focused on the primary
slide at hand.
But, on the integrated iPhone
display, you can see presenter
notes, and the next slide, tools
essential to any presentation.
Or, maybe you have a game.
But, typically you'd have soft,
overlaid controls.
Well, you could create an
entirely custom interface to
control your game, and put that
on the iOS device's display, and
have your full, unobstructed and
immersive gaming experience on
the external display.
When designing your applications
for an external display, there
are some key things that you
should think about.
Aside from the obvious size
differences, your iPhone is
personal.
And so, you should consider the
kind of information that you
show on this display as private.
Whereas, the external display
will typically be situated in an
environment where many people
can see it, such as a TV in a
living room, or a projection
system in a conference hall.
So, you should assume that the
information shown on this
display is public.
>> Additionally, while the
displays built into iPhone and
iPad are interactive, the
external display is not.
So, you should avoid showing UI
elements, or other interactable
controls on the external
display.
>> So, let's apply this kind of
thinking to our demo app, and
see what we can come up with.
Here's our optimized version for
the external display.
As you can see, we're now
showing the selected photo full
size on the external display.
And, on the integrated display,
we're showing just the
thumbnails, and a new selection
indicator to show the photo that
is currently being shown full
screen.
While simple, this is a really
powerful use of this design.
To show you how we built this
into our demo app, we're going
to cover three topics.
Connectivity, behavior, and
connection transitions.
Let's start with connectivity.
How do you know if you have an
external display connected?
UIScreen has a class variable,
screens, which contains a list
of all the connected displays,
including the device, built into
the iPhone.
So, if there's more than one
element in this array, you know
you have an external display
connected.
Additionally, because the
external display can be
connected and disconnected at
will, UIKit will post
notifications to help you know
when this happens.
So, you should listen for the
UIScreen
.didConnectNotification, and the
.didDisconnectNotifications.
And, bring up and tear down your
UI accordingly.
Peter, can you show our
developers just how easy it is
to set up a second user
interface?
>> Ben, I'd be happy to.
Let's jump into our code for our
UIScreen connection callback.
Here, we'll set a local variable
to the last screen in the
screens array.
We know that this is the
external screen, because we're
inside of our
didConnectNotification callback.
Next, we'll make a new UI window
to show on this external
display.
And, we'll assign its screen
property to the screen.
Next, we're going to want to
make sure we set up this window.
We factored this into a
function, but all we're doing
here is making a root view
controller, and sticking it on
the window, the same way we'd do
for the onboard display.
And, finally, we're going to
mark this window as not hidden
to show it on the external
screen.
So, that's connection.
Now, let's look at
disconnection, which is even
easier.
So, here we are inside of our
UIScreen
.didDisconnectNotification
handler, and all we have to do
here is hide the window, and nil
out our local reference to it,
to free up any resources.
And, that's it.
We've implemented screen
connection and disconnection in
our app.
>> Wow, Peter, that was really
easy.
The next thing you're going to
want to think about is changing
your app's default behavior for
when it has an external display
connected.
Let's look at an example of some
code from our demo app.
This is the code that's called
when we tap on a photo in your
collection view.
When we're in single display
mode, we create our
photoViewController and push it
onto our navigation stack.
But, when we have an external
display connected, we're already
showing that photoViewController
full screen in that second UI,
so we just tell it to present
that photo.
Really easy.
The third thing you should think
about when designing for an
external display is you should
handle connection changes with
graceful transitions.
Let's go back to our demo app to
illustrate this.
Here you can see our demo app is
currently showing a photo full
size.
And, we haven't yet connected
the external display yet.
Watch what happens when we plug
it in.
What happened here, is we popped
our viewController back to the
thumbnail view while
simultaneously showing that
previously selected photo full
size on the external display.
And, it's these graceful
transitions that really help
preserve the context, and help
your customers understand where
they are in your app's flow.
So, that's external display
support.
It's really easy to set up.
Just consider the different
display contexts when designing
your application, and be sure to
handle connection changes
gracefully.
To learn more about this, check
out this talk from WWDC 2011.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> Layout-driven UI is a
powerful way to write your app
to make it easier to add
features, and easier to debug.
Layout-driven UI helps us deal
with the number one cause of
issues in iOS apps, and that's
managing UI complexity.
I'm sure you've been here
before.
I know I have.
You add some code, and a gesture
callback.
You add even more UI update code
in a notification callback.
And, more when you get a value
trigger from a UI control.
And, suddenly your app is in
this weird, and hard to
understand state.
And, you have to follow these
strange orders to reproduce
these unusual bugs.
And, as you add more features to
your app, the problem gets worse
and worse.
If we instead follow a simple
recipe, and push these UI
updates into layout, we can get
rid of these bugs, and make it
much easier to add features.
Let's walk through the recipe
for adding layout-driven UI to
your app.
>> The first thing you should
do, is you need to identify and
track all of the state that
affects your UI.
Then, every time that states
changes, you should dirty the
layout system by calling
setNeedsLayout.
Finally, you'll want to update
your UI with this state in
layoutSubviews.
And, that's it.
>> So, what I love about this
recipe is just how easy it is to
follow.
And, if we apply layout-driven
UI to our app holistically,
while considering the three core
components of an iOS app,
layout, animations, and
gestures, you'll find that our
implementation of all three of
these works harmoniously, in a
really awesome way.
Let's start with layout.
Layout is the process by which
you position your application's
content onscreen.
But, we're also recommending
that you do all other UI updates
in layout.
Let's look at a simple sample
app that we wrote to highlight
this.
Ben, can you take us through
this app?
>> Sure, Peter.
So, there's a really simple
sample app, with this cool guy
in the middle.
He shows when we're feeling
cool.
When we're not, he hides away.
But, we're feeling quite cool
right now, Peter.
So, let's bring him back in.
>> Great. So, while this is a
simple example, it's really
important to walk through, so we
can understand how layout-driven
UI works.
So, let's go through a skeleton
of this app, and follow through
the layout-driven UI recipe that
Ben showed us earlier.
So, here we've got our managing
view that hosts this cool guy
view, in our coolView, which I
wrote ahead of time.
So, Ben, what's the first step
in our recipe?
>> Well, we need to identify and
track that state that affects
our UI.
>> So, remember what Ben said.
The cool guy is there when we're
feeling cool.
And, he's not there when we're
not.
So, I guess we'll have a
variable called feelingCool.
OK. Ben, what's the second step
in the recipe?
>> Well, now, every time this
state changes, we need to dirty
the layout system by calling
setNeedsLayout.
But, we need to make sure that
every time this state changes
this happens.
And, this state could change
from various places in our
application.
So, Peter, how can we ensure
that we're always dirtying the
layout system when there's
changes?
>> I'm happy you asked, because
I think I've got a good idea for
this.
We can use a feature called
Swift property observers.
These let us run code before or
after a property is set.
So, we can use the didSet
property observer to call
setNeedsLayout.
This is a really excellent use
of Swift property observers in
your app.
OK. So, we're almost done.
Ben, what's the last step in the
recipe?
>> Well now, Peter, using this
state, we need to update our UI
in layoutSubviews.
>> OK, easy.
We'll override layoutSubviews,
and we'll updated the isHidden
property of our cool guy view
based on the value of
feelingCool.
And, that's it.
That's all you need to do to add
layout-driven UI to your app.
Now, while this works really
well for this simple example, it
works well for some more complex
ones earlier.
Ben and I were up really late
last night playing this new
macOS The Gathering trading card
game, which is sweeping the
Apple campus.
We built this fun little deck
builder app to help us win the
tournament next weekend, which
we're really going to do.
It lets you pick up and drag
these cards around, and you can
fling them into this little deck
area.
And, it's really fast, and fun,
and fluid.
We can pick up two cards at the
same time.
I think with this app we can
really show you how
layout-driven UI works, and
importantly, we can beat Ben's
officemate next weekend.
So, let's walk through the other
two core aspects of an iOS app,
and how we can apply
layout-driven UI to them,
starting with animations.
>> Animations are the hallmark
of any great iOS experience.
The life-like motion of your
user interface truly makes your
apps feel alive.
UIKit has some great API
available to help you create
these delightful animations.
The UIViewPropertyAnimator API
is a really powerful tool, and
it was turbocharged last year
with a bunch of new features.
To learn all about how to use
it, check out Advanced
Animations from UIKit from WWDC
2017.
In addition to this, the tried
and true UIView closure API is
also a great way to make these
animations.
>> So, great.
We can use UIViewAnimations with
our layout-driven UI-based app.
One thing to keep in mind, is
we're always going to want to
use the beginFromCurrentState
animation option.
This tells UIKit to take the
current onscreen position of
your view, even if it's
mid-animation, when doing
animation.
And so, this lets us do these
really wonderful, interruptible
interactive animations.
Let's look at an example in our
macOS The Gathering trading card
game app.
So, here we've got a variable
that tracks what cards are in
our deck.
And, using those Swift property
observers we talked about
earlier, we're dirtying the
layout system every time this
changes by calling
setNeedsLayout.
Next, when we want to put a card
in the deck, all we have to do
is add that card to this array,
which will dirty our layout, and
then inside of an animation
block, using this
beginFromCurrentState option, we
call layoutIfNeeded.
This will trigger a call to our
code in layoutSubviews, which
will move all of our views
around, play the appropriate
animation state transitions.
And, what's really excellent
about this, that I really want
to highlight here, is notice how
we didn't add any special case
for these animations.
We just kind of got this
animated layout for free by
doing our layout inside of an
animation block.
This is really, really awesome.
So, that's how we can add
animations to our layout-driven
UI app.
Finally, let's take about the
third core aspect of an iOS app,
and that's gestures.
And, of course, we can't talk
about gestures without talking
about UIGestureRecognizer,
UIKit's awesome API for adding
gestural interactions to your
app.
>> UIKit provides a number of
great concrete subclasses of
UIgestureRecognizer.
Everything from pans to pinches
to swipes to rotation.
You should be able to create the
kind of interactions you want,
using these.
And, they're highly customizable
as well.
If you want something really
crazy, you can always subclass
UIGestureRecognizer yourself as
well.
>> When looking between the
built-in
UIKitGestureRecognizers, it's
important to understand the
difference between discrete and
continuous gestures.
Discrete gestures tell you that
an event happened.
They start in the Possible
state, and then they don't pass
go, they don't collect $200.
They move immediately into the
Recognized state.
These are really useful for fire
and forget interactions in your
app, but won't tell you at every
phase during the interaction.
>> The other type of gestures
are continuous gestures.
These provide a much greater
level of fidelity to you.
Like discrete gestures, they
start out in the Possible state,
but as they begin to be
recognized, they move to the
Began state.
As they track, they enter the
Changed state.
And, at this point you're
receiving a continuous stream of
events as the gesture moves
around.
Finally, when the gesture is
complete, it moves to the Ended
state.
One of our favorite types of
continuous gestures is the
UIPanGestureRecognizer.
And, there are two great
functions available to help you
get the most out of it.
translationInView will tell you
where the gesture is tracking,
relative to your views.
And, velocityInView will tell
you how fast your gesture is
moving.
And, this is really powerful for
handing off velocity between a
gesture and a subsequent
animation.
To learn all about how to build
really great gesture
interactions using these, check
out Building Interruptible and
Responsive Interactions from
WWDC 2014.
>> So, I also love
UIPanGestureRecognizer.
And, we used it to help build
that card dragging behavior you
saw earlier.
Let's look at how we did this
using layout-driven UI.
Again, we have a local variable,
which tracks the offsets for
each of our cards that the
gesture has applied.
And again notice every time this
variable changes, we're
triggering setNeedsLayout, using
one of Swift's property
observers.
Next, inside of our
panGestureRecognizer callback
function, we're just going to
grab the current translation and
view out of the gesture, and
associate this gesture to one of
our cards.
We'll then increment the offset
for this card in this
dictionary.
And finally, in layoutSubviews,
we'll make sure to update the
position of our card views based
on their offsets from this
dictionary.
Notice again how we're not
really doing anything special,
other than -- besides the
traditional layout-driven UI
case.
We just have this piece of state
that happens to be driven by a
gesture, and we're responding to
it in layoutSubviews.
In fact, if you follow this
pattern throughout your app,
you'll find that it makes a lot
of these types of interactions
much easier to adopt.
So that's layout-driven UI.
Remember the recipe.
Find and track all of that state
that affects your UI.
And, use Swift property
observers to trigger
setNeedsLayout whenever this
state changes.
Finally, in your implementation
of layoutSubviews, make sure to
update your view state based on
this state that you tracked.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> The iOS experience is all
about being responsive.
And, you want to get your
customers to your delightful
experiences as quickly as
possible.
There is one step between them
tapping on your icon, and being
delighted.
And, that one step is your
launch time.
To help you optimize this, we're
going to take you through the
five high-level components that
make up the anatomy of a launch.
Starting with number one,
process forking.
Peter, what can we do in this
phase of the launch?
>> Well, for process forking,
it's really complicated.
You're going to want to read the
Man pages for fork and exec, and
familiarize yourself with POSIX
fundamentals.
No, no, I'm just kidding.
iOS will take care of process
forking for you.
>> We'll deal with number one
for you.
Let's look at number two.
[ Audience Laughter ]
Dynamic linking.
At this phase, we're allocating
memory to begin executing your
application.
We're linking libraries and
frameworks.
We're initializing Swift,
Objective-C, and Foundation.
And, we're doing static object
initialization as well.
And, typically we see this can
take 40 to 50% of the typical
launch time of an app.
And, one key thing to remember
is at this point, none of your
code has run.
So, it's vital that you
understand how to optimize this.
Peter, do you have any great
advice for our developers?
>> I'm happy you asked, Ben.
It's important that you take
great care when optimizing the
linking phase of your app's
launch time.
Because it takes up such a large
amount of your launch time.
My first piece of advice for you
is to avoid code duplication
wherever possible.
If you have redundant functions,
objects, or structs, remove them
from your app.
Don't repeat yourself.
Next, you're going to want to
limit your use of third-party
libraries.
iOS first-party libraries are
cached, and may already be in
active memory if another
application is using them.
But, third-party libraries are
not cached.
Even if another app is using the
same version of a library as
you, we'll still have to pull in
the framework if your app uses
it.
So, you should really limit your
use of these third-party
libraries as much as possible.
And, finally, you're going to
want to avoid static
initializers, and having any
behavior in methods like plus
initialize, and plus load.
Because these have to run before
your app can do any meaningful
work.
>> To learn more about this
vital part of your launch time,
check out App Start-up Time:
Past, Present, and Future from
WWDC 2017.
The next phase of your launch is
your UI Construction.
At this point, you're preparing
your UI, building up your
viewControllers.
The system is doing state
restoration, and loading in your
preferences.
And, you're loading in the data
that you need for your app to
become responsive.
So, Peter, what can we do at
this phase of the launch to
optimize?
>> You'll want to optimize the
UI construction phase to be as
fast as possible for your app.
This means returning as quickly
as possible from the UI
application activation methods.
WillFinishLaunching,
didFinishLaunching, and
didBecomeActive.
Because UIKit waits for you to
return from these functions
before we can mark your app as
active.
Next, you're going to want to
avoid any file system writes
during your application launch,
as these are blocking, and
require a sys call.
Hand in hand with these, you're
going to want to avoid very
large reads during app launch as
well.
Instead, consider streaming in
only the data you absolutely
need right now.
And, finally I encourage you to
check your database hygiene.
It's always a good idea to stay
clean.
If you're using a library like
CoreData, consider optimizing
your schema, to make it as fast
as possible.
And, if you're rolling your own
solution with SQLite, or similar
technology, consider vacuuming
your database at a periodic
interval.
For example, every time your app
gets updated.
>> Thanks, Peter.
The next phase of the launch is
when we create your very first
frame.
At this point, core animation is
doing all the rendering
necessary to get that frame
ready.
It's doing text drawing.
And, we're loading and
decompressing any images that
need to be shown in your UI.
So, Peter, do you have any more
sage advice for this phase of
the launch?
>> Oh, do I.
When preparing your first frame,
it's really important that you
take great care to only prepare
the user interface that you
absolutely need during launch
time.
If your user hasn't navigated to
a particular section of your
app, avoid loading it.
And, instead, pull it in lazily
when you absolutely need it.
Also, you should avoid hiding
views and layers that should not
be visible when we first
navigate to your app.
Even when views and layers are
hidden, they still have a cost.
So, only bring in the views and
layers that you absolutely need
for your first frame.
>> The final phase of your
launch is what we call extended
launch actions.
These are tasks that you have
potentially deferred from your
launch path to help you get
responsive faster.
So, while your app may be
responsive at this point, it may
not be very usable yet.
This phase is really all about
prioritizing what to do next.
Bring in the content that needs
to be onscreen right now.
And also, if you're loading
content from a remote server, be
sure to consider that you may be
in challenging network
conditions.
And, have a placeholder UI ready
to go if necessary.
So, those are the five
high-level components that make
up the anatomy of a launch.
We've one more thing for you
today.
ABM. A: Always.
B: Be. M: Measuring.
>> Coffee is for quick apps.
>> It's essential that you
understand where your launch
time is going.
So, measure it regularly using
the Time Profiler.
Any time you change code in the
path -- in your launch path,
you'll want to remeasure.
And, take statistical averages.
Don't depend on a single profile
to check your launch time.
So, laser-fast launches.
Get responsive fast.
Use only what you need.
And, measure, measure, measure.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> Scrolling is a key part of
the iOS user experience, and a
huge part of the experience
inside your apps.
iPhone and iPad are magical
sheets of glass that can
transform into anything your app
would like them to be.
So, it's important that you work
to help preserve this illusion
of your app's content sliding on
this magic sheet of glass.
At Apple, we've got a phrase
that we like to say, that your
app should feel smooth like
butter.
But, from time to time, you have
some hitches and stutters that
make it feel less like butter,
and more like peanut butter.
And, you've seen this before.
Your app feels choppy or
stuttery.
Ben, what are some causes of the
slow behavior in apps?
>> Well, Peter, this slow
behavior that you're describing
is really that we're dropping
frames.
And so, we need to understand
why that might be happening.
And, there are two key areas
where this can happen.
The first is you could be doing
too much computation.
And, the second is you could be
doing too much complex graphics
compositing.
Let's look at each of these in
turn, starting with computation.
How do you know if you're doing
too much computation?
Well, the Time Profiler, built
into Instruments, is the
ultimate tool for this.
It can give you down to the line
measurements for just how much
CPU time your code is using.
It's a really powerful tool, and
we encourage you to go and check
out Using the Time Profiler in
Instruments from WWDC 2016.
>> So, once you've identified
these hot spots, using the Time
Profiler tool, we've got some
great tips for you to optimize
them.
The first is to use
UICollectionView and UITableView
prefetching.
These are pieces of API that
will tell you while the user is
scrolling towards particular
cells, and can give you an
opportunity to preload that
data.
There was a wonderful talk given
by two very handsome presenters
on this in 2016 that I encourage
you to watch.
The next tip that I have for
you, is to push as much work as
possible off of the main queue
and onto background queues,
freeing up the main queue to
update your UI and handle user
input.
Ben, what kind of work can we
push off the main queue?
>> Well, there's some usual
stuff that you might expect,
like network and file system
access.
These should never be running on
the main thread.
But, maybe some other stuff that
you might not expect, like image
drawing and text sizing.
UIGraphicsImageRenderer, and its
distributed string, both have
functions available that are
safe to use on a background
thread, that might just help you
move some of that complex
computation off of your main
queue.
>> Wow, Ben, those are great
tips.
I never would have thought to do
that off of the main queue.
So, let's say I've run the Time
Profiler.
I've used prefetching, just like
those guys told me to.
And, I've pushed as much work as
possible off of the main queue,
but my app is still slow.
Surely this isn't my problem,
right Ben?
>> Well, Peter, we may not be
out of the woods just yet.
While we may have optimized our
computation, we could still be
having problems with our
graphics system.
Fortunately, there's another
great tool available here.
The Core Animation instrument is
a really powerful way to see
exactly what your frame rate is
doing.
And, also at the same time,
looking at your GPU utilization.
It's another really powerful
tool.
And, to learn all about how to
use it, check out Advanced
Graphics and Animations for iOS
Apps from WWDC 2014.
>> Once you've identified that
your app is graphics-bound,
we've got some great low-hanging
fruit for you to investigate.
Usually, you have a
graphics-bound app due to
overuse of one of two things:
visual effects, or masking and
clipping.
Visual effects, like blur and
vibrancy, are expensive, and so
you should use them tastefully
within your apps.
You should also definitely avoid
things like blurs on blurs on
blurs, as this will cause the
GPU to work in overdrive,
slowing down your app.
Also, you should avoid masking
and clipping wherever possible.
Instead, if you can achieve the
same visual appearance by just
placing opaque content on top of
your views, then I would
encourage you to too that,
instead of using the masked
view, or masked property of
UIViewer CA Layer.
So, that's how we can optimize
smooth scrolling performance.
Make sure to run the Time
Profiler, and Core Animation
instruments on your apps.
Use prefetching, and push as
much work as possible off of the
main queue.
And, try to use visual effects,
and masking and clipping
sparingly.
For even more information about
profiling, check out this great
talk from WWDC 2015.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> Continuity is one of the most
magical experiences across Apple
platforms.
And, Handoff is a fantastic way
to truly delight your customers.
The ability to take a task from
one device, and seamlessly
transition it to another device
is an absolutely awesome
experience.
Handoff works between iOS,
macOS, and watchOS.
It doesn't require an internet
connection because it uses
peer-to-peer connectivity, and
best of all for all of you, is
it's really easy to set up.
So, how should you think about
using Handoff in your
applications?
Well, let's go through a few
examples of how we do it in some
of our Apple apps.
Let's say I get a message from
my handsome co-presenter, and I
want to reply on my iPhone X
with a humorous animoji.
Well, I can get right back into
that conversation, right from
the App Switcher on iOS.
>> Or, if I'm editing a document
in Pages on my Mac, and I have
to run, and I want to hand it
off to my iPad, I can do so by
tapping the icon in the Dock.
>> Or, again, if I'm casually
browsing photos on my watch, and
I find one from a previous WWDC,
and I just want to go and look
at all the photos in that album,
I can get right back into my
Photo library on my iPhone,
without having to go search for
that one photo.
Handoff is really powerful, and
it can save your customers so
much time when moving from
device to device.
So, we're going to show you just
how easy it is to adopt.
And, it's all built on top of
the NSUserActivity API.
NSUserActivity represents a
current state or activity that
you're currently doing.
In this case, we're composing an
email.
When this activity is created,
all of the nearby devices that
are signed into the same iCloud
account all show that Handoff is
available.
On the Mac, you'll see an icon
down in the Dock.
When you click on this Mail
icon, the activity will be
transferred over to the Mac, and
Mail can launch and continue
exactly where you left off.
So, let's look at the code
necessary to set this up.
On the originating device, you
start by creating your
NSUserActivity with a given
type.
And, this type represents the
kind of activity that your user
is currently doing.
You then set a title, and set
isEligibleForHandoff to true.
And you then want to populate
your userInfo dictionary.
And, you need to fill this with
all the information necessary to
be able to continue the
activity.
In this case, our example is a
video, and we're including a
video ID, and a current play
time.
Finally, you'll want to set this
activity to your
viewController's userActivity
property.
This will cause it to become the
current activity, whenever that
viewController is presented.
And, that's all you need to do
on the originating device.
On the continuing device, first
of all, your app needs to
declare support for the type of
activity that you created.
Then, you need to implement two
UIApplicationDelegate callbacks.
The first is application
willContinueUser
ActivityWithType.
And, this is called as soon as
you click or tap on the icon to
initiate the handoff.
At this point, we don't have the
NSUserActivity object ready yet,
but you know the kind of
activity that's going to be
continued, so you can begin
preparing your UI.
Very shortly after, you'll
receive
applicationContinueRestoration
handler, which will contain the
fully reconstructed
NSUserActivity object.
From that point, you can set up
and continue the experience
right on that device.
>> If you've got more
information than can fit in a
userInfo dictionary, there's
great feature of NSUserActivity
that you can use, called
continuation streams.
All you have to do is set the
supportsContinuationStreams
property to true.
Then, on the continuing device,
you'll call the
getContinuationStreams method on
the NSUserActivity, which will
provide you with an input and an
output stream.
Back on the originating device,
the NSUserActivity's delegate
will receive a callback
providing it with input and
output streams as well.
And, through these channels, you
can do bi-directional
communication between the
originating and the continuing
device.
But, you're going to want to
finish this as fast as possible,
because the user may be moving
the devices apart to leave.
For more about streams, check
out the Stream Programming Guide
on developer.apple.com.
>> Now, this is great for moving
things that wouldn't be
appropriate to put in the
userInfo dictionary, like images
or video content, such as in our
email handoff example earlier.
But, for document-based apps,
the handoff story is even
easier.
Because you get much of this
behavior for free.
UIDocument and NSDocument
automatically create
NSUserActivity objects to
represent the document that is
currently being edited.
And, this works great for all
documents stored in iCloud.
All you have to do in your
applications is configure your
info.plist accordingly.
In addition to app-to-app
handoff, we also support
app-to-web browser handoff.
If you have a great web
experience to go alongside your
native app experience, and the
continuing device doesn't have
your native app installed, you
can handoff to Safari, and
continue the activity right in
the web browser.
>> Handoff also supports web
browser-to-app handoffs.
You need to configure a list of
approved app IDs on your web
server, and then you need to add
an associated domain entitlement
in your iOS app.
And then, the user can
seamlessly continue from your
web experience to your app on
iOS.
For even more about this, check
out this great Handoff talk from
2014.
>> So, that's Handoff.
Go out and implement it in your
applications.
Truly delight your users, and as
an added bonus, the
NSUserActivity API is used all
over the system experiences.
In things like Spotlight search,
and the new Siri Shortcuts
feature.
For more about these, check out
these talks, from previous
WWDCs.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> You write amazing apps and
experiences.
But, from time to time, you have
problems that you need to
investigate.
And, for that, we're going to
teach you some Matrix-level
debugging skills.
But first, a word of warning.
Before we give you this red
pill, and show you just how deep
the rabbit hole goes, I want to
let you know that the methods
that we're going to show you in
this section are great for
debugging, but must not be
submitted to the App Store.
If you do, your application will
be rejected, and you'll have a
bad day.
So, with that warning, let's get
started.
We're going to start with a
detective mindset.
How you should approach problems
that you find in your program.
Next, we're going to talk to you
about how to debug issues with
your views and view controllers.
We're going to teach you about
LLDB, and how you can use it to
identify state issues in your
app.
And finally, we're going to look
at some techniques for some
great memory issues that you
might run into that make you
feel less than great.
So, let's start with a detective
mindset.
When you're looking at a problem
in your program, you want to
make sure to verify your
assumptions.
What do you expect your program
to be doing?
And then, verify that it's
actually doing that.
This can be a great step, when
you start to debug issues in
your app.
Once you're pretty sure which of
your assumptions is being
violated, you can start by
looking for clues.
You'll use the tools that we'll
show you during this section to
poke and prod at your objects
and structs.
And then, you're going to want
to test your hunches, by
changing state in your app, and
verifying that you found the
issue.
Let's start with a sample bug
that's a real bug.
One of the great things that I
get the privilege of working on
here at Apple, is the screenshot
editor.
Recently, we were debugging an
issue, where my screenshot pen
tools were missing, which is
pretty bad.
Ben, are there any tools we can
use to help diagnose this issue?
>> Absolutely.
Built right into Xcode, is the
View Debugger.
You can launch it by simply
clicking on this icon in the
bottom toolbar.
And, Xcode will show you a 3D
representation of your entire
view hierarchy.
As you can see here, our pencil
controls are still there, but
they're being occluded by this
full screen view in front of it.
So, we need to go and look at
where we're building this UI,
and see what's happening with
the ordering there, Peter, I
think.
>> That's great.
The Xcode View Debugger is a
wonderful tool for debugging
view issues in your app.
There are even more tools that
you can use to help out with
this.
UIView recursiveDescription,
UIView parentDescription, and
the class method
UIViewController printHierarchy
are great tools for debugging
view and view controller issues
in your app.
Again, they're also great things
to not include when you submit
to the App Store.
It's important to note that
these are Objective-C selectors.
So, before using them, you'll
want to put your debugger into
Objective-C mode, using this
command.
We're going to walk through each
of these debugging methods,
step-by-step, and how they can
help you, starting with UIView
recursiveDescription.
>> So, UIView
recursiveDescription will print
the view hierarchy of the
receiver -- the subview
hierarchy.
And, some associated properties
to help you understand the
layout attributes.
Let's take a look at an example.
We have another bug in our
screenshots UI with a missing
view.
So, we're going to call
recursiveDescription on our
viewController's view.
Now, this might look like a wall
of debug text, and that's
because it is.
But, we know what we're looking
for.
Our screenshots view is there.
We can see it.
And, on inspection, we can see
that it is currently hidden.
So, we need to go and look at
everywhere we're setting the
hidden property on this view,
and really understand why it's
not showing.
In addition to
recursiveDescription, UIView
also has parentDescription,
which will walk up the view
hierarchy to the parent views,
until it reaches no -- to a nil
parent.
It'll print the same kind of
debugging information.
>> RecursiveDescription and
parentDescription are great for
UIView issues.
But, sometimes you have a
problem with UIViewControllers.
And, for that you can use the
great class method,
UIViewController printHierarchy.
Recently we had a bug in our
screenshot editor, where one of
our viewControllers had not yet
received the viewDidAppear
message.
And so, it hadn't set up its
state appropriately.
By running UIViewController
printHierarchy, we can get an
output of all of our presenting
viewControllers, our presented
viewControllers, our
parentViewControllers and
childViewControllers, and even
our presentationControllers.
It's Controllerpalooza.
So, let's run printHierarchy in
our screenshot UI.
Here we can see our
viewController hierarchy.
And, when we inspect the
viewController that we're having
the problem with, we can see
that it's stuck in the appearing
state.
So, we had missed a callback.
And so, we need to look into our
app to where we're calling this
callback, and then we found the
issue.
So, great.
Using these methods, you can
identify view and viewController
issues.
But, sometimes you have a more
fundamental issue with your app.
And, for that we can use some
great state debugging tips that
we have for you.
LLDB's expression command can
let you run arbitrary code in
the debugger.
Think about that.
Any code that you can run in the
source editor, you can write
right in the debugger, and run
while your program is running.
This is so useful for debugging.
You can call functions on your
structs, get properties on your
objects, and better diagnose
what your program is doing.
For even more about debugging,
check out this great talk on how
to debug with LLDB from 2012,
and how to debug with Swift from
2014.
There's some great functions
that you can run inside of LLDB
with the expression command,
that we're going to teach you.
And, the first one, is dump.
[ Laughter ]
>> Dump will print all of your
Swift objects and structs
properties.
Let's go through another bug
that we have in some of our
custom UI.
We have a view with a number of
subviews, including some labels,
and an imageView.
And, right now one of our labels
is missing.
So, we're going to run dump on
our parent view, and take a look
at what's going on here.
So, we've found our missing
label.
It is here, but it's -- if we
bring up and look at the
imageView that's alongside it,
we notice that the frame of
these two things, they both have
the same origin.
So, what's likely happening
here, is that the label is
obstructed by the imageView.
So, we need to go and look at
our layout code again, I think.
In addition to dump for Swift
objects, if you still have some
Objective-C code lying around,
NSObject also has the
ivarDescription method.
This will print all of the
instance variables of your
Objective-C objects.
We have another bug in our
screenshot's code, where our
crop handles aren't working for
some reason.
If we call ivarDescription on
our screenshot's view, we can
see by looking closely, that our
cropEnabled ivar is currently
set to no.
So, we have a good place to
start investigating this bug.
>> That's great.
Using dump and ivarDescription
are great ways to diagnose
problems with your app.
Another wonderful debugging tip
and trick that we have for you
is breakpoints.
Breakpoints let you pause the
program at arbitrary states of
execution, and run commands.
And, using the LLDB command
line, or the Xcode UI, you can
even add conditions before these
breakpoints are run, and
commands to run every time the
breakpoint is hit.
Breakpoints are an essential
part of your debugging workflow.
And, you can use the expression
command, and dump, and
ivarDescription, with the
breakpoints that you set up in
Xcode.
I really encourage you to use
breakpoints next time you're
debugging an issue with your
app.
But, sometimes we don't have an
issue with views or
viewControllers.
We don't have an issue with
state, instead we have a really
hairy memory management issue.
Ben, are there any tools we can
use for this?
>> Well, I'm glad you asked
Peter, because yes, there is
another great tool built into
Xcode.
The Xcode memory debugger.
This tool will help you
visualize exactly how your
application is using memory.
Peter and I were debugging an
issue the other day, where we
had a leaking viewController.
And, we could see that here that
it's being held onto by a block.
By enabling Malloc stack
logging, we were able to see the
full backtrace of exactly when
this block was allocated.
By zooming in, we can see that
this block was actually created
by that viewController.
And so, that block is holding
onto that viewController.
But that viewController is also
holding onto the block.
And, there's our retain cycle.
>> Wow.
Great! The Xcode memory graph
debugger is such a great tool
for diagnosing issues like this
in your app.
For even more, check out the
Debugging with Xcode 9 talk from
2017.
So, that's how you can debug
your app like a pro.
Make sure to think like a
detective whenever you encounter
problems with your program.
Use the Xcode view debugger, and
memory graph debugger to dive
deep on view- and memory-related
issues.
And, use LLDB's expression
command with dump, and all the
other great debugging methods we
talked about here.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> So, we've covered six really
exciting topics this morning,
this afternoon.
But, we've barely scratched the
surface.
We encourage you to go out and
check out the talks that we
referenced throughout this
presentation, and add even more
delight to your applications.
>> For more information, check
out our page on the developer
portal, and thank you.
We hope you had a great
conference.
>> Thank you.