[ Music ]
>> Hi. I'm Conor Hughes from the
iOS Accessibility team and I'm
here to talk about making your
drags and drops in iOS
accessible.
Let's get started.
Let's briefly go over what we're
going to cover.
We'll start with a very brief
refresher of the basics of Drag
and Drop.
Then, we'll go into come
concepts behind the
Accessibility Drag and Drop API.
And then, we'll go into some
examples, first, exposing an
ancestor's drag from an
accessibility element, and then
exposing multiple drops from an
Accessibility element.
To recap Drag and Drop at a high
level, Drag and Drop is a
technology introduced with iOS
11 and provides powerful ways
for someone using your
application to transfer data
both within the application and
between applications.
Drag and Drop introduced the
concept of interactions, which
are hosted by views in your
application.
To start a drag from a view, you
add a UIDrag interaction object
to it.
To accept a drop, you add a
UIDrop interaction.
If you're not familiar with
these classes you should watch
the Introducing Drag and Drop
session from WWDC2017 for more
information, and then come back
to this video.
Now, let's start to talk about
accessibility.
Of course, you want to expose
the power of your Drag and Drop
interactions to people using
your app through an assistive
technology like Voiceover.
There are a few accessibility
problems the accessibility Drag
and Drop API's were designed to
solve.
First, your accessibility
element might not host
interactions directly.
For instance, your accessibility
element might be a view whose
subviews host interactions.
Or your element might descend
from a view that hosts
interactions that are logically
associated with it.
The solution is that the
Accessibility Drag and Drop
API's allow you to specify
logical drags and drops to the
system in a way that makes them
usable with assistive
technologies.
Let's get into those API's now.
The UIAccessibilityDragging
informal protocol defines two
properties that you use to
express drags and drops to
Accessibility.
It deals with the concept of
Drag Sources and Drop Points.
Drag Sources describe where to
start drags that are associated
with an element and Drop Points
describe places associated with
an element where items can be
dropped.
To use these properties, you can
assign to them or override the
getter to provide data on
demand.
These drags and drops are
exposed to users of assistive
technologies in much the same
way as Accessibility custom
actions are.
So, that's the API, there.
Often, drags and drops are
exposed automatically to
Accessibility by the system.
And if they're found
automatically they're assigned a
default name but note that only
interactions in an element
subtree are automatically
exposed.
The UIAccessibilityDragging
protocol allows you to expose
exactly the interactions that
make sense, wherever they may
actually live in your View
hierarchy.
Allows you to specify a great
name for each one.
So, you should really consider
implementing it to provide the
best experience for someone
using your application through
an assistive technology.
Now, let's look at an example of
how you can expose drags with
the UIAccessibilityDragging
informal protocol.
Let's say we're building a bar
graph and we've chosen to draw
the bars by configuring CALayer
objects.
And we're going to try and
enable dragging of the bars
themselves, to drag the bar
data.
So, here is an example of how
that might look.
And again, each of these bars is
going to be a CALayer object.
How would we go about
implementing drag for this?
It might look something like
this.
Note that because layers aren't
views they can't host
interactions.
So, the bar graph itself has the
interaction installed.
And in this itemsForBeginning
session callback, depending on
the bar that is hit tested, we
return different data in the
drag item.
Note that even though I only
have one drag interaction I am
using it to support multiple
logical drags.
This is a totally supported
approach and it is an example of
how powerful, in general, the
base Drag and Drop API's are.
Now, how do you make this
accessible?
A good approach to making a
graph like this accessible is to
expose each bar as an
Accessibility element, which
I've done here.
Note that what I'm doing here is
providing data about the logical
structure of my app's content to
the Accessibility Runtime.
That enables assistive
technologies to expose the
content in a different way.
We'll need to do the same thing
to make the drags accessible,
and to do so we'll need to learn
some more specifics about the
UIAccessibilityDragging informal
protocol.
First, let's learn about the
class UIAccessibility
LocationDescriptor.
This class is data that
describes where an interaction
is by specifying a point in a
view with a particular name.
So, for an example in our bar
graph, a location descriptor for
dragging that bar there, might
look like this.
Its name might be Drag Bar Data.
The view would be the bar graph
view itself.
And the point would be a point
that's located within the bar.
So, what do we do with
UIAccessibility
LocationDescriptor options?
Well, we assign them to the two
properties mentioned earlier.
The two properties in the
protocol are accessibilityDrag
SourceDescriptors and
accessibilityDrop
PointDescriptors.
DragSourceDescriptors is used to
expose drag sources that are
logically associated with an
element and DropPointDescriptors
exposes places to drop that are
logically associated with this
element.
These are the properties you use
to describe to Accessibility
what can be dragged from and
dropped into a given element.
One important point to be aware
of is that the descriptors must
reference the View that actually
has the interaction.
So, for instance, you shouldn't
reference a point in your window
that happens to be within the
View that hosts the interaction.
You should specify that view
itself.
So, pulling it together; to
expose a single drag from some
element doesn't take that much
code, at all.
You make a Descriptor that
specifies that drag by
specifying a point in the View
that hosts the interaction and
giving it a name.
And then, you set the
accessibilityDrag
SourceDescriptors property
element to an array that
includes that descriptor.
Let's go back to our bar graph
code that set the Accessibility
elements of the graph view.
What do we need to do to expose
dragging each element?
We compute a point within the
bar represented by that element
in the View's coordinate space,
make an appropriate descriptor
with that point in that View.
And set the accessibilityDrag
SourceDescriptors property of
the element.
And that's it.
Now, let's look at a slightly
different example.
Let's try to expose multiple
drops from a single element.
This might be useful for a
situation like a contact card,
where the card is small enough
that we're going to expose it as
one element to Accessibility.
But there are multiple wells
into which we can drop content
into the card.
So, for instance, it might have
a portrait and a space for you
to drop arbitrary attachments
for that contact.
Now, that we know how to use the
UIAccessibilityDragging informal
protocol, exposing these is
straightforward.
We can override the
accessibilityDrop
PointDescriptors getter of the
View, compute the midpoints of
the two wells, and then return
two location descriptors that
name each drop point.
So, in summary, because you want
everyone to be able to use all
the cool features you build into
your app, you want to make sure
that the drags and drops
associated with Accessibility
elements in your app are exposed
to assistive technologies.
To do so, use the
accessibilityDrag
SourceDescriptors property to
specify what drag should be
exposed, and the
accessibilityDrop
PointDescriptors property to
specify what drop should be
exposed.
Finally, these properties are
just arrays of UIAccessibility
LocationDescriptor objects,
which describe to Accessibility
where these drags and drops are
in your application and how to
activate them.
For more information, you can
check out this video online.
And thanks for watching.