[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Good afternoon and welcome to
Getting the Most out of
Playgrounds in Xcode.
My name is Tibet Rooney-Rabdau
and with me today are my
teammates Alex Brown and TJ
Usiyan.
I love that every time I have a
new coding idea I can jump right
into a playground to try it out.
In today's session we will share
with you our favorite work
flows.
This is a great session for
those not too familiar with
playgrounds in Xcode, as well as
those diving deeper.
We're going to start out todays
talk with playground
fundamentals, a brief overview
of playgrounds, markup, and
imbedded resources.
Then we'll show you how to run
step-by-step in a playground.
We'll discuss tips to give you
more control of your code
execution.
Lastly we'll finish with
advanced techniques including
the wonderful world of Custom
Playground Display Convertible.
We will use this protocol to
customize your inline results.
We will also discuss how to use
workspaces to exercise code in
your frameworks.
Playgrounds provides an
interactive place to explore
Swift, create learning
environments or others, and
prototype parts of your app.
Let's get started with a quick
tour of Playgrounds in Xcode.
When you first open a
playground, Xcode shows you the
standard editor.
This is the basic editor mode
you use in Xcode with a couple
additions.
What is unique about this editor
when you're in a playground is
the result sidebar on the right
hands side displaying the result
of each expression in your code.
You also have the ability to add
these results as inline results.
This is done by selecting the
rectangular button beside your
result in the result sidebar.
This will then show your result
inline with your Swift Code.
In this example you can see this
demonstrated where "Hello,
playground" is added below our
string variable declaration.
Let's take a look at the
assistant editor mode.
What is interesting about this
mode in Playgrounds in Xcode is
that you can visualize your
results in more detail by using
a live view.
In this example I've created a
live view using UIView that
shows a welcome message.
But you could also use
UIViewController for iOS and
[inaudible] playgrounds and for
macOS playgrounds NSView and
NSViewController.
Now let me show you a short
snippet that demonstrates how to
show Live View.
First you need to import
PlaygroundSupport.
PlaygroundSupport is a framework
provided by Xcode to allow
playgrounds to interact with
Xcode, including support for
showing live views.
You import this playground
support framework so you can use
its API.
Once you've created a
viewController using the
standard UIKit or AppKit APIs,
you need to hand it over to the
PlaygroundSupport framework.
You do this by setting the Live
View property of the current
playground page to your
viewController.
This signals to Xcode that it
should show your viewController
in the assistant editor.
To give your playgrounds an
extra bit of polish, you can
include some markup text.
It is especially great when
you're making a playground to
share with others.
With markup you can include
stylized text, images, and video
in your playground.
Now let's take a quick
walkthrough what is possible
with markup.
Here I've included some markup
comments with text for a poem
I'm writing.
A markup comment is like a
regular comment but with a colon
after the forward slashes.
The rest of the comment is then
treated as markup text.
If you have multiple lines of
comments next to each other they
form one block of markup text.
You can also use multiline
comments by putting a colon
after the first asterisks.
Here's our markup in Xcode now.
It is showing the raw markup of
the poem I wrote.
To show it in its rendered form,
select the button in the top
right corner of the window,
which shows Xcode's Inspector.
Then select Render Documentation
under Playground Settings.
The lines in my poem are now
rendered.
Other interesting things you can
do with the markup are adding
headings to a Playground peach.
You can use headings to create
structure in your playground.
You can use number signs to
supply up to three levels of
heading.
In this example the title of my
poem "Roses are Red" as a first
level heading, the subtitle, "An
Ode to Markup" as a second level
heading, and the byline as a
third level heading.
Remember to add at least one
space between the number sign
and the heading string,
otherwise you'll have a number
sign connected to your heading
when rendered.
This is what the headings look
like rendered when included with
the lines in my poem.
You can see that the first level
heading is largest, followed by
the second level, and then the
third level heading.
You can also format the text in
your markup content.
You can wrap a string of
characters on a single asterisk
on each side to italicize the
text between the asterisks.
You can also use backticks to
display text with Code Font.
Finally, if you use two
asterisks instead of one the
text will be bold.
Let's take a look at this
rendered.
You can see that red and blue
are italicized.
Markup is in Code Font and fun
is in bold.
Let's take a look at using lists
in markup.
If a markup comment starts with
a number followed by a period,
it will create an item in a
numbered list.
In this example, I've added the
lines of my poem to a numbered
list.
Here you can see the lines of my
poem rendered in a number list,
each line representing an item
in a numbered list.
You can also create a bullet to
list in markup.
A bulleted list is like a number
list except each line starts
with an asterisks instead of a
number.
This is how my poem in rendered
in a bulleted list with each
line in my poem represented as a
bulleted item in a bulletin
list.
Markup can also contain links.
In this example I've created a
link to roses and violets.
To create a link you wrap the
text in brackets and then place
the destination of the link in
parentheses after.
Another way you can create a
link is by using a reference.
In this example I've created a
reference named 1, but this can
be any string.
It doesn't have to be a number.
When creating and using a link
reference you wrap the name in
brackets.
When creating a reference you
add a colon and then the
destination to the link.
Here are the links represented
in rendered form, Roses,
Violets, and Fun are shown in
blue to represent a link.
Up to this point we treated a
playground as a single location,
but playgrounds can contain
multiple pages, each with their
own markup and code.
To create a new playground page,
select the playground and then
open the file menu.
Select New, then Playground
Page.
You could also create a
playground page by control
clicking on the playground and
then selecting New Playground
Page.
You can create links in your
markup, which navigate between
pages.
To go to the previous page, you
can create a link where the
destination is @previous.
To go to the next page you can
create a link where the
destination is @next.
Finally, if you want to navigate
to a specific page, you create a
link where the destination is
the file name for that page
without the extension and by
replacing any spaces or special
characters with their percent in
coded form.
You can also imbed some
additional content to make you
playgrounds even more powerful.
You can add additional Swift
files to the sources folder,
which is at the top level of the
playground.
Each page also has its own
sources folder.
Sources are compiled as separate
modules where they are
automatically imported where
visible so you don't have to
handle import statements.
Since these are compiled as
separate modules, you can use
access control to control what
is exported from your axillary
sources.
Anything you want to use as your
main playground source should be
marked as Public.
A great example of things to put
into the sources folder is
helper code such as classes or
extensions that are outside of
the main playground.
Playgrounds can also contain
other resources.
Resources are any other file
that you'd like to use in your
playground such as images,
audio, video, storyboards, and
ZIPs.
Just like sources, there's a
resources folder at the top
level of the playground as well
as for each page.
You can use these resources that
you've added to your playground
both in your markup and code.
Similar to how you create a link
in your playground, you can use
this highlighted syntax to imbed
an image in your markup.
You specify the image name, in
this case MyPicture.jpg.
You also specify alternate text
describing the image along with
hover title text that shows my
pointer is over the image.
Both alternate text and hover
title text can also be used for
accessibility to benefit
voiceover users.
And here we access the same
imaging code using the standard
UIImage or NSImage APIs.
Similarly, to images you can
also imbed videos in your
markup.
This is done by using a syntax
similar for that images with
additional support for
specifying a poster image along
with the width and height of the
video.
For other resources that you
want to access in code, such as
this video, you can use the
standard Bundle APIs for finding
resources.
This example uses a URL for
resource with extension API to
ask the main bundle for URL for
Mvideo.mp4.
Resources in your playground are
automatically treated as
resources of the main bundle.
For more information on the
markup you can use in your
playgrounds and the playground
support framework we discussed
earlier, please visit
developer.apple.com.
With that please welcome my
teammate Alex Brown to the stage
so he can tell you more about
exciting new changes to
playgrounds in Xcode 10.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Tibet.
I'm Alex Brown and I'm a Core OS
Engineer.
I want to ask you a question.
Have you ever woken up with a
great coding idea but then
struggled to set it down before
you reach your code editor?
Perhaps it's your inbox that
gets in the way or perhaps you
haven't yet set up your project
within Xcode.
Whether you're a beginner just
getting started with Apple APIs,
a seasoned engineer with a
deadline, or a data scientist
building machine learning
models, I want to tell you that
Xcode playgrounds are the
fastest way to get started
coding against Apple's APIs.
In Xcode 10, playgrounds are
faster and more responsive than
ever allowing you to execute
your code in a step-by-step
fashion.
First I'd like to get you
familiar with a new UI for doing
this.
If you're familiar with
playgrounds, your eye should
immediately jump to the blue
line over the not line numbers.
There's a new play button which
tracks your pointer.
A blue line over the line
numbers mean these lines are
ready to execute and when you
click the Play button this means
run all of the blue lines up to
and including the one with the
play button on it.
Let's see what that looks like.
There we go.
You can see just the first three
lines of the playground are
executed.
The results are visible on the
right-hand side.
You can also see that the play
button has now gone gray.
This indicates that these lines
of code are no longer ready to
execute.
You just executed them.
There's a second reason that
they play button might be gray.
This means you're hovering over
some code, which is not a
top-level line of code.
This includes code inside
function brackets and inside of
fall loop.
If you wish to execute a fall
loop you need to move your
pointer to the closing brace
where the play button will go
blue then you'll be able to
execute it.
There's also a great keyboard
shortcut, Shift Return.
This is just like pressing
Return at the end of typing a
line of code, but it also means
execute this line, and it move
the cursor to the next line
ready to write some more code.
Blue code also has a second
interpretation.
It means code that it's safe to
edit without resetting your
playground.
Why is this important?
If you edit code above the blue
line this is modifying code that
you've already executed.
So you'll have to resent your
playground to take account of
your changes.
When you edit code above the
blue line, the playground resets
automatically.
Sometimes you'll need to reset
your playground manually and you
can do this using the stop
button in the Debug bar at the
bottom of the screen.
So why run in a step-by-step
fashion?
Why have we added this feature?
Firstly, executing just one more
line is fast.
It's way faster than restarting
a playground and waiting for it
to catch up with your thoughts.
Secondly, it allows you to
respond to live data.
Write a line of code, execute
it, see what the results are,
and this should lead you
naturally to the next line of
code to write.
And thirdly rerunning a
playground every time can give
you different values every time.
This can happen, for instance,
if you're accessing a network
resource or you're generating
random numbers.
By executing step-by-step your
data model stays stable and
easier to understand.
So let's take a look at a simple
example that you can try
yourselves.
I like games.
I like card games and board
games and computer games.
I even like writing games.
Now I'm not too hot at it so I
like to keep my games small.
This is a really small game.
It's the game of roshambo.
It's the schoolyard game of
rock, paper, scissors.
I've written the rules as a
simple function check, which
tells us if we've won.
I've also written a computer
player, which simply makes one
of the moves at random.
By executing step-by-step we can
execute line six where the
computer player plays and see
what the result is before making
our move.
In this case the computer player
has played "rock" and we've
played "paper".
Paper beats rock and we win the
game.
This might sound a little bit
like cheating, but it's an
extremely powerful technique.
It's an extremely powerful
technique when you're trying to
learn a new and unfamiliar API
or exploring a data structure
whose types and values you don't
yet know.
So that's a very simple example.
Now we're going to look at
something a little bit more
magical with a demo.
[ Applause ]
So we started off with one game,
I'm going to move on to another.
This is the game of Tic-tac-toe.
I've already been working on
this a little while.
I've built the game engine and
I've made a first version of the
UI.
I've moved all of that code
aside into the auxiliary
sources.
This gets it out of our way and
allows us to focus on the next
steps -- actually playing the
game and refining the UI a
little.
I'm also going to use a live
view, but first let's look back
at the blue control over the
line numbers.
You can see that it tracks the
mouse pointer.
So let's get started by loading
the game board.
Let's rotate it so we can see
it.
This is the Tic-tac-toe game
board.
You can see I've been able to
execute the first half of the
playground and I've still got
some lines left in the
playground to execute.
These include my first move.
Let's run that.
There we go.
So you can see we're going to be
playing the game in code and
viewing the results with the
live view.
Let's let the computer play and
have a turn.
Few, that's great.
The computer player is
completely random.
So it's just possible it's going
to beat me today.
[ Laughter ]
So I've shown you how we can
execute some of the lines of
code and then step-by-step
execute lines of code which are
already present in the
playground.
But we can do more than that.
It's always safe to add new code
at the end of a playground.
So let's make another move.
There we go.
Now, I can click the Play button
to execute this line of code and
I think now we'll let the
computer have another go.
That's great.
[ Laughing ]
You should notice a couple of
things here.
Number one, in the beginning the
board was flat.
I had to rotate it so it was in
a position where we could view
it.
As we execute more lines of
code, it doesn't rotate back to
its original position.
This is pretty good because I
could write lines of code to
rotate it to the correct
position, but this would involve
something called [inaudible],
and I don't think I'm quite
ready to learn that yet.
The second reason it's good is
because if the computer player
was allowed to play again, every
time we executed new code it
would effectively get a do-over,
which would be a little unfair.
Let's finish this up.
I think I can take the game home
from here.
Is that the right move?
That's great.
[ Applause ]
You can see the game has
highlighted my winning move by
placing three red circles.
That's not too fancy.
I'm looking for something which
really makes it feel like a
celebration.
So I've been working on a new
version of the UI.
In a traditional development
environment, you would have to
set up a complex harness to
automatically play you deep into
the game or whatever the API was
you were using so that we could
test out something that happened
later on in the program.
But in a playground, because I'm
able to execute step-by-step, I
can play it manually to the end
of the game and then write new
lines of code to update
whatever's going on at that
point.
Let's do that now.
I've prepared a new effect for
the end of the game using a
particle system.
Let's use Shift Return to
execute it.
Boom. And that feels much more
like a win.
[ Applause ]
So let's review what we've just
seen.
By running step-by-step we can
explore an idea a line at a
time.
This enables us to have a
conversation between code and
data.
Every time we learn a new fact
we can write the next line of
code to explore it a little
more.
We can use Shift Return to keep
our hands on the keyboard and
our brains in the zone.
And finally, by adding a dynamic
live view to a playground, we
can create a second view of our
model and we can seamlessly
shift between manipulating it in
a graphical environment and
using code.
So whether you're a beginner,
just learning about new Apple
APIs or an experienced
programmer trying to sketch out
the bones of their next great
app, the next time you have a
coding inspiration we invite you
to get started with a
playground.
Just in case you're still
looking for ideas I've got three
right here.
Number one if you're creating
your own API, one of the best
ways to showcase it is to create
a follow along tutorial for your
API.
Users can execute the code
step-by-step and see in real
time what it does.
Number two you can download and
explore some publicly available
data using the playground
step-by-step to drill down into
your data.
You could get this from maps,
from local government, or
perhaps a class project.
Finally, like I did, you could
create a game or an animation.
Start off simple using SpriteKit
or SyncKit and line by line
enhance it until it's completely
awesome.
So I hope we've shown you today
that playgrounds are not a toy.
They're fun but they're serious
fun.
They allow you to explore code
and data interactively.
This is great whether you've
downloaded an unknown snippet of
JSON using a rest API from the
Internet, or if you're dealing
with hundreds of thousands or
millions of lines of data for a
machine learning application.
And to find out more about that
use case I encourage you to
download and watch the Create ML
sessions in your WWDC
application.
Secondly there's really no
better way to learn how to use
Apple APIs.
Whether you're just getting
started or your trying out a new
API, which you've learned about
at this WWDC.
You don't just have to use
Apple's APIs.
You can also import your own
frameworks into playgrounds.
And one of the best ways to
showcase this is to create
custom representations of your
data types allowing developers
to view the most relevant
information at a glance.
And to talk more about these two
advanced concepts, I'd like to
invite TJ to the stage.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Alex.
My name is TJ Usiyan and I'm an
Xcode Engineer.
By the time I finish my section,
I'm sure that all of you will
agree that every librarian
framework that you ship will and
can be improved with the
addition of a playground.
Playgrounds provide a richer
experience when providing
readme's, tutorials, and general
API documentation.
One of the ways that they can do
this is by, as Alex said,
providing your own
representation in playgrounds.
I'm going to cover all of these
things starting with Custom
Playground Display Convertible,
which will allow you to provide
custom representations of your
types in playgrounds so that
users can get a nice summary.
I'll follow that up with how to
import your frameworks into
playgrounds.
And finally, I'll cover a little
bit of troubleshooting tips for
when things don't go exactly as
you'd expect.
Let's start with Playground
Display Convertible.
So as you know, when a user
types in a line of code values
show up on the right hand side
in the result sidebar.
For types that are no optimized
for playgrounds there are two
ways that playgrounds will
generate this description.
For types that do not conform to
Custom String Convertible, we
will create a structured
representation using the Swift
type.
For types that do conform to
Custom String Convertible, we
will use the result of calling
descriptions.
When this isn't enough sometimes
your users will tap on the Quick
Look button on the right-hand
side.
They will also tap or click on
the Inline Results button.
When they do this a custom
representation will show up.
Often a textual representation.
And for many types this is
perfectly enough but sometimes
maybe you would like to return a
number.
This is still text though and
there are times when text isn't
going to be enough and you would
like to return something
graphical, maybe a picture.
The way to control what you
return is to implement Custom
Playground Display Convertible,
a new protocol introduced in
Xcode 9.3 and Swift 4.1.
It replaces Custom Playground
Quick Lookable, which was
deprecated in the same versions.
Let's take a look at conformance
right now.
You can see here that conforming
involves only returning one
property, Playground
Description.
Playground Description is of
type Any, which means you can
return anything that you feel
best describes your value.
Now, there are certain types
that have specialized
representations already and
those are provided by Apple.
Here's a list of the types with
specialized representations as
of Xcode 9.3 and Swift 4.1.
The types on the left have a
particularly textual
representation.
The types on the right have a
graphical representation.
I invite you to try each of
these and decide which best
represents your value in a
playground.
Once you've done this you'll
want to ship all of your types,
and your values, and your API to
your users.
I'm going to show you how to
import your own custom
frameworks into playgrounds
alongside Apple frameworks.
Typically, when you build a
single framework in a project,
that framework will end up in
the Built Products Directory.
When you want to import it into
a playground, that is where the
playground will work.
The simplest way to make sure
that your playground will see
your framework is to add the
playground to your project.
This is the strategy that I
suggest for simple projects
where you have access the
project and are willing to edit
it.
This is what that would look
like in the Project Navigator.
Once you've added this project,
or once you've added this
playground to your project, I
have a little bit of advice.
Remember building is very much
like walking in that you have to
remember to build before you
run.
Now, sometimes you have more
than one project, more than one
framework, maybe you have two,
three, four, and in this case
that Built Products Directory
situation that I just described
is actually multiplied.
There are multiple Build Product
Directories if you have separate
projects.
This can be a problem when you
want to import your code into a
playground.
The simplest way to address this
is to add each project to a
workspace, a single workspace,
and then when you build each
project, those frameworks will
end up in that one Built
Products Directory for your
workspace.
After that just add the
playground to that workspace and
everything should be fine.
This is what that should look
like in the project navigator.
Now, let's say you've done this,
you followed my instructions and
things don't work out how you
expect.
You say, "TJ lied to me."
You're going to want to check
the Built Products Directory to
make sure that everything ends
up there as you expect.
Here's how you can do that.
You're going to go to File,
Project Settings, and then we're
going to click the Advanced
button.
On this screen in light gray
we'll see that there is a
Products destination.
You'll click on that and that
should bring you directly to the
Built Products Director for the
project that you have open.
This is what that should look
like in Finder.
Now let's see all of this
brought together in a demo.
[ Applause ]
Now those of you who know me
know that I have a pretty
enduring interest in music.
I'm actually so interested in
music that I have found this new
notation, well new to me
notation, called Helmholtz
notation.
And I feel that many, many
people should know about this
and it should be much more
widely used.
So I've created a framework to
share with other developers so
that they can use it in their
code.
You can see here that I've
included a playground and I've
also, as the result of extensive
research on Wikipedia written up
a little playground that
describes the notation.
Follow it, followed by a few
values so that we can see the
results on the right hand side
with the notation.
If I render this documentation
this will all end up in Pros
with the links highlighted in
blue just as Tibet spoke of.
And before I build, or before I
run I'm going to build.
Then let's run our playground,
yay.
[ Applause ]
You can see here that on the
right-hand side in the results I
have this interesting notation.
I really think that this
notation is interesting because
the lower pitches are
represented by uppercase
letters.
The higher pitches are
represented by lowercase letters
and the exact octave is
indicated by either commas or
apostrophes, the count thereof.
Now, hopefully you all get this
looking at this notation, and
hopefully I've explained it very
well, but I've actually had some
trouble with some of the people
I'm tutoring.
They're not taking to it as well
as I'd like.
So I actually have a separate
framework that I've created with
a keyboard visualization that I
think will really help them ease
into this notation.
Since I want to use that, I'm
actually going to create a
separate playground in a
workspace where I can import
both frameworks without changing
either of the frameworks.
So to do that I'm going to
quickly close this, I'm going to
create a brand new workspace by
going to File, New Work Space,
and I'm going to name this
Tutoring.
Just put that on the desktop.
Then I'm going to add each
framework by going to File, Add
Files.
I'm going to start with
Helmholtz, my framework that I
just had open, then File, right
there, Keyboard.
Then I'm going to add a new
playground by going to File,
New, Playground.
A blank playground is fine.
My Playground is a fine name, a
fine as name as any.
I'm going to start by importing
Helmholtz, and My Keyboard.
After that I'm just going to
quickly do a little test to make
sure that pitches show up as I
expect.
I'm going to build each of my
frameworks.
I'm going to make sure to choose
each one from the schemes.
Later on I might want to make a
separate scheme that builds both
of these projects in one go, but
I don't have time on stage right
now.
And then I'm going to run My
Playground in it.
Everything works as expected.
But again this visualization is
not helping.
I have some younger students who
have only seen a piano, so I
have a little snippet here that
quickly creates a view in
playground description,
configures it, and actually I
have one more line that I wanted
to write on stage.
Custom text equals description.
And after I configure my view
I'm going to return it.
Simple as that.
Made much simpler by the fact
that I happen to have a
framework already on hand.
Now, I want to run this line,
line 4 again, but with my
conformant.
So I'm going to reset this
playground by clicking on the
stop button down here.
And then I'm going to rerun this
entire playground after I add my
inline result.
And you can see here --
[ Applause ]
You can see here that I have a
nice visualization of a keyboard
that my students can recognize
along with the notation that I'm
trying to teach.
Now let's cover or let's go back
over what we've learned today.
Tibet covered the fundamentals
of playgrounds, the layout and
playground markup syntax.
Alex explained the power of
running step-by-step in
playgrounds.
And I covered Custom Playground
Display Convertible and
importing your own code.
So hopefully, now that I've
given this session and all of us
have -- and we've explained
playgrounds and the power that
you can get, we hope to see that
every project has a playground
next year.
If you have any questions please
feel free to visit us in the
labs and we'll see you next
year.
[ Applause ]