[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Good afternoon.
My name is Shane.
I'm with the Darwin Runtime
team.
And I'd like to welcome you to
measuring performance using
logging.
So we heard a lot about
performance on Monday.
Performance is one of those
things that's key to a great
user experience.
People love it when their games
and their apps are fast,
dynamic, and responsive.
But software is complex so that
means that when your app is
trying to do something,
sometimes a ton of things can be
going on and that means you can
find some performance wins in
some pretty unlikely places.
But doing so, unearthing those
of performance wins requires an
understanding, sometimes a deep
understanding of what it is your
program is doing.
It requires you to know when
your code is executing exactly,
how long a particular operation
is taking.
So this is one place where a
good tool can make a real
difference.
And we know that building better
tools, making them available to
you, is one of the ways that we
can help you be a more
productive developer.
So today I'm going to talk about
one of those tools.
Today, I'm going to talk about
signposts.
Signposts are a new member of
the OSLog family.
And we're making them available
to you in macOS.
We're making them available to
you in iOs.
And you can use them in Swift
and in C, but the coolest thing
is we've integrated them with
Instruments.
So that means Instruments can
take the data that signposts
produce and give you a deep
understanding of what it is your
program is doing.
So first a little history.
We introduced OSLog a couple of
years ago.
It's our modern take on a
logging facility.
It's our way of getting
debugging information out of the
system.
And it was built with our goals
of efficiency and privacy in
mind.
Here you can see an example of
OSLog code where I've just
created a simple log handle and
posted a hello world to it.
Signposts extend the OSLog API,
but they do it for the
performance use case.
And that means they are
conveying performance related
information, and they're
integrated with our developer
tools and that means you can
annotate your code with
signposts and then pull up
Instruments and see something
like this.
So Instruments is showing you
this beautiful visualization of
a timeline of what your program
is doing and the signpost
activity there.
And then on the bottom there's
that table with statistical
aggregation and analysis of the
signpost data, slicing and
dicing to see what your
program's behavior is really
like.
In this session, I'll talk about
adopting signposts into your
code and show you some of what
they're capable of.
And then we're going to
demonstrate the new Instrument
signpost visualization to give
you an idea how signposts and
Instruments work together.
So let's start.
I'm going to start with a really
basic example.
Imagine that this is your app.
And what you're trying to
investigate is the amount of
time a particular part of the
interface takes to refresh.
And you know to do that you want
to load some images and put them
on the screen.
So once again, an abstract,
simple view of this app might be
that you're doing the work to
grab an asset.
And after you've gotten them
all, the interface is refreshed.
What a signpost allows us to do
is to mark the beginning and the
end of a piece of work and then
associate those two points in
time, those two log events with
each other.
And they do it with an os
signpost function call.
There are two calls.
One with .begin and one with
.end.
Here I've represented the begin
with that arrow with the b
underneath it.
And I represented the end with
the arrow with the e under it.
And then we're going to relate
those two points to each other
to give you a sense of what the
elapsed time is for that
interval.
All right.
In code, there's this simple
implementation of that algorithm
where for each element in our
interface, we're going to fetch
that asset and that's the piece
of operation that we're
interested in measuring.
So to incorporate signpost into
this code base, we're going to
simply import the module
os.signpost that contains that
functionality.
And then because signposts are
part of the OSLog functionality,
we're going to create a log
handle.
Here, this log handle takes two
arguments, a subsystem and a
category.
The subsystem is just probably
the same throughout your
project.
It looks a lot like your bundle
ID.
And it represents the component
or the piece of software, maybe
the framework that you're
working on.
The category is used to relate
-- to group related operations
together or related signposts.
And you'll see why that could be
useful later in the session.
Once we have that log handle,
we're just going to make two
calls to os signpost.
One with .begin.
One with .end.
We're going to pass that log
handle into those calls.
And then for the third argument,
we have a signpost name.
The signpost name is a string
literal that identifies the
interval that identifies the
operation that we're interested
in measuring.
That string literal is used to
match up the begin point that
we've annotated or that gets
marked up with that os signpost
begin called and the end point.
So on our timeline, it just
looks like this.
At the beginning of each piece
of work, we've dropped an os
signpost.
At the end of each piece of
work, we've dropped an os
signpost.
And because those string
literals at the begin and end
call sites line up with each
other, we can match those two
together.
But what if we're interested in
also measuring the entire amount
of time the whole operation,
that whole refresh took?
Well, in our code, we're just
going to add another pair of os
signpost begin and end calls.
Pretty simple.
And this time I've given it a
different string literal, so a
different signpost name.
This time refresh panel to
indicate that this is a separate
interval, separate from the one
inside the loop.
In our timeline, we're just
marking two additional
signposts.
And that matching string literal
of refresh panel will let the
system know that those two
points are associated with each
other.
All right.
It's not a super simple example.
If your program ever does step
one and then step two then step
three in a sequential fashion
then that would work.
But in our systems, often we
have a lot of work that happens
asynchronously.
Right.
So instead of having step one,
step two, step three, we're
often kicking things off in
sequence, right, and then
letting them complete later.
So that means that these
operations can happen
concurrently.
They can overlap.
In that case, we need to give
some additional piece of
information to the system in
order for it to tell those
signposts apart from each other.
And to do that, so far we've
only used that name.
Right.
That name will match up the end
and the beginning point.
So that string literal so far
has identified intervals, but it
hasn't given us a way to
discriminate between overlapping
intervals.
To do that, we're going to add
another piece of data to our
signpost calls called a signpost
ID.
The signpost ID will tell the
system that these are the same
kind of operation but each one
is different from each other.
So if two operations overlap but
they have different signpost
IDs, the system will know that
they're two different intervals.
As long as you pass the same
signpost ID at the begin call
site and the end call site,
those two signposts will be
associated with each other.
You can make signpost IDs with
this constructor here that takes
a log handle, but you can also
make them with an object.
This could be useful if you have
some object that represents the
work that you're trying to do
and the same signpost ID will be
generated as long as you use the
same instance of that object.
So this means you don't have to
carry or store the signpost ID
around.
You can just use the object
that's handy.
Visually, you can think of
signpost IDs as allowing us to
pass a little bit of extra
context to each signpost call
which can relate the begin and
end markers for a particular
operation with each other.
And this is important because
not only can these operations
overlap, but they often take
differing amounts of time.
Let's see this in our code
example.
So here's our code.
I'm going to transform that
synchronous fetch async call in
to an asynchronous one.
So here I'm just going to give
it a completion handler.
This is a closure that will run
after the fetch asset is
complete.
And then I've also added a
closure, a completion handler
for running after all the assets
have been fetched.
In each case, I've moved that os
signpost end call inside of a
closure to indicate that that's
when I want that marked period
of time to end.
Okay.
So because we think that these
intervals will overlap with each
other, we're going to create new
signpost IDs for each of them.
Notice in the top example I've
created one with the constructor
taking a log handle.
And the second one, I've made
off that object that is being
worked on, the element.
And then I simply pass those
signpost IDs into the call sites
and we're done.
You can think of signpost as
being organized as a kind of
classification or hierarchy.
Right.
All these operations are related
together by the log handle
meaning that log category.
And then for each operation that
we're interested in, we've given
it a signpost name.
Then because those signposts
could overlap with each other,
we've given them that signpost
ID that tells the system that
that's a specific instance of
that interval.
This interface was built
specifically to be flexible so
you control all the arguments
into your begin site and your
end site.
You control that signpost name,
the log handle you give it, and
the ID.
We've done this because as long
as you can give the same
arguments at the begin site and
the end site, those two
signposts will get matched with
each other.
That means your begin and end
sites can be in separate
functions.
They can be associated with
separate objects.
They may even live in separate
source files.
We've done this because we want
you to be able to adopt it into
your code base.
And so whatever entry and exit
conventions you have, you can
use these calls.
So that's how to measure
intervals with signposts.
You may want to convey some
additional information, some
additional performance relevant
information along with your
signposts.
And for that, we have a way to
add metadata to signpost calls.
So here's your basic signpost
call.
To that, we can add an
additional string literal
parameter.
This allows you to add some
context to your begin and end
call sites.
Perhaps you have multiple begin
and exit points for a particular
operation, but the string
literal is also an OSLog format
string.
And that means I can use it to
pass additional data into the
signpost.
So here, for example, I've used
that %d to pass in four
integers.
But because it's an OSLog format
string, I can also use it to
pass many arguments of different
types.
So here I've passed in some
floating-point numbers.
And I've even used the format
specifier to tell the system how
much precision I want.
You can pass dynamic strings in
with the string literal
formatter.
And that'll let us pass in
information that comes from a
function call or comes from a
user entered piece of
information.
And we reference that format
string literal with a fixed
amount of storage which means
that you can feel free to make
it as long and as human readable
as you like.
This human readable string is
the same one that will be
rendered up in the Instruments.
So you can feel free to give it
some context.
I've given it here for the
various arguments.
And Instruments will be able to
show that full rendered string,
or it still has programmatic
access to the data that's
attached.
In addition to metadata for
those intervals, you may want to
add individual points in time.
That is, in addition to the
begin signpost and the end
signpost, you may have a
signpost that's not tethered to
a particular time interval but
rather just some fixed moment.
And for that, we have an os
signpost with the event type.
The os signpost with the event
type call looks just like the
same as the begin and end, this
time with the event type.
And it marks a single point in
time.
You could use this within the
context of an interval or maybe
because you want to track
something that's independent of
an interval like a user
interaction.
So for that fetch asset interval
we're talking about, maybe you
want to know when you've
connected to the service that
provides that asset.
Or maybe you want to know when
you've received a few bytes of
it.
You can use this to update the
status or progress of a
particular interval many times
throughout that time of that
interval.
Or you might be tracking maybe a
triggering event like maybe a
user interface interaction like
somebody has just swiped to
update that interface.
Although, if you're really
investigating in a performance
problem, they might be swiping a
lot so this might be what you
see instead.
If you have signpost enabled,
they're usually on by default,
but I'd like to talk about
conditionally turning them on
and off.
First I'd like to emphasize that
we built signpost to be
lightweight.
That means we've done a lot of
work to optimize them at emit
time.
We've done this through some
compiler optimizations that make
sure that work is done in front
instead of runtime.
We've also deferred a lot of our
work so that they're done on the
Instruments backend.
And that means that while
signposts are being emitted,
they should take very few system
resources.
We've done this because we want
to minimize the impact to
whatever your code is running.
And we've also done it because
we want to make sure that even
if you have very small time
span, you can emit a lot of
signposts to get some
fine-grained measurements.
But you may want to be able to
turn your signposts off.
Maybe you want to eliminate as
much overhead as you can from a
particular code path.
Or you might have two categories
of signposts, both of which are
super-high volume and you really
are only interested in debugging
one or the other at a given
point in time.
Well, to do that we're going to
take advantage of a feature of
OSLog, the disabled log handle.
So the disabled log handle is a
simple handle.
And what it does is every OSLog
and os signpost call made
against that handle will just
turn into something very close
to a no-op.
In fact, if you adopt this in C,
we'll even do the check for you
in line and then we won't even
evaluate the rest of the
arguments.
So you can just change this
handle at runtime.
Let me show you an example.
So we're going to go back to the
very first example code that we
had.
And you see that initialization
of that log handle up top.
Well, instead I'm going to make
that initialization conditional.
So I'm either going to assign it
to the normal os log constructor
or I'm going to assign it to
that disabled log handle.
If we take the first path, all
the os signpost calls will work
as I described, but if we take
the second path, those os
signpost calls will turn into
near no-ops.
So as I said before, notice that
I didn't have to call any of my
call -- I didn't have to change
any of my call sites.
I only had to change the
initialization.
And I made the initialization
conditional on an environment
variable.
This is the kind of thing that
you can set up in your Xcode
scheme while you're debugging
your program.
Now I said you didn't have to
change in the call sites, but
maybe you have some
functionality that is
instrumentation specific.
That is, it might be expensive
but it might only be used for
while debugging.
So in that case, you can check a
particular log handle to see if
signposts are turned on for it
with the signposts enabled
property.
The signposts enabled property
can then be used to gate that
additional operation.
Okay.
So all the examples that I've
shown so far have been in Swift,
but signposts are also available
in C.
All the functionality I've
talked about so far is
available: the long handles,
emitting the three different
kinds of signposts, and managing
your signpost identifiers.
For those of you who are
interested in adopting in C, I
encourage you to read the header
doc.
and header doc covers all this
information that I have but from
a C developer's perspective.
All right.
Now you've seen how to adopt
signposts in your code.
And maybe you have a mental
model of what they represent.
So I would love for you to see
how signposts work in concert
with Instruments.
And for that, I'm going to turn
it over for the rest of the
session to my colleague, Chad.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> All right.
Thank you, Shane.
Now today I want to show you and
demonstrate for you three new
important features in
Instruments 10 to help you work
with signpost data.
The first is the new os signpost
instrument.
And that instrument allows you
to record, visualize, and
analyze all of the signpost
activity in your application.
The next feature is points of
interest.
I'll talk a little bit about
what points of interest are and
when you might want to emit one.
And then I'm also going to show
you the new custom instruments
feature and how you can use it
with os signposts to get a more,
I guess, refined presentation of
your signposts.
So let's take a look at that in
a demonstration.
Okay.
Now to start with, we're going
to take a look at our example
application first.
And that is our Trailblazer
application.
This app is -- shows you the
local hiking trails.
And it basically downloads these
beautiful images for you as we
scroll.
Now you'll notice that initially
we have a white background and
then the image comes in later
and fills in.
And this is a pretty common
pattern in an application like
this.
And sometimes it's implemented
with a future or a promise but
this pattern -- as much as it
helps with performance, it's
also pretty difficult to
profile.
And the reason for that is
because there are a lot of
asynchronous activities going
on.
As the user scrolls, there are
downloads that are in-flight at
the same time.
And if the user scrolls really
quickly like this then the
download may not complete before
the image cell needs to be
reused.
And so then we have to cancel
that download.
If we fail to do that, then we
end up with several downloads
running in parallel that we
didn't really want.
So let's take a look at how we
can use signposts to analyze the
application of our Trailblazer.
Now inside the trail cell, we
have a method called
startImageDownload.
And this is invoked when we need
to download that new image, and
it's passed in the image name
that should be downloaded.
Now we have a download helper
class here that we create an
instance of an pass in the name
and set ourself as the delegate
so it'll call us back when it's
downloaded.
And in this case, since the
downloader represents the
concurrent activity that's going
on, this asynchronous work, it's
a great basis for a signpost ID.
So we're going to create our
signpost ID using our downloader
object.
Now to start our signposts,
we're going to do an os signpost
begin.
And we're going to send it to
our networking log handle so
take a real quick look at our
networking log handle.
You see we're using our
Trailblazer bundle ID and a
category of networking.
Now we're going to pass an image
or, sorry, a signpost name of
background image so that way we
can see all of our background
image downloads.
And it will pass that signpost
ID that we created.
And we'll attach some metadata
to begin to convey the name of
the image that we are
downloading.
So then we'll start our
download, and we'll set our
property to track that.
We have it currently
runningDownloader.
Now when that finishes, we'll
get this didReceiveImage
callback here.
And we'll set our image view to
the image that we received.
And we'll call end on the
signpost.
And we'll use the exact same log
handle, the same name, the same
signpost ID but this time we're
going to attach some end
metadata to say finished with
size.
And you'll notice here that
we've annotated this particular
parameter with Xcode colon
size-in-bytes.
And what this does is it tells
Xcode and Instruments that this
argument should be treated as a
size-in-bytes for both display
and analysis.
Now these are called engineering
types.
And they can be read about in
the Instruments developer help
guide which is under the help
menu in Instruments.
Now once we've completed our
downloading, we can set that
back to nil.
Now there are two ways that we
can finish a download.
That was the success path.
And then we have to consider the
cancel path.
So in prepare for reuse, if we
currently have a running
downloader, we're going to need
to first cancel that downloader.
So in that case, we're going to
emit an end for the interval,
and we're going to use that same
logging handle, signpost name,
signpost ID.
And we're going to use cancelled
as the end metadata to separate
it from when we finish
successfully.
Now that's enough to actually do
some profiling.
So we're going to go over here
to a product profile.
And that will start up
Instruments once we've finished
building and installing.
That will start up Instruments
here.
And we can create a new blank
document.
Then we can go to the library,
and I can show you how to use
that new os signpost instrument.
So we have our new os signpost
instrument here.
And we'll just drag and drop
that out into the trace.
We'll make a little bit of room
here for it and then we will
press record.
And I'll bring our iPhone back
up here to the beginning.
All right.
So now we'll do some scrolling
and then we'll also do some
really, really quick scrolling.
And then we'll let that settle
down.
Now we can go back to
Instruments and see what kind of
data we recorded.
So I'm going to stop the
recording.
And now you'll notice here that,
in the track view, we have a
visualization of all of our
background image intervals.
Now that's the signpost name.
Now if we hold down the option
key and we zoom in, you can see
there are intervals.
And intervals are annotated with
the start metadata and the end
metadata.
Now if we zoom back out and then
take a look at the trace here
again, we'll notice that we have
no more than five images that
are running downloads in
parallel, which is a good thing.
That means that our cancellation
worked.
And if we want to confirm that,
we can come in here and you can
see that a lot of these
intervals have metadata that
says that it was cancelled in
the download.
Now if you want to take -- if
you want to look at a numerical
-- or let's say you want to look
at the durations of these
intervals then you can come down
here to the summary of
intervals.
And we see a breakdown by
category and then by signpost
name and then by the start
message and then by the end
message.
So if we make this a little bit
smaller, you can see that we
made 93 image download requests.
Of those, 12 were for location
one.
Of those 12, seven were
cancelled and five finished with
a size of 3.31 megabytes.
Now if you look over here, these
are the statistics about our
durations.
And you can see that the minimum
and the average of the cancelled
intervals is significantly
smaller than when we finished
with the full downloads.
And that's exactly what you
would expect to see in this
pattern.
Now if you want to see all of
the cancelled events because
you're interested in seeing
those, you can put this -- focus
arrow and it will take you to a
list view where you can see all
the places where location one
had an end message of cancelled.
And as we go through this,
you'll see that the inspection
head on the top of the trace
will move forward to each one of
those intervals.
So you can track all the failure
cases if that's what you're
interested in.
Now that's a great way to view
the times of those intervals,
the timing of those intervals.
But what if you wanted to do an
analysis of the metadata?
What if you wanted to determine
how many bytes of image data
that we've downloaded over the
network?
Well, we've emitted metadata
messages like finished with size
and then the size.
It would be great if we could
total that argument up.
So if you want to do that, you
can come over here to the
summary of metadata statistics.
You can see that we have it
broken down by the subsystem,
the category, and then the
format string and then below the
format string, the arguments
within that format string.
And since our format string only
has one, that's simply arg0.
Now Instruments has totaled this
up.
And it knows that this is a
size-in-bytes.
And so it gives us a nice
calculation of 80 megabytes.
So we've downloaded 80 megabytes
of image data total.
Now you can see the different
columns here.
You've got it min, max, average,
and standard deviation.
So this is a great way to take a
look at just statistical
analysis of the values that
you're conveying through your
metadata.
Now Shane mentioned that
signposts were very lightweight
and that is totally true except
when you run Instruments the way
I just ran Instruments.
In what we call immediate mode,
which is the default recording
mode, Instruments is trying to
show and record the data in near
real time.
And so when it goes into
immediate mode recording, all
the signposts have to be sent
directly to Instruments.
And we have to bypass all of
those optimizations that you get
from buffering in the operating
system.
Now with our signposts -- with
our signposts application here,
we're not really emitting enough
intervals to really notice that
overhead, but if you have a game
engine and you want to emit
thousands of signposts per
second, that overhead will start
to build up.
So in order to work around that,
what you can do is change the
recording mode of Instruments
before you take your recording.
And the way you do that is by
holding down on the record
button and selecting recording
options.
And then in this section here
for the global options, you can
see that we have our immediate
mode selected.
And we can change that to last
five second mode.
Now this is often called
windowed mode.
And what it tells the operating
system and the recording
technology is that we don't need
every single event.
We just want the last five
seconds worth.
And when you do that,
Instruments will step out of the
way and let the operating system
do what it does.
Now this is a very common mode.
We use this in system trace.
We use this in metal system
trace and the new game
performance template.
And so it's a very common way to
look for stutters and hangs in
your application.
All right.
So that is our os signpost
instrument.
Now let's talk about points of
interest.
Now if we come back to our
Trailblazer application here,
you notice that when I tap on a
trail, it pushes a detail.
If I go back and tap on a
different trail, it'll push a
different detail.
Now it would be great if we
could track every time these
detail views come forward
because then we can tell what
our user is trying to do, and we
can tell where our user is in
the application.
Now you could certainly do this
with a signpost, but you'd have
to drag in the os signpost
instrument and record all of the
signpost activity on the
application.
And it sort of dilutes how
important these user navigation
events are.
So what we allow you to do is
promote them to what are called
points of interest.
Now if I go to our code for the
detail controller and we look at
our viewDidAppear method, you
can see that I'm posting -- I'm
creating an os signpost event
saying that a detail appeared
and with the name of the detail.
Now this is sent to a special
log handle that we've created
called points of interest.
And the way that you create that
is by creating a log handle with
your subsystem identifier and
the systems points of interest
category.
So this is a special category
that Instruments will be looking
for.
And when it sees points here,
it'll place them into the points
of interest instrument.
So if we come back here and take
a time profile, you can see that
we have our points of interest
instrument automatically
included.
And if we do a recording and we
do that same basic action, we go
into the Matt Davis Trail and
then we'll come back here to
Skyline Trail and then we'll go
back and we'll do one more for
good measure.
Now when you go back to
Instruments, you can see that we
have those points of interest
prominently displayed.
So you can see where your user
was in the navigation of your
app.
And you can correlate this with
other performance data.
And so points of interest are
really a way for you to pick and
choose some of the most
important points of interest in
your application and make them
available to every developer
that's on your team or in your
development community.
And they can be seen right here
in the points of interest.
All right.
So that is the points of
interest instrument and how you
create points of interest from
signposts.
Now another great feature of
Instruments 10 is the ability
for you to create custom
instruments.
And so to demonstrate what you
can do with custom instruments
in os signpost, we've created,
as part of our project, a
Trailblazer instruments package.
Now I'm going to build and run
that now.
And you'll see when we do that,
we start a separate copy of
Instruments that has our just
built package installed.
And if we bring that version
forward, we'll see that we now
have a Trailblazer networking
trace template.
And if we choose that, we can
see that we have a Trailblazer
networking instrument in our
trace document.
And let's take a recording and
see what the difference is
between our points of interest
or, I'm sorry, our os signpost
and what this custom instrument
can do.
So we'll do the same type of
thing.
We'll do some basic downloading.
And then we'll come back and
we'll analyze our trace.
Now the presentation here is
significantly different.
So let's zoom in and take a look
at it.
You'll notice here on the left,
instead of breaking it down by
signpost name, we've broken it
down by the image being
downloaded.
So now we can see that image two
was downloaded at this point and
at this point.
Now we've labeled each one with
the size in megabytes of the
download.
And we've also colored them red
if the download size is larger
than 3 1/2 megabytes.
So this is a custom graph that
we created as part of our custom
instrument.
Now we've also defined some
details down here.
We've got a very simple list of
our download events.
And, again, you can navigate
through the trace with those.
And we also have -- let me see
if I can get this back into
focus here.
We also have a summary for all
the downloads.
Very simple.
We just want to do a count and a
sum.
And then we also have this cool
thing called Timeslice.
And in a Timeslice view, what
we're trying to do is answer
that question I was asking
before of how many of these
things are actually running in
parallel?
Well, if you want to take a look
at the intervals running in
parallel, you just scrub the
inspection head over here
through time, and you can see
exactly what is intersecting
that inspection head at any
given point in time.
So it's a great and a different
way to look at your signpost
data.
Now if you are working with
others on a project or you're
part of the development
community, using a custom
instrument is a great way to
take the signpost data and
reshape it in a way that someone
else can use and interpret
without having to know the
details of how your code works
so they are a very important
feature.
Now the great news is that to
create an instrument like that,
the entire package definition is
about 115 lines of XML and so
custom instruments is very
expressive and very powerful but
also very easy.
And that is the conclusion of
our demo.
[ Applause ]
So in today's session, we took a
look at the signpost API, and we
showed you how to use it to
annotate interesting periods of
activity and intervals inside
your application.
We showed you how to collect
metadata and get that metadata
into Instruments for
visualization and analysis.
And we showed you how to combine
custom instruments in os
signpost to create a more
tailored presentation of your
signpost data.
Now all this really comes down
to us being able to give you the
kind of information that you
need to help you tune the
performance of your application.
And so we're really excited to
see how you use os signpost and
Instruments together to improve
the user experience of your
application.
That is the content for today.
For more information, you can
come see us in a lab, technology
lab 8 at 3:00 today.
And I also have session 410,
creating custom instruments
tomorrow where I'll be going
over the details of how custom
instruments works and show you
how we created our Trailblazer
networking instruments package.
Thank you very much.
Enjoy the rest of your
conference.
[ Applause ]