[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Good morning, welcome to
What's New in LLVM.
I'm Jim Grosbach, your friendly
neighborhood pointy hair boss.
I'm here to tell you a little
bit of background about the LLVM
project before we dive into the
deep technical details of all
the exciting new things that we
have for you today.
Start off, LLVM is more than
just the compiler, it is the
background for the Clang
compiler, for the C family of
languages that we all use every
day, but it also powers the
Static Analyzer, the sanitizers,
the LLDB debugger, and is the
optimization code generation
framework underneath the GPU
shader compilers for all of
Apple's mobile platforms.
In addition to this, it also
powers one additional little
project that you may have heard
of from time to time called
Swift.
And like Swift LLVM is an open
source project.
We all operate under the
watchful eye of our LLVM wyvern
here, he's normally a very
friendly fellow, though I do
have to caution you he gets a
little bit cranky if you call
him a dragon so don't do that.
As an open source project LLVM
is a partnership, we work with
industry partners, academics,
researchers and hobbyists from
all over the world and in
different parts of the industry
and many more all over the
place.
This is really fantastic, we
work together to build the
greatest tools that we possibly
can to move technology forward.
And if you ever have a compiler
itch that you would like to
scratch we would like to invite
you to participate with us and
go to the LLVM website here at
llvm.org or you can come talk to
us later today later today in
the LLVM labs and many of our
compiler engineers from Apple
will be there and I'm sure will
be more than happy to talk your
ear off about anything and
everything compiler related
you've ever wanted to know.
So for today we have a great set
of things that we want to share
with you.
We have updates on automated
reference counting that makes it
even easier for the compiler to
help you with your memory
management.
We have new diagnostics in Xcode
10 and new checks in the Static
Analyzer to help catch bugs in
your project sooner at build
time to improve the quality of
your code.
We have compiler features that
improve security, both of
Apple's platforms and of your
apps.
And new features to allow you to
take advantage of all of the
really great new things on the
hardware architectures to get
the performance that we all want
out of our platforms and
architectures.
So with that I would like to
invite my colleague Alex up to
talk about ARC.
Alex.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Jim.
Automatic reference counting has
greatly simplified Objective-C
program since we introduced it a
couple of years ago.
A couple of restrictions made it
harder to migrate from the old
manual retain release mode over
to ARC.
I'm happy to say that we've now
lifted one such restriction.
Xcode 10 has support for ARC
object pointer fields in C
structures.
[ Applause ]
Let's take a look at an example
let's say we'd like to write a
food ordering app and we'd like
to create a data structure which
represents a menu item.
In Xcode 9 and earlier it would
have been impossible for us to
actually use a C structure with
ARC object pointer fields, so we
would have had to use a C, an
Objective-C class here.
Xcode 10 now allows us to
actually create a C structure
that has ARC object pointer
fields.
Let's keep going and keep
writing our food ordering app.
Let's create a function that
orders free food for us.
In the function let's create a
variable item of type menu item
with a price of zero.
Then let's pass this item into
another function that actually
orders the food for us.
When the item is created the
compiler has to synthesize code
which retains the ARC object
pointer fields in the item.
The code comments on the slide
demonstrate the code that the
compiler synthesizes.
This code ensures the name and
the price of the item are not
released prematurely before the
item is actually used.
Now at the end of the function
item goes out of scope and is
deallocated from the stack so
the compiler has to synthesize
code which releases the ARC
object pointer fields in the
item.
This ensures that the name and
the price are not leaked when
the item is released.
Previously it was possible to
use Objective-C object pointer
fields when using manual
retained release mode, but you
had to write the retains and
releases yourself.
With ARC the compiler hides all
of this complexity for you and
synthesizes code that retains
and releases the fields.
So the compiler is really your
friend here and it does the
correct job of managing memory
for variables on the stack and
also for fields in other
structures, and also instance
variables inside Objective-C
classes.
But there is one place we have
to put in a little bit of extra
work to support structures with
ARC object pointer fields and
that place is heap.
Let's go back to our structure,
let's say you would like to
allocate an array of menu items
on the heap.
Now if this was an Objective-C
interface we could have used an
NSArray here, but it's not so
let's use malloc and free.
Now this code actually has two
issues.
First issue, the memory is not
zero initialized when it's
allocated, which means that
their pointers will be invalid
which will cause undesired
runtime behavior for your
program at runtime.
The second issue is that the ARC
object pointer fields are not
cleared before the memory is
deallocated which will cause
runtime memory leaks in your
program.
Now to fix the first issue you
can replace the call to malloc
with a call to calloc.
This will ensure that your
memory is zero initialized,
which will remove all of those
nasty unexpected runtime issues.
To fix the second issue you can
write a loop before it's
allocated in your memory to
clear out all of the ARC object
pointer fields in your items.
This will ensure that the name
and the price in the items are
not leaked when the items are
freed.
Now this is an exciting new
feature and if any of you were
put off from migrates over to
ARC because of lack of features
like that I hope that support
from ARC object pointer fields
in Xcode 10 will help you
reconsider your choice.
Now let's take a look at
Objective-C pointers and
structures in general and see
where and how can the structures
be used in different language
modes in Xcode 10.
So in Xcode 10 you can use
structures that have Objective-C
object pointer fields across
different language modes.
For example, you can use the
same structure in C Objective-C
or even Objective-C++.
And it will work correctly even
when you're compiling your code
in ARC or in the manual retain
release mode.
In Xcode 10 we actually unified
the Objective-C++ ABI between
calls to functions that took in
or returned structures that had
ARC object pointer fields in
Objective-C++.
And this was done through an ABI
change in Xcode 10 and ABI
change affects functions in
Objective C++ which return or
take in a structure by value
that has ARC object pointer
fields and no special member
functions like constructors or
destructors.
Now if you are not sure what
this means for you or whether
your code is affected by this
ABI change please take a look at
Xcode's release notes where we
describe in more details the
effects and the impact of this
ABI change.
Now there is one caveat when it
comes to the ARC object pointer
fields and C structures, they're
not supported in Swift.
So if you try to use a structure
that has ARC object pointer
fields from Swift you will just
get a compilation error because
the structure will not be found.
In addition to new features like
support for ARC object pointer
fields Xcode 10 comes with a lot
of new compiler diagnostics.
We actually have over a hundred
new warnings in Xcode 10 and
today I'd like to talk about two
of them.
The first warning might be of
interest to those of you who
have mixed Swift and Objective-C
code.
So as you know Swift code can be
imported into Objective-C and
Xcode allows you to do that by
generating a header file that
describes the Swift interface
using Objective-C declarations.
And you can import this header
file into your own Objective-C
code to get access to the
underlying Swift declarations.
Now let's get more specific and
let's talk about how Swift's
closure parameters are important
to Objective-C.
So right now on the screen you
see an example of a Swift
protocol called Executor.
This protocol defines a function
member called performOperation
which takes in a closure
parameter called handler.
Now in Swift closure parameters
are non-escaping by default,
which means that they should not
be retained or called after the
function returns.
Now it can be easy for the
program and to forget that this
contract exists when conforming
to the executive protocol in
Objective-C.
For example, as you see right
now on the slide we have a
dispatch Executor interface in
Objective-C and conforms to the
Executor protocol, so it
provides the performOperation
method which takes in the
handler block parameter that
corresponds to Swift's handler
closure parameter.
But just by looking at the
Objective-C code we have no way
of knowing whether the handler
parameter can escape or not.
Xcode 10 now provides a warning
that helps us to remember that
this parameter is actually
non-escaping.
To fix this this warning you can
annotate your block parameter
with the NS NOESCAPE annotation.
You should also annotate the
implementation of the method or
the parameter in the
implementation of the method
with NS NOESCAPE annotation.
Now the NS NOESCAPE annotation
is simply a reminder for you the
programmer to ensure that you
don't store or call the handler
block after they perform
operation method returns.
So it's there for you to help
you remember that there is this
contract that exists between
your Swift and Objective-C code.
Now the second warning might be
of interest to those of you who
work with more low-level code
and who care about the way that
structures are laid out in
memory.
Let's take a look at one
structure.
So in C structures have to
follow strict layout and
alignment rules.
In this particular structure
that you see right now on the
slide the compiler has to insert
a 2-byte pattern between the
second and the third field of
the structure.
Sometimes you might want to
relax these rules and the
compiler provides a pragma pack
directive that you can use to
control the layout and the
alignment of your structures.
Now in this example we use the
pragma pack push, 1 directive to
remove this fixated layout and
to ensure that our structure is
tightly packed.
This can be useful when
serializing your structures or
when transferring your
structures over the network.
Now pragma pack is typically
used with a push and a pop
directive, but it can be easy
for the programmer to forget to
insert the pop into the code.
Xcode 10 will now warn about
code that doesn't have a
corresponding pragma pack pop
directive and to point you to
the location of the push.
So to fix this warning you
should take a look at the
location of your push directive
and insert the pop directive at
the corresponding location in
your code.
So in our case we can insert the
pop directly after the packed
structure.
Once we do that the new layout
rules will apply only to the
packed structure so they won't
affect any other structures in
our program.
These two new warnings that I
mentioned are enabled by default
in Xcode 10 and they are there
to help you write more correct
and more robust code.
And to talk more about more
correct and more robust code I'd
like to invite George up on
stage who will talk about the
new static analyzing
improvements in Xcode 10.
George.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks Alex, so I would like
to tell you about some of the
improvements we have done for
Xcode 10 for the Clang Static
Analyzer.
So the Clang Static Analyzer is
a great tool for finding HK
hard-to-reproduce bugs in your
program.
And not only the Static Analyzer
finds the bug for you it also
displays the visualization in
Xcode of the paths which
[inaudible] the bug.
So here nil is added to
NSMutableArray which can cause a
crash later on.
And Static Analyzer shows you
the path for this crash so you
can see how the application can
be fixed.
And I would like to tell you
about three of the new
improvements we have done.
Firstly, we have a new check for
detecting Grand Central Dispatch
anti-patterning, which can cause
poor performance and hangs of
your replication.
Secondly, we have a new check
for detecting a misuse of
autoreleasing variables inside
autorelease pools which can
cause crashes with [inaudible].
And finally, we have improved
performance and visualizations
for the Clang Static Analyzer.
So let's start with a new check
for detecting Grand Central
Dispatch anti-pattern.
So many APIs on our platforms
are asynchronous, but sometimes
developers would like to use
them in a synchronous way for
one reason or another.
Maybe because their code is
already running on the
background queue or maybe
because the function cannot
proceed at all until the
required value is available.
And the tempting solution there
is to use a semaphore to ensure
synchronization.
So that's what's happening in
this example, so here there is
an SXPC object self.connection
and we use its property
remoteObjectProxy to call, to
get the current task name
asynchronously from a different
process.
And then we wait on a semaphore
which is signal to inside the
callback.
And that helps to ensure that by
the time the function returns
the task name is available.
So this approach works but has
known performance implications.
So the main problem here is when
you wait using a semaphore on
some asynchronous process you
might be waiting on a queue with
a much lower priority than yours
costing prior inversion which
[inaudible] performance and
cause hangs.
And moreover using a semaphore
in such a way also spawns
useless threads which further
degrades the performance.
And to help you address this
issue now Static Analyzer warns
on such cases helping to see
where the issue occurs.
Now let's see how the issue can
be fixed.
In the best-case scenario there
is a synchronous API available
which can be used in stat.
So for an SXPC connection there
is an [inaudible] API
synchronousRemoteObjectProxy
which when used in start
eliminates the need for the
semaphore and runs much foster.
Alternatively, if no such
synchronous API is available you
could restructure your
application to use continuations
in stat and just calls the
required function inside the
callback.
So this check is not enabled by
default but we encourage you to
enable it in build settings in
order to make sure no such
problem securing your
application and it runs as fast
as possible.
Now let's talk about the second
check for detecting the
autoreleasing variables
outliving the lifetime of the
autorelease pool.
So the autoreleasing qualifier
specifies that the value has to
be released once the control
exits the autorelease pool.
So here we have an example where
we create an error variable
inside the autorelease pool and
once the control is outside of
the autorelease pool the
variable is released and
subsequently destroyed.
And autoreleasing pools are a
useful feature of Objective-C to
help contain the big memory
footprint of your applications
and to ensure that thumbprints
are destroyed where necessary.
However, it can cause unexpected
crashes and they're even more
unexpected because you don't
even need to write the word
autoreleasing in your
application to have those
crashes.
So for instance, there is a
validation function here and it
takes in out parameter NSError.
And out parameters are actually
autoreleasing in Objective-C
under ARC by default.
So when we write to this out
parameter inside the autorelease
pool and then the function exits
the error value is actually
released.
And then if the caller tries to
read the value of this error
variable they might crash with
use-after-free.
That pattern is already hard to
detect, but it actually gets
even worse when you don't even
control the part of the
application which has the
autorelease pool.
So here is a similar function
which [inaudible] and out
parameter error and then it
calls an
enumerateObjectsUsingBlock which
is a popular foundation API
which calls a block on every
element of a collection.
However
enumerateObjectsUsingBlock
actually calls [inaudible] given
block inside the autorelease
pool of return.
So a similar problem occurs here
that when we create an error
value inside the block and write
it to the out parameter it will
actually get released by the
time the control reaches out of
enumerateObjectsUsingBlock.
And then when the caller tries
to read it they also can crash
with the use-after-free.
And previously we have
introduced the compiler warning
which warns when an implicitly
autoreleasing out parameter is
captured in the block.
And the compiler warning
suggested to make such
parameters explicitly
autoreleasing.
But we have noticed that such
issue kept occurring, so in
Xcode 10 we introduced a more
powerful Clang Static Analyzer
warning which knows which APIs
call the provided block inside
the autorelease pool and warns
about such cases.
So now let's see how this issue
can be fixed.
And the simplest fix here is
just to introduce a strong local
variable and then when you're
inside the block write a value
into the strong variable in
stat.
And then only copy to the out
parameter once the control is
outside of the block and you
know it's not inside the
autorelease pool and it's safe
to write into the autoreleasing
variable.
And finally, we also have
improved performance and
visualizations of the Clang
Static Analyzer.
So in Xcode 10 we have improved
the analyzer to explore your
program in a more efficient way
so now it finds up to 15% more
bugs during the same analysis
time.
And not only it finds more bugs
the bug report it now generates
tend to be smaller and more
understandable.
And what I mean by that is
sometimes in Xcode 10 you would
get examples which have a lot of
steps and a lot of arrows and
which would be somewhat hard to
comprehend.
And in many of those examples in
your version of Xcode we give
you a much smaller error path
which is much easier to see and
you can see the issue much
faster.
So in order to use Static
Analyzer on your projects you
can use Product, Analyze or you
can even enable Analyze During
Build to make sure no analyzer
issue gets unnoticed.
So I encourage you to use the
Static Analyzer, it's a great
tool to find your bugs before
users do.
And now my colleague Ahmed will
talk about low-level
improvements.
>> Thank you George.
[ Applause ]
So as Alex and George told you,
we have lots of warnings and
Static Analyzer checks in the
compiler, but you also have the
sanitizer and all of these tools
help you find lots of bugs,
including security bugs.
So I'm sure you all have lots of
tests and use all these great
tools to find all the bugs in
these tests.
But for some of the most
egregious security bugs we want
to make sure that they don't
happen in release builds if
somehow they snuck past all the
testing.
So for those we have mitigations
in the code generator that are
always emitted even in release
builds.
So I'm Ahmed, I work on the code
generator and today I'm going to
tell you about a new mitigation
in Xcode 10.
So to see how that works we need
to understand how the stack
works.
So here I have a simple C
function called dlog and I use
it to print a string that I'm
passed into a dlog bug.
So in this case it's called with
a string hello.
And the way this works is we
need to allocate some memory to
keep track of this call.
So we allocate that into a
region called the stack.
So the stack grows down towards
the null pointer or address
zero.
So when we do our dlog hello
call this allocates what's
called the stack frame and the
stack frame contains things like
the return address so that we
know to go back to main.
But it also contains other
things like parameters and local
variables.
So for instance if I have a log
file [inaudible] local variable
that lives in the stack frame.
So now if I try to make another
function call to this dlog file
function that in turn will
allocate its own stack frame.
And when it's done it's going to
deallocate the stack frame and
return back to the caller.
So now let's look at this stack
frame in more details.
So let's say I change my
function to have a local buffer,
so it's a 4 bytes character
array.
And I'm trying to prepare my
debug string by first doing a
strcpy of the string that I'm
passed into that buffer.
So this does the obvious copy by
[inaudible], so it does H-E-L-L.
But then there's a problem at
this point we already wrote 4
bytes and that we already
exhausted all 4 bytes available
in our buffer.
So if we keep going which is
what strcpy will do then we're
going to override the return
address and this is a big
security problem.
So if an attacker controls the
string that I'm copying which is
not that hard, then it can
control the return address.
If it can control the return
address then they control
basically what the program does
next, so it's a big security
problem.
So if you had a test that caught
this and you ran the address
sanitizer, then you will have
had an easy way to fix this.
And really what I should have
done here is strncpy that knows
about the size or even better
use a higher-level API like
NSString or [inaudible] string.
But still sometimes these bugs
can survive into release builds
and we avoid these by using
what's called the Stack
Protector.
So the Stack Protector changes
the layout of the stack frame to
add a new field the canary so
that when we do our write we
have a little bit of code right
before the return of the
function that checks whether the
canary is still valid.
So if we keep writing in strcpy
we're going to override the
canary first and then we're
going to check the canary first
before returning and that's
going to abort.
So we turned ad potentially
exploitable security
vulnerability into a reliable
crash and that's not good for an
attacker.
So this is what's called the
Stack Protector.
It defects certain kinds of
stack buffer overflows, which is
the attack that we just saw.
And it's already enabled by
default in many versions of
Xcode.
So next I'm going to talk about
a trickier case where we
introduced a new mitigation.
So let's say I took my function,
again my dlog function and I
changed the buffer so that now
it's a variable length array.
And the length comes from a
parameter called len.
So let's say len in a specific
call is something big like
15,000, so now the stack frame
has to be at least 15,000 bytes
long.
But memory is not all
immediately available, so memory
is split into pages and the
stack grows only when necessary.
So for instance, when we try to
access by 10,000 of the buffer
that's in the next page of the
stack that's not yet available
so it's going to do a page fault
in the CPU that talks to the
opening system, the operating
system sees that we have the
right to grow the stack, and it
grows it and we can continue
writing.
So this all happens under the
hood.
But say an attacker controls the
length and it makes it huge, big
enough that it spans many pages.
So now there's a new problem,
the memory is not infinite so if
we keep allocating in this stack
eventually we'll hit another
region of memory that's already
allocated and usually that's the
heap.
And when we do that then we're
going to clash with the heap,
with whatever is already used in
there, so that's usually things
like malloc and new.
So if we try to see what would
happen with our strcpy example
then we will try to write the
bytes one by one.
So we do H-E-L, etcetera.
And from the standpoint of the
CPU, the code that's generated
and the operating system this is
all fine because we're just
writing into a page that's
already available and allocated.
But it really isn't because this
is part of the heap, this is not
part of our local stack
allocated array.
So when we do our writes we're
actually overriding some
completely unrelated piece of
information like I don't know a
Boolean that checks whether we
should check a password.
So this is another important
security flaw.
So this is something that we
mitigated with a new feature and
the future works by emitting
some new codes at the entry of
the function that checks whether
it's okay to have the stack
frame.
So it asks the operating system
above the maximum size of the
stack and if you try to make an
allocation that's bigger than
that then it actually aborts.
And again, this turns a
potentially exploitable security
bug into a reliable crash and
that's no good for an attacker.
So this is Stack Checking, it
detects something that you might
have heard of called Stack Clash
and it's enabled by default in
Xcode 10.
So next I want to talk about a
new set of features we added in
Xcode 10 and that's support for
new extension, sect extensions.
So as you all know we have lots
of great Apple devices and one
of the great things about Xcode
is that with just a few build
settings you can target your
code for each of these devices.
And so under the hood in macOS,
iOS, watchOS, etcetera we tweak
every OS so that it uses
everything that's available on a
specific piece of hardware.
So it guarantees maximum
performance no matter where we
run.
And so if you an app with
extremely high-performance
requirements that's something
that you might want to do as
well.
So we have three features to
talk about that are available in
the iMac Pro and the iPhone 8
Plus and X.
And let's start with the iMac
Pro.
So the iMac Pro has the Intel
Xeon CPU which has a set of new
features called AVX-512.
So AVX-512 is a set of new
instructions with vector
registers.
And these provide benefits over
X86-64, so in X86-64 we can only
assume that we have 128-bit
vectors available, so that's
guaranteed on any Mac ever
that's Intel powered.
Now it happens that any new Mac
today has more than that, but
the iMac Pro is the first that
has 512-bit registers.
And with the Auto-Vectorizer
that's enabled in the Xcode
Clang this is great because it
means that we can have many more
elements in the vector.
So this can greatly improve
throughputs.
But there are other benefits
with AVX-512, so for instance we
not only have bigger vectors we
also have more of them.
So on X86-64 we only have 16 now
we have 32, so this is a lot of
data to process.
And even if for some reason the
auto-vectorizer is not able to
make use of these vectors then
we still have ore skill
registers or even for code that
just does float or double.
There are lots of performance
benefits in AVX-512.
So let's look at how we can
exploit it in my compute
[inaudible] expensive function.
So the first thing I'm going to
do is to keep around my existing
function because that's going to
be the fallback that I have that
runs on all Macs.
Next, I can try to specialize my
function.
So one way to do that is using
the target attributes.
And that tells the compiler that
it's okay to assume that this
function has AVX-512, so it only
runs on an iMac Pro.
So if you use simd.h, for
instance the simd float4 128-bit
vector type then now we might
have better performance than the
AVX-512 version using the same
code.
And if you use the even larger
vector types, so for instance
simd float16, then now you have
much better performance than the
AVX-512 version where the
512-bit vector is actually
native.
And if you go all the way down
to X86 intrinsics, then now you
can start using the new AVX-512
variance, as well as the M512
types.
So if you want to specialize
larger units of codes, so not
just individual functions but
files, targets, libraries, then
you can use the new AVX-512
value of the additional vector
extensions build setting.
So when you do that there are
some things to keep in mind and
if you're familiar with AVX-1
and AVX-2 these are very similar
issues.
So you can only pass large
vectors, so 256 bits and up from
and to AVX-512 functions.
So the ABI is different from the
generic and a specialized
variance, so you cannot pass
them between those.
Additionally, these vectors are
large and they're large enough
that their natural alignment is
too big for what's guaranteed by
things like malloc.
So you have to take that into
account when allocating these
anywhere other than the stack.
And so in general all of these
things are things that we are
already go through lots of
things in the opening system.
So for instance, if you can at
all use accelerate.framework and
it's much easier to do so
because we already specialized
all the functions for every
single microarchitecture.
So this is AVX-512.
Now we also have new features on
the iPhone 8, 8 Plus and X.
So one of the first feature is
ARM v8.1 Atomics and that's
thanks to one of the great
things about the iPhone X and
that's the A11 Bionic chip.
So the A11 Bionic chip has one
great new feature compared to
the A10 which is its support for
six CPUs, six cores running all
at the same time and that's a
first in iOS.
And since you have more cores
than you probably have more
threads all at the same time and
with more threads you might need
more synchronization to make
these threads cooperate.
And that's implemented using
atomics.
So the A11 chip also introduces
a new family of atomic
instructions that are better
optimized for the new extra
cores.
So let's look at how that works.
So the way atomics work is
through a small sequence of
codes.
So suppose I have a thread and
it's trying to access main
memory, so it has an atomic
shared variable in there and
it's just trying to increment
it.
So under the hood the code
generator will emit a small
sequence of codes that first
takes exclusive excess of a
cache line and that's a small
region of memory that contains
completely this atomic variable.
Now that we have exclusive
access we can load from the
variable, then we can do our
increment on the temporary
loaded value and store the
result back.
And we know that this is safe
because we have exclusive
access, so no other thread could
have changed the value while
we're computing our temporary
results.
But now suppose another thread
does access either the same
variable or another variable in
the same cache line.
So both are going to try to have
exclusive access over this
variable and that is not
possible, that's what it means
to be exclusive.
So both of them are going to
fail their exclusive access and
they're going to have to try
again until one of them
succeeds.
And this is not ideal for
performance.
So in ARM v8.1 which is the
architecture in the A10 CPU we
have new instructions that do
this all in a single step and in
some cases, that can greatly
improve performance.
So again, this is something that
you can specialize code for
using the per function
specialization or for entire
targets.
And this is something that's
only really useful when you have
your own C11 or C++ 11 atomics.
So in general, it's much easier
to use the higher-level
libraries like GCD or PThread or
os unfair lock, etcetera.
So these are already tweaked for
ARM v8.1, but they also
cooperate to the operating
system to have even better
performance.
So another feature in the A11
CPU is 16-bit floating points.
So you are all familiar with the
two standard floating point
types, so we have double which
is 64 bits and float which is 32
bits.
So on A11 we also have the
16-bit float16, this has much
less range and precision so it's
not as useful for as many cases.
But in some cases like machine
learning or when you're trying
to talk to GPU via Metal this is
great because it's smaller and
it's faster to compute.
And that's even more true if you
put them in vectors where you
can put more of them in the same
ARM vector.
So this is also something that
you can specialize code for and
in general something to keep in
mind with all of these features
is that they're not available
everywhere.
So when you want to use them you
have to always make sure that
they're actually dynamically
available on the device you're
running and you can do that
using sysctlbyname.
And so in general we already do
all this in system framework, so
it's much easier to just rely on
those.
So these are three new
instruction set extensions, we
have on the iMac Pro AVX-512 and
on iPhone X, 8, and 8 Plus we
have Atomics and 16-bit floating
points.
So that's just part of all the
new features in Xcode.
So from ARC object pointers in C
Structs to the improved static
analyzer there are lots of great
things in Xcode 10.
And there are also some things
that we didn't even talk about
like for instance, over a
hundred new warnings and support
for C++ 17 standard library
function.
So if you want to learn more we
have the video and the slides
available on the website soon.
And if you're here at the
conference come join us at the
lab this afternoon.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]