[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Good afternoon, everyone!
Welcome to Behind the Scenes of
the Xcode Build Process.
My name is Jake Petroules, and
I'm an engineer on the Xcode
Build System Team.
And today we're going to be
exploring the Xcode build
process.
I'll start by telling you all
about Xcode 10's new build
system which is written from
scratch in Swift.
And provides improved
performance and reliability.
We'll answer questions like what
exactly happens when you press
Command B?
How is the build process
structured?
And how does Xcode use the
information in your project file
to determine how to model and
orchestrate the build process?
Next we'll venture into the
compiler realm.
And find out about Clang and
Swift builds your source code
into object files.
We'll show how headers and
modules work.
See how the compilers find
declarations in your code, and
how the Swift compilation model
fundamentally differs from that
of C, C++ and Objective-C.
Finally, we'll land at the
linker which performs one of the
final steps in the build
process.
We'll explain what symbols are
and how they relate to your
source code.
And how the linker takes the
object files produced by the
compilers and glues them
together to produce the final
executable for your application
or framework.
By the way, we're going to use a
small sample app called PetWall
as a running example throughout
this talk.
It's just a small iOS app that
displays photos of our pets.
So let's first understand what
the build process is and how it
works when building a typical
app like PetWall in Xcode.
You can see here we've got an
app target, a framework, a bunch
of different source code files
in Swift and Objective-C.
And maybe this looks a bit like
your own project.
So when you build an app,
there's a number of steps
involved to go from the source
code and resources in your
project to the package that
you're shipping to customers or
uploading to the App Store for
distribution.
You have to compile and link
source code.
Copy and process resources like
headers, asset catalogues and
storyboards.
And finally code sign and maybe
even do some custom work in a
shell script or a make file like
building API documentation for
your framework or running code
linting and validation tools.
Now most of these tasks in the
build process are performed by
running command line tools.
Like Clang, LD, AC tool, IB
tool, Code sign, and so on.
These tools have to be executed
with a very specific set of
arguments and in a particular
order based on the configuration
of your Xcode project.
So what the build system does
for you is to automate the
orchestration and execution of
these tasks each time you
perform a build.
And since there can be tens of
thousands of tasks or even more
involved in a build process with
a complex graph of
interdependencies.
It's definitely not something
you want to be manually typing
into the terminal 110 times a
day.
Let the build system do that for
you.
Now I mentioned that the tasks
in the build process are
executed in a particular order.
Let's talk about how that
ordering is determined and why
it's important.
The order in which build tasks
are executed is determined from
the dependency information that
is the tasks, the inputs that a
task consumes, and the outputs
that it produces.
For example, a compilation task
consumes a source code file like
PetController.m as input and
produces an object file like
PetController.o as output.
Similarly, a linker task
consumes a number of object
files produced by the compiler
in previous tasks.
And produces and executable or
library output.
Like the PetWall executable that
will go into our .app bundle.
And hopefully you're starting to
see a bit of a pattern emerge
here.
You can see how the dependency
information flows through this
graph structure which ultimately
informs the order of execution.
Now if you look at the
compilation tasks in the graph
as sort of like lanes of
traffic.
You can see hoe the compilation
tasks are totally independent in
their own lanes and can
therefore run in parallel.
And because the linker task
takes everything else's input,
we know that has to come last.
So the build system uses
dependency information to
determine the order in which
tasks should be run and which
tasks can be run in parallel and
we call this dependency order.
Now that we've covered what the
build process is, let's go into
a little more detail on how it
works.
What happens when you press
build?
So the first step is for the
build system to take the build
description, your Xcode project
file.
Parse it, take into account all
the files in your project, your
targets and the dependency
relationships.
Your build settings, and turn it
into a tree-like structure
called a directed graph.
And this represents all the
dependencies between the input
and output files in your project
and the tasks that will be
executed to process them.
Next the low-level execution
engine processes this graph,
looks at the dependency
specifications and figures out
which tasks to execute.
The sequence or order in which
they must be run and which tasks
can be run in parallel.
Then proceeds to execute them.
And by the way, our low-level
build execution engine for the
new build system is called
llbuild.
And it's open source and
developed on GitHub.
If you're interested in build
systems development, feel free
to check it out and see how it
works.
We'll have a link to this and
other open source components
related to the build process at
the end of the talk.
Okay, let's talk about
discovered dependencies.
Now since you can never have too
much dependency information, the
build system might actually
discover more information during
the task execution process.
For example, when Clang compiles
an Objective-C file, it produces
and object file as you'd expect.
But it can also produce another
file that contains a listing of
which header files were included
by that source file.
Then the next time you build,
the build system uses the
information from this file to
make sure that it recompiles the
source file if you change any of
the header files that it
includes.
And you can see the dependency
path through PetController.h,
PetController.d, .n, all the way
to the .o file.
Now we've been talking a lot
about how the build system's
main job is to execute tasks.
And of course the bigger your
project, the longer the build
process will take.
So you don't want to run all of
these tasks every single time
you build.
Instead, the build system might
only execute a subset of the
tasks on the graph.
Depending on the changes you've
made to your project since the
previous build.
We refer to this as an
incremental build and having
accurate dependency information
is very important in order for
incremental builds to work
correctly and efficiently.
Now we talked about how changes
affect the build system, and how
they relate to incremental
builds.
So how does the build system
actually detect changes?
Each task in the build process
has an associate signature which
is the sort of hash that's
computed from various
information related to that
task.
This information includes the
stat infor of the task's inputs
like file paths and modification
time stamps.
The command line indication used
to actually perform the command.
And other task-specific metadata
such as the version of the
compiler that's being used.
The build system keeps track of
the signatures of tasks in both
the current and the previous
build.
So that it knows whether to
rerun a task each time a build
is performed.
If the signature of any given
task is different than the
signature that it had in the
previous build, then the build
system reruns that task.
If they're the same, then it's
skipped.
That's the basic idea behind how
incremental builds work.
So now that we have an idea of
what the build process is and
how it works, how can you help
the build system do its job?
Let's go back to basics for a
moment.
A build process is a series of
tasks executed in a particular
order.
But remember that the build is
represented as a directed graph.
So we don't want to think about
the order in which these tasks
should be executed because
that's the build system's job.
Instead, as developers, we need
to think about dependencies
between tasks and let the build
system figure out how to best
execute them according to the
graph's structure.
This lets the build system order
tasks correctly and parallelize
where possible in order to take
full advantage of multicore
hardware.
So where do dependencies come
from?
For certain tasks, dependency
information comes from knowledge
built into the build system.
The build system ships with
rules for the compiler, the
linker, the asset catalogue and
story board processors and so
on.
And these rules define what kind
of files are accepted as inputs
as well as what outputs are
produced.
There's also target dependencies
which roughly determine the
order in which targets are
built.
And in some cases, the build
system can compile sources of
different targets and parallel.
Previously in Xcode, when a
target was built, it required
the compilation of the entire
dependent target to be completed
before it could start.
In Xcode X's new build system,
targets can start building
sooner.
This means that your compile
sources phase can start earlier
providing your some
parallelization for free.
However, note that if you're
making use of any run script
phases, those script phases will
need to complete before this
parallelization can take effect.
Somewhat related to target
dependencies are implicit
dependencies.
For example, if you list a
target in your link library with
binaries build phase and
implicit dependencies are
enabled in the scheme editor,
that's on by default, by the
way, the build system will
establish an implicit dependency
on that target even if it's not
listed in target dependencies.
Next up are build phase
dependencies.
In the target editor, you'll
notice that there's a number of
build phases.
Copy headers, compile sources,
copy bundle resources and so on.
The tasks associated with each
of these phrases are usually
running groups according to the
order in which the phases are
listed.
But the build system might
ignore that order if it knows
better.
Like if you have a link library,
linked binary with library space
ordered before compile sources.
And note that there's cases
where having the wrong build
phase order can cause build
issues or failures, so make sure
to understand your dependencies
and verify that your build
phases are in the right
sequence.
There's also scheme order
dependencies.
If you have the parallelize
build check box enabled in your
scheme settings, you get better
build performance and the order
of your targets in your scheme
doesn't matter.
However, if you turn parallelize
build off, Xcode will attempt to
build their, your targets in the
order you listed them in the
build action of the scheme one
by one.
Target dependencies still have
higher priority in determining
which targets build first.
But otherwise, Xcode will
respect that ordering.
Now it might be tempting to use
this as it gives you a
predictable build order even if
you haven't set your
dependencies correctly.
But you're sacrificing a lot of
parallelization when you do this
and slowing down your build.
So we recommend that you leave
the parallelize builds checkbox
enabled, set up your target
dependencies correctly and don't
rely on ordering.
Lastly, dependency information
comes from you, the developers.
If you're creating custom shell
script build phases or build
rules, make sure to tell the
build system what its inputs and
outputs are.
This lets the build system avoid
rerunning the script tasks
unnecessarily.
And can help make sure that they
are executed in the right order.
You can define the inputs and
outputs in the run script phase
editor.
And the paths of these files
will be made available to your
script as environment variables.
Don't rely on auto-link for
target dependencies in your
project.
The client compiler has a
feature called auto-link which
can be enabled using the link
frameworks automatically build
setting.
This setting allows the compiler
to automatically link to the
frameworks corresponding to any
modules you import without
having to explicitly link them
in your link library's build
phase.
However, it's important to note
that auto-link does not
establish dependency on that
framework at the build system
level.
So it won't guarantee that the
target you depend on is actually
built before you try to link
against it.
So you should rely on this
feature only for frameworks from
the platform STK.
Like Foundation and UIKit since
we know those will already exist
before the build even starts.
For targets in your own
projects, make sure to add
explicit library dependencies.
You might also need to create
project references by dragging
and dropping another Xcode
project into your project's file
navigator in order to reveal the
targets of other projects you
depend on.
In conclusion, with accurate
dependency information, the
build system can better
parallelize your builds, and
help ensure that you get
consistent results every time so
that you can spend less time
building and more time
developing.
For more information on how to
speed up your builds and make
the most of all those cores in
your shiny new iMac Pro, we'd
recommend that you check out
Building Faster in Xcode
Session.
And with that, I'm going to hand
it over to Jurgen, who's going
to take you into the realm of
the compiler.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Jake.
And now we're going to talk
about what happens behind the
scenes when Xcode build system
invokes the Clang compiler.
Hello, everyone.
My name is Jurgen, and I'm a
Compiler Engineer on a Clang
Frontend Team.
Today I'm going to talk about
two features you might not know
about.
The first feature is called
header maps and how we use them
to communicate information from
the Xcode build system to the
Clang compiler.
The second feature is called
Clang modules and how we use
them to speed up your builds.
Some of you might only use Swift
by now.
But I want to tell you, Swift
uses Clang behind the scenes.
So there might be something
interesting for you here, too.
So what is Clang?
Clang is Apple's official C
compiler and all the other C
language family such as C, C++,
and of course Objective-C which
is used for the majority of all
frameworks.
As Jake mentioned in the
beginning, the compilers invoked
[inaudible] for every input file
and it creates exactly one
output file which is then later
consumed by the linker.
If you want to access APIs from
the iOS, or you want to access
implementations from your own
code, you usually have to
include something what is called
a header file.
A header file is a promise.
You promise somewhere else this
implementation exists.
And they usually match.
Of course if you update only the
header file-- only the
implementation file and forget
the header file, you broke your
promise.
Very often this doesn't break
the compile time because the
compiler trusts your promise.
Usually this breaks during link
time.
The compiler usually does
include more than one header
file, and this is done for all
compiler invocation.
So let's have a look at our
example application and see how
we deal with header files.
This is PetWall, it's a
mixed-language application.
The application itself is
written in Swift.
And it uses a framework that's
written in Objective-C.
And it has a support library
aesthetic archive that use--
that's written in C++.
Over time, our application grew.
And we start to reorganize it so
we can find things easier.
For example, we moved all the
cat-related files into a
subfolder.
We didn't have to change any of
our implementation files.
And it still works.
So it makes you wonder how does
Clang find your header files?
Let's look at a simple example.
This is one of our
implementation files we use in
our code and we include our
header file called cat.h. How
can we figure out what Clang
does?
Once thing you could do is you
can go into the build logs, look
what the Xcode build system did
to compile this particular file.
And copy and paste that
invocation.
You drop it into a terminal and
add the -v option.
Dash-v is symbol for verbose.
And then Clang will tell you
lots of information.
But let's just concentrate on
the one that matter which is the
search paths.
I say search paths and many of
you might expect to see now here
search paths that point back to
your source code.
But it's not how this works.
Instead you will see something
called headermaps.
Headermaps are used [inaudible]
by the Xcode build system to
communicate where those header
files are.
So let's have a look at those.
Let's have a look the most
important two file-- headermap
files we care about.
The first two entries simply
append the framework name to
your header.
Those two headers in the
beginning are public headers.
I say you shouldn't rely on this
feature.
The reason is we keep this there
to keep existing projects
working but there might be
issues down the road with Clang
modules so we suggest that you
always specify the framework
name when you include a public
or private header file from your
own framework.
Third entry is a project header.
In this case, this is not
required.
And the whole purpose of the
headermap is to point back to
your source code.
As you can see, we do the same
thing for the public and private
headers.
We always point back to your
source code.
We do this so that Clang can
produce useful error and warning
messages for the files in your
source directory and not a
potential copy that might be
somewhere else in the build
directory.
Since many people were not aware
that we use headermaps, you run
into certain issues.
A very common one is that we
forgot to add the header to the
project.
It is in the source directory,
but it is not in the project
itself.
So always add your headers to
the project.
Another issue is that if you
have headers with the same name,
they might shadow each other.
So always try to use unique
names for your headers.
This also applies to system
headers.
If you have a local header in
your project that has the name
as a system header, it will
shadow the system header so you
should try to avoid this.
Talking about system headers.
How do we find those?
Another example from our
PetWall.
Here in this case we include
Foundation.h header file which
is in our SDK.
We can do the same thing we did
before when you were looking for
our own header files.
But now we're looking for the
system header.
It's just that headermaps are
only for your own headers.
So we can ignore them.
Let's focus on the include path
[inaudible] matter.
So at default, we always look in
two directories in the SDK.
the first one is user include,
the second one is system library
frameworks.
Let's have a look at the first
one.
It's a regular include
directory.
So the only thing we have to do
is we have to append the search
term.
In this case,
Foundation/Foundation.h. And we
won't find the header because
it's not there.
But it's okay.
Let's try the next entry.
Let's look into system library
frameworks.
This one is a frameworks
directory that means Clang has
to behave a little bit
different.
First of all, it has to identify
what is the framework and check
if the framework exists.
After that, it has to look in
the headers directory for the
header file.
This case, it finds it so it's
fine.
But what happens if we don't
find the header?
For example, we have a bogus
header that doesn't exist.
It obviously fails to find it in
the headers directory.
But the next, it will also look
in the private headers
directory.
Apple doesn't ship any private
headers in its SDK.
but your project, your
frameworks might have public and
private headers.
So we always will look there
too.
Since it's a bogus header, it's
not there either.
Interesting now, we actually
will abort the search now.
We will not keep searching in
other search directories.
The reason is we already found
the head-- we already found the
framework.
Once you find the framework, we
expect to find the header in
this framework directory.
If you don't find it, we
complete abort the search.
If you're curious how your
implementation file looks like,
after all those headers got
imported and preprocessed.
You can ask Xcode to create a
preprocessed file for you, for
your implementation file.
This will create a very large
output file.
So how big is that file?
Let's use a very simple example.
Foundation.h is a very
fundamental header, fundamental
header to our system.
It is-- you are very likely to
import this header either
directly or indirectly for some
other header file.
That means every compiler
invocation you're most likely
going to have to find this
header.
At the end of the day, Clang has
to find and process over 800
header files for the single
include statement.
That's over 9 megabyte of source
code that has to be parsed and
verified.
And that happens for every
compiler invocation.
That's a lot of work, and it's
redundant.
So can we do better?
One of the features you might be
aware of is called precompiled
header files.
That's one way to improve this.
But we have something better.
A few years back, we introduced
Clang modules.
Clang modules allow us to only
find and parse the headers once
per framework and then store
that information on disk so it's
cached and can be reused.
This should have improved your
build times.
In order to do that, Clang
modules must have certain
properties.
One of them, one of the most
important one is context-free.
What do I mean by context-free?
You can see here two code
snippets.
In both cases we import the
PetKit module.
But we have two different macro
definitions beforehand.
If you would use a traditional
model of importing those
headers, that means they're
[inaudible] included.
The preprocessor would honor
this definition and apply it to
the header file.
But if you would do that, that
means the modules would be
different for each header case,
and we couldn't reuse it.
So if you want to use modules,
you cannot do that.
Instead, the module will ignore
all those context-related
information that allows us to
be, that allows it to be reused
across all implementation files.
Another requirement is modules
have to be self-contained.
That means they have to specify
all the dependencies.
Which also has a nice advantage
for you because it means once
you import a module, it will
just work.
You don't have to worry about
adding any additional header
files to make that import work.
So how do we know or how does
Clang know it should build a
module?
Let's look at a simple example
here NSString.h. First Clang has
to find this particular header
in the framework.
And we already know how to do
that.
And it's the
Foundation.framework directory.
Next the Clang compiler will
look for a modules directory and
a Module Map relative to the
header's directory and it's
there.
So what is a Module Map?
A Module Map describes how a
certain set of header files
translate onto your module.
So let's have a look.
The Module Map is actually very
simple.
This is the whole Module Map for
foundation.
That's it.
It obviously describes what is
the name of the module which is,
Foundation.
And then it also specifies what
headers are part of this module.
You'll notice there's only one
header file here, only
Foundation.h. But this is a
special header file.
This is the umbrella header
which is also marked by the
special keyword umbrella.
That means Clang has also to
look into this particular header
file to figure out if NSString.h
is part of the module.
And yeah, it's there, okay.
So now we have found out
NSString.h is part of the
foundation module.
Now Clang, now Clang can upgrade
this textual import to a module
import and we know we have to
build the foundation module to
do that.
So how do we build the
foundation module?
First of all, we create a
separate Clang location for
that.
And that Clang location contains
all the header files from the
foundation module.
We don't transfer any of the
existing context from the
original compiler invocation.
Hence, it's context-free.
The thing we actually transfer
are the command line arguments
you passed to Clang.
Those are passed on.
While we build the foundation
module, we mod-- the module
itself or the framework, the
framework itself will include
additional frameworks.
That means we have to build
those modules too.
And we have to keep going
because those might also include
additional frameworks.
But we already can see there is
a benefit here.
Some of those imports might be
the same.
So we can always start reusing
that module.
All those modules are
[inaudible] to disk into
something called a module cache.
As I mentioned, the command line
arguments are passed on when you
create that module.
That means, that means those
arguments can affect the content
of your module.
As a result, we have to hash all
those arguments and store the
modules we created for this
particular compiler invocation
in a directory matching that
hash.
If you change the compiler
arguments for different
limitation file, for example
you'd say enable cat, that is a
different hash and that requires
Clang to rebuild all the
module's inputs into that
directory matching that hash.
So in order to get the maximum
reuse out of the module cache,
you should try to keep the
arguments the same, if possible.
So this is how we find and build
modules for system frameworks
but what about your frameworks?
How do we build modules for
those?
Let's go back to our original
cat example, and this time we
turn on modules.
If we would use a headermap
again, the headermap will point
us back to the source directory.
But if you look at that source
directory, we have a problem
now.
Theirs is no modules directory.
It doesn't look like a framework
at all and Clang doesn't know
how to do this in this case.
So we introduced a new concept
to solve this, and it's called
Clang's Virtual File System.
It basically creates a virtual
abstraction of a framework that
allows Clang to build the
module.
But the abstraction basically
only points to the files back in
your directory.
So again, Clang will be able to
produce [inaudible] and errors
for your source code.
And that's how we build modules
for, when you have frameworks.
As you remember, in the
beginning I mentioned there
might be issues if you don't
specify the framework name.
So let me give you an example
where this can go wrong.
This is a very simple-- very
simple code example.
We only have two imports.
The first import imports the
pet, PetKit module.
The second import, you and I
know this is also part of the
PetKit module, but Clang might
now be able to figure that out
because you didn't specify the
framework name.
In this case, it might be
possible you get duplicate
definition errors.
That's basically, that basically
happens when you import the same
header twice.
Clang works very hard behind the
scenes to fix the most common
issues that happen like this.
But it cannot fix all of them.
And this is just a simple
example.
Let's just make a little tweak.
Let's change the context.
Now the module import won't be
affected by this at all because
as I said, we ignore the
context.
The cat import is still a
textual inclusion of the header
which will observe this change.
So now you might not even have
duplicate definitions.
You might even have
contradictory definitions.
Which can mean we cannot fix,
Clang cannot fix this for you.
So as I recommended in the
beginning, always specify the
framework name when you import
your public or private headers.
And now I'm handing it over to
Devin who's going to talk about
Swift and how Swift uses Clang
modules.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Jurgen.
We're now going to dive into the
details of how Swift and the
build system work together to
find declarations across your
project.
To recap some of what Jurgen
told you, Clang compiles each
Objective-C file separately.
This means if you want to refer
to a class to find in another
file, you have to import a
header that declares that class.
But Swift was designed to not
require you to write headers.
This makes it easier for
beginners to get started with
the language.
And avoids you having to repeat
a declaration in a separate
file.
However this does mean that the
compiler has to perform some
additional bookkeeping.
I'm going to tell you how that
bookkeeping works.
Let's return to our example,
PetWall app.
The app has a view in
ViewCcontroller, written in
Swift.
An Objective-C app delegate.
And Swift unit tests.
In order to compile even just
this top PetViewController part
of the file, the compiler has to
perform four different
operations.
First, it has to find
declarations.
Both within the Swift target and
also coming from Objective-C.
Further, it has to generate
interfaces describing the
contents of the file.
So that its declarations can be
found and used in Objective-C
and in other Swift targets.
In the rest of this section of
the talk, I'm going to walk
through this example to
illustrate each of these four
tasks.
Let's start with finding
declarations within a Swift
target.
When compiling
PetViewController.swift, the
compiler will look up the type
of PetView's initializer so that
it can check the call.
But before it can do that, it
needs to parse PetView.swift and
validate it.
To make sure that the
declaration of the initializer
is well formed.
Now, the compiler's smart enough
to know that it doesn't need to
check the body of the
initializer here.
But it does still need to do
some work just to process the
interface parts of the file.
What this means is that unlike
Clang, when compiling one Swift
file, the compiler will parse
all the other Swift files in the
target.
To examine the parts of them
that are relevant to the
interfaces.
IN Xcode 9, this resulted in
some repeated work in repeated
build-- in incremental debug
builds.
Because the compiler compiled
each file separately.
This enabled the files to be
compiled in parallel, but it
forced the compiler to
repeatedly parse each file.
Once as an implementation to
produce a .o, and multiple times
as an interface to find
declarations.
Xcode 10 reduces this overhead.
It does so by combining the
files into groups that share as
much work as possible.
While still allowing maximum
parallelism.
This reuses parsing within a
group and only repeats work
across groups.
Since the number of groups is
typically relatively low, this
can significantly speed up your
incremental debug builds.
Now, Swift code doesn't only
call other Swift code.
It can also call Objective-C.
Returning to our PetWall example
app, we can see that, that this
is crucial since the system
frameworks such as UIKit are
written in Objective-C.
Swift takes a different approach
than many other languages.
And it doesn't require you to
provide a foreign function
interface.
This is where you would have to,
for example, write a Swift
declaration for each Objective-C
API you want to use.
Instead, the compiler embeds a
large part of Clang inside of it
and uses it as a library.
This makes it possible to import
Objective-C frameworks directly.
So where do Objective-C
declarations come from?
The compile-- the importer will
look in headers depending on the
type of the target.
In any target, when you import
an Objective-C framework, the
importer finds declarations in
the headers exposing Clang's
module map for that framework.
Within a framework that mixes
Swift and Objective-C code, the
importer finds declarations in
the umbrella header.
This is the header that defines
the public interface.
In this way, Swift code inside
the framework can call public
Objective-C code in the same
framework.
Finally, within your app and
unit tests, you can add imports
to the target's bridging header.
To allow declarations from them
to be called from Swift.
Now when the importer brings in
declarations, it often changes
them to make them more
idiomatic.
For example, it will import
Objective-C methods that use the
NSError idiom as throwing
methods using Swift's built-in
error handling language feature.
In particular, it will drop
parameter type names following
verbs and prepositions.
For example, the drawPet atPoint
method has the word pet.
For a parameter of type pet
following the verb draw.
And similarly the word point for
a parameter of type CGPoint
following the preposition at.
These words are omitted in Swift
when the method is imported as
simply draw at.
So how does this work?
Well, you might be surprised to
know that the compiler contains
a list of common English verbs
and prepositions.
Because it is just a hard-coded
list and human language is
messy, sometimes it's missing
words.
Furthermore, in order to match
Swift's naming conventions, the
importer will also rename
methods to remove words based on
the part of speech.
For example the verb feed is not
in the list, and so feedPet is
not imported as feed as we might
expect.
When this happens, you can use
the NS Swift Name annotation to
have the compiler import the
method exactly as you want.
Now if you want to check to see
how your Objective-C header will
be imported into Swift, you can
always go to Xcode's related
items popup.
This is in the upper left-hand
corner of the source editor.
If you select generated
interfaces, it will show you how
the interface will look in
different versions of Swift.
So that's how Swift imports
Objective-C.
But what about the other
direction?
How does Objective-C import
Swift?
The answer is that Swift
generates a header that you can
pound import.
This allows you to write classes
in Swift and call them from
Objective-C.
Let's see how this works.
The compiler will generate
Objective-C declarations for
Swift classes extending NSObject
and methods marked at obc.
For apps in unit tests, the
header will include both public
and internal declarations.
This allows you to use internal
Swift from the Objective-C parts
of your app.
For frameworks, however, the
generated header provides only
public declarations.
Since it's included in your
build products and it's part of
the framework's public
interface.
On the right, you can see that
the compiler ties the
Objective-C class to the mangled
name of the Swift class which
includes the name of the module,
PetWall.
Now I'm going to tell you about
modules in a bit, and Louis will
tell you about mangling.
But for now, the thing to know
is that this prevents a conflict
in the runtime when the two
modules define a class with the
same name.
You can tell Swift to use a
different name for the class in
Objective-C by passing an
identifier to the obc attribute.
But if you do this, you're
responsible for making sure the
names don't conflict.
Here I've used the PWL prefix so
to reduce the likelihood of a
conflict.
With this change, I can refer to
the class as PWLPetCollar in
Objective-C.
The compiler takes a similar
approach to generating
interfaces to other Swift
targets.
To do this, Swift builds on
Clang's concept of a module,
which Jurgen told you about.
And more deeply integrates it
into the language.
In Swift, a module is a
distributable unit of
declarations.
And to be able to use those
declarations you have to import
the module.
You can import Objective-C
modules.
XEtest, for example.
And in Xcode each Swift target
produces a separate module.
Including your app target.
This is why you have to import
your app's main module in order
to test it from your unit tests.
When importing a module, the
compiler deserializes a special
Swift module file to check the
types when you use them.
For example, in this unit test,
the compiler will load the
PetViewController parts of the
PetWall Swift module to make
sure that you're creating the
controller correctly.
This is similar to how the
compiler finds declarations
within a target as I showed you
earlier.
Except that here, the compiler
loads a file summarizing the
module rather than parsing Swift
files directly.
The compiler produces this Swift
module file a lot like a
generated Objective-C header.
But instead of text, it's a
binary representation.
It includes the bodies of
inlineable functions much like
static inline functions in
Objective-C or header
implementations in C++.
However, one thing to be aware
of is that it does include the
names and types of private
declarations.
This allows you to refer to them
in the debugger which is really
handy.
But it does mean that for
example, you shouldn't name a
private variable after your
deepest, darkest secret.
For incremental builds, the
compiler produces partial Swift
module files and then merges
them into a single file that
represents the contents of the
entire module.
This merging process also makes
it possible to produce a single
Objective-C header.
In many ways, this is similar to
what the linker does when it
smooshes together your object
files into a single executable.
And to tell you more about that,
I'll hand it off to Louis and
the linker.
Louis?
>> Thank you, Devin.
[ Applause ]
Hi, I'm Louis Gerbarg.
I work on the linker.
Which is one of the final steps
in the Xcode build process.
So let's get to it.
So first off I want to go over
what we're going to talk about.
We're going to talk about what a
linker is.
We're going to talk about the
input that it takes which are
dylibs and object files and what
they are.
And we're also going to talk
about symbols which are what
those contain.
So at the end of this, I'm going
to tie this together with an
act-- with an example because
this is pretty dense stuff.
So if it seems a little
confusing.
Hold on, and hopefully we'll
make it clearer.
So what is the linker?
It's like I said, it's one of
the final processes in the
build.
And what we do is we combine all
of these .o files that have been
built by the two compilers into
an executable.
All it does is move and patch
code.
It cannot create code, and this
is important and I will show
that in the example.
But we take these two kinds of
input files.
The first one being dylibs or
being libraries.
There are multiple-- the first
one being object files.
Which are what come out of your
build process.
And the second one being
libraries which consist of
several types including dylibs,
tbd's, and .a files or static
archives.
So what are symbols?
A symbol is just a name to refer
to a fragment of code or data.
These fragments may refer to
other symbols which you would
see if you write a function that
calls another function.
Symbols can have attributes on
them that affect how the linker
behaves.
And there are a lot of these.
I'm just going to give you one
example which is a weak symbol.
So a weak symbol is an
annotation on a symbol that says
it might not be there when we
run the syst-- when we build
the, when we run the executable
on the system.
This is what all the
availability markup that says
this API is available on iOS 12.
And this API's available on the
iOS 11.
This, that's what it all boils
down to by the time it gets to
the linker.
So the linker can determine what
symbols are definitely going to
be there versus what symbols it
may have to, it may have to deal
with at runtime.
Languages can also encode data
into the symbol by mangling it,
as Devin mentioned earlier.
And you'll see that in both C++
and Swift.
So we have symbols which are
these names referring to code
and data.
So the compilers generate object
files.
And those object files are just
collections of those code and
data.
They are not executable.
While they are compiled code,
they aren't finished.
There are bits missing which is
what the linker's going to glue
together and fix up.
Each fragment in one of those
files is represented by a
symbol.
So for the printf function,
there's code represented by a
symbol.
For any of the functions in
PetKit which we're going to see
in a second, the same thing.
And fragments may reference
undefined symbols.
So if your .o file refers to a
function in another .o file,
that .o file's undefined.
And the linker will go and find
those undefined symbols and link
them up.
So I said that object files are
the output of your compiler
actions.
So what are libraries?
Libraries are files that define
symbols that are not part of the
target you are building.
So we have dynamic libraries,
and those are Mach-O files that
expose code and data fragments
for executables to use.
Those are distributed as part of
the system.
That's what our frameworks are.
And a number of you also use
your own frameworks.
There are also TBD files, or
text-based dylib stubs.
So what are those?
Well, when we made the SDKs for
iOS and macOS, we had all these
dylibs with all these great
functions like MapKit and WebKit
that you may want to use.
But we don't want to ship the
entire copy of those with the
SDK because it would be large.
Ant the compiler and linker
don't need.
It's only needed to run the
program.
So instead we create what's
called a stub dylib where we
delete the bodies of all of the
symbols and we just have the
names.
And then once we did that, we've
made a textual representation of
them that are easier for us to
use.
Currently, they are only used
for distributing the SDKs to
reduce size.
So you may see them in your
project, but you don't have to
worry about them.
And they only contain symbols.
Finally, we have static
archives.
So static archives are just
collections of .o files that
have been built with the AR tool
or in some cases the lib the lib
tool which is a wrapper for
that.
And according to the AR
[inaudible] page, the AR utility
creates and maintains groups of
files combined into an archive.
Now that may sound a lot like a
TAR file or a ZIP file, and
that's exactly what it is.
In fact, the .a format was the
original archive format used by
UNIX before more powerful tools
came around.
But the compilers of the time
and the linkers of the time
natively understood them, and
they've just kept using them.
So it really is just an archive
file.
One thing worth noting is they
also prenate dynamic linking so
back in those days, all of the
code would be consid-- would be
distributed as archives.
Because of that, you might not
want to include all of the C
library if you're using one
function.
So the behavior is if there's a
symbol in a .o file, we would
pull that whole .o file out of
the archive.
But the other .o files would not
be brought in.
If you're referencing symbols
between them, everything you
need will be brought in.
If you're using some sort of
non-symbol behavior like a
static initializer, or you're
re-exporting them as part of
your own dylib, you may need to
explicitly use something like
force load or all load to the
linker to tell it bring in
everything.
Or these files, even though
there's no linkage.
So let's go through an example
to try to tie this altogether.
So up on stage we have an
example of a playSound function
because what fun would be
looking at pets without
listening to them?
And you know it calls playSound.
You know, there's a function on
cat that calls playSound.
That seems pretty simple.
So let's look at the assembly
that generates.
So here's cat.o that comes out
of it.
Now if we look, we can see we
have the string purr.aac which
would be our AAC sound file.
And that gets copied into cat.o.
You'll note that the name purr
file does not appear in there
anywhere.
The reason is, that's a static.
And those of you who are
familiar with C, that means it's
a nonexported name.
Nobody else can refer to it.
Since nobody else can refer to
it, we don't need it.
It's not included.
And then we see Cat purr becomes
an actual symbol: dash, open
bracket, Cat purr, close
bracket.
Pretty much what you'd expect.
And then we see we actually have
to get this variable we're going
to pass into playSound.
And you'll note there are two
instructions referring to that.
And that's because we don't know
where this string is going to
end up in the final executable.
We don't have a concrete address
for it.
But we know that on RM64 which
is what this assembly is, it
could take at most two
instructions.
So the compiler leaves us with
two instructions.
And it leaves the symbolic
offset, the symbolic values page
and page off that the linker
will come in and fix up later.
Finally, now that we've loaded
that string into x0, we can call
playSound except for we're not
calling playSound.
We're calling underbar underbar
z9playSound PKc.
Now what is that?
That's a mangled symbol because
if you note, it says cat.mm.
This is Objective-C++.
And playSound is actually a C++
function.
So if you're not familiar with
those, you can go to terminal
and you can actually use tools.
So if you run Swift-demangle and
pass in a symbol, it will
attempt to demangle it.
It didn't work.
It's not a Swift symbol.
But C++ filts, which is the C++
demangler shows us that this is
in fact a symbol for playSound.
But not only is it playSound, we
know it takes one argument.
And that one argument is a const
char star because C++ encoded
that extra data into the mangled
symbol.
Okay, so now we have a .o. In
fact, we're building a project,
we'll have a lot of them.
So what are we going to do with
that?
Well, first off, the build
system is going to pass all of
the .o's in as inputs to the
linker.
And the linker's going to start
by creating a file to put them
in.
In this case we're building
PetKit which is an embedded
framework inside of PetWall.
And so we'll just start by
copying.
We'll create what's called a
text segment.
Which is where we keep all of
the code for an application.
And we'll take the cat.o and
we'll copy it in.
But we're going to split it into
two sections.
One for that string, and one for
the executable code.
But we now know the absolute
addresses of these things so the
linker can go and rewrite cat.o
to load from a specific offset.
You'll notice that the second
instruction just went away.
We replaced it with what, with a
null instruction that does
nothing.
But we cannot remove the
instruction because we can't
create or remove code.
It would mess up all of the
sizing that we've already done.
So instead it just is removed.
It, it's just replaced with a no
operation.
Finally we branch.
Okay, but we branch and what are
we going to do?
Because we have this undefined
symbol?
Well, we're going to go and keep
looking through, and all of our
.o's have been included at this
point.
So we'll start looking at the
static archives [inaudible] and
PetSupport.a is there.
And inside of PetSupport.a, we
have a couple of files including
PetSounds.o. And if we look, we
see that matching file-- that
matching symbol for playSound.
So we pull it in.
We'll note that we do not pull
in PetCare.o. Because that .o
file did not have any symbols
that were referred to by any of
the other portions of the
application.
Okay, so we pulled that in, but
now that needs, open which we
didn't define.
You'll see in the, in the, the
conversion we copied in.
We actually replaced it with
something called open$stub.
Now why did we do that?
Well we kept looking, and we
found a copy of open.
And that copy of open is in the
lib system TBD file.
And so we said I know this is
part of the system library.
I'm not going to copy this into
my application.
But I need to put enough
information in the information
to make it so that it can call
this.
So we create a fake function
that's just a template where we
replaced a function with
whatever we're pulling out of
lib system which is open in this
case.
And if you look in that
function, it actually loads from
a pointer, open$ pointer.
And jumps to it.
So we just need a function
pointer, just like any normal C
function pointer.
And we'll create that down in
the data segment which is where
global variables would be if you
had any globals.
But it's just set to zero.
So if we dereference null and
jump to it we're going to crash.
So we then add what's called a
link edit segment.
And the link edit is metadata
that the linker tool uses to
leave information for the
operating system and what's
called the dynamic linker to fix
this up at runtime.
And for more information on that
you should look at the
Optimizing App Startup Time
session from 2016.
So I just want to go back over
what we went through today.
So Jake talked about the build
system and how you can use
dependencies to optimize your
built process for multi-core.
Jurgen walked through Clang and
how it finds headers for you.
And what you can do to optimize
your build-through modules.
Devin walked through how Swift
expand modules and all of the
things that we've implemented
this year like [inaudible]
processing to speed up your
builds.
And then finally the linker
takes the outputs of both
compilers and builds them into
your application.
At which point Xcode will go
and, and code [inaudible] and
package it up with other parts
of your application for
distribution.
So most of this is open source,
available if you're really
curious.
You can look at Swift or Clang
or the llbuild execution engine
at these URLs.
And I just want to thank you all
for coming.
And I hope you've had a great
WWDC.
And we'll be in the labs.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]