[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Hello.
Welcome to Testing Tips &
Tricks.
My name is Brian Croom.
My colleague, Stuart, and I are
really excited to share some
great testing techniques with
you that we have been learning
recently.
As the conference was
approaching, we thought it would
be really cool to have an app
that we could use to find cool
things to see and do around the
area of the convention center.
We've been building this app,
giving it views for finding
various point of interest around
San Jose and listing how far
they are away from you.
Now, of course, we wanted to
make sure we had a really great
test suite for this app that we
could run to give us confidence
that our code was working
properly and would keep working
as we continue development.
Today, we want to share four
simple techniques with you that
we found really helpful while
writing tests for our app.
Some strategies for testing
networking code in your app,
some tips for tests dealing with
foundation notification objects,
ways to take advantage of
protocols when making mock
objects in your tests, and a few
techniques for keeping your
tests running really fast.
Let's start talking about
networking.
To allow for dynamic content
updates, we've been building our
app to load its data from a
remote web server.
Here are some things that we
found useful when writing tests
for networking code.
But first, quick, a recap from
last year.
At WWDC 2017's Engineering
Testability session, we
discussed the pyramid model as a
guide to how to structure a test
suite, balancing thoroughness,
understandability, and execution
speed.
In summary, an ideal test suite
tends to be composed of a large
percentage of focused unit
tests, exercising individual
classes and methods in your app.
These are characterized by being
simple to read, producing clear
failure messages when we detect
a problem, and by running very
quickly, often in the order of
hundreds or thousands of tests
per minute.
These are complemented by a
smaller number of medium-sized
integration tests that targeted
discreet subsystem or cluster of
classes in your app, checking
that they worked together
properly, each taking no more
than a few seconds to run.
And the suite is topped off by a
handful of end-to-end system
tests, most often taking the
form of UI tests that exercise
the app in a way very similar to
how the end-user will do so on
their devices, checking that all
the pieces are hooked up
properly and interact well with
the underlying operating system
and external resources.
A test suite following this
model can provide a
comprehensive picture of how an
app code's base is functioning.
For testing the networking stack
in this app, we really wanted to
take the pyramid model to heart
and use it as a guide for how to
structure our test suite.
Here, we see the high-level data
flow involved in making a
network request in the app and
feeding the data into the UI.
In an early prototype of the
app, we had a method in our view
controller that was doing all of
this in a single place, and it
looked like this.
The method takes a parameter
with the user's location and
uses that to construct a URL for
a service API endpoint with a
location as query parameters.
Then it uses Foundation's
URLSession APIs to make a data
task for a get request to that
URL.
Then the server responds, it
would unwrap the data, decode it
using foundation's JSONDecoder
API, into an array of point of
interest values, which is a
struct that I declared elsewhere
and conforms the decodable
protocol.
And it stores that into a
property to drive a table view
[inaudible] implementation,
putting it onto the screen.
Now, it's pretty remarkable that
I was able to do all of this in
just about 15 lines of code,
leveraging the power of Swift
and Foundation, but, by putting
this together in the one method,
I [inaudible] the
maintainability and especially
the testability of this code.
Looking at the base of our
testing pyramid, what we really
want to be able to do here is
write focus unit tests for each
of these pieces of the flow.
Let's first consider the request
preparation and response parsing
steps.
In order to make this code more
testable, we started by pulling
it out of the view controller
and made two methods on this
dedicated
PointsOfInterestRequest type,
giving us two nicely decoupled
methods that each take some
values as input and transform
them into some output values
without any side effects.
This makes it very
straightforward for us to write
a focused unit test for the
code.
Here we're testing the
makeRequest method just by
making a sample and put
location, passing it into the
method, and making some
assertions about its return
value.
Similarly, we can test the
response parsing by passing in
some mock JSON and making
assertions about the parsed
result.
One other thing to note about
this test is that I'm taking
advantage of XCTest support for
test methods marked as throws,
allowing me to use try in my
test code without needing an
explicit do catch block around
it.
Now, let's see the code for
interacting with URL session.
Here, again, we pull it out the
view controller, made a
APIRequest protocol with methods
matching the signature of the
methods from the request type
that we just saw.
And this is used by an
APIRequestLoader class.
That's initialized with a
request type and a urlSession
instance.
This class has a loadAPIRequest
method which uses that
apiRequest value to generate a
URL request.
Feed that into the urlSession,
and then use the apiRequest
again to parse in your response.
Now, we can continue write unit
test for this method, but right
now I actually want to move up
the pyramid and look at a
midlevel integration test that
covers several pieces of this
data flow.
Another thing that I really want
to also be able to test at this
layer of my suite is that my
interaction with the URLSession
APIs is correct.
It turns out that the foundation
URL loading system provides a
great hook for doing this.
URLSession provides a high level
API for apps to use to perform
network requests.
[Inaudible] objects like
URLSession data tests that
represent an inflight request.
Behind the scenes though,
there's another lower-level API
URLProtocol which performs the
underlying work of opening
network connection, writing the
request, and reading back a
response.
URLProtocol is designed to be
subclassed giving an
extensibility point for the URL
loading system.
Foundation provides built-in
protocols subclasses for common
protocols like HTTPS.
But we can override these in our
tests by providing a mock
protocol that lets us make
assertions about requests that
are coming out and provide mock
responses.
URLProtocol communicates
progress back to the system via
the URLProtocolClient protocol.
We can use this in this way.
We make a MockURLProtocol class
in our test bundle, overriding
canInit request to indicate to
the system that we're interested
in any request that it offers
us.
Implement canonicalRequest for
request, but the start loading
and stop loading method's where
most of the action happens.
To give our tests a way to hook
into this URLProtocol, we'll
provide a closure property
requestHandler for the test to
set.
When a URLSession task begins,
the system will instantiate our
URLProtocol subclass, giving it
the URLRequest value and a
URLProtocol client instance.
Then it'll call our startLoading
method, where we'll take our
requestHandler to the test
subsets and call it with a
URLRequest as a parameter.
We'll take what it returns and
pass it back to the system,
either as a URL response plus
data, or as an error.
If you want to do test request
cancellation, we could do
something similar in a
stopLoading method
implementation.
With the stub protocol in hand,
we can write our test.
We set up by making an
APIRequestLoader instance,
configure it with a request type
and a URLSession that's been
configured to use our
URLProtocol.
In the test body, we set a
requestHandler on the
MockURLProtocol, making
assertions about the request
that's going out, then providing
a stub response.
Then we can call loadAPIRequest,
waiting for the completion block
to be called, making assertions
about the parsed response.
Couple of tests at this layer
can give us a lot of confidence
that our code is working
together well and, also, that
we're integrating properly with
the system.
For example, this test that we
just saw would have failed if I
had forgotten to call a resume
on my data task.
I'm sure I'm not the only one
who's made that mistake.
Finally, it can also be really
valuable to include some system
level end-to-end tests.
Actually test a UI testing can
be a great tool for this.
To learn more about UI testing,
refer to the UI testing in Xcode
session from WWDC 2015.
Now, a significant challenge
that you encounter when you
start to write true end-to-end
tests is that when something
goes wrong when you get a test
failure, it can be really hard
to know where to start looking
for the source of the problem.
One thing that we were doing in
our test recently to help
mitigate this was to set up a
local instance of a mock server,
interrupting our UI tests to
make requests against that
instead of the real server.
This allowed our UI test to be
much more reliable, because we
had control over the data being
fed back into the app.
Now, while using a mock server
can be really useful in this
context, it is also good to have
some tests making requests
against the real server.
One cool technique for doing
this can be to have some tests
in the unit testing bundle that
call directly into your apps in
that work in Stack and use that
to direct requests against the
real server.
This provides a way of verifying
that the server is accepting
requests the way that your app
is making them and that you're
able to parse the server's
responses without having to deal
with the complications of
testing your UI at the same
time.
So, to wrap up, we've seen an
example of breaking code into
smaller, independent pieces to
facilitate unit testing.
We've seen how URLProtocol can
be used as a tool for mocking
network requests,
and we've discussed how the
power of the pyramid can be used
to help us structure a
well-balanced test suite that'll
give us good confidence in our
code.
Now, I want to call Stuart to
the stage to talk about some
more techniques.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks.
Thanks, Brian.
So, the first area I'd like to
talk about is some best
practices for testing
notifications.
And to clarify, by notification
here, I'm talking about
foundation-level notifications
known as NSNotification and
Objective-C.
So, sometimes we need to test
that a subject observes a
notification, while other times
we need to test that a subject
posts a notification.
Notifications are a one-to-many
communication mechanism, and
that means that when a single
notification is posted, it may
be sent to multiple recipients
throughout your app or even in
the framework code running in
your app's process.
So, because of this, it's
important that we always test
notifications in an isolated
fashion to avoid unintended side
effects, since that can lead to
flaky, unreliable tests.
So, let's look at an example of
some code that has this problem.
Here, I have the
PointsOfInterest
TableViewController from the app
Brian and I are building.
It shows a list of nearby places
of interest in a table view, and
whenever the app's location
authorization changes, it may
need to reload its data.
So, it observes a notification
called authChanged from our
app's CurrentLocationProvider
class.
When it observes this
notification, it reloads its
data if necessary, and, then,
for the purpose of this example,
it sets a flag.
This way, our test code can
check that the flag to see if
the notification was actually
received.
We can see here that it's using
the default notification center
to add the observer.
Let's take a look at what a unit
test for this code might look
like.
Here in our test for this class,
we post the authChanged method
notification to simulate it, and
we post it to the default
NotificationCenter, the same one
that our view controller uses.
Now, this test works, but it may
have unknown side effects
elsewhere in our app's code.
It's common for some system
notifications like UI
applications
appDidFinishLaunching
notification to be observed by
many layers and to have unknown
side effects, or it could simply
slow down our tests.
So, we'd like to isolate this
code better to test this.
There's a technique we can use
to better isolate these tests.
To use it, we first have to
recognize that
NotificationCenter can have
multiple instances.
As you may note, it has a
default instance as a class
property, but it supports
creating additional instances
whenever necessary, and this is
going to be key to isolating our
tests.
So, to apply this technique, we
first have to create a new
NotificationCenter, pass it to
our subject and use it instead
of the default instance.
This is often referred to as
dependency injection.
So, let's take a look at using
this in our view controller.
Here, I have the original code
that uses the default
NotificationCenter, and I'll
modify it to use a separate
instance.
I've added a new
NotificationCenter property and
a parameter in the initializer
that sets it.
And, instead of adding an
observer to the default center,
it uses this new property.
I'll also add a default
parameter value of .default to
the initializer, and this avoids
breaking any existing code in my
app, since existing clients
won't need to pass the new
parameter, only our unit tests
will.
Now let's go back and update our
tests.
Here's the original test code,
and now I've modified it to use
a separate NotificationCenter.
So, this shows how we can test
that our subject observes a
notification, but how do we test
that our subject posts a
notification?
We'll use the same separate
NotificationCenter trick again,
but I'll also show how to make
use of built-in expectation APIs
to add a notification observer.
So, here's another section of
code from our app, the
CurrentLocationProvider class.
I'll talk more about this class
later, but notice that it has
this method for signaling to
other classes in my app that the
app's location authorization has
changed by posting a
notification.
As with our view controller,
it's currently hardcoding the
default NotificationCenter.
And here's a unit test I wrote
for this class.
It verifies that it posts a
notification whenever the
NotifyAuthChanged method is
called, and we can see in the
middle section here that this
test uses the addObserver method
to create a block-based
observer, and then it removes
that observer inside of the
block.
Now, one improvement that I can
make to this test is to use the
built-in
XCTNSNotificationExpectation API
to handle creating this
NotificationCenter observer for
us.
And this is a nice improvement,
and it allows us to delete
several lines of code.
But it still has the problem we
saw before of using the default
NotificationCenter implicitly,
so let's go fix that.
Here's our original code, and
I'll apply the same technique we
saw earlier of taking a separate
NotificationCenter in our
initializer, storing it, and
using it instead of the default.
Going back to our test code now,
I'll modify it to pass a new
NotificationCenter to our
subject, but take a look at the
expectation now.
When our tests are expecting to
receive a notification to a
specific center, we can pass the
NotificationCenter parameter to
the initializer of the
expectation.
I'd also like to point out that
the timeout of this expectation
is 0, and that's because we
actually expect it to already
have been fulfilled by the time
we wait on it.
That's because the notification
should have already been posted
by the time the
NotifyAuthChanged method
returns.
So, using this pair of
techniques for testing
notifications we can ensure that
our tests remained fully
isolated, and we've made the
change without needing to modify
an existing code in our app,
since we specified that default
parameter value.
So, next, I'd like to talk about
a frequent challenge when
writing unit tests, interacting
with external classes.
So, while developing your app,
you've probably run into
situations where your class is
talking to another class, either
elsewhere in your app or
provided by the SDK.
And you found it difficult to
write a test, because it's hard
or even impossible to create
that external class.
This happens a lot, especially
with APIs that aren't designed
to be created directly, and it's
even harder when those APIs have
delegate methods that you need
to test.
I'd like to show how we can use
protocols to solve this problem
by mocking interaction with
external classes but do so
without making our tests less
reliable.
In our app, we have a
CurrentLocationProvider class
that uses CoreLocation.
It creates a CLLocationManager
and configures it in its
initializer, setting its desired
accuracy property and setting
itself as the delegate.
Here's the meat of this class.
It's a method called
checkCurrentLocation.
It requests the current location
and takes a completion block
that returns whether that
location is a point of interest.
So, notice that we're calling
the request location method on
CLLocationManager, here.
When we call this, it'll attempt
to get the current location and
eventually call a delegate
method on our class.
So, let's go look at that
delegate method.
We use an extension to conform
to the CLLocationManagerDelegate
protocol here, and we call a
stored completion block.
Okay, so let's try writing a
unit test for this class.
Here's one that I tried to
write, and, if we read through
it, we can see that it starts by
creating a
CurrentLocationProvider and
checks that the desired accuracy
and whether the delegate is set.
So far, so good.
But then things get tricky.
We want to check the
checkCurrentLocation method,
since that's where our main
logic lives, but we have a
problem.
We don't have a way to know when
the request location method is
called, since that's a method on
CLLocationManager and not part
our code.
Another problem that we're
likely to encounter in this test
is that CoreLocation requires
user authorization, and that
shows a permission dialog on the
device if it hasn't been granted
before.
This causes our tests to rely on
device state.
It makes them harder to maintain
and, ultimately, more likely to
fail.
So, if you've had this problem
in the past, you may have
considered subclassing the
external class and overriding
any methods that you call on it.
For example, we could try
subclassing CLLocationManager
here and overriding the
RequestLocation method.
And that may work at first, but
it's risky.
Some classes from the SDK aren't
designed to be subclassed and
may behave differently.
Plus, we still have to call the
superclass' initializer, and
that's not code that we can
override.
But the main problem is that, if
I ever modify my code to call
another method on
CLLocationManager, I'll have to
remember to override that method
on my testing subclass as well.
If I rely on subclassing, the
compiler won't notify me that
I've started calling another
method, and it's easy to forget
and break my tests.
So, I don't recommend this
method, and instead to mock
external types using protocols.
So, let's walk through how to do
that.
Here's the original code, and
the first step is to define a
new protocol.
I've named my new protocol
LocationFetcher, and it includes
the exact set of methods and
properties that my code uses
from CLLocationManager.
The member names and types match
exactly, and that allows me to
create an empty extension on
CLLocationManager that conforms
to the protocol, since it
already meets all the
requirements.
I'll then rename the
LocationManager property to
LocationFetcher, and I'll change
its type to the LocationFetcher
protocol.
I'll also add a default
parameter value to the
initializer, just like I did
earlier, to avoid breaking any
existing app code.
I need to make one small change
to the checkCurrentLocation
method to use the renamed
property.
And, finally, let's look at that
delegate method.
This part is a little trickier
to handle, because the delegate
expects the manager parameter to
be a real CLLocationManager, and
not my new protocol.
So, things get a little more
complicated when delegates are
involved, but we can still apply
protocols here.
Let's take a look at how.
I'll go back to LocationFetcher
protocol that I defined earlier,
and I'll rename that delegate
property to
LocationFetcherDelegate.
And I'll change its type to a
new protocol whose interface is
nearly identical to
CLLocationManagerDelegate, but I
tweaked the method name, and I
changed the type of the first
parameter to LocationFetcher.
Now I need to implement the
LocationFetcherDelegate property
in my extension now, since it no
longer satisfies that
requirement.
And I'll implement the getter
and the setter to use force
casting to convert back and
forth to
CLLocationManagerDelegate, and
I'll explain why I'm using force
casting here in just a second.
Then in my class' initializer, I
need to replace the delegate
property with
locationFetcherDelegate.
And the last step is to change
the original extension to
conform to the new mock delegate
protocol, and that part's easy--
all I need to do is replace the
protocol and the method
signature.
But I actually still need to
conform to the old
CLLocationManagerDelegate
protocol too, and that's because
the real CLLocationManager
doesn't know about my mock
delegate protocol.
So, the trick here is to add
back the extension which
conforms to the real delegate
protocol but have it call the
equivalent locationFetcher
delegate method above.
And earlier, I mentioned that I
used force casting in the
delegate getter and setter, and
that's to ensure that my class
conforms to both of these
protocols and that I haven't
forgotten one or the other.
So, over in my unit tests, I'll
define a struct nested in my
test class for mocking, which
conforms to the locationFetcher
protocol and fill out its
requirements.
Notice, in its RequestLocation
method, it calls a block to get
a fake location that I can
customize in my tests, and then
it invokes the delegate method,
passing it that fake location.
Now that I have all the pieces I
need, I can write my test.
I create a MockLocationFetcher
struct and configure its
handleRequestLocation block to
provide a fake location.
Then I create my
CurrentLocationProvider, passing
it the MockLocationFetcher.
And, finally, I call
checkCurrentLocation with a
completion block.
Inside the completion block,
there's an assertion that checks
that the location actually is a
point of interest.
So, it works.
I can now mock my classes' usage
of CLLocationManager without
needing to create a real one.
So, here, I've shown how to use
protocols to mock interaction
with an external class and its
delegate.
Now, that was a lot of steps.
So, let's recap what we did.
First, we defined a new
protocol, representing the
interface of the external class.
This protocol needs to include
all the methods and properties
that we use on the external
class, and, often, their
declarations can match exactly.
Next, we created an extension on
the original external class,
which declares conformance to
the protocol.
Then we replaced all our usage
of the external class with our
new protocol, and we added an
initializer parameter so that we
could set this type in our
tests.
We also talked about how to mock
a delegate protocol, which is a
common pattern in the SDKs.
There were a few more steps
involved here, but here's what
we did.
First, we defined a mock
delegate protocol with similar
method signatures as the
protocol that we're mocking.
But we replaced the real type
with our mock protocol type.
Then, in our original mock
protocol, we renamed the
delegate property, and we
implemented that renamed
property on our extension.
So, although this approach may
require more code than an
alternative like subclassing,
it'll be more reliable and less
likely to break as I expand my
code over time, since this way
the compiler will enforce that
any new methods I call for my
code must be included in these
new protocols.
So, finally, I'd like to talk
about test execution speed.
When your tests take a long time
to run, you're less likely to
run them during development, or
you might be tempted to skip the
longest running ones.
Our test suite helps us catch
issues early, when fixing
regression is easiest.
So, we want to make sure our
tests always run as fast as
possible.
Now, you might have encountered
times in the past when you
needed to artificially wait or
sleep in your tests, because the
code your testing is
asynchronous or uses a timer.
Delayed actions can be tricky,
so we want to be sure to include
them in our tests, but they can
also slow things down a lot if
we're not careful.
So, I'd like to talk about some
ways that we can avoid
artificial delays in our tests,
since they should never be
necessary.
Here's an example.
In the points of interest app
Brian and I are building, in the
main UI, we have a strip at the
bottom that shows the featured
place.
It basically loops through the
top places nearby, rotating to
show a new location every 10
seconds.
Now, there are several ways I
might implement this, but, here,
I'm using the timer API for
foundation.
Let's look at a unit test that I
might write for this class.
It creates a
FeaturedPlaceManager and stores
its current place before calling
the scheduleNextPlace method.
Then it runs the run loop for 11
seconds.
I added an extra second as a
grace period.
And, finally, it checks that the
currentPlace changed at the end.
Now, this isn't great, and it
takes a really long time to run.
To mitigate this, we could
expose a property in our code to
allow us to customize that
timeout to something shorter,
like 1 second.
And here's what that kind of a
code change might look like.
Now, with this approach, we can
reduce the delay in our tests
down to one second.
Now, this solution is better
than the one we had before.
Our tests will definitely run
faster, but it still isn't
ideal.
Our code still has a delay, it's
just shorter.
And the real problem is that the
code we're testing is still
timing dependent, which means
that, as we make the expected
delay shorter and shorter, our
tests may become less reliable,
since they'll be more dependent
on the CPU to schedule things
predictably.
And that's not always going to
be true, especially for
asynchronous code.
So, let's take a look at a
better approach.
I recommend first identifying
the delay mechanism.
In my example, it was a timer,
but you could also be using the
asyncAfter API from
DispatchQueue.
We want to mock this mechanism
in our tests so that we can
invoke the delayed action
immediately and bypass the
delay.
Here's our original code again,
and let's start by looking at
what this scheduledTimer method
actually does.
The scheduledTimer method
actually does two things for us.
It creates a timer, and then it
adds that timer to the current
run loop.
Now, this API can be really
convenient for creating a timer,
but it would help us to make
this code more testable if I
actually break these two steps
apart.
Here, I've transformed the
previous code from using
scheduledTimer to instead create
the timer first and then add it
to the current runLoop second,
which I have stored in a new
property.
Now, this code is equivalent to
what we had before, but, once we
break these two steps apart, we
can see that runLoop is just
another external class that this
class interacts with.
So, we can apply the mocking
with protocols technique we
discussed earlier here.
To do that, we'll create a small
protocol, containing this
addTimer method.
I've called this new protocol
TimerScheduler, and it just has
that one addTimer method, which
matches the signature of the
runLoop API.
Now, back in my code, I need to
replace the runLoop with the
protocol that I just created.
And in my tests, I don't want to
use a real runLoop as my
TimerScheduler.
Instead, I want to create a mock
scheduler that passes the timer
to my tests.
I'll do this by creating a new
struct nested in my unit test
class called MockTimerScheduler,
conforming to the TimerScheduler
protocol.
It stores a block that will be
called whenever it's told to add
a timer.
And with all the pieces in
place, I can write my final unit
test.
First, I create a
MockTimerScheduler and configure
its handleAddTimer block.
This block receives the timer.
Once it's added to the
scheduler, it records the
timer's delay, and then it
invokes the block by firing the
timer to bypass the delay.
Then, we create a
FeaturedPlaceManager and give it
our MockTimerScheduler.
And, finally, we call
scheduleNextPlace to start the
test, and, voila, our tests no
longer have any delay.
They execute super fast, and
they aren't timer dependent, so
it'll be more reliable.
And, as a bonus, I can now
verify the amount of timer delay
using this assertion at the
bottom.
And that's not something I was
able to do in the previous test.
So, like I said, the delay in
our code is fully eliminated
using this technique.
We think this was a great way to
test code that involves delayed
actions, but, for the fastest
overall execution speed in your
tests, it's still preferable to
structure the bulk of your tests
to be direct and not need to
mock delayed actions at all.
For example, in our app, the
action being delayed was
changing to the next featured
place.
I probably only need one or two
tests that show that the timer
delay works properly.
And, for the rest of the class,
I can call the show next place
method directly and not need to
mock a timer scheduler at all.
While we're on the topic of text
execution speed, we had a couple
of other tips to share.
One area we've seen concerns the
use of NSPredicateExpectations.
We wanted to mention that these
are not nearly as performant as
other expectation classes, since
they rely on polar rather than
more direct callback mechanisms.
They're mainly used in UI tests,
where the conditions being
evaluated are happening in
another process.
So, in your unit tests, we
recommend more direct
mechanisms, such as regular
XCTestExpectations,
NSNotification, or
KVOExpectations.
Another testing speed tip is to
ensure that your app launches as
quickly as possible.
Now, most apps have to do some
amount of setup work at launch
time, and, although that work is
necessary for regular app
launches, when your app is being
launched as a test runner, a lot
of that work may be unnecessary.
Things like loading view
controllers, kicking off network
requests, or configuring
analytics packages-- these are
all examples of things that are
commonly unnecessary in unit
testing scenarios.
XCTest waits until your app
delegates did finish launching
method returns before beginning
to run tests.
So, if you profile and notice
that app launch is taking a long
time in your tests, then one tip
is to detect when your app is
launched as a test runner and
avoid this work.
One way to do this is to specify
a custom environment variable or
launch argument.
Open the scheme editor, go to
the test action on the left
side, then to the arguments tab,
and add either an environment
variable or a launch argument.
In this screenshot, I've added
an environment variable named
IS-UNIT-TESTING set to 1.
Then, modify your app delegate's
appDidFinishLaunching code to
check for this condition, using
code similar to this.
Now, if you do this, be sure
that the code you skip truly is
nonessential for your unit test
to function.
So, to wrap up, Brian started by
reminding us about the testing
pyramid and how to have a
balanced testing strategy in
your app, showing several
practical techniques for testing
network operations.
Then, I talked about isolating
foundation notifications and
using dependency injection.
We offered a solution to one of
the most common challenges when
writing tests, interacting with
external classes, even if they
have a delegate.
And we shared some tips for
keeping your tests running fast
and avoiding artificial delays.
We really hope you'll find these
tests useful and look for ways
to apply them the next time
you're writing tests.
For more information, check out
our session webpage at this
link, and, in case you missed
it, we hope you'll check out
Wednesday's What's New in
Testing session on video.
Thanks so much, and I hope you
had a great WWDC.
[ Applause ]