[ Music ]
>> Hello, and thanks for tuning
in.
My name is Anil Katti and I'm an
AVFoundation Engineer at Apple.
Today, I'm going to present some
best practices and recommended
patterns for adopting
AVContentKeySession API.
AVContentKeySession is an
AVFoundation API that enables
delivery of FairPlay Streaming
keys on Apple platforms.
So, here's what I'll cover in
the session.
I'll start with an overview of
FairPlay streaming and
AVContentKeySession.
I'll then present some ways you
can optimize playback using
AVContentKeySession.
I'll, also, cover some common
pitfalls around FairPlay
Streaming key delivery and
answer a few frequently asked
questions from developers, along
the way.
So, let's get started.
FairPlay Streaming was
introduced back in 2015 to help
protect HLS streams delivered to
our platforms.
FairPlay Streaming specification
specifies a set of steps an app
needs to follow in order to
securely deliver content
decryption keys so the platform
could decrypt and play back
encrypted media.
While delivering FairPlay
Streaming keys your app works as
a liaison between the platform
and your key server.
When it receives an on-demand
key loading request from
AVFoundation it, in turn,
requests for an Encrypted Key
Request, also known as SPC.
The SPC is then sent to the key
server, which responds back with
an Encrypted Key Response, also
known as CKC.
Finally, the app provided CKC
back to AVFoundation so it could
start decryption and playback.
Until recently, apps used the
generic AVFoundation API called
AVAssetResourceLoader to deliver
content decryption keys.
But last year we introduced the
new AVFoundation Class called
AVContentKeySession that was
designed specifically around
content decryption keys.
We had two goals in mind for
AVContentKeySession.
One, to simplify key loading
process and provide applications
better control over the life
cycle of content decryption
keys.
And two, serve as a home for new
content protection features.
AVContentKeySession adoption has
been great, so far.
And already, a majority of
FairPlay Streaming keys
delivered on our platforms come
through AVContentKeySession.
The API has helped developers
optimize key delivery in their
applications.
I will present some ways you
could get more out of the API.
But before that, let's see what
makes AVContentKeySession
different.
With AVAssetResourceLoader
applications could load keys
only when AVFoundation requires
one and sends an on-demand key
loading request.
This, typically, happens when
AVFoundation downloads
playlists, parses them, and then
finds out that the content is
encrypted.
Further, AVFoundation could send
these key loading requests at
any point during playback.
For example, AVFoundation sends
new key loading requests if it's
switched to a radian that uses a
different key in the middle of
the playback.
AVContentKeySession,
essentially, changes that model.
It decouples key loading from
media loading or playback and
gives applications more control
over the timing of key loading.
AVContentKeySession allows
applications to initiate key
loading on their own at any
point in time.
This opens up new use cases,
allows applications to optimize
key delivery, and improve
different aspects of playback
experience.
Playback startup is one such
thing AVContentKeySession could
help improve.
Instead of waiting for
AVFoundation to send on demand
key loading requests.
After requesting playback, you
could use AVContentKeySession to
proactively load keys that you
predict might be required in the
near future based on user
actions.
You could do all this, even
before a user picks something to
play.
We call this key preloading or
prewarming.
Further, if you have assets that
use multiple keys across
different radians, you could
batch up all key requests before
even talking to your key server.
This reduces some load on the
key server, and also, eliminates
round trips for each keys.
You could initiate key loading
process by calling
processContentKeyRequest method
on an AVContentKeySession
instance.
Once you call this method
AVContentKeySession will send
you an AVContentKeyRequest
object by invoking the delegate
callback.
AVContentKeySession allows you
to perform FairPlay Streaming
specific operations like request
encrypted key requests and
respond with encrypted key
response.
Okay. So, now let's say you have
successfully preloaded a
particular key.
Is it possible that the key is
requested again after the
playback starts?
Yes, that's possible.
The app could receive an
on-demand key loading request if
the playback route changes, for
instance.
Keep in mind that the user could
decide to AirPlay the content to
an Apple TV or plug in a
Lightning to Digital AV adapter.
And in these cases, we need new
keys for decryption.
So, the app should always be
prepared to answer on-demand key
loading requests, even when it
preloads keys.
Here's another frequently asked
question around this topic.
How could the app preload all
keys that might be required
during playback?
Well, in order to preload a key,
you need the corresponding key
identifier.
The one that's specified in
EXT-X-KEY tag in the HLS
playlist.
We recommend that you obtain all
key identifiers and asset
[inaudible] from your server in
an out-of-band fashion.
Another option is to include all
key identifiers in the master
playlist as session keys while
authoring the content and use
preloads eligible content keys
property on
AVAssetResourceLoader.
At this point I would like to
point out that we have a
dedicated session about
optimizing HLS performance in
general, not just key delivery.
You should definitely check that
out.
Moving on from preloading,
AVContentKeySession could also
help you scale your live
offering.
Are you wondering how?
Well, you could use
AVContentKeySession to disperse
key loading requests from
clients that are streaming your
live content.
Typically, live streams rotate
keys periodically in order to
add an extra layer of protection
for the content.
It is easy to imagine that these
keys appear at the exact same
time when clients refresh live
playlists.
When that happens, millions of
clients request keys, all at
once, resulting in huge impulse
load on the key server.
When you disperse this key
request event across a small
time window before they appear
and before the EXT-X-KEY tag
appears in the playlist, you're,
basically, load balancing
requests reaching your key
server.
We covered this use case in
detail with sample code during
last year's session on HLS.
So, do check out the sessions
were recording on
developerapple.com or WWDC app.
Apart from allowing you to
manage and deliver content
decryption keys
AVContentKeySession also serves
as a home for new FairPlay
Streaming content protection
features.
We released one such feature
last year.
We call it Offline Rentals.
Offline Rentals is a FairPlay
Streaming feature that allows
you to specify two expiration
durations on persistent keys;
storage and playback duration.
Storage duration specifies for
how long you wish the key to be
valid while it is sitting in
your storage.
That is, before being used for
playback.
It is, typically, large, like 30
days.
Playback duration, on the other
hand, specifies how long you
with the key to be valid after
it was used for playback.
It is, typically, shorter than
storage duration.
For example, 24 hours.
This feature allows you to
specify such expiration
durations when you create
persistent keys and the platform
ensures that the two expiration
durations are enforced, even
when the device is offline.
So, you might be wondering how
and where can you specify these
two expiration durations.
FairPlay introduced a new TLLV
called Offline Key TLLV for this
purpose.
This has to be signaled in the
CKC that is used while
requesting persistent key.
In terms of code, you generate a
persistent key by calling this
method on
AVPersistableContentKeyRequest
Object.
This returns a persistent key
data blob that you should save
in your app storage and use it
to answer future key loading
requests.
Note that this key is valid
until the end of storage
duration, 30 days from our
example.
So, when you use this key to
start the playback for the first
time you might receive an
updated persistent key through a
new delegate callback.
When the delegate callback is
involved you should discard the
original persistent key and save
this updated persistent key in
your app storage.
You should use this to answer
future key loading requests.
Note that this updated
persistent key is valid until
the end of playback duration, 24
hours from our example.
So, with that, let's shift gears
and talk about error handling,
now.
Error handling is one of the
most important topics from the
perspective of improving
playback experience.
Successfully loading keys
involves a number of steps and
something is bound to fail at
some point or another.
So, when something fails the
first thing you should do is
report the failure back to
AVFoundation using
AVContentKeyRequest or
AVAssetResourceLoadingRequest.
Some errors are fatal and some
are not.
You should help platform make
that decision.
Another thing you should do is
monitor error logs and access
logs, investigate the root
cause.
And try to mitigate errors so
your users can get the best
experience they deserve on our
platforms.
If you haven't already, you
should also check out one of our
recorded sessions from last year
to learn more about error
handling, in general.
Over the years we've seen
developers fall into a few
pitfalls around FairPlay
Streaming key delivery.
We have seen apps that hold on
to key responses for too long.
When AVFoundation sends you a
key loading request you should
provide a response as soon as
possible.
Delays in key delivery could
result in playback timing out.
By the way, you should be able
to identify and debug timeouts
by surveying your playerItems
accessLogs.
Another pitfall is around HDCP
enforcement.
It is important to keep in mind
that HDCP requirement for your
assets is signaled inside
encrypted key response from your
key server.
If you wish to enforce different
HDCP levels for different
radians, you should specify
different key identifiers for
those radians.
And provide appropriate key
responses from your key server.
Lastly, you should be careful
while responding to key loading
requests with persistent keys
because persistent keys are tied
to the device they were
generated on.
For example, you should not use
a persistent key to respond to a
key loading request from an
AirPlay session.
Doing so will result in playback
failure.
We made some API changes in iOS
11.2 to help you avoid and catch
such issues sooner, rather than
later.
Let me walk you through some
code snippets to explain.
If you are using
AVContentKeySession to deliver
keys, now you won't even be able
to RequestPersistableContentKey
request object if the
AVContentKeyRequest cannot
accept the persistent key as a
response.
So, when requesting a
PersistableContentKeyRequest
field you should respond with an
online FairPlay Streaming key
from your key server.
If you are using
AVAssetResourceLoader, before
responding with a persistent key
data blob you should check if
persistent key is listed as one
of the accepted content types in
the newly introduced
allowedContentTypes property.
So, I hope this provided some
overview of AVContentKeySession
and clarified a few questions
you might have had.
To summarize, we covered what
makes AVContentKeySession
different.
We saw how this API could be
used to improve playback startup
and scale live streaming.
We spoke a little bit about
Offline Rentals, what it really
is, and how to do it the right
way.
We, finally, highlighted best
practices around handling errors
while delivering FairPlay
Streaming keys and common
pitfalls that you should be
aware of.
Thank you, for listening.
And please, visit
developer.apple.com for more
information about this session
and other related sessions.
Thanks.