[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you.
My name is Dan Omachi, I'm an
engineer in Apple's Metal
Ecosystem Team.
Now my main role on that team is
to help developers learn Metal
and have a great experience
using it.
But prior to this I worked on
Apple's OpenGL and OpenGL ES
frameworks for many years.
And even before joining Apple I
worked on a couple of other
OpenGL implementations.
So I'm really proud of what
we've accomplished with OpenGL
over the past years, but I'm
also really excited about the
direction Metal's taking us.
Today my colleague Sukanya
Sudugu and I are going to give
you a brief introduction to
Metal and provide some guidance
about how you can easily port
your OpenGL apps over.
Now this is particularly
important this year because as
announced in yesterday's state
of the union OpenGL, openGL ES
and OpenCL are deprecated.
Now existing and soon-to-be
launched apps can still use
OpenGL ES on tvOS and iOS12 and
OpenGL and OpenCL on macOS 10.14
Mojave and this will remain so
for some time.
However, new projects should
target Metal from their
inception.
So if you're not already
familiar with Metal, then it's
time to get started.
Before you rip out all of your
OpenGL code and start porting it
all to Metal you've got a few
options to consider.
Apple offers several high-level
frameworks that do rendering,
different kinds of rendering,
SpriteKit for 2D games, SceneKit
for some 3D, Core Image for
great effects.
Also, each of the major
third-party game engines already
use Metal as their primary
renderer.
But you may decide that these
approaches just aren't for you
and the path forward is to do it
yourself in Metal, that's what
we'll talk about today.
So let's start out with Metal
design and some fundamental
concepts.
So OpenGL was originally
designed 25 years ago and its
core reflects the origins of
hardware accelerated 3D
graphics.
So updates with new versions and
extensions have really served us
well by exposing new GPU
features and performance
techniques.
However, there are still some
fundamental design choices that
no longer apply to current
hardware.
The OpenGL pipeline was
originally an entirely fixed
function and although today
OpenGL supports a programmable
pipeline it doesn't neatly match
that of modern GPUs.
Also, asynchronous processing is
not a core feature of the API,
there are a number of features
which allude to the fact that
the GPU works in parallel with
your app but much of this is
implicit.
And 25 years ago only the most
expensive workstations and
servers had multiple cores.
So designing an efficient
multithreading model wasn't a
priority.
So back in 2014, it was clear to
us that a new application
interface for the GPU was
necessary.
Obviously, we needed an
interface that could efficiently
harness the GPU's power.
To do that the app needed the
CPU out of the way so the GPU
could do its thing.
But when an app needs the CPU
for rendering it needs to be
able to use all of the CPU,
including its multiple cores.
If the interface needed to be
predictable to prevent
developers from falling into
hidden pitfalls in the API every
call should have an obvious
consequence and few operations
should be performed implicitly.
Part of this predictability
would be the need to control
where resources were placed and
if and when synchronization was
necessary.
Now Apple had a few other
requirements.
We wanted this interface to be
approachable, it needed to have
the right balance between
low-level control and clear
usage because the easier it is
for you to understand something
the more effectively and
efficiently you can use it.
And of course, we designed Metal
to map well to all modern GPUs.
In particular, we knew that
hardware coming down the
pipeline needed software that
could push it.
This included the Apple designed
GPU of the A11 bionic.
So how is Metal different than
OpenGL?
Well you perform the most
expensive operations less often.
Objects are designed in such a
way that API state can be
translated and prepackaged into
GPU commands at creation.
This way, there's much less cost
to use them later on when
actually rendering.
The graphics pipeline with
Vertex and fragment shaders also
reflects the modern GPU.
So it's less costly to translate
the API's configuration to GP
commands.
This doesn't mean the pipeline
is entirely different or
requires some whole new way of
thinking.
The main difference in Metal is
that the grouping of the
pipeline stages into objects is
more efficient, not that the
pipeline itself is changed.
Metal also has a clear model for
multithreaded execution.
There are a number of different
ways for applications to drive
the GPU from different threads,
but for each there are explicit
but unconstraining rules to do
this.
Additionally, the most commonly
used objects like textures,
buffers and shaders can safely
and efficiently be used across
threads.
Metal does not need to perform
any expensive internal logging
operations to prevent these
objects from getting into some
invalid state.
Finally, the execution model
reflects what really goes on
between software and the GPU.
Many of the implicit operations
performed by OpenGL are
explicitly performed by an
application using Metal.
This allows you to make
intelligent decisions as to when
and how your app uses the GPU.
It also means there's less
software between your
application and the GPU.
Most Metal calls go directly to
the GPU driver and that driver
also needs to do less processing
to translate from API calls to
GPU commands.
So let's dive in and see how
this works.
All GL calls are performed on an
OpenGL context.
The context does a ton of
things, it tracks API state, it
manages OpenGL objects and other
memory, and translates and
submits GPU commands.
Metal splits all of these jobs
of an OpenGL context into a
number of smaller objects.
The first object that creates is
a Metal device which is an
abstract representation of a
physical GPU.
The device creates objects such
as textures, buffers and
pipeline objects which contain
shaders.
It also creates a key object
called a Metal command queue.
The command queue really only
has one job, to create a
sequence of command buffers.
Here we've created one command
buffer and a command buffer is
simply a list of GPU commands
that your app will fill and send
to the GPU for execution.
Typically your app will create a
single command buffer per frame,
however, there are some
situations where it makes sense
to create two or three in a
frame.
But an app doesn't write these
commands directly to the command
buffer, instead it creates a
Metal command encoder.
The command encoder translates
API calls into GPU instructions
and writes them to the command
buffer.
After a series of commands have
been encoded your app will end
encoding and release the encoder
object.
There are actually a couple
different kind of encoders and
your app can create new encoders
from the command buffer to
encode more commands.
Now it's important to note that
up until now on this diagram the
GPU hasn't done any work.
Metal has created objects and
encoded commands all with the
CPU.
It's only after your app has
finished encoding commands and
committed the command buffer
that the GPU begins to work and
executes those commands.
You can also encode commands to
multiple command buffers in
parallel on separate threads.
Now I've already spoken about
how the command queue produces a
sequence of command buffers and
that you create a command
encoder from a command buffer.
Let's take a closer look at
these encoder objects used to
write to our command buffers.
There are three main types.
There's the Render Command
Encoder whose commands resemble
that of an OpenGL command string
where you set state, bind
objects, and issue draw calls.
There's the Blit Command Encoder
with which you can issue texture
and buffer copy operations.
You can also use it to generate
Mipmap for textures and transfer
pixel data from buffers similar
to how glReadPixels operates
with OpenGL's pixel buffer
objects.
And then there's the Compute
Command Encoder which allows you
to dispatch commute kernels.
The Render Command Encoder is
probably the encoder you'll
become most familiar with as
it's responsible for the
majority of operations that a
graphic centric app needs.
The set of commands encoded into
a Render Command Encoder is
often referred to as a Render
Pass.
In a Render Pass you set up
render objects for the graphics
pipeline and issue draw commands
with those objects.
This includes operations similar
to glDrawArrays and
glDrawElements and other OpenGL
draw commands.
Each Render Command Encoder is
strongly associated with a set
of render targets.
And the render target is simply
a texture that can be drawn to.
This includes color, depth and
stencil textures, as well as
multi-sample textures.
You specify a set of render
targets when you create a render
command encoder from a command
buffer.
And all draw commands are
directed to these targets for
the lifetime of the encoder.
To direct commands to a new set
of targets you end encoding with
a current render command encoder
and create a new encoder with
new targets.
This creates a very clear
delineation between commands
directed to different sets of
render targets.
Let's talk a little bit about
the object you'll use for
rendering.
Metal has a number of similar
objects to OpenGL.
There are textures, buffers,
samplers and pipeline state
objects which resemble OpenGL's
program objects, and also depth
stencil state objects which
don't really exists in OpenGL
but are just the containers for
the same depth and stencil state
that OpenGL's got.
One significant difference
between OpenGL and Metal objects
are how they are created and
managed.
The objects are all created from
a device object so they're
associated with a single GPU.
You set most of an object state
when you create it by specifying
properties in a descriptor
object.
All states set when the object
is created is fixed and
immutable.
Although the state of textures
and buffers are fixed upon
creation, data contained by
these objects can be changed.
Metal can do all the expensive
setup for an object once when
it's created.
OpenGL's mutable model makes it
completely possible that if your
app touches a little piece of
state the recompilation of that
object may occur.
And even if your app doesn't
change an object state OpenGL
needs to check a hierarchy of
flags to confirm this before
drawing.
So with this immutable model
Metal never needs to check for
object state changes make draw
calls much faster.
Additionally, objects can be
efficiently used across threads,
Metal never needs to lock an
object to prevent it from
getting into an invalid state
from a change on another thread.
So let's talk about porting.
Here is the typical phase, here
are typical phases of a
rendering application.
You build the app compiling
source and bundling your assets.
Start up and initializing it.
Loading the assets and
initializing objects that will
persist for the lifetime of your
application.
And you repeatedly render
setting up state, issuing many
draw calls, and presenting frame
after frame.
I'll talk about developing for
Metal in the earlier stages of
the application's lifetime,
including building shaders
offline and creating object's
initialization.
And Sukanya will describe how to
port your per frame rendering
code.
So let's start out with
application build time which is
where shaders are typically
compiled.
We'll begin with a look at the
shading language.
The Metal shading language is
based on C++.
So just like C++ you can create
classes, templates, structures,
define enums and namespaces.
Like GLSL there are built-in
vector and matrix types, and
numerous built-in functions and
operators commonly used for
graphics.
And there are classes to specify
sampler state and operate on
textures.
The best way to describe the
language is just to show you.
So here is a vertex and fragment
shader pair.
The vertex keyword at the
function at the top specifies
that that function is a vertex
shader, likewise for the
fragment keyword for the
function at the bottom.
Note that they have custom names
unlike GLSL where every shader
is just called main.
This is important because it
allows you to build large
libraries of unique shaders
using names to indicate what
they do.
Anything passed from your
application is an argument to
one of these shaders.
There aren't any loose variables
outside of functions as there
are with GLSL.
As you can see, there are these
bracketed symbols next to each
parameter.
These are attribute specifiers
which extend upon the C++
language to indicate special
variables.
So this vertex ID attribute
indicates that this VID
parameter should contain the
index of the current vertex when
this vertex executes.
It's used down here in two
places to index into an array of
vertices.
These parameters here with a
buffer attribute specifier these
indicate that these variables
are filled by buffer's objects
set in the Metal API.
I'll talk more about how the
Metal API relates to these in
just a minute.
But first let's take a closer
look at some of the types used
here.
Now these are all custom types
that you would define.
The vertices parameter here is
defined as a pointer to a vertex
type and its definition is right
here.
The structure has two members, a
model position member and a
texture coordinate member.
It defines the layout and memory
of each vertex in a vertex array
passed into this vertex shader.
Let's look at this vertex output
type returned by our vertex
shader.
Its definition here specifies
what's passed down for the
rasterization stage and
eventually to the fragment
program.
The four-component
floating-point member named
clipPos has this position
attribute specifier next to it.
This indicates that this member
will serve as the output
position of our vertex shader.
This texCoord member which
doesn't have an attribute
specifier defaults to a variable
that will be interpolated with
the texture coordinate values of
other vertices defining the
rasterized triangle much like a
varying in GLSL.
Let's take a look at some of the
parameters of our fragment
shader.
So we're using this vertexOutput
struct that we just looked at
down here as an input to our
fragment shader.
And it gives us the interpolated
texture coordinate that we
constructed in the vertex shader
and we use it here to sample
from a texture.
In our application code which is
written in Objective-C we use a
Render Command Encoder to map
objects to shader parameters.
The index argument with each of
these calls are similar to
OpenGL's attribute indices,
vertex attribute indices, and
textured units.
They specify indices which map
to indices in our shader
parameters.
So by calling the encoder's set
fragment buffer method with an
index of three we map this my
uniform buffer object to the
uniform's parameter of our
encoder, of our shader.
We make similar calls to set our
texture and sampler objects.
Now I want to talk about one
library that's incredibly useful
for shader development.
This is called SIMD.
Now SIMD is actually a library
that's separate from Metal and
is used in many orthogonal
frameworks.
But it was built with Metal in
mind.
SIMD defines vector and matrix
types commonly used to implement
graphics algorithms, so this
includes three and four
component vector types and three
by three and four by four matrix
types.
One of the nicest features of
this library is that you can use
it to share code between your
application code and your
shading language code.
This is really useful because
you can define the layout of
data passed from your
application to your shaders with
structures using these types.
Here's how it works.
You create a structure with data
you'd like to pass from your
application to your shaders.
So for instance, if you want to
pass down a model view
projection matrix to the and the
position of the SIMD primary
light source you can use SIMD
types in your structure to do
this.
You put the structure's
definition and a header which
you would include in both your
application code and Metal
files.
This way the data layout used by
your shaders matches what you've
set in your code because they're
using the same types.
This makes bugs due to layout
mismatches much less common.
One of the key ways in which
Metal achieves its efficiency is
by doing work earlier and less
frequently.
So you'll use Xcode to compile
Metal shader files when you
build your application.
This runs a front-end
compilation performing string
parsing, shader analysis, and
some basic optimizations.
It converts your code into a
binary intermediate
representation that is usable on
any hardware.
Actual GPU machine code isn't
built until your app runs on the
user's system.
But this removes half the
compiled time needed when your
app runs.
The built intermediate
representation binary is
archived into a Metal library
file.
Xcode will compile all the Metal
shader source files into a
default Metal library, placing
it into your app bundle for
retrieval at runtime.
In addition to having Xcode
built shaders you also can build
shaders during your app's
runtime.
Some OpenGL apps construct
shaders at runtime by
concatenating strings or running
a source code generator of some
kind.
For those gathering all of the
shaders at build time can be a
challenge.
But for bring up purposes or if
built time compilation just
isn't possible for your app
Metal is able to compile shaders
from source at runtime just like
OpenGL.
However, there are a number of
disadvantages to this, most
obviously you give up on the
performance savings of keeping
this work off the user's system.
You won't see any shader
compilation errors at built time
so you'll only find out about
them when you run your app.
Finally, if you compile at
runtime you can't include
headers in your shaders, so you
can't share types between your
shaders or your application
code.
If you use runtime share
compilation to get your app up
and running quickly I strongly
encourage you to spend some time
getting your shaders to build
within Xcode.
This way you can benefit from
not only the runtime performance
savings but also these
conveniences in shader
development.
Let's move onto the steps your
app will need to take to
initialize your Metal renderer,
so this includes creating a
number of objects.
I'll start out with the devices
and command queues and then I'll
describe how to create objects
for your assets, including
textures, buffers and pipeline
objects.
So devices and queues.
These are the first objects
you'll create.
The device is an abstract
representation of a GPU.
It's responsible for creating
objects that are used for
rendering including these
textures, buffers and pipeline
objects.
In iOS since there's only ever
one GPU there's only one device
you can get, but on macOS
systems can have multiple
devices since there may be both
an integrated and discrete GPU
and even multiple eGPUs.
Usually though, getting the
default device is sufficient for
most applications.
And getting this device is
really simple, you call
MTLCreateSystem
DefaultDevice.
One of the first things you'll
do with this device is create a
command queue.
The queue is used mostly in your
applications render loop to
obtain command buffers each
frame, but you want to create
the command queue at
initialization.
Typically, a single queue is
sufficient but more complex apps
that execute many tasks in
parallel may need multiple
queues.
Creating a queue is also really
simple, you call newCommandQueue
with the device you just
created.
And once you've got your queue
you can get command buffers for
your render loop.
Let's move on building your
render objects.
I'm going to talk about creating
three types of objects used for
rendering, textures, buffers and
pipelines.
Let's start with textures.
As mentioned earlier, you create
render objects from a device
object.
You'll use a descriptor object
to create most of these.
Descriptors are really simple
objects without any true
methods.
They only contain properties
needed for object setup.
So for example, to create a
texture you'd use a texture
descriptor.
You specify the properties that
you'd like the created texture
to have.
So things like the type of
texture, 2D, 3D, cubeMap.
The texture's dimensions and the
number of Mipmaps you'd like it
to have.
And the pixel format of data in
the texture.
Once you've set the desired
values for each of the
properties you call a method on
the device to create a usable
texture object.
This also allocates the memory
backing the texture image.
Once you've created the object
you no longer need the
descriptor as it's only used for
object creation.
And properties you set in the
descriptor are locked and can no
longer be changed.
However, the contents of the
texture image can be modified.
So I want to talk about one
property you'll set in the
texture descriptor and you'll
also use when creating a buffer.
This is called the storage mode.
As mentioned, when you create a
texture object Metal allocates
memory for it right then and
there.
The storage mode property tells
Metal in which pool memory it
should be allocated.
The simplest option shared
storage mode gives both the CPU
and the GPU access.
For buffers this means you get a
pointer to the memory backing
the object.
Protectors, this means you can
call certain easy-to-use methods
to set and retrieve data from
the texture.
You can use private storage mode
which only gives the GPU access
to the data, this allows the
Metal to apply some
optimizations it would be unable
to if the CPU also had access to
that data.
But only the GPU can directly
fill the contents of this type
of texture.
You can indirectly fill data
from the CPU using a blit
encoder to copy from a second
intermediate resource using
shared storage.
On devices with dedicated video
memory setting the resource to
use private storage allocates it
in video memory only.
Finally, on macOS you can use a
third storage mode called
managed storage.
This allows both the GPU and CPU
to access the object data.
And on systems with dedicated
video memory Metal may create a
mirrored memory backing for
efficient access by both
processors.
Because of this, explicit calls
are necessary to ensure data is
synchronized for GPU and CPU
access.
Here's an example of creating a
texture object.
First you create a texture
descriptor and set a number of
properties in it, including the
storage mode.
And then we create a texture
using the device.
To fill a texture's image data
we calculate the bytes per row
and just like with GLText
[inaudible] we specify a region
to load.
And then we call the texture
object's replace region method
which copies the data into the
texture from a pointer we
supply.
Now there are a few notable
differences between OpenGL and
Metal texture objects.
While OpenGL does have a sampler
object they are optional.
Wrap modes and filters can be
set in the texture's object
itself in OpenGL.
In Metal you need to create a
separate sampler object or
specify sampler parameters in
your shaders.
Texture image data is not
flipped in Metal.
OpenGL uses a bottom-left origin
while Metal uses a top-left
origin.
So make sure you're aware of the
difference when loading your
textures.
Desktop OpenGL also performs
conversions when the data
supplied is in a different
format than the internal format.
However Metal similar to OpenGL
ES does not, so you'll need to
make sure your assets are
already in the proper format or
implement paths to perform
conversions.
Let's move on to buffers.
Metal uses buffers for all
unstructured data.
They're really similar to
OpenGL's vertex, element and
uniform buffers.
So if you're already using these
buffers in OpenGL you'll have an
easier time with your port.
Creating a buffer is pretty
simple with a device you call
newBufferWithLength specifying
the size of the buffer you want.
You also specify a storage mode.
You load a buffer through the
contents property, which is
simply a void pointer to the
memory backing the buffer.
To Metal's core the data is
completely unstructured, so it's
up to you to define the layout
in your application and share
your code.
Here we're casting the contents
pointer to a structure which
uses some of the SIMD types I
mentioned earlier.
We set the members of the
structure which fills in the
buffer's data using the layout
or application as is defined
with the structure's definition.
As mentioned earlier, you can
share a structure's definition
between your application and
share code which ensures the
layouts match between these two
components.
A common mistake is a mismatch
between buffer data and how it's
interpreted in the shader due to
an assumption or due to
assumptions about alignment.
For instance, you might assume
that the shading language's
float3 type consumes only 12
bytes.
Three 4 byte components is 12
bytes right.
Well if you pack your data that
way you'll run into trouble
because the shading language
actually interprets a float3 as
consuming 16 bytes.
That's because the types are
kept as stricter alignments for
CPU and GPU optimal CPU and GPU
usage.
Similar problems often occur
with three by three matrices.
If you really want to tack, if
you really want to pack data
tightly there are pack types
available in the Metal shading
language.
After passing a pack data in a
buffer your shader code would
need to pack data, would you
need to pass that packed data to
a regular vector before it can
perform operations on that data.
So when you're bringing up your
application I recommend using
the most convenient storage
modes.
This makes it more easy to
access the data in those
resources.
So in iOS create all textures
and buffers with
StorageModeShared.
On macOS you can't use
StorageModeShared with textures,
but StorageModeManaged does make
image data access easier,
although private storage is most
optimal.
You can use StorageModeShared
with buffers on macOS, but be
careful with this.
If you mix data that both the
CPU and GPU needs access to with
data only the GPU needs access
to it can be difficult to
detangle these two types of data
later on and put them in
separate memory pools.
Now that I've described a little
bit about creating textures and
buffer objects directly I'd like
to mention the MetalKit
framework which can easily
create textures and vertex
buffers from common file
formats.
There's a texture loading class
and some functionality to create
Metal buffer backed meshes
loaded by Model I/O.
Let's talk about shaders and the
render pipeline objects that
contain them.
You create one of these pipeline
state objects using a render
pipeline descriptor object.
The object contains a vertex and
fragment shader pair.
It also specifies the layout of
vertices feeding the vertex
shader.
And also blend state and the
pixel formats of render targets
that the fragment and shader can
render to.
Just like with the texture
object you call method on the
device which will produce an
immutable render state pipeline
object.
And also like a texture object
you only need the descriptor to
create that object.
Here's some code showing how to
build these pipeline state
objects.
Before you create the pipeline,
you'll need to get the shaders
out of a Metal library.
This line here loads the default
Metal library that we built in
Xcode.
For this library you can obtain
your vertex and fragment shader
using their function names.
You create a render pipeline
descriptor object where you set
these shading functions and also
specify render target pixel
formats.
Finally, you use the device with
the descriptor object we've set
up to produce a pipeline state
object.
The most significant difference
between the OpenGL and Metal
graphics pipelines is that while
an OpenGL program object
contains just a vertex and
fragment shader pair Metal
pipeline objects also include a
vertex layout, blend state, and
render target pixel format.
So you need to know all of these
things before you build a
pipeline.
Having these extra pieces of
state in the pipeline enables
Metal to fully compile shaders
into GPU machine code upon
object creation.
This is something that's not
possible with OpenGL's program
objects.
Now you'll need to build a
system that allows you to create
pipelines when you initialize
your app.
It helps if you can choose a
canonical vertex layout and a
limited set of render targets.
This reduces the combinations of
state your app uses and the
number of pipeline objects
needed.
However, not everyone knows up
front which pipelines their app
will need.
A common first step in porting
an app to Metal is to keep a
dictionary of pipelines you've
already made.
As your app encounters new
combinations of state it can
build and store pipelines using
the descriptors as keys.
Keep in mind this solution I
mentioned is kind of a hack and
you want to avoid shipping your
app with it.
This is because creating any of
these objects is expensive.
When you create a pipeline
object the GPU compiler kicks in
and translates and optimizes the
shader's binary intermediate
representation to machine code.
If your app creates these
just-in-time during its render
loop you're likely to see stalls
and a reduced frame rate for a
short period of time.
Allocating memory for textures
and buffers is also an expensive
operation, that's not even
accounting for the processing
required to fill in these
resources with data.
However, once you've created
these objects using them in your
render loop requires very little
CPU over [inaudible] since so
much is done up front.
With that I'd like to hand it
over to Sukanya who will talk
about porting your render loop.
[ Applause ]
>> Good evening everyone, I am
Sukanya Sudugu, GPU software
engineer at Apple.
I am super excited to share some
of our porting experience with
you, so let's continue porting.
Dan already talked about
application setup, so by now you
would have built all your
shaders and also created all
persistent objects needed for
frame generation.
So now let's dive into your
application's render loop which
is the code that runs for every
frame.
With Metal you will explicitly
manage the asynchronous nature
of GPU's execution in your
render loop.
So this includes obtaining and
submitting command buffers to
GPU with the list of GPU
commands.
And updating your resources in
such a way that allows the GPU
to asynchronously read from it
which you have written in your
render loop.
And encoding render passes by
creating render command
encoders.
And finally, presenting your
frames to the display.
So let's first talk about this
command buffer object.
One of the key changes from
OpenGL is that Metal provides
explicit control over command
buffers, which means it's up to
you to create these command
buffers and you can decide when
to commit them to GPU for its
execution.
So the straightforward thing to
do is to create one command
buffer which will render your
whole frame.
And once your application is up
and running and if you perhaps
see some idle time on GPU, then
you might want to consider
splitting your frame across
multiple command buffers.
And then the GPU can get started
executing one command buffer
while CPU is encoding the
others.
Alternatively, splitting your
frame encoding across multiple
threads requires you to create
one command buffer per thread.
But keep in mind that there is
some additional CPU cost
associated with each command
buffer.
So you should be using as few as
possible.
Metal also provides an API to
register a completion callback,
which will be involved when GPU
completes executing this command
buffer.
So let me show you all these
APIs in action.
So you will have created command
queue in your application
initialization method.
Now in render loop you will use
it to obtain command buffer by
calling its command buffer
method.
Now you will encode commands
into this command buffer.
I'll talk more about this
encoder shortly.
But when you are finished
encoding you will call commit
method so that this command
buffer will be submitted to GPU
for its execution.
Now you have two options for
what to do while this command
buffer is being executed on GPU.
You can wait by calling this
waitUntilCompleted method which
is similar to glFinish in
OpenGL.
This method will synchronously
wait and only returns when all
the commands in the command
buffer has been executed by the
GPU.
Alternatively, before you commit
this command buffer to GPU you
can add a completion handler,
which will be invoked when GPU
is done executing this command
buffer.
This allows CPU and GPU to
execute in parallel.
Also this allows us to track and
efficiently update shared
resources whose data is changing
every frame.
Since we are here let's talk
more about these resource
updates and see how we can make
them efficient using this
completion handler.
So almost all applications will
be pushing new data to GPU every
frame.
For example, new shaded uniforms
needed for animations.
In Metal CPU can write to this
shared resources anytime even if
GP is accessing the same memory
at the same time.
Metal does not protect you
against these data-races.
This compares to OpenGL which by
default prevents these
data-races either by waiting for
the GPU workloads to finish or
by doing extra copies, which may
not be optimal for your
application.
With Metal you can implement any
optimal synchronization strategy
which suits best for your
applications.
So in most cases, best approach
is to multi-buffer your shared
resources so that CPU and GPU
are never trying to access the
same buffer simultaneously.
So let's see an example, you
have an OpenGL application and
you just ported it to Metal and
it is using single buffer for
these dynamic data updates and
you did not implement any
synchronization method yet in
your application, then here's
what will happen.
Your application will write to
that buffer while generating
commands for the first frame and
then submits this command buffer
to GPU.
Then GPU when it is executing
this command buffer will try to
read from this buffer.
And while you're updating the
same buffer for the next frame
GPU is still reading from this
buffer.
So this is clearly a race
condition and the results are
undefined.
There are a few potential fixes
which you can implement in your
application.
The simplest is to call the
command buffer's
waitUntilCompleted method after
every frame.
But this waits for the GPU to
finish reading before you
override this buffer for the
next frame.
But as you can see, here this is
a very poor utilization of both
CPU and GPU, so this is not
something you want to do in your
shipping code.
But it is very useful to get
your Metal application up and
running.
And even to detect that if your
application really indeed has
these kind of data conflicts.
The efficient way to synchronize
your resource updates is to use
multiple buffers.
So in this case we will use
three buffers to triple buffer
our dynamic data updates.
So in frame 1 we will write to a
buffer and then the GPU will
read from it.
And in frame 2 we will write to
another buffer avoiding this
race condition.
Similarly, in frame 3 we will
write the third buffer.
But now we have used up all
three buffers and exhausted our
buffer pool.
We need to wait for the GPU to
finish the frame 1 so that we
can reuse it for frame 4.
Now this completion handler will
come handy, it will let us know
when GPU has done executing this
frame.
So when frame 1 is done we can
reuse its buffer for frame 4 and
so on.
So let's look at a sample.
For triple buffer implementation
outside your render loop first
we will create a FIFO queue of
three buffers.
And we also need a
frameBoundarySemaphore which is
initialized to start value as 3.
So this says semaphore will be
signaled at each frame boundary,
that is when GPU finishes
executing a frame allowing the
CPU to reuse its buffer.
Also initialize buffer index to
point to the current frame's
buffer.
And in our render loop before we
write to a buffer we need to
first ensure that its
corresponding frame has
completed its execution on the
GPU.
So at the beginning of the frame
we wait on our
frameBoundarySemaphore.
Once the semaphore is signaled
indicating that the current
frame has completed its
execution on GPU now it's safe
to grab its buffer and reuse for
new frame data.
And we will now encode some
commands to bind this buffer to
GPU.
And before we commit this
command buffer to GPU we will
add a completion handler to this
command buffer for this frame.
After adding completion handler
we will commit this command
buffer to GPU.
Now once GPU finishes executing
this frame our completion
handler will be invoked which
will then signal this frame
semaphore.
This allows CPU to reuse its
buffer for new frame encoding.
So this was a simple triple
buffer implementation which you
can adopt for handling any
dynamic data resource updates.
Now that we have our command
buffer and also, we have handled
our resource updates let's talk
more about render pass encoders
which you will use to encode
your draw calls.
As Dan mentioned earlier,
command encoders translate API
calls into GPU hardware commands
in a command buffer.
I will be talking about render
command encoders which provides
APIs for typical graphics,
operations like setting your
pipelines, texture buffer
objects, and also issuing the
draw calls.
So when creating your encoder
you need to first set the render
targets.
So here is a render pass
descriptor where you will set
the render targets and then ask
the command buffer to create a
new encoder for this render
pass.
And now you can use this encoder
to encode your draw calls.
One key change from OpenGL is in
Metal once the encoder is
created you cannot change its
render targets because GPU
performs much better when it
sees a largest span of draw
calls which are rendering to the
same set of render targets.
So Metal API reflects this by
giving an explicit start and end
to a render pass.
Now all the draws issued by this
encoder will be rendering to
these render targets.
When you want to draw to a
different set of render targets
then you end this render pass
and start a new one.
And here is where we are
creating a render pass
descriptor and binding color and
depth attachments.
Now you can use that descriptor
and create a render command
encoder.
Now all the draws issued by this
encoder will be rendering to
these targets.
Additionally, in Metal you can
also provide load and store
actions for these attachments
for optional GPU bandwidth
usage.
So these load and store actions
allow you to control how the
texture contents will be handled
before and after a rendered
pass.
So here we have color and depth
attachments for a render pass.
If it specified the load action
as clear for both of these
render targets the GPU will
first clear their contents.
Then the GPU will execute
commands in this encoder
rendering to these render
targets.
Now you can specify the store
actions to be performed at the
end of the render pass.
Here for the color buffer since
the store action is store it
will preserve the contents of
this color buffer at the end of
the render pass.
And for the depth attachment,
since we said store action as
don't care it will discard its
contents.
So these texture load and stores
are expensive GPU operations
that consumes memory bandwidth.
So choose clear and don't care
wherever possible.
And here is how you set your
action.
In this example we specify clear
as a load action and set the
clear color.
And here we specify store action
as store.
Similarly, you can specify load
and store action for each of the
render targets you set in this
render pass descriptor.
So that's how we configured our
render targets.
Now you can create the encoder
from this descriptor and we can
start encoding draw calls.
But before that I want to show
you some OpenGL commands and
they will show you their Metal
equivalents.
So this is a typical OpenGL draw
sequence.
In this segment first we bind a
frame buffer which will set all
the render targets.
Then we bind our program which
contains vertex and fragment
shader.
And we bind vertex buffer
containing vertex data.
And then we bind another buffer
containing all the uniforms.
And then we'll set a texture to
sample from.
And finally, we draw.
So here is the Metal equivalent,
it's a few more lines of code
since it's explicit but it's
actually very similar to OpenGL.
First, we create a render
command encoder using render
pass descriptor which has our
render targets.
Then we set a pipeline object
which has our shaders.
Then we set a buffer for
accessing our vertex shader and
this happens to contain the
vertices we will draw with.
Note that the Metal doesn't
distinguish between buffers
containing uniforms or those
containing vertices.
So we will use the same API to
set uniform buffer.
So here the first call will give
buffer access to vertex shader
while the second call will give
access to the fragment shader.
Next, we set a texture for our
fragment shader to sample from.
And then we draw.
And once we are done encoding
commands we will indicate this
to Metal by calling endEncoding
on the encoder object.
So this was a simple example of
a metal render pass.
Now that we have a complete
render pass let's see how to get
these renderings onto the
display.
With OpenGL you present your
rendered frame onto the screen
but you don't explicitly manage
the system's render buffers also
known as drawables.
But with Metal to get your
content displayed on the screen
first you need to obtain the
special textures called
drawables from the system.
So you can use a MetalKit view
which will provide you a
drawable texture for each frame.
And once you obtain this
drawable you can encode render
passes and render to these
drawables just like you would
render to any other texture.
However, unlike other textures
now you can present this
drawable to your view.
So let me show you a code
sample.
First, I want to mention that
these drawables are limited
shade system resources, so you
should hold on to them as
briefly as possible.
This means that you should
encode all your offscreen render
passes before you acquire a
drawable.
Then you can create a MetalKit
view for either a fully
populated render pass descriptor
which you can directly use to
create encoders, which is what
you see here or you can ask for
a specific texture using
view.currentDrawable property.
And then you can build your own
render pass descriptor around
it.
Once you are finished encoding
your frame you can call the
command buffer's present
drawable method which puts your
drawable onto the screen when
GPU finishes executing this
command buffer.
So now once GPU is done
executing this frame you should
see your frame on the display.
So that was our quick tour to
get your renderings onto the
display with Metal.
But I have a few more tips to
share.
It is possible to port one
render pass at a time into
Metal.
The IOSurface and CVPixelBuffer
APIs can be used to create a
texture which can be shared
between OpenGL and Metal.
This will allow you to render to
a texture in OpenGL and then
read from it in Metal or vice
versa.
So some of the applications can
leverage this to port
incrementally, especially with
plugin architectures which are
built around OpenGL.
So there is a sample code linked
to this session showing exactly
on how to do this.
Now that you have a Metal
application you can adopt all
new Metal features.
If your application is CPU bound
then multithreading your CPU
encoding work can help.
You can encode multiple command
buffers simultaneously on
separate threads.
You can even split single
command buffer encoding across
multiple threads using parallel
render command encoder.
Also, GPUs compute by planned
processing APIs is built right
into Metal.
You can use GPU in whole new
ways.
To start with instead of CPU you
can leverage compute pipeline to
generate graphics GPU data.
By letting GPU to generate its
own data you're not only
reducing the CPU utilization and
synchronization points now you
are freeing up the data
bandwidth to GPU.
Now with this high bandwidth
compute processor you can
implement many more complex
algorithms like these.
Metal supports many more great
features which you can adopt in
your application to improve its
performance.
In addition, as part of your
porting process we highly
encourage to use our Metal
powerful debugging and
optimization tools which are
integrated right into Xcode.
So Metal has a great API
validation layer that will print
detailed information about any
improper API usage and also
suggests some potential fixes.
This is a GPU debugger which
gives you a capability to step
through your Metal calls and
view how your frame is being
rendered step-by-step.
You can view all the resources
associated with your frame.
It also provides the GPU expert
tips based on your resource
usage.
For this year we have also added
shader debugging capability
where you can debug your shader
functions just like other
functions.
We also added a shader profiler
which showing a rich set of
performance metrics related to
your shaders.
And also, a dependency viewer
which allows you to evaluate
dependencies between the render
passes and you can potentially
merge any redundant render
passes to improve your
application's performance.
And finally, the Metal system
trace tool in instruments will
give you a complete view of your
application's behavior and
performance so we highly
recommend using these tools to
ease your porting effort.
Wrapping it up, OpenGL and
OpenCL are deprecated.
They are still around but we are
discouraging their future use.
It is time to adopt Metal.
We have full suite of developer
tools, a lot of experience
helping many teams successfully
go through this effort and come
out with substantially improved
performance.
I'm hoping the information we
shared today will give you
smooth porting experience.
And we are very happy to talk to
you about your applications and
how to get them up and running
with Metal.
So we will be available tomorrow
afternoon at OpenGL to Metal
porting lab and there are many
upcoming sessions on Metal.
I recommend attending these
sessions to learn more about how
to debug and optimize your
applications with Metal.
With that I thank you all for
attending and I hope you enjoy
the rest of your week.
[ Applause ]