[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Hi, everybody.
My name is Sean James and I'm a
GPU Software Engineer.
Today, I'm going to talk about
Ray Tracing.
So, you may have seen our Ray
Tracing demo in the State of the
Union and want to learn more.
Or you may be interested in
using Ray Tracing in your own
apps.
Today, I'll talk about how you
can use Ray Tracing in your
applications and how you can
accelerate it on the GPU using
METAL.
Specifically, using METAL
Performance Shaders.
METAL Performance Shaders is a
collection of GPU Compute
Primitives optimized for all of
our iOS and macOS devices.
MPS includes support for image
processing, linear algebra, and
machine learning.
We've talk extensively about
these topics in previous
sessions.
This year, we've also added
support for training.
And there's an entire session
about this topic tomorrow.
For today, I'll talk about the
new support we've added this
year for Ray Tracing.
So first, what is Ray Tracing?
Ray Tracing applications are
based on following the paths
that Rays take as they interact
with the scene.
Rays can model light, sound, or
other forms of energy.
So, Ray Tracing has applications
in rendering, audio, and physics
simulation.
But rays can, also, represent
more abstract concepts, like
whether or not one point is
visible from another.
So, Ray Tracing also has
applications in collision
detection, artificial
intelligence, and pathfinding.
For today, though, I'll focus on
rendering as an example of how
you can use Ray Tracing in your
applications.
So, you may be familiar with the
rasterization pipeline.
The rasterizer works by
projecting one triangle at a
time onto the screen and shading
the corresponding pixels.
This can be implemented very
quickly in GPU hardware, which
makes this the method of choice
for games and other real time
applications.
But the rasterization model
makes it difficult to simulate
certain physical behaviors of
light.
One example is reflections.
With the rasterizer, reflections
are, typically, implemented
using approximations, such as
cube maps and screen space
reflections.
But with the Ray Tracer we can
compute accurate reflections,
directly.
Another example is shadows.
With the rasterizer, shadows are
typically implemented using
shadow maps.
But these can be tricky to
implement without suffering from
aliasing and resolution issues.
Furthermore, soft shadow mapping
techniques tend to produce
uniformly soft shadows.
With the Ray Tracer we can
directly compute whether or not
a point if in shadow.
So, we can produce clean
shadows, including realistic
transitions from hard to soft
shadows as the distance between
objects increases.
One final example is global
elimination.
This simulates light bouncing of
off surfaces in the scene.
Global elimination can be very
difficult to model with the
rasterizer.
But it's actually modeled quite
naturally with the Ray Tracer.
In fact, many games and real
time applications that include a
global elimination component,
actually, precompute it using a
Ray Tracer and store the result
into textures.
Which are then mapped back onto
the geometry at run time.
Of course, there are many other
effects that we can simulate
with the Ray Tracer, such as
ambient occlusion, refraction,
and area light sources.
As well as camera effects, such
as depth of field and motion
blur.
This makes Ray Tracing the
method of choice for
photorealistic offline rendering
applications.
The tradeoff is that Ray Tracing
is significantly more
computationally expensive than
rasterization because we're
doing so much more work to
simulate these effects.
So, let's first take a closer
look at how rendering works with
the Ray Tracer, and then we'll
see how we can accelerate is
with METAL.
So, we use an algorithm called
Path Tracing.
In the real world, photons are
emitted from light sources and
they bounce around until they
enter the camera or your eye.
But most of those photons
actually never make it to the
camera.
So, this would be very
inefficient to simulate.
Fortunately, due to properties
of light we can, actually, work
backwards, starting from the
camera.
We start by casting primary rays
from the camera into the scene.
We then compute shading at the
intersection points.
Shading consists of figuring out
how much light is arriving at
the shading point and what
fraction of that light is
reflected back towards the
camera.
There are, actually, two sources
of light, which we'll handle
separately.
The first source is direct
light.
This is light that arrives
directly at the shading point
from the light source.
We can easily compute how much
light is arriving directly and
what fraction of that light is
reflected back towards the
camera.
All we need to do is check that
the shading point is not,
actually, in shadow, before
adding the lighting to the
image.
To do this, we can cast
additional shadow rays from the
shading point towards the light
source.
If the shadow ray doesn't make
it all the way to the light
source, then the original
shading point was in shadow.
So, we shouldn't add the
lighting to the image.
The other source of light is
indirect light.
This is light that bounces off
of other surfaces in the scene
before reaching the shading
point.
To collect indirect light, we
can cast secondary rays in
random directions from the
shading point.
We then, repeat the shading
process at the secondary
intersection points.
We'll first compute how much
light is arriving directly at
the second intersection point
and what fraction of that light
is reflected back towards the
previous intersection point.
And, ultimately, back into the
camera.
We'll also need to cast another
shadow ray from the secondary
intersection point.
And we can repeat this process
however many times we'd like to
simulate light bouncing around
the scene.
Now, in order to get these nice
soft shadow and bounced lighting
effects we, actually, need to
cast many shadow and secondary
rays per point along the path.
This means that the number of
rays, actually, grows
exponentially with the number of
bounces.
To avoid this exponential growth
we'll, instead, choose just one
shadow ray and one secondary ray
direction at each bounce.
This will result in a noisy
image but we can average the
results together over multiple
frames.
Each frame will, also, generate
its own set of primary rays, so
this, also, gives us the
opportunity to implement camera
effects such as depth of field
and motion blur.
So, let's translate this all
into a diagram.
First, we'll generate primary
rays.
Then, we'll find the
intersections with the scene.
Then, we'll compute shading at
the intersection points.
And remember, that this is an
iterative process, which will
generate additional shadow and
secondary rays, which will be
intersected with the scene,
again.
And finally, we'll write the
shaded color into our image.
So, this is describing a
rendering application.
But a significant fraction of
the time is, actually, spent on
ray triangle intersection
testing.
This means that the performance
of the intersector has a huge
impact on the overall rendering
performance, even though, it has
nothing to do with the actual
lighting and shading.
This core intersection problem
is, also, common to all Ray
Tracing applications.
So, we decided to solve this
core intersection problem for
you, so that you can start with
a high performance intersector
and just focus on the details of
you app.
So, this year, we're introducing
the MPSRayIntersector API.
This is an API which accelerates
ray triangle intersection
testing on the GPU on all of our
macOS and iOS devices.
We wanted to make it easy to
integrate his into existing
apps, so we simply take in rays
through a METAL buffer.
MPS will find the closest
intersection along each ray and
return the results in another
METAL buffer.
All you need to do is provide a
METAL command buffer at the
point in your application where
you'd like to perform
intersection testing.
And we'll encode all of the
intersection work into the
command buffer for you.
So, let's take a closer look at
the problem that we're trying to
solve.
Oh. Okay. So, 3D models are,
usually, represented as arrays
of triangles.
What we need to do is search
through those triangles and
figure out which ones intersect
each ray.
And furthermore, we need to
figure out which intersection
point is closest to the ray's
origin.
And the simplest way to do this
would be to just loop through
all the triangles and check for
intersection with the ray.
But for anything but the
smallest scenes, this would be
far too slow.
So instead, we built a data
structure that we call an
Acceleration Structure.
The acceleration structure works
by recursively dividing the
scene into groups of triangles
that are located nearby in
space.
When you want to intersect a ray
with a scene, we intersect the
ray with the bounding boxes in
the tree.
If a ray misses a bounding box,
then we can skip the entire
subtree.
In the end, we're left with just
a fraction of the triangles that
we actually need to check for
intersection with the ray.
So, this is the main way that we
speed up ray triangle
intersection.
Of course, this is a simplified
example.
In a real scene the acceleration
structure can be quite a bit
more complicated.
We can see from this
visualization that the
acceleration structure is
adapting to the complexity of
the geometry.
This means that we spend most of
our time searching for
intersections only in areas of
high geometric complexity, which
is what we want.
Now, I'm describing this to give
you an intuition for what the
acceleration structure is and
how it works.
But you, actually, don't need to
worry about this, too much,
because MPS will take care of
all of this for you.
Remember that we'll model our
scene using triangles.
And those triangles will
themselves be represented by
vertices in a vertex buffer.
All you need to do is call MPS
to build an acceleration
structure from your vertex
buffer.
When you're ready to search for
intersections, you simply
provide this acceleration
structure back to the
intersector.
So, let's see how we can use
this to build a real
application.
We'll break this app into three
stages.
First, we'll generate primary
rays, find the intersections
with the scene, and compute
shading.
This will be equivalent to what
we could have done with the
rasterizer, but we'll take it
further in the next steps.
So next, we'll add shadows.
MPS has special support for
shadow rays, which can make this
application even faster.
And finally, we'll simulate
light bouncing around the scene
using secondary rays.
This would be very difficult to
do with the rasterizer, but
we'll see that it's, actually, a
straightforward extension with
Ray Tracing.
So, let's start with primary
rays.
There are five things that we
need to do.
First, we'll create a ray
triangle intersector.
Then, we'll create an
acceleration structure from our
vertex buffer.
Next, we'll generate primary
rays and write them into our ray
buffer.
We'll then, find the
intersections between those rays
and the scene, using the
intersector.
And finally, we'll use the
intersection results to compute
shading.
So, let's start with the
intersector.
The MPSRayIntersector class
coordinates all of the ray
triangle intersection testing.
All we need to do to create one
is provide the METAL device that
we want to use for intersection
testing.
Next, we'll create the
acceleration structure.
This is represented by the
MPSTriangleAccelerationStructure
class.
Again, all we need to do to
create one is provide the same
METAL device we used to create
the intersector.
We then, attach our vertexBuffer
and specify the triangleCount.
And finally, we build the
acceleration structure.
We only need to do this once.
And then, we can reuse the
acceleration structure as many
times as we'd like.
So next, we'll generate primary
rays and write them into our ray
buffer.
To do this, we'll launch a
two-dimensional compute kernel
with one thread per pixel.
Each thread will write this ray
struct into the ray buffer.
We can think about our output
image as floating on a plane in
front of the camera.
Primary rays are emitted from
the camera, so we'll simply set
the origin to the camera
position.
To compute the direction, we'll
find the direction from the
camera position through the
corresponding pixel on the image
plan.
Now that we have our primary
rays, we'll use the intersector
to find the intersections of the
scene.
The encodeIntersection call will
tie together everything we've
created, so far.
First, remember that we'll
encode into a METAL command
buffer.
We, actually, have a couple of
options for what type of
intersection search we'd like to
do.
In this case, we'll just use
nearest, which will find the
closest intersection along each
ray.
We'll then, provide the ray
buffer, which contains the
primary rays we just created, as
well as an intersection buffer,
which will contain the
intersection results.
We, also, need to provide the
rayCount, which in this case, is
just the image width times the
image height.
And finally, we'll provide our
accelerationStructure.
MPS will find the closest
intersection along each ray and
return the results in the
intersection buffer.
So, all that's left is to use
the intersection data to compute
shading.
To do this, we'll launch another
compute kernel.
We can apply lighting and
textures similar to the way that
we would in a fragment shader.
Most of the standard texture and
math functions that are
available in a fragment shader
are, also, available in a
compute kernel.
But shading, typically, depends
on both the intersection point
and vertex attributes, such as
colors and normals.
In a fragment shader the GPU
would interpolate these for us.
But we'll need to interpolate
them ourselves based on the
intersection data.
So, let's first look at how we
can compute the intersection
point.
Remember that a ray is defined
by its origin and direction.
This is the intersection struct
returned to us by the
intersector.
The distance field will tell us
how far we would need to go in
the ray direction to get from
the ray origin to the
intersection point.
And this distance will be
negative if the ray doesn't
intersect anything.
The primitiveIndex tells us
which triangle we hit.
And the last field is what we'll
use to interpolate vertex
attributes.
This field contains the first
barycentric coordinates called U
and V.
And these correspond to the
location of the intersection
point relative to the vertices
of the triangle.
There are, actually, three
barycentric coordinates, but
they add up to one.
So, we can compute the third
coordinate W by subtracting the
first two from one.
If we have a vertex attribute
defined at each vertex of our
triangle, then the interpolated
vertex attribute is just the sum
of the attributes at each vertex
weighted by the barycentric
coordinates.
For example, if we have a color
defined at each vertex, then the
interpolated color is just the
weighted sum of the colors at
each vertex.
So, at this point we've created
a ray intersector and an
acceleration structure.
We then, generated primary rays
and found the intersections with
the scene.
We computed shading at the
intersection points, and then
wrote the shaded color into our
image.
So, let's take a look at the
We can see the geometry
represented by the acceleration
structure, as well as the
interpolated vertex colors and
lighting we just computed.
Now that we have an image on
screen we're ready to add some
additional effects.
So, we'll start by adding
shadows to our image.
To do this, we need to check if
the light can actually reach the
shading point before adding it
to the image.
To do this we can cast
additional shadow rays from the
intersection points towards the
light source.
If a shadow ray doesn't make it
all the way to the light source,
then the original shaded point
wasn't shadow.
So, we shouldn't add its color
to the image.
We'll modify our shading kernel
to write out additional shadow
rays into another METAL buffer.
We'll then, find the
intersections with the scene,
again.
And then, we'll launch one final
kernel which will conditionally
write the shaded color into the
image based on whether or not
the shadow rays intersect at
anything.
So, let's start with the changes
to the shading kernel.
Now, shadow rays are a little
different than primary rays.
First, we need to provide a
maximum intersection distance so
that our shadow rays don't
overshoot the light source.
We also don't need to know which
triangle we hit or what the
barycentric coordinates were.
So, there are some optimizations
we can do.
And finally, remember that we
can't write the shaded color
into the image until we know
whether or not the original
shading point was in shadow.
So, we need a way to pass the
color from the shading kernel
through the intersector, all the
way into the final kernel, which
will update the image.
To do this, we can customize our
ray struct.
So, first we have several
options for what data we
actually provide to the
intersector.
In this case, we'll use a data
type which includes minimum and
maximum distance fields.
MPS will ignore any
intersections outside of this
range, which will prevent our
shadow rays from overshooting
the light source.
Second, if you have
application-specific data
associated with your rays you
can append that data at the end
of the ray struct and provide a
rayStride.
MPS will skip past this data
when reading from your ray
buffer.
In this case, we'll add the
shade of color to the end of the
ray, so that we can propagate it
from the shading kernel through
to the final kernel.
We configure these options on
the ray intersector.
First, we'll set the rayDataType
to match our struct type.
Then, we'll set a rayStride to
skip past the color at the end
of the struct.
Next, we'll run the shadow rays
through the intersector.
This was our original call to
the intersector.
Remember that shadow rays are
only checking for visibility
between the original shading
point and the light source.
So, there are two optimizations
we can do.
First, just like we can
customize the rayDataType, we
can also customize the
intersection data type or what
data is returned to us by the
intersector.
In this case, we only need to
know if the distance is positive
or negative, indicating a hit or
a miss.
So, we can set the intersection
data type to just distance.
This will save some memory
bandwidth reading from and
writing to the intersection
buffer.
Second, because we don't,
actually, need to know which
triangle we hit, we can end the
intersection search as soon as
we hit any triangle.
This is, typically, much faster
than searching for the closest
intersection.
MPS has a special mode for this,
which we can turn on by passing
the any intersectionType instead
of nearest.
Finally, we can launch our last
kernel, which will add the color
to the image.
Each thread will read in one
shadow ray and the corresponding
intersection data.
If the intersection distance was
positive, then the original
intersection point was in
shadow.
So, there's nothing more to do.
Otherwise, the intersection
point wasn't in shadow.
So, we should read in the ray
color and write it into the
output image.
And that's all we need to do to
add shadows to our image.
We can see that each shaded
point is now checking whether or
not the light source is visible
before adding the lighting to
the image.
Because we're using a ray tracer
we can, also, randomly sample
the surface of the light source,
which gives us these nice soft
shadows.
So last, we'll look at secondary
rays.
Remember that secondary rays
simulate light bouncing around
the scene.
All we need to do to add
secondary rays is move all of
our kernels into a loop.
In each iteration we'll choose a
new random direction to continue
they ray's path.
So, modify the shading kernel to
produce the rays for the next
iteration.
Once we finish updating our
image we can simply loop back to
the first intersection test.
And we can repeat this loop
however many times we want rays
to bounce.
So, let's look at the changes to
the shading kernel.
In each iteration we'll move the
ray origin to the intersection
point.
We'll then, choose a random
direction to continue the path.
And finally, we'll multiply the
ray color by the interpolated
vertex color.
This will cause the light to
take on the color of whatever
surface it bounces off of.
In a more advanced application,
this would be a much more
complicated calculation.
But by choosing the random ray
directions, carefully, we can
actually get the rest of the
math to cancel out.
And this works even though we're
working backwards from the
camera as long as we're careful
to tint the direct lighting by
the ray color at each
intersection point.
So, that's all we need to do for
secondary rays.
So, we can see that light has
started to bounce off of the
walls and onto the sides of the
boxes and ceiling.
So, that's it for our example
app.
We started by getting an image
on screen with primary rays and
shading.
Then, we added shadows.
And finally, we simulated light
bouncing around the scene with
secondary rays.
So, let's switch to the demo and
take a look at this running
live.
So, here's the application we
just wrote up and running on the
12.9-inch iPad Pro.
We've, actually, extended this
application to support more
advanced lighting, shading,
textures, and more.
So, let's switch to a more
complicated scene, which used
many of these features.
Here's the Amazon Lumberyard
Bistro scene you saw running in
the State of the Union on four
GPUs.
The scene has almost one million
triangles.
But, even with these advanced
lighting and shading techniques
we're still able to achieve
almost 20 million rays per
second on an iPad Pro.
And that's a combined
measurement including primary,
shadow, and secondary rays.
So, we've created what we think
is an easy to use API that you
can use to start implementing
these types of applications
today.
So, that's if for our demo, for
now.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
So, don't worry if you didn't
catch all of that because this
application will be available
for download as a sample.
The sample demonstrates
everything I've talked about
today and more.
We recommend that you get
started by downloading the
sample and adding your own
geometry, lighting, shading, and
so on.
There's, also, a lot more to the
API that I didn't have time to
talk about, today.
So, we, also, recommend that you
take a look at the documentation
and headers.
And with that, I'll hand it off
to my colleague, Wayne, who will
talk about how we can extend
this to multiple GPUs.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Sean.
Hi, everyone.
So, say you're working on your
Mac.
It has an internal GPU.
But you've, also, plugged in a
couple or really high
performance eGPUs.
And what we'd like to be able to
do is use all of these GPUs
together to make Ray Tracing go
as fast as we possibly can.
So, how are we going to do this?
Well, there's three things we
need to think about.
First of all, how are we going
to divide up the work between
GPUs?
Secondly, at some point the GPUs
are going to need a way to
exchange data.
So, how are we going to deal
with that?
And finally, we need a way to
keep everything synchronized.
Now, for this, I'll show you how
to use the new METAL Events
feature that we're introducing
here, this week.
So, let's get started.
So, to divide up the work we're
going to use something called
Split Frame Rendering.
The idea here is to partition
our frame into regions.
And then, we'll assign each of
these regions to a different
GPU, so that they can be
rendered in parallel.
Now, each GPU will run the full
rendering pipeline that Sean
described earlier.
So, that's everything from
initial ray generation right
through to shadow rays and
shading.
Now, once all GPUs have finished
we'll pick whichever one is
connected to the display and
we'll copy across all of our
completed regions for
composition.
Now, composition could just be
stitching the regions together
into one frame buffer.
Or you might want to combine
them with the results of a
previous render to refine the
image and remove noise.
Now, before we can render
anything, we need to make sure
that each GPU has a complete
copy of the scene.
Assets, such as your vertex
buffers and your textures need
to be replicated on all GPUs.
And so, do the triangle
acceleration structures that
Sean introduced earlier.
Now, for the acceleration
structures, we really wanted to
avoid you having to build them
from scratch for each GPU.
So, we added an API that enables
you to take an existing
acceleration structure and make
a copy for each GPU that you
want to use.
Now, this copy is nonrecursive.
So, any buffers that you have
attached to your acceleration
structure, for example, your
vertex and your index buffers,
you'll need to copy those
separately.
And then, attach them to the
acceleration structure that we
just created.
So, now that the data is
replicated on all GPUs we're
ready to start rendering.
Now, the interesting thing for
our multi-GPU perspective is
that this part of the pipeline
is virtually unchanged from what
Sean described earlier.
The only difference we need to
make for multi-GPU is to
restrict regeneration to
whichever part of the screen a
particular GPU is working on.
Everything else is the same.
So, for that reason, let's move
straight on to what's, probably,
the trickiest stage for
multi-GPU, and that's its final
composition phase here.
Now, for best performance on
macOS, each GPU will render into
its own private buffer.
And once rendering has finished
we need to copy that buffer over
to whichever GPU we're using for
composition.
Now, we can't copy between the
buffers, directly, because METAL
resources can only be used on
the device that they were
created on.
So, you can't create a buffer on
one GPU, and then try and attach
it to a Blit encoder on a
different GPU.
That's just not going to work.
So, this means that our copies
will need to go through system
memory.
Now, to make this as efficient
as we can, we use the buffer
arrangement that you see here.
We're going to create two METAL
buffers; one on each device that
wrap a common CPU allocation.
And as the buffers wrap the same
underlying memory anything that
is written into the METAL buffer
on device A is, also, visible to
the METAL buffer on device B.
Now, as I mentioned earlier, for
performance reasons on macOS all
of the actual rendering work is
done using private buffers.
And then, we Blit our completed
regions through system memory
when it's time to copy them to a
different GPU.
So, here's a quick look at how
to set this up.
First, we create our buffer on
device A, using METAL shared
storage mode.
And this allocates system
memory, internally.
And we can get appointed to it
using the .contents method.
We, then create a buffer on
device B using the NoCopy API to
wrap the memory that we just
allocated to buffer A.
Now, something to be aware of
for this API is that the buffer
needs to be a multiple of page
size.
So, you'll need to pad the
length when you create the
original buffer.
So, now that we're able to share
memory between devices we need
to think about synchronization.
Now, to help with this we have
an example timeline here to help
us visualize two GPUs running in
parallel.
The dark boxes represent command
buffers and the green boxes
represent work that we've
encoded into those command
buffers.
For example, using a compute
command encoder.
So, the GPU at the top there, is
going to do some rendering.
And when it's finished, it'll
Blit its completed region into
the shared buffers that we were
just talking about.
Now, while that's going on GPU B
is, also, doing some rendering.
Now, this is the GPU that we're
going to use for composition.
So, at some point it's going to
need the buffer that was
produced by GPU A.
Now, we can see here that we
have a problem.
There's no synchronization in
this area, here.
So, there's nothing to prevent
GPU B from trying to read the
buffer before GPU A has finished
writing to it.
Now, to deal with this we can
use METAL Events.
With METAL Events, we'll insert
a wait into the command buffer.
So, while the GPU is executing,
it'll reach the wait, and then
it's just going to stop.
And what it's waiting for is a
signal from the other GPU.
Once that signal is received we
know that GPU A has finished
writing to the buffer and it's
now safe for GPU B to access it.
So, this is an elegant way to
fix our synchronization problem.
But, clearly, having a GPU,
potentially, a very powerful GPU
just sitting there waiting is
not good.
So, we need to make this wait as
short as possible and, ideally,
we want the GPU working instead
of waiting.
So, what I'm talking about,
here, is load balancing.
So currently, we just split the
screen equally between GPUs.
And there's a couple of problems
with this.
Firstly, it doesn't take into
account that you might be using
GPUs of different performance.
If one GPU is much faster than
the other, then it stands to
reason that, yeah, it's going to
finish first.
And the other problem is that
some parts of the screen are
more complicated to render than
others.
They take longer.
They might have more complex
geometry or more complex
materials.
So, to fix this, we need to
adjust our region sizes
adaptively.
Now, the aim here is for each
GPU to take, approximately, the
same amount of time to render
its part of the scene.
Now, the way we do this is we
start with the fixed partitions
that you see here, and we render
a frame.
And we time how long each GPU is
working for.
And then, we use that to decide
how big a region to give each
GPU the next time around.
And we do this the whole time
your application is running.
So, it constantly adapts to the
performance of the GPUs that you
have connected.
And wherever you are and
wherever you're looking in your
scene.
So, to measure how hard a GPU is
working, we use command buffer
completion handlers.
Now, completion handler is a
block of CPU code that you can
have run after the GPU has
finished executing your command
buffer.
Now, on iOS command buffers have
a couple of useful properties
that you can read to find out
how long it took to run on the
GPU.
But these aren't available on
macOS.
So, we need to come up with an
approximation.
And the way we do this is we
store the host time when each
command buffer completion
handler was called.
And if you do this for every
command buffer, you can then use
the differences between these
times to figure out how long the
GPU was running for.
So, for example, to estimate how
long the three command buffers
shown here took execute, we've
measured the time between the
completion handler was called
for command buffer 3 and command
buffer 0.
So, that's the theory.
And now, let's see it in action.
All right.
So, this is the Amazon
Lumberyard Bistro scene that
Sean was showing you earlier.
And this time, it's running on a
MacBook Pro.
And you can see in the top left
of the screen here, we have a
rays per second metric.
As you can get an idea for how
it's running.
So, this includes the primary
rays, secondary rays, and the
shadow rays.
They're all included in this
metric.
So, you can see, we're getting
about 30 million rays per
second.
And it'd be nice if we were
going a little faster.
So, I'm going to enable one of
the eGPUs that I have connected,
here.
So, you can see from the text
there, we're now running on an
RX 580, as well as the internal
GPU, here.
And performance has doubled to
about 60 million rays per
second.
And you can also see the green
lines here that we're using to
help visualize how the load is
split between GPUs.
So, one GPU is rendering
everything above the line.
And one GPU is rendering
everything below.
So, with the eGPU we're now
going about twice as fast as we
were before.
I was kind of hoping for a bit
more, there.
And so, the problem is the eGPU
is sitting there waiting.
And that's because we're using
these fixed partitions.
So, if we switch on the adaptive
load balancing, here, you see
the RX 580 just grabs a big
chunk of the work, now.
And we're going much faster than
we were, previously.
So, the scene here has
approximately one million
triangles.
And we're now going to switch to
an outside view.
It's the same Amazon Lumberyard
scene but we're outside, now.
And this scene has approximately
3 million triangles.
And I have another GPU sitting
here.
So, we'll turn that one on, too.
And, this time, it's a Vega 64.
So, you see the Vega grabbing a
big chunk of the work, there.
And what's interesting about
this configuration is we have
three very different GPUs
working together.
They're different architectures
and they're very different
performance, too.
But they're all working together
to help produce this great
image.
[ Applause ]
So, today we introduced the
MPSRayIntersector, a new API
that you can use to accelerate
ray triangle intersections on
the GPU.
As you saw from my demos, it's
available on all of our iOS and
macOS platforms.
And it scales really well as you
add multiple GPUs on macOS.
Now, we're really excited to see
how you use Ray Tracing in your
applications.
We used Path Tracing in our
example, today.
But there's also hybrid
rendering.
You might want to incorporate
Ray Tracing to do really nice
looking shadows or ambient
occlusion or reflections.
And there's also non-rendering
in cases.
For example, autosimulation,
physics, AI collisionless
action.
There's a ton of stuff you can
do with this.
So, to help you get started you
can find sample code on
developer.apple.com.
So, be sure to check that out.
Also, the header files are full
of documentation and information
on some additional features that
we weren't able to cover today.
And finally, we have our lab
session tomorrow from 12.
Sean and I will be on hand to
talk more about the API and to
help you get started with Ray
Tracing in your application.
So, we hope you can join us for
that.
So, thank you, for coming to our
talk.
And enjoy the rest of WWDC.
[ Applause ]