[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Hello, everybody.
Welcome.
I'm really excited to be here
today.
So let's get started.
Shaders are important part of
graphics, and they help you
create great-looking games and
apps.
Given the massively parallel
execution environment, working
with shaders is not easy.
There are a number of things
that can go wrong during
development, and even when you
get it right, they have to
perform really fast.
My name is Alp and today I am
going to show you great tools
and workflows to help you debug
and profile Metal shaders.
Let's talk about Metal first.
Metal is not just about the
framework and the language.
We have Metal kits, Metal
Performance shaders, and we have
great tools to make your
development process efficient
and easy.
With Metal system trace, fully
integrated into instruments, you
get visibility into how your CPU
and GPU work in parallel and the
runtime performance of your app.
It's a great first tool to start
profiling your apps, and seeing
your bottlenecks.
But today, my focus is going to
be on Metal frame debugger.
Metal frame debugger lets you
capture Metal work with a frame
of a game, or computer upload,
and step through your course.
Inspect state and resources.
And it provides great profiling
features, giving you access to
GPU counters and pipeline
statistics.
It is fully integrated into
Xcode, providing you one place
to debug and profile your Metal
workloads.
And this year, we have some
great additions to Metal frame
debugger.
With the dependency viewer, now
you get visibility into how your
encoders are working together
and connected through the use of
resources.
It's a great tool to navigate
your workload and just
understand how your [inaudible]
are working together to create
that frame.
Tomorrow at 10:00 a.m., we have
Metal Game Performance
Optimization talk, and part of
it, we will be covering the
dependency viewer.
But today I will be focusing on
geometry viewer, shader
debugger, and enhanced shaded
profiler.
And I will be showing you
workloads that will help you in
your day-to-day shaded elements.
So, let's start with the
geometry viewer.
Vertex Stage is the first stage
of the graphics pipeline.
And when you get it wrong, it
can mess up your entire scene.
So it is important to rule out
some of the vertex issues before
moving on to debugging your
shaders.
In Vertex Stage, there are
several things to check.
Mainly, your vertex inputs, your
indices, and your vertex
outputs.
Last year, with Xcode 9, we
introduced input attribute view
where we can see all this data
combined in a table view format.
But it is still hard to debug
such visual data without really
correlating back to 3D.
So that's why this year we
combined all this data and
created one place you can
visualize and inspect it.
Now, I would like to introduce
you to geometry viewer.
[ Applause ]
>> Geometry viewer is a new tool
that visualizes the
post-transform vertex data in 3D
so that you can actually see
what your vertex output is.
Alongside, it provides you your
data input indices and output,
so that you can actually
correlate that back to 3D.
It is available per-draw call
just like your attachments and
bond resources, so you'll have
one place to investigate all
your vertex issues.
Now, let's take a look at three
common vertex problems, and
let's see how you can use
geometry viewer to tackle them.
So this is the first problem,
and I am going to draw call,
drawing the tree, and as you can
see, some of the vertices of the
triangle is off screen, causing
this triangle to get skewed.
Just using the geometry viewer,
you can click on the visibly
wrong triangle.
And just using the viewer below,
you can see all the data that
these vertices are taking in and
outputting.
And in our second case, I'm on
the same draw [inaudible] but
this time, the tree is
completely missing.
Just using the geometry viewer
and the free fly camera, you can
see that the tree is drawn
completely outside of the
Frustum.
So it makes sense that it is not
rendered on screen.
So it is really easy to use
geometry viewer to detect cases
like this, and on to our last
case, sometimes it's not even
possible to form triangles to
visualize in 3D.
And these are tricky to debug.
You might have degenerated
triangles, where you have
multiple of your vertices going
into the same location.
Or you might have infinites and
[inaudible] in your vertex
output position, which is
undefined behavior for GPU.
Thankfully, geometry viewer
detects these cases and provides
an issue button for you.
With a single click to that, you
can get a list of issues it
finds.
In this case, it found several
degenerate triangles.
Clicking one, you can directly
see the data.
And just looking at this data, I
can clearly tell that two of my
vertices are going to the
origin, so it's a degenerate
triangle.
And so as you've seen in all
these examples, geometry viewer
is a powerful tool to quickly
investigate all your
geometry-related issues, and if
the problem is in your inputs,
then you have to go back and
check your model.
But if the problem is in your
output, then you have to debug
vertex shaders.
Which brings us to our next
topic.
Debugging shaders, using the new
Shader Debugger.
Shaders are hard to debug.
They have math-heavy code, with
lots of vector operations.
And they are highly parallel.
The shader code you are writing
gets executed millions of times,
every single frame.
Here is the scene from Unity's
Book of the Dead demo, that
we've seen in the keynote and
State of the Union earlier this
week.
In a single frame of this scene
makes 10 million vertexing
locations, and rendering into 60
million triangles, every single
frame, in all the different
passes.
So when you have a problem with
your shaders, it's not going to
be easy to find where the
problem is, which shader it is,
and what part of the shader
code.
So to help you debugging your
shaders, now I'm really excited
to introduce to you the new
Shader Debugger [applause].
Shader Debugger is a new tool
for debugging all Metal shaders,
providing you rich visualization
across thousands of threads at
once, and it shows you the real
data from GPU, not from
emulator.
It provides you flexible way of
setting, so that you can follow
your execution easily, without
needing to have breakpoints at
all.
And it is fully integrated into
Metal frame debugger, so that
you have everything you need to
debug your shaders.
Now, I would like to bring my
colleague, Xavier, to the stage,
to show you Shader Profiler in
action.
Xavier?
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Alp, and good
afternoon everyone.
For today's demo, I wanted to
create a cool-looking water
simulation, but as you can see,
there are some geometry
problems.
My name is Xavier, and I am
really excited to show you how
to use the new Shader Debugger
and geometry view ware to
identify and fix geometry
issues.
So we are going to start by
taking our friend capture.
You can easily do this by
clicking on the UP cutter button
here in the debug bar.
Now that we have captured our
frame, we can start debugging
our issue.
Since we are having geometry
problems, we are going to use
the new Geometry Viewer.
The Geometry Viewer allows you
to navigate and inspect the
geometry of your draw call.
The water surface should be
smooth, but as we can see, there
is a steep cliff.
So let's pick one of the
triangles that looks wrong.
For example, this one.
And now, let's select the broken
vertex that is the one here at
the bottom.
You can easily do this, by using
this table here.
So now that we have found our
broken vertex, let's take the
input positions.
As we can see here, all of the
input positions are very similar
for all of the vertices of this
triangle, and in fact, the white
coordinate is exactly the same.
So this looks correct, and it
was inspected.
Seeing the input is correct, but
as we can see here, in the 3D
view, the output is wrong, then
the problem has been our vertex
shader.
So let's use the new Shader
Debugger to debug and fix this
issue, just by clicking on the
Debug button that you can find
here in the bottom right corner.
And just like that, we are now
in the Shader Debugger.
It is that easy.
The first thing that you will
notice in the Shader Debugger is
that alongside your source code,
you have access to all the
variables that were modified on
its line, and if you want more
details about your variables,
you can just open the detail
views by clicking in this detail
view button here.
The detail view will show you in
language of source code the full
value of the variable.
And not just that, but also the
value of the variable across all
the vertices of the triangle
that you are debugging.
Here in the Debug Navigator, you
have access to the [inaudible]
history, which shows you what
your shader did from the very
beginning to the very end, and
as you can see, it's really easy
to step through your code by
just using the arrow keys.
As you may have noticed, as I
navigate through the navigator,
its position in the source code
is highlighted.
And this works in both
directions.
You can select one line in your
source code and its position in
the Debug Navigator will be
selected.
And at any point, you have
access to all the variables that
are alive in a scope by just
taking the variables view, here
at the bottom.
So now that we are more familiar
with the Shader Debugger, let's
debug our issue.
The water is calculated by
generating a displacement vector
that is later added to our final
position.
So let's get more information
about this displacement vector
just by opening this detail
view.
As we can see here in the detail
view, the right coordinate for
the vertex that we are debugging
is a big, negative number,
compared to its more positive
one in the other vertices that
were correct.
Then the issue must be in how we
are calculating this
displacement vector.
So let's use the debug navigator
to go through the function and
investigate what is happening.
And here, without even having to
read the code, we can already
tell that there is something
going wrong.
One of our variables has a value
that is not a number, and this
is likely corrupt in further
math.
So let's check why this is
happening.
If we check here in the
debugger, it turns out that we
are doing this operation on this
negative number, and this is
what is causing the [inaudible].
So now that we have found the
cause of our issue, let me
quickly fix this just by
swapping those two lines, so
that we don't do operation on a
negative number.
And now that we have done our
changes to the shader, let's try
out those changes just by
clicking in the reload changes
button, here in the debug bar.
Reloading the shaders will run
your full [inaudible] using the
new shaders, so that you can
check the results right away.
And as we can see here now our
water surface is smooth.
But let's check it in action,
just by clicking on the continue
button here in the debug bar.
And, as we can see [applause
begins] now our water simulation
is correct.
In this ex-- in this demo, we
have seen how to take a frame
cocktail, how to use the new
geometry viewer to find broken
vertices, and how to use the new
Shader Debugger to debug and fix
your vertex shaders.
Thank you, and back to Alp.
[ Applause ]
>> Pretty cool, huh?
Thank you, Xavier.
Now that you have seen Shader
Debugger in action, let's take a
closer look at how you can use
this tool for your debugging
needs.
First things first, though.
Let's talk about how you can get
into the Shader Debugger.
Here I already captured a frame,
and am on the last roll call,
and then you will have draw or
dispatch call selected, the
debug shader button on the debug
bar will be enabled for your
easy access to the Shader
Debugger.
Clicking that will show a view
for you to select the thread
you're interested in.
And selecting threads means
different things depending on
the type of shader you are
debugging.
For fragment shader, you will be
using the pixel inspector to
select the pixel you want to
debug.
For vertex shader, you will be
using the geometry viewer we
have just seen to select the
vertex you want to focus on.
And for compute, you will be
using the controls to select the
thread you are interested in.
And then, just click the debug
button, and that's it.
You are in the Shader Debugger.
And whilst you're in the Shader
Debugger, it is so easy to
inspect any variable you are
interested in.
You just need to go to the
source line you have the
variable, and that is all you
have to do.
You don't need any break points,
you don't need to step through
your code.
The values of the modified
variables in the line are going
to be available on the side bar.
And as you have seen in the
demo, we highlight [inaudible]
and infinite values in there, so
that it's really easy to spot
common mistakes.
You can just use the button on
the side bar to enable the
detail views, and get full
details about your variables.
This is pretty handy, especially
if you want to inspect the
complex [inaudible] and want to
dive into different components.
Or you can just hover on any
variable you have in your source
code, and you will instantly see
the value of the variable at
that point.
And this is partially useful if
you are sampling from a texture,
like in this example, and you
want to quickly check whether
this is the right texture.
And just like in CPU debuggers,
you have access to your
variables view, showing you all
your variables in scope.
So inspecting variables is a
core part of debugging your
shaders, but that is only half
of the story.
You also want to know what is
the order of your code getting
executed?
And Shader Debugger makes this
really easy as well.
When you get into Shader
Debugger, in the Debug
Navigator, you will see all your
source line execute by your
shader for your selected
threads.
And you can select any line you
want and directly navigate to
that.
This also provides a unique
stepping experience where you
can just use your cursor keys to
step through your code.
Functions are groups in the
navigator, so that you can just
expand them and step into them.
This also enables backward
debugging, which is a really
powerful way of debugging your
shaders.
Just find the variable that has
the wrong value, and just work
your way backward to see where
it got wrong, and why.
Also you can use the filtering.
Filtering is a great way to
focus, and you can filter for
anything you are interested in
your shader code.
Filter will be matching with
function calls, variables,
resources.
And your shader code might span
across many different files, but
if you use filter, it will only
match with what your shader
executed, so it's a really great
way to focus.
So far, what we have seen is
great for debugging a single
thread, but what about other
threads?
Shader Debugger also gives you
access to other threads based on
the initial thread you selected.
What this means is, for vertex,
you'll get the primitive of your
selected vertex.
For fragment, you'll get direct
angle area, and on your selected
pixel.
For compute, you'll be getting
the full thread group of your
selected compute thread, so that
you have access to all variables
interacting with the thread
group memory.
Now, let's look at how accessing
other threads can help you debug
fragment shaders.
So while your code executes
millions of different pixels,
seeing a single variable for a
single pixel may not help you in
all the cases.
Here, I have an example, I'm
calculating a gradient, and I
can't see the single gradient
value.
But I can't really tell whether
this gradient value is good for
my pixels, or bad for my pixels.
With a single click, to bring up
the detail views, I can see this
gradient value across thousands
of other pixels around my pixel,
and now I can tell this gradient
is not correct because I can
clearly see it's not smooth.
As you've seen, detail views
help you understand your shader,
and identify good and bad values
for your shaders.
You can quickly hover into any
other pixel to instantly see the
value of that variable for that
pixel.
And you can also use this view
to switch threads.
Switching threads is great for
comparing cases where you can
clearly see good and bad pixels.
You can quickly switch between
them and see what the back pixel
is doing.
Once we switch threads, we
update the execution history and
the variable views, so that you
can fully debug your
newly-selected threads.
This gets even better.
Detail views also help you
understand your divergence.
So whenever you enable detail
view, the mask on the right-hand
side will always show you what
other threads executed the same
line of code.
In this example, it's
conditional, and just looking at
the mask, I can clearly tell
that roughly half of my threads
executed inside this-- if
conditional, in a diagonal
shape.
So now, to show you how you can
use detail views to fix problems
in fragment shaders, I would
like to invite Xavier back to
the stage.
Xavier?
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Alp.
After fixing our geometric
problems in the first demo, I
added highlights as a process
and effect.
But the results were not as
suspected.
So I took a frame capture to
debug the issue.
It was here in the [inaudible]
view, we can see that our
highlights are actually
generating dark areas in the
bottom parts.
So let's use the Shader Debugger
to debug and fix this issue.
By not pressing, I'm bringing up
the pixel inspector, which
allows you to select the pixel
that you want to debug.
So here, we are going to select
one of the pixels, for example
this one, and to start the
Shader Debugger, you have to
click the debug button here on
the bottom right corner.
And now, we are debugging the
frame and shader.
As we can see here, the
highlights are generated in
three different steps.
So let's use the detailed views
to quickly understand what is
happening.
Let's start at the beginning on
this close first one.
As we can see here, we are just
sampling from our original
color, and this looks correct.
So let's see what is next.
Here, we are accumulating
highlights in one of the
directions, so let's take the
results by opening the detailed
view.
And as we can see here in the
detailed view, there is already
dark area in the bottom part,
right here, so then the problem
must be in how we are
accumulating those highlights.
As you can see, detailed views
are a powerful tool to
understand your shader without
even having to read the code.
So let's use the Debug Navigator
to go to that first one and
investigate what is happening.
As we can see here, this
function is mainly a loop that
iterates a few times,
accumulating samples from
[inaudible] map.
Loops are highlighted just in
the Shader Debugger, which means
that you can navigate through
your iterations using the Debug
Navigator, and you will get,
alongside with your source code,
the value of the variables at
each one of the iterations.
If we focus here, we can see
that as I navigate through the
different iterations, the values
change.
But what is really powerful is
combining this with detailed
views.
So here, we are going to bring
up the detailed view for final
color, that this is where we are
accumulating our highlights.
And now let's iterate using the
Debug Navigator.
As we can see, as I iterate, we
are starting to accumulate
highlights in our final color.
But as I continue iterating
toward the end of the loop, we
are actually seeing this, there
is a pattern.
So let's investigate why this is
happening.
As we see here in the Debugger,
we can actually see that our
weight is negative.
And this is what is causing the
color to be distracted rather
than accumulated in our final
color.
So now that we have found the
cause of our issue, let me
quickly fix this.
And now, let's check the
results, just by checking in the
reload changes button, here in
the debug bar.
And as we can see here, now
there is no more other carriers,
but let's see it in action, just
by clicking on the Continue
button.
And indeed, now our highlight
looks correct.
This is just an example of how
you can use the Shader Debugger
and its powerful detailed views
to debug [inaudible] Shaders.
Thank you.
And back to Alp.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Xavier.
Now that you have seen
everything about Shader
Debugger, let's recap what we've
talked about so far.
Shader Debugger is specifically
designed for debugging Metal
shaders, taking into account of
the highly parallel nature of
GPUs, and as you've seen, it's
great for fixing bugs with the
highlights to nans and
infinites, it is so easy to spot
common mistakes, and also it's
great for understanding your
shader.
With the detailed views, you
don't even need to read the code
to understand what your shader
is doing.
And also it provides excellent
environment to develop your
shaders in.
Just get into Shader Debugger
and start editing, and read out
to quickly iterate all your
results.
Shader Debugger supports iOS,
Mac, OS and tvOS with the recent
hardware.
And it is yours to enjoy with
Xcode 10.
[ Applause ]
>> And now that we've seen how
you can use geometric viewer and
the Shader Debugger to debug
your shader problems, now let's
focus on how we can make your
shaders run faster.
So optimizing your use of GPU is
important, because you want your
apps to run fast, and consume
less battery for a great user
experience.
But before starting to optimize,
it is important to know what to
optimize.
If you are GPU bound, typical
Metal workload has many
different passes.
And knowing which pass to focus
on is quite important.
The good news is we have great
profiling tools built into Metal
frame debugger to help you with
this.
GPU counters gives you high
level performance [inaudible] of
your app.
That you can see, time
[inaudible] or draw call, and
also providing you different
counters showing bottlenecks.
And from here, once you know
your expansive pass, you can
just move to pipeline
statistics.
And here you get great compile
for your shaders, giving you the
type of instructions you have.
And using the Shader Profiler,
you get visibility into timings
for draw call or per-pipeline
states.
So today, I'll be focusing on
Shader Profiler, and I will show
you work flows that will help
you optimize your shaders.
So once you are in the Metal
frame debugger, going to read by
performance navigator, you will
see all your pipeline states
sorted by the time it takes to
execute them.
This is a great place to see all
your expansive pipelines that we
are optimizing.
And here, you also have access
to your draw-calls, using these
pipeline states, so that you can
directly navigate to one and see
what it is drawing.
And if you're in iOS or tvOS,
just going to the Shader Source,
you'll get the per line
execution cost.
This is a great place to see
where you are spending the most
time in your shaders, per line
basis.
And once you are in your shader
source, you can just start
editing your code, and reload to
see if it makes any difference
in timing.
Or you can just get into Shader
Debugger.
This is a great workflow if you
are trying to optimize an
algorithm or when I just get
through this control flow, and
when I understand whether you
can.
So Shader Profiler helps you a
lot trying to optimize your
shaders, but we made this even
better for A11.
Now, A11 [inaudible] being the
completely [inaudible] design
GPU, now we have hardware
support to give you even more
insight in what your shaders are
doing.
Now with A11, you get this
chart, per line, showing you the
cost breakdown of the executed
line.
So Shader consists different
execution units, and if you are
using one of them heavily, you
might be bottlenecked by that.
So seeing ALU and memory
breakdown gives you visibility
into like time spent in
different execution units.
We did a lot of work for how
precision instructions to be
much more efficient in A11.
So using health, overflows,
might bring significant things
on your GP budget.
And another category now you
have visibility into is
synchronization, which is an
important category to look at
because you want your Shader
core to be busy doing work, not
waiting for synchronization.
And in your shader code, if you
are reading from texture,
buffers, or using atomics or
barriers, you might have stalls
waiting for synchronization.
And also now we provide you
ability to see cost of in-line
functions, you are calling from
your shaders.
This way you can directly
navigate to your most expensive
function, and start optimizing
that [applause].
>> Welcome to the Apple designed
A11 bionic chip.
We can provide better profiling
data than ever.
This year, we are introducing
per line timing information and
instruction categories, even in
inline functions.
My name is Max, and I am going
to help you max out your Shader
performance [applause].
So I've captured the same water
simulation again, but this time,
on my iPhone.
Let's begin by change to view
frame by performance.
We now see a list of pipelines
being used in our frame, ordered
by time, and we can easily see
that the noise pipeline is
taking a significant amount of
time.
Disclosing this, we can see that
we spent nearly all the time in
our fragment Shader.
But this year, we can go deeper.
We can see the time we are
spending each inside of each of
the functions that this shader
is calling.
Just clicking here goes to the
source code file, and directly
jumps to the right line.
And that is the start of our
investigation.
So what we see here right now on
the right-hand side is a
percentage of time we are
spending inside of this
function, and further down the
percentage of time we spend in
each file-- each line.
Be aware the Shader Profiler
works on optimized code, so the
compiler can reorder the
instructions and there may be no
timing information for some
lines.
Next to the timing information,
we have the instruction
categories.
Let's take a look.
We can see that we spend time in
ALU doing math operations, we
are reading from memory, from
textures, but what raises my
concern is the time we are
spending in synchronization,
specifically, waiting on memory
here.
That means our GPU could not
read data fast enough, and it
could not hide this latency by
doing ALU work in other threads.
So let's figure out why.
Just following the performance
numbers, we will arrive at this
line, where we spent over 50% of
our entire shader time.
Taking a look into the
instruction categories again, we
can see that we spend a
significant amount in
synchronization.
But why?
We are using a color value here
that we have read from a color
texture here using an offset.
This offset was read from a
noise texture here.
So we have a dependent texture
read.
The GPU could not process until
data from the texture read
became available.
So what can we do about this?
Well, instead of reading from a
noise texture, we could just
simply calculate a noise value
in our GPU.
Let me do that.
Now, let me update my Shader.
The Shader is now sent to the
device as we compiled, and then
the entire frame is rerun and
reprofiled, because changing a
single Shader or pipeline might
influence your entire GPU
timing.
Once that is done, let's take a
look.
We can see that we now spend
just three milliseconds in the
shader from down over to 20.
But let's also take a look into
the instruction categories.
Here we can see that we nearly
eliminated the entire time in
synchronization, and we keep our
GPU busy doing work for us.
So, as a summary, when you
detect the bottleneck in your
shader, the per line timing
information tells you exactly
where your problem is, and the
instruction categories help you
to understand why.
That's it for me.
Back to my colleague, Alp.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Max.
And before closing, I would like
to talk about one last thing to
make it easier for you to work
with these new great tools.
Hopefully all of you are already
compiling your Shaders offline,
so that you are not paying the
runtime cost of online
completion.
And if you are compiling your
shaders offline, now we have a
new compiler option to save
Shader sources into the built
Metal [inaudible] so that you
have access to your shader
sources from anywhere using
these tools.
If you are compiling your
shaders using Xcode Project, you
can just go to Build Settings,
and Enable this option.
Or if you are compiling using
command line, you can just pass
dash MO option to the Metal
compilers.
But please remember to only
enable this in debug builds so
that you don't mistakenly ship
your shader sources alongside
your app.
All right.
Let's recap what we talked about
today.
We started with geometric
viewer, providing you one place
to investigate all your vertex
related issues, and debugging
visual problems, please remember
to check with geometric viewer
first, and make sure that your
geometry is right before moving
on to debugging your shaders.
And then we have seen shader
debuggers, powerful tools to
debug all your Metal shaders.
Great for fixing bugs,
understanding your shaders, and
just developing your shaders.
And within [inaudible] profiler,
now you get even more visibility
into what your GPU is doing with
the power of A11 bionic chip.
For more information, please
check the link.
Tomorrow at 10:00 a.m., we have
a great talk on Metal game
performance optimization, where
we will be talking about common
performance problems that we
found in games and tools
available for you to detect and
fix them.
Thank you [applause].