[ Music ]
>> All right.
[ Applause ]
>> My name is Pierre-Olivier
Martel.
I'm an engineering manager in
the Security, Engineering, and
Occupational Group here at
Apple.
And today, along with two of my
colleagues, I am here to talk to
you about some of the new
security features in macOS
Mojave and how you can make the
most of it in your apps.
I'll start by going over some of
the high-level security
improvements that went into the
OS this year.
And then I would like to
dedicate the rest of this
session to talk about some of
the enhancements that we are
putting in Gatekeeper.
A few years ago we introduced a
feature called Systemic Security
Protection to macOS with the
goal to increase the protection
of the operating system by
making it so that platform
binaries are protected from
modification both on disk and at
runtime.
This year we are taking it one
step further by enforcing
additional code-sending
requirements on platform
binaries.
The system will now enforce the
validity of code signatures
throughout the lifetime of
system processes and will
automatically abort any process
that deviates from its code
signature or that attempts to
execute any code that is not
properly signed by Apple.
In addition to that, the system
will monitor it - the dynamic
loading of any libraries,
frameworks, and plug-ins and
enforce that - those objects
also be signed by Apple.
It's a mechanism that has been
enforced on iOS for several
years now, and we are excited to
make this to be for the macOS.
Of course, not that this only
applies to the system.
This does not apply - it does
not apply to your apps.
However, there still remains a
few system extension points
throughout the operating system
that have not yet made the move
to the app extensions model.
And those are technically
considered to be platform
binaries; OK, it's the plug-in
loaders.
So for those we are going to
relax that policy, and the
system will still allow these
processes to load code that is
either third-party signed or
completely unsigned.
So if you ship any of these
plug-ins in your app, please
make sure that you test on the
developer preview and make sure
it works properly.
If not, please let us know.
Next, I would like to talk about
UI automation.
The security model of a macOS,
especially when it comes to user
data access, relies on the user
making security decisions for
their self - for themselves.
We deliberately captured those
decisions, either via the user
intent using the mechanisms like
the open/save dialogs or
drag-and-drop operations -- or
by a user consent, with more
explicit authorization dialogs
or asking the user to make
security configuration changes
in System Preferences.
As such, it's critical for the
operating system to be able to
differentiate between the user
actually making these decisions
and software driving the UI on
their behalf.
In the past we have made a few
targeted enhancements to some of
the system authorization dialogs
to make sure that they can
detect and block these synthetic
events.
But these decision points have
become so pervasive across the
OS that we need a better model.
In macOS Mojave, the system will
only allow UI events to be
dispatched by processes that the
user has specifically configured
to control the UI on their
behalf and effectively
impersonate them.
This configuration is made in
the Security and Privacy Press
pane in the System Preferences.
And it's currently co-located
with the existing accessing to
the key list.
This is the list of APIs that
will be impacted moving forward.
They mostly fall under two
categories.
First, the kidlet [phonetic]
Layer: IOHIDPostEvent and the
IOHIDSetMouseLocation; and then
second, at the CG Layer.
If you attempt to post any CG
event or if you create any CG
event tab, we are now providing
the Listen Only option --
effectively creating what we
call a modifying tab.
And the user will have to
approve those processes as well.
And then next, we put a lot of
focus of hardening Safari
itself.
It is, after all, one of the
most important Internet facing
applications on the machine.
So it deserves special
attention.
In Mojave, Safari, as well as
every satellite processes that
ship as part of it, it's fully
sandboxed.
If you are a web developer, this
may potentially have an impact
on your local development
workflow due to the way that
Safari now acts as its local
resources on this.
If you want more details, please
check out the What's New in
Safari and WebKit session this
Friday.
And then of course, WebKit has
been sandboxed for many years
now.
We put a lot of attention in
auditing the existing sandboxes
as well as removing any risky
and unnecessary dependencies
from those.
For example, the web content
process no longer needs access
through the Windows server, to
the dock, or to the network.
If your app uses the system
WebKit, then there is nothing
for you to do in order to adopt
this.
You will automatically benefit
from those improvements.
Next, I'd like to talk about
Gatekeeper.
So Gatekeeper has done a great
job over the years in stopping
widespread malware attacks on
the platform.
It's here.
We would like to make it better.
And we are focusing on three
main aspects.
First, I invite Kelly onstage to
tell you about a new security
mechanism that puts the user in
control over the way apps access
their personal data.
Then I'll introduce a new
security feature that you as a
developer can adopt in your apps
to increase their security and
their transparency.
And then finally, I am sure you
are all very impatient to hear
more about the Developer ID
notary service that Sebastian
mentioned in his talk yesterday.
So I invite Garrett onstage to
tell you more about that.
All right?
Let's get started.
Kelly?
[ Applause ]
>> OK, thank you Pierre.
Hi, my name is Kelly Yancy.
I'm with the OS Security Team
here at Apple.
And I am really excited today to
tell you about the new user data
protections in macOS Mojave.
Now in macOS High Sierra, these
APIs --
-- prompt the user for consent
before allowing apps to access
their respective data.
With these prompts,
well-intentioned software can
honor the user's preferences
with regards to how they access
their personal data.
Well now, in macOS Mojave,
access to this data requires
user consent -- even for apps
that access the Backing/Store
directly via the file system.
Now apps that currently use
prescribed APIs to access this
data should be well prepared.
But as always, we encourage you
to test your apps against the
latest macOS release.
Now if your app does access the
underlying databases directly
via the file system, be aware
that that may - that access may
now block the calling thread
while the operating system
presents an authorization prompt
to the user.
And in a world where computers
do billions of operations per
second, it turns out people are
relatively high latency.
So you don't want to do that I/O
in your app's main thread, or it
may appear hung while the prompt
is displayed.
So here is an example of code
that accesses the user's
pictures via the file system.
Now by default, the Photos app
stores the user's Photos library
in the Pictures folder.
So when this code traverses the
user's Photos library, it may
now trigger an authorization
prompt for access to the user's
photos -- where it would not
have in macOS High Sierra.
Now apps that traverse the
user's Home folder could trigger
multiple approval prompts, not
just for photos -- for contacts,
for calendars, and so on -- as
many apps that traverse the
entire file system, such as disk
management or backup software.
So user can pre-approve such
apps by adding them to the new
System Application Data category
in the System Preferences
Security and Privacy pane.
By doing so, the user
preauthorizes those apps to
access all of their
privacy-sensitive data without
prompting.
Authorization can also be
preconfigured in education or
enterprise environments via MDM
server as long as it's a
user-improved enrollment.
When the user is prompted to
authorize access to their
personal data, it is important
to communicate the purpose of
that access.
Imagine that you just installed
an app that you had never used
before.
And the very first time you
launch it, you saw this prompt.
That's a tough decision.
But we can make that decision
easier by including purpose
text, which makes it clear why
the app is requesting access and
what the consequences of
declining that access would be.
Now your app can specify the
text displayed in the
authorization prompts displayed
on its behalf by including keys
in your Info.plist file.
So here are the Info.plist keys
for each of the APIs that we
have been looking at.
Now you may notice that these
are largely the same as on iOS.
I want to call out one
difference, and that's the
Locations Services Info.plist
key.
This key is actually deprecated
on iOS, but I assure you it is
the correct key to use in macOS
Mojave.
So these keys will be required
for apps linked against the
10.14 SDK.
So besides informing the user,
these keys are also being used
to inform the operating system
that -- as the developer -- you
intend for your app to access
the user's personal data.
And should an app try to access
the user personal data but not
include the appropriate key and
purpose string for that data,
macOS Mojave assumes that that
access was unintended -- and the
app exits.
For compatibility, these keys
are optional for apps that link
- that target older SDKs.
So for example, if you have an
app that still targets the 10.13
SDK and tries to access the
user's personal data via one of
these APIs, the app will not
exit but will display a prompt
lacking the purpose string --
like the first one that we saw a
minute ago.
So we still encourage you to
include the Info.plist keys in
your apps, even if you are
targeting an older SDK, so that
the user is better informed why
your app is accessing their
data.
So in addition to these
prompting categories, macOS
Mojave also restricts access to
this privacy-sensitive user data
as well.
So the operating system will not
prompt for authorization to
access this data via the file
system.
Only the respective system apps
or services have access to this
data plus any apps that the user
has preauthorized for system
application data via the
Security and Privacy Preference
pane that we just saw.
In addition, authorization may
be preconfigured via MDM
enrollment.
Another way that this data can
be accessed is via scripting.
So Mail, Messages, and Safari
are all scriptable, exposing
some of their functionalities
automation by other apps.
Let's use Mail for an example.
Mail's local database contains
lots of personal information.
It has the e-mail addresses of
my friends, family, companies I
do business with.
And then there is the contents
of the mail messages themselves
-- my private correspondence, my
shopping receipts, my shipping
notifications, and my temporary
passwords for services I forgot
the password of.
So the Mail app necessarily has
access to its own local
database.
And in macOS Mojave, other apps
do not.
But since Mail can be scripted
by other applications, we need
to be sure that Mail only shares
my personal information with my
consent.
Because we want the user to be
in control of how apps they have
trusted with access to their
data act on behalf of other
apps, macOS Mojave will include
prompts like this one,
authorizing apps to control
other apps.
Now the developer preview does
not currently require
authorization to automate other
apps.
But you can try this new
protection out in a future
preview.
Only if the user consents will
Mail accept being automated by
other apps.
So this applies to Apple events.
But there are exceptions.
And there are exceptions for
Apple events that are not
particularly privacy sensitive
-- for example, opening
documents in a default
application, opening URLs in the
default handler for that URL
scheme, or opening other
applications.
Finally, macOS Mojave brings
every one of my favorite
features from iOS.
User authorization for camera
and microphone: I think I am
going to decline this one.
So apps can - that's not a link
in [inaudible] - apps can
enumerate the camera and
microphone hardware without user
consent.
But initiating capture requires
user authorization.
And this applies to all devices
supported by the built-in
drivers.
Now your app can query the
authorization status.
And this is useful if you'd like
your app's user experience to
reflect user's previous
decisions.
And this API provided by
AVFoundation is the same as on
iOS.
And what's interesting is it
doesn't just return a simple
Boolean yes/no.
It actually returns an
enumeration of four possible
values.
And I'd like to drill down on
those because I think these are
relevant.
The first one, notDetermined,
means that the user has not
previously been consented for
your app to access the camera or
microphone.
So should your app try to access
that hardware, the operating
system will display a prompt at
that time.
The restricted value actually
means that the user cannot
consent, that the hardware --
the camera or microphone -- has
been disabled -- the parental
controls or mobile device
management.
The denied value means the user
has previously been prompted,
but the user declined to give
consent.
They don't want your app to
access that hardware.
And finally, the authorized
value means that the user has
previously been prompted, and
they did consent and your app
can access that hardware.
So we believe it's important to
prompt in context.
And this is the reason why the
operating system currently
displays the prompts kind of
just in time.
At the moment that your app
accesses the microphone of the
camera, the operating system
will present a prompt when
necessary.
And we feel that that's the
right time because the user has
the most context to understand
why your app is accessing the
hardware.
But there are times where your
app might want more control over
the timing of those
authorization prompts.
For example, if your app opens a
new window, and in that window
displays frames from the camera
or a visualization of the audio
from the microphone, you might
want to avoid displaying an
empty window if the user
declines authorization -- in
which case it's better to prompt
before opening the window.
So AVFoundation provides this
API so that you can preflight
that authorization.
And I'd like to call out that
this API is actually
asynchronous.
It takes a block with - that is
called with a Boolean value of
whether your app has access or
not.
So this is a little bit
different than the enumeration
that we just saw.
That block may be invoked
immediately when you make - when
your app makes this call.
For example, if the user has
previously already consented or
denied access, the operating
system already knows that answer
and can immediately invoke the
block telling you what that
answer is.
Similarly, if the parental
controls or MDM server has made
that hardware unavailable, the
callback is immediately invoked
with a Boolean value of fault.
But it's also possible that this
callback will be invoked later
-- possibly much later -- as a
prompt is displayed while we are
waiting for - and then only when
the user makes their decision
will this callback actually be
invoked.
At that time we will know the
Boolean "Yes your app has
access" or "No it doesn't."
So your app can include purpose
text for both the camera and
microphone.
And as with the other purpose
strings, these are required for
apps linked against the 10.14
SDK, and optional and certainly
encouraged because they are
informative for apps linked
against earlier SDKs.
So to recap: Here is an overview
of all the topics that we just
looked at.
macOS Mojave does not solicit
user approval for access to this
user data.
Only the respective system apps
and apps the user has
preapproved via the Security and
Privacy Preference pane, or
preconfigured the parental
controls or MDM are permitted to
access this data.
And here are the categories of
user data and devices the apps
may access with user consent.
Now the operating system --
macOS -- presents the
authorization prompt to the user
the first time the app accesses
this data.
And then it remembers the user's
decision.
And this is great for users
because then they only see one
prompt per app per piece of
data.
They don't get multiple prompts.
But as a developer, you may
actually want to get
pre-prompted so that you can
test how your app behaves while
the prompt is displayed, if the
user consents, and if the user
declines authorization.
So for that purpose macOS
provides a tool, called tccutil,
that you can use to make the
operating system forget your
previous answers to consent
prompts.
So the next time that you run
your app, and your app requires
authorization, the operating
system will re-prompt.
So this tool is provided for
testing purposes only.
Your app should not invoke this
tool automatically, even in
debug builds.
So in summary, ensure your
approval prompts are presented
in context.
This is important so that the
user understands why they are
being prompted.
And add Info.plist keys so the
user understands what your app
is going to do with the data and
what functionality will be
unavailable if they decline.
Access approval-gated resources
from threads other than the main
thread so that your app doesn't
appear to be hung while waiting
for approval.
And gracefully handle failure to
access approval-gated resources
in the event that the user does
decline.
But finally, when the user does
consent, be responsible with the
user's personal data.
So these are the new user data
protections available in macOS
Mojave.
Thank you, and I will turn the
stage back to over to Pierre to
tell you about the enhanced
runtime protections.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks Kelly.
So in the few years since the
maturity of system integrity of
protection to the Mac, a lot of
you have asked us what you could
do in your apps to adopt some of
the runtime protections that we
afford to the rest of the
system.
Until now, there wasn't really a
good story for this.
Today, we are introducing a new
set of runtime protections that
you can easily adopt within your
app.
It is a new opt-in mechanism
that is available within the
10.14 SDK.
It effectively sets a new
security baseline for your app
by enabling the full set of
runtime protections that the
system provides, and requiring
you - requires you to opt to
back into more risky behaviors
or ideas.
It is easily configurable with a
new set of unrestricted
entitlements.
Unrestricted here means that
these entitlements are available
to everybody without any prior
approval.
It can be easily configured from
within the Xcode UI.
And then finally, it is fully
backward compatible if you need
to be able to deploy your app to
older releases of macOS and its
version.
So as we add more features to
this one time in the future,
apps that have already shipped
will not be impacted.
Now let's see what - let's talk
about these new protections.
First off, code signing: When
you opt into this new runtime,
the system will enforce that
every single executable page
within your address space must
be backed by the original code
signature that shipped with your
app.
It is a fine behavior for most
apps out there.
Of course it might be
undesirable in some of these
cases.
So let's see how we can
configure this.
Let's say, for example, that
your app has a scripting runtime
for which you have
high-performance requirements --
in which case, you'll most
likely use JIT compiled code if
you want to execute a runtime.
With this, you can use the first
entitlement in this list.
It gives you access to the new
MAP JIT flag in the MMAP system
call, which allows you to create
what we call JIT regions, which
are memory regions that are
readable, writable, and
executable.
And if you have a poliacre
[phonetic] system,
where you might expect to be
able to execute load plug-ins
that are not properly signed or
not signed at all, then you have
to use the second entitlement in
this list.
And finally, if your app needs
the ability to modify its own
code pages at runtime,
effectively breaking its own
code signature, then you will
have to use the last entitlement
in the system.
And note that the vast majority
of apps should not need that
functionality.
But we still want it to operate
anyway.
Next, library validation: When
you opt into the new runtime,
the system will enforce the code
signature of every library,
framework, and plug-in that you
dynamically load at runtime, and
by default will enforce that.
These modules have - these
objects have to be signed by
Apple and shipping as part of
the OS -- or that they be signed
with the same Team ID as the
main executable that ships with
your app.
If you have a plug-in ecosystem
here and you need the ability to
load objects that are signed by
another team, you can use this
entitlement to relax that
policy.
Note that it still requires you
to load signed code; it just can
be signed by other teams.
If you need the ability to load
fully unsigned code, you will
need to use one of the
entitlements from the previous
slide.
Next, debugging: Apps that are
opting into the new runtime
cannot be debugged and cannot
debug other apps.
If you need the ability to debug
your app while it's opting into
the new runtime, you can use the
get-task-allow entitlement.
Note that Xcode will
automatically add this
entitlement for you when you hit
Build and Run from Xcode.
So if you use Xcode as part of
your local development workflow,
then you don't need to do
anything.
Executable will also make sure
that the entitlement is properly
stripped from your signature
when you do an export for
distribution.
If you don't use Xcode, make
sure you don't ship your app
with this entitlement unless you
really need it.
If your app is actually a
debugger, then you will use the
second entitlement in the list.
And then finally, in the few
rare occasions where your app
needs to rely on the DYLD
environment variables to modify
its BFU [phonetic]
at runtime, then you can use the
last entitlement in this list.
And finally, your resource
access: This runtime requires
you to be transparent about the
kind of data classing that your
app needs to access.
So if your app attempts to
access any data that is part of
one of the protected categories
that Kelly described in his
previous section, and you don't
have the appropriate entitlement
signed in your app, then the
system will automatically
terminate it.
We have entitlements that map to
every single category that Kelly
described.
But remember that just adding
this entitlement is not enough.
You also need to add a purpose
string if you are linking
against the 10.14 SDK.
And finally, it does not
automatically grant you access
to the data.
The user is still in control of
the final decision.
So how do we enable this?
Well, from Xcode you can go into
Target setting in the
Tap-ability tab.
There you will find a new hard
and Runtime section, which you
can enable.
We have checkboxes for every
single of the entitlements that
are previously described.
And then a few more comportable
[phonetic] using the using the
Command Line interface, then we
can use the new runtime option
in the codesign command.
And in order for you to validate
that you have properly enrolled
and opted into this new runtime,
you can use the dash-dash
display option.
And here, the things to look for
are the runtime flag as well as
the runtime version.
All right.
Now let's look at the final
piece of that puzzle and talk
about notarized apps.
Garrett?
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks Pierre.
Hi everyone.
I'm Garrett, and I work on the
Trusted Execution Team here at
Apple.
Now my colleague earlier, Kelly,
talked about one way we help
protect users from malicious
software by ensuring the user is
always in control of their
private data.
I'd like to talk about another
way that we protect users from
malicious software.
And that's by identifying and
blocking malicious software so
it doesn't have the chance to
run.
Now the Mac App Store is a great
place for users to find and
download new software.
And people can confidently
install apps knowing that Apple
has taken steps to ensure they
are not harmful.
Now the Mac App Store is getting
a lot of attention this year,
and that's great.
But we also understand that some
developers need the flexibility
of the Developer ID program.
Together, Gatekeeper and
Developer ID have done a great
job of preventing widespread
outbreaks of malicious software.
And today, we are making the
Developer ID program even safer
with the introduction of app
notarization.
Now app notarization is a
process designed to help
identify and block malicious
software before distribution
while still maintaining all the
flexibility of the Developer ID
program.
That means that you can continue
to ship your apps the way you do
today with the same capabilities
that they have today.
And the key to this is the
Develop ID notary service.
Now the notary service is an
automated service that performs
security checks of Developer ID
signed content.
It's an optional extension to
the Developer ID program, and
it's not an app review.
Starting today, developers can
start uploading
distribution-ready content to
the notary service.
And assuming that those
applications, installer
packages, and disk images don't
contain any malicious software,
the notary service will issue a
notarization ticket back to your
application.
That ticket can be stapled and
then distributed alongside your
application.
And when Gatekeeper launches a
notarized app for the first
time, it can verify the
notarization and provide a new
first-launch experience.
Now your development workflow
prior to distribution is
completely unchanged.
Now you may have heard, in the
State of the Union, that this
process will be required in the
future.
And while that's true, for now
notarization is completely
optional while we roll the
service out and listen to
feedback.
Before we move on, I want to
make one important point.
This is not an app review.
The notary service is simply
performing a set of security
checks to ensure that your
content can be distributed
safely.
So what does this actually look
like for your development
workflow?
Well here's a high level and
simplified overview of the
development process.
Over on the left, a developer
iterates on an application local
to their system building
features, debugging, and signing
with their Mac Developer
certificate.
When the application is ready
for release, it's signed with
the Developer ID certificate,
and a final test task can be
performed.
After that, the content can be
distributed directly to users --
who can run it -- or Gatekeeper
can verify that it wasn't
tampered with; and the user gets
to run your application.
For this app to be notarized,
only one additional step is
required.
You continue to develop locally,
just like before.
And once you sign it with your
Develop ID certificate, a copy
can be uploaded to the Apple
notary service.
Assuming that the Developer ID
content doesn't contain anything
malicious, a ticket will be
issued back that can be attached
to the content through a process
we call stapling.
And then the stapled content can
be distributed just like before.
And when it ends up on a user's
system, Gatekeeper will verify
notarization and provide the new
first-launch experience.
Now because this is a highly
automated process, we are
targeting providing tickets back
within an hour.
But we'll be working to improve
the speed and quality of the
service as we roll it out.
So let's talk a little more
about those security
requirements I mentioned
earlier.
Well, first and foremost, no
malicious software.
If the security check finds
anything malicious inside of the
Developer ID signed content, it
will immediately create a
special kind of ticket called a
revocation ticket and
immediately notify the
developer.
Second, all executables need to
be properly code signed.
And this is important to make
sure that when the application
ends up on a develop - on a
user's system, Gatekeeper can
verify that it wasn't tampered
with.
And finally, all binaries must
opt into the enhanced runtime
that Pierre described earlier so
they can benefit from the
additional protections of the
operating system without
reducing their capabilities.
So assuming that you have an app
that's ready for notarization,
how do you actually go about
uploading it?
Well, it's built into the
Archive and Distribution
workflow inside of Xcode.
So if you already use that, you
are pretty much set.
Here you can see the Archive
pane of the Organizer.
And I have the Watch Grass Grow
app already archived.
So I click the Distribute App
button on the right.
I'll be taken to my distribution
options.
I'll continue to distribute it
via Developer ID just like I
have in the past.
And when I select that, I'll
have a new option -- to upload
to the notary service.
Clicking Next will show a
progress bar while the Developer
ID content is uploaded to the
notary service.
And as soon as the upload is
complete, you'll be notified
that notarization has started.
From here you can export a copy
of your app to perform any local
testing that you might want to
do in parallel.
And if you click Close, you'll
be taken back to the Archive
pane; and you can see that the
status has switched to
Processing.
When notarization is complete, a
push notification will arrive
and Xcode will notify you that
notarization is done.
Xcode will then automatically
download the ticket, staple it
to your content.
So the next time you go into the
Archive pane and click Export,
you'll already have a stapled
Developer ID notarized
application.
And when the user launches it
for the first time, they'll see
a new version of the
first-launch dialog that
includes your app's icon.
Now we understand that not
everybody uses Xcode's
distribution workflow, although
this Xcode works - dah.
The Xcode workflow is available
today in the preview.
We have also built a set of
command line tools to perform
every step of this so that you
can integrate them with any
custom flows [phonetic] you
have.
And the first step is to upload
a copy for notarization.
Now the notary service accepts
Zip files, installer packages,
and disk images.
So if you have a bare
application, you'll need to zip
it up prior to uploading to the
notary service.
The tool for working with the
notary service is altool.
Here you can see a command line
indication sending the Watch
Grass Grow image up for
notarization.
Note that altool does require
authentication, but you can pass
in your credentials via
Environment Variables or the key
chain.
Once upload is complete, you'll
get a UUID that can be used to
monitor status of processing.
But you can also turn back and
pass the altool to check on the
status of your notarization.
Here we see another command line
indication of altool to just
check the status of
notarization.
And then you can see here that
notarization was complete, was
successful.
And importantly, there is a log
file that comes back from the
notarization service.
This is a great place to check
for any warnings, or it tells
you exactly what was included in
your notarization ticket.
So you can make sure that
everything in your package was
notarized properly.
And the last step before you
distribute content is to staple
your notarization ticket to
whatever content you are going
to distribute.
Now we have a special tool for
that called Stapler.
Now you can staple tickets
directly to applications, disk
images, and installer packages.
And Stapler combines both
retrieving the ticket and
attaching it to the content in
one easy step.
Here you can see I am stapling
the ticket directly to this
image.
After that's done, I can
distribute the disk image, and
the users will already get a
notarized application.
So as a quick reminder, in macOS
Mojave, for non-notarized apps
we'll continue to keep the
first-launch dialog that
Gatekeeper has always had for
Developer ID applications.
For notarized applications,
they'll get a new version of
this dialog that prominently
displays the app's icon.
And if the user does manage to
download software that has
malicious content in it, the
content won't run, and they'll
be treated to this warning.
Now this is not a new
capability; macOS has always had
the capability to block
applications like this.
But notarization does allow us
to identify specific malicious
content earlier and provides a
much better experience than if a
developer needs to revoke their
entire Developer ID certificate.
So that's how to build notarized
apps and how they are going to
help keep Mac users safer.
What can you do?
Well, the notary service is
available today.
So feel free to start uploading
your applications.
And there is no reason to wait
for your next app update.
The service will gladly check
your back catalog, too.
So send in anything you have
got.
We are looking for feedback
while we roll the service out.
So if you have any issues with
notarization, please come to the
labs and we'd love to work
through them with you.
Remember that signing issues,
for now, will be warnings but
are going to become errors in
the future.
And when macOS Mojave ships
later this year, Gatekeeper will
be highlighting notarized
applications to users.
But then in a future macOS
release, Gatekeeper will be
requiring notarized apps by
default.
And that's all for Gatekeeper.
So now I'd like to hand it back
to Pierre for some closing
words.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you Garrett.
All right, let's look at the key
takeaways from this session.
First, the macOS Mojave, the
user is now in control over the
way apps can access their
personal data.
It means your app needs to be
ready to handle their decisions
-- first, because the user make
take a while before they
actually give you an answer.
Second, because they might
completely decline the request.
Additionally, please be
transparent to the user about
what did I need to access and
why you need to access it, using
new entitlements and purpose
strings for this effect.
Also, make sure you request
access to this data in context
-- in the context where the user
can actually understand why you
need it and is more likely to
grant you this request.
We have a new higher runtime,
which you can adopt in your app
today.
It effectively increases the
security and the transparency of
your app.
It does not take away any of the
capabilities that you have
today.
It just requires you to opt into
them.
And finally, please help us make
our users feel more secure and
stop malware as soon as possible
by getting your apps notarized.
The Developer ID notary service
is open for submission right
now.
If you need more information
about this session, please check
out our developer website.
We have a lab immediately after
this section from 3:00 to 6:00
and then another lab tomorrow
from 9:00 to 12:00.
And finally, there will be
another lab on Thursday
dedicated to signing and
distribution.
Again, thank you very much for
coming.
Hope you have a great rest of
the week.
[ Applause ]