[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Hello and good afternoon
everyone.
Welcome to our session on
natural language processing.
I'm delighted to see so many of
you here today, and I'm really
excited to tell you about some
of the new and cool features
we've been working in the NLP
space for you.
I'm Vivek, and I'll be jointly
presenting this session with my
colleague, Doug Davidson.
Let's get started.
Last year, we placed your app
center stage and told you how
you could harness the power of
NLP to make your apps smarter
and more intelligent.
We did this by walking you
through the NLP APIs available
in NSLinguisticTagger.
NSLinguisticTagger, as most of
you are familiar with or have
used at some point, is a class
and foundation that provides the
fundamental building blocks for
NLP.
Everything from language
identification to organization,
part of speech tagging, and so
on.
We achieve this in
NSLinguisticTagger by seamlessly
blending linguistics and machine
learning behind the scenes.
So you, as a developer, can just
focus on using these APIs and
focus on your task.
All that's great.
So what's new in NLP for this
year?
Well, we are delighted to
announce that we have a
brand-new framework for NLP
called Natural Language.
Natural Language is now going to
be a one-stop shop for doing all
things NLP on device across all
Apple platforms.
Natural Language has some really
cool features, and let me talk
about each of those.
First, it has a completely
redesigned API surface, so it
supports all the functionalities
that NSLinguisticTagger used to
and still does but with really,
really Swift APIs.
But that's not it.
We now have support for custom
NLP models.
These are models that you can
create using Create ML and
deploy the model either using
Code ML API or through Natural
Language.
Everything that we support in
Natural Language, all of the
machine learning NLP is high
performed.
It is optimized for Apple
hardware and also for model
size.
And finally, everything is
completely private.
All of the machine learning in
NLP that is powered in Natural
Language is done on device to
protect user's privacy.
This is the very same technology
that we use at Apple to bring
NLP on device for our own
features.
So let me talk about each of
these features of Natural
Language.
Let's start with the Swift APIs.
As I mentioned, Natural Language
supports all the fundamental
building blocks that
NSLinguisticTagger does but with
significantly better and easier
to use APIs.
In order to provide some of
these APIs and go over them, I'm
going to illustrate them with
hypothetical apps.
So the first app that we have
here is an app that you wrote,
and as part of the app, you
enable a social messaging or
peer-to-peer messaging feature.
And an add-on feature in this
app that you've created is the
ability to show the right
stickers.
So based on the content of the
message, which in this case is
"It's getting late, I'm tired,
we'll pick it up tomorrow
morning, good night."
Your app shows the appropriate
sticker.
You parsed this text, and you
bring up the sticker.
The user can attach it and send
it as a response.
So all of this is great.
This app has been doing really
well.
You've been getting rave
reviews.
But you also get feedback that
your app is not multilingual.
So it so happens that users are
bilingual these days.
They tend to communicate in
several different languages, and
your app, when it gets the
message in Chinese, simply
doesn't know what to do with it.
So how can we use natural
language to overcome this
problem?
Well, we can do this with two
simple calls to two different
APIs.
The first is language
identification.
With the new Natural Language
framework, you start off by
importing Natural Language.
You create an instance of
NLLanguageRecognizer class.
You attach the string that you
would like to process, and you
simply call the dominant
language API.
Now this will return the single
best hypothesis in terms of
language for the string.
So the output here is
essentially simplified Chinese.
Now in Natural Language, we also
support a new API.
There are instances where you
would like to know the top-end
hypothesis for a particular
string.
So you'd like to know what are
the top languages along with
their associated probabilities.
So you can envision using this
in several different
applications where there's a lot
of multilinguality, and you want
that leeway in terms of what
could be the top hypothesis.
So you can do this with a new
API called Language Hypotheses.
You can specify the maximum
number of languages that you
want, and what you get back is
an object with the top-end
languages and their associated
probabilities.
Now in order to tokenize this
Chinese text, you can again see
the pattern is very similar.
You again import Natural
Language.
You create an instance of the
NLTokenizer, and in this
particular instance, you specify
the unit to be word because you
want to tokenize the string into
words.
You attach the string, and you
simply call the tokens method on
the string, on the object.
And what you get is an array of
tokens here.
Now with this array of tokens,
you can look up the particular
token here is goodnight, and lo
and behold, you have
multilingual support in your
app.
So your app can now support
Chinese with simple calls to
language identification and
tokenization APIs.
Now let's look at a different
sort of an API.
I mean language identification
and tokenization are good, but
we would also like to use auto
speech tagging, named entity
recognition, and so on.
So let me illustrate how to use
named entity recognition API
again with the hypothetical app.
So here's an app.
It's a news recommendation app.
So as part of this app, your
user has been going and reading
a lot of things about the royal
wedding, so a really curious
user.
They want to find everything
about the royal wedding.
So they've perused a lot of
pages in your app, and then they
go on to the search bar, and
they type Harry.
And what they see is completely
things that are not pertinent to
what they've been looking for.
You get Harry Potter and so on
and so forth.
What you'd like to see is Prince
Harry, something related to the
royal wedding.
So now you can overcome this
issue in your app by using the
name entity recognition API.
Again, as I mentioned, the
syntax here is very familiar.
Those of you who have been used
to using NSLinguisticTagger,
they should look familiar and
feel familiar, but it's much
easier to remember and to use.
You import Natural Language.
You now create an instance of
NLTagger, and you specify the
scheme type to be name type.
If you want part of speech
tagging, then you would specify
the scheme type to be lexical
class.
You again specify the string
that you want to process.
In this particular instance, you
specify the language, so you set
the language to be English.
So if you were not familiar or
if you're not sure about what
the language is, Natural
Language will automatically
recognize the language using the
language identification API
under the hood.
And finally, you call the tags
method on this object that you
just created.
You specify the unit to be word
and the scheme to be name type.
And what you get as an output is
the person names here, Prince
Harry and Meghan Markle, and the
location to be Windsor.
Now if the user were to go back
to the search bar, based on the
contextual information of what
the user has been browsing, you
can significantly enhance the
search experience in your app.
So there's a lot more
information about how to use
these APIs.
You can go to the developer
documentation and find more
information.
What I'd like to emphasize here
is NSLinguisticTagger is still
supported, but the future of NLP
is in Natural Language.
So we recommend that and
encourage you to move to Natural
Language so that you can get all
the latest functionalities of
NLP in this framework.
Now let's shift gears and look
at a situation where you have an
idea for an app, or you need a
functionality within your app
that Natural Language does not
support.
What do you do?
So you can certainly create
something, which will be great,
but what if we gave you the
tools to make that much easier?
To talk about custom NLP models
and how to build custom NLP
models using Create ML and use
the subsequent models, which are
essentially Code ML models in
Natural Language, I'm going to
hand it over to Doug Davidson.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks Vivek.
So I'm really excited about the
new Natural Language framework,
but the part I'm most excited
about is support for portraying
and using custom models.
And why is that?
I'd just like you to think for a
second about your apps, maybe
the apps you've written or the
apps that you want to write, and
think about how they could
improve the user experience if
they just knew a little more
about the text that they deal
with.
And then think for a second
about how you analyze text.
So maybe you look at some
examples of text, and you learn
from them, and then you
understand what's going on, and
then you can look at a piece of
text, and at a glance, you can
figure out something about
what's going on with it.
Well, if that's the case, then
there's at least a reasonable
chance that you can train a
machine learning model to do
that sort of analysis in your
app automatically for you,
giving it examples that it can
train and learn from and produce
a model that can do that
analysis.
Now, there are many, many types
of machine learning models for
NLP, and there are many
different ways of training it.
Probably many of you are already
training machine learning
models, but our task here has
been to produce ways to make
this sort of training really,
really easy and to make it
integrate really well with the
Natural Language framework and
APIs.
So with that in mind, we are
supporting two types of models
that we think support a broad
range of functionality and that
work well with our paradigm in
NLTagger of applying labels to
pieces of text.
So the first of model we're
supporting is a text classifier.
A text classifier takes a chunk
of text, maybe it's a sentence
or a paragraph or an entire
document, and applies a label to
it.
Examples of this in our existing
APIs are things like language
identification, script
identification.
The second type of model we
support is a word tagger, and a
word tagger takes a sentence
considered as a sequence of
words, and then applies a label
to each word in a sentence in
context, and examples of
existing APIs are things like
speech tagging and named entity
recognition.
But those are sort of general
purpose examples of these kinds
of models.
You can do a lot more with them
if you have a special purpose
model for your specific
application.
Let me give you some
hypothetical examples.
So, for text classification,
suppose you're dealing with user
reviews, and you want to know
automatically whether a given
review is a positive review or a
negative review or somewhere in
between.
Well, this is the sort of thing
you could train a text
classifier to do.
This is sentiment
classification.
Or suppose you have articles or
just article summaries or maybe
even just article headlines, and
you want to determine
automatically what topic they
belong to according to your
favorite topic classification
scheme.
This again is the sort of thing
that you can train a text
classifier to do for you.
Or going a little further,
suppose you're writing an
automated travel agent, and when
you get a request from a client,
the first thing you want to know
probably is what are they asking
about?
Is it hotels or restaurants or
flights or whatever else that
you handle.
This is the sort of thing that
you could train a text
classifier to answer for you.
Going on to word tagging.
So we provide word taggers that
do part of speech tagging for a
number of different languages,
but suppose you happen to need
to do part of speech tagging for
some language that we don't
happen to support quite yet.
Well, with custom model support,
you could train a word tagger to
do that for you.
Or named entity recognition.
So we provide built-in named
entity recognition that
recognizes names of people and
places and organizations, but
suppose you had some other kind
of name that you were
particularly interested in that
we don't happen to support right
now.
So, like for example, product
names.
So you could train your own
custom named entity recognizer
as a word tagger that would
recognize names or other terms
of whatever sort you are
particularly interested in.
Even further, for your automated
travel agent, once you know what
the user is asking about,
probably the next thing you want
to know is what are the relevant
terms in their request.
For example, if it's a flight
request.
Where do they want to go from
and to?
So a word tagger can identify
various kinds of terms in a
sentence.
Or another application, if you
need to take a sentence and
divide it up into phrases, noun
phrases, verb phrases,
propositional phrases.
With the appropriate sort of
labeling, you could train a word
tagger to do this, and many,
many other kinds of tasks can be
phrased in terms of labeling,
applying labels to portions of
text, either words in sequence
or chunks of text in the text
classifier.
So these are supervised machine
learning models, so there are
two phases always involved.
The first phase is training, and
the second phase is inference.
So training is what you do in
part of your development
process.
You take labeled training data,
and you feed it into Create ML
and produce a model.
Inference is then what happens
in your app when you incorporate
that model into your application
at run time when it encounters
some piece of data from the
user, and then it analyzes that
data and predicts the
appropriate labels for it.
So let's see how these phases
work.
So let's start with training,
and training always starts with
data.
You take your training data, and
then you feed it in to in this
case Create ML in a playground
let us say or a script
[inaudible] as you may have seen
in the Create ML session.
Create ML calls the Natural
Language framework under the
hood to do the training, and
what comes out is a core ML
model that's optimized for use
on device.
So let's look at what this data
might look like.
So Create ML supports a number
of different data formats.
Right here we're showing our
data in JSON because JSON makes
things perfectly clear, and this
is a piece of training data for
a text classifier that's a
sediment classifier.
So each training example, like
this one, consists of two parts,
a chunk of text, and the
appropriate label for it.
And so this for example is a
positive sentence, so the label
is positive, but you can pick
whatever label set you want.
Now, then when you start using
Create ML, the Create ML
provides a very, very simple way
to train models in just a few
lines of code.
First line, we just load our
training data from our JSON
file.
So we give it a URL to the JSON
file, create a Create ML data
table from it.
Then in one line of code, create
and train a text classifier from
this data.
All you have to tell it is what
the names of the fields are,
text and label, and then once
you have it, one line of code
writes that model out to disk.
Now for training a Word Tagger,
it's very similar.
The data is just a little more
complicated because each example
is not a single piece of text.
It's a sequence of tokens, and
the labels are, again, a
sequence of labels, the same
number of labels, one label for
each token.
So this, for example, is
training data for a Word Tagger
that does name identity
recognition, and each word, each
token, has a label, either none,
it's not a name, or org, it's an
organization name or prod, it's
product name, or a number of
different other labels for
whatever kinds of names you're
recognizing.
So each token has a label, and
each sample consists of one
sequence of tokens and their
corresponding labels.
And then the Create ML to train
this is almost identical.
You load the training data into
a data table from the JSON.
Then you create and train a Word
Tagger, in this case instead of
a text classifier, and then you
write it out to disk.
Now, there are a number of other
options and APIs available in
Create ML.
I encourage you to, if you
haven't already, take a look at
the Create ML session, which
happened yesterday, and Create
ML documentation for more
information on that.
Now, once you have your model,
we then go to the inference
part.
So you take your model, you drag
it into your Xcode project.
Xcode compiles it and includes
it in your applications
resources, and then what do you
do at run time?
Well, it's a Core ML model.
You could use it like any other
Core ML model, but the
interesting thing is that these
models are able to work well
with the Natural Language APIs
just like our built-in models
that provide the existing
functionality for NLP.
So what will happen is data
comes in.
You pass it to Natural Language,
which will use that model and do
everything necessary to get all
of the labels out and then pass
back either a label, single
label for a classifier or a
sequence of labels for a tagger.
And so how do you do this in
Natural Language API?
First thing you have to do is
just locate that model in your
application's resources, and
then you create an instance of a
class in Natural Language called
ML Model from it.
And then, well, the simplest
thing you can do with it, at
least for a classifier, is just
pass it in a chunk of text and
get a label out.
But the more interesting thing
is that you can use these models
with NLTagger in exactly the
same way that you use our
built-in models for an existing
functionality.
So let me show you how that
works.
In addition to the existing tag
schemes that we have for things
like named identity recognition
part of speech tagging, you can
create your own custom tag
scheme, give it a name, and then
you can create a tagger that
includes any number of different
tag schemes.
Your custom tag scheme or any of
our built-in tag schemes or all
of them, and then all you have
to do is to tell the tagger to
use your custom model for your
custom tag scheme.
And then you just use it
normally.
You attach a string to the
tagger, and you can go through
and look at the tags for
whatever unit of text is
appropriate for your particular
model, and the tagger will
automatically call the model as
necessary to get the tags and
return the tags to you and will
do all the other things that
NLTagger does automatically,
like language identification,
tokenization and so on and so
forth.
So I want to show this to you in
a simple hypothetical example.
And this hypothetical example is
an app that users will use to
store bookmarks to articles they
may have run across and then
might be intending to read later
on.
But the problem with this
application as it currently
stands is that the list of
bookmarks is just one long list
with no organization to it.
Wouldn't it be nice if we could
automatically classify these
articles and put them into some
organization according to topic?
Well, we can train a classifier
to do that for us.
And the other thing is that the
articles, when we look at them,
it's a long stream of text.
Maybe we'd like to highlight
some interesting things in those
articles like for example names.
Well, we have provided built-in
name identity recognition for
names of people, places, and
organizations, but maybe we also
want to highlight names of
products, so we could train a
custom word tagger to identify
those names for us.
So let me go over to the demo
machine.
And so here's our application as
it stands before we apply any
natural language processing.
As you can see, even just one
long list of articles on the
side and a big chunk of text for
our article on the right.
Well let's fix that.
So, let's go into -- so the
first part of training a model
is data, and fortunately, I have
some very hard-working
colleagues at Apple who have
collected for me some training
data to train two models.
The first model is a text
classifier that will classify
articles according to topic.
So this is some of what the
training data looks like.
Each training example is a chunk
of text and the appropriate
label by topic, entertainment,
politics, sports, and so on and
so forth.
And I also have some training
data to train a word tagger that
will recognize product names in
sentences.
So this training data is pretty
simple.
Each example consists of a
sentence considered as a
sequence of tokens and then a
sequence of labels, and each
label is either none, it's not a
product name, or prod, it is a
product name.
So, let's try to train with
these.
So first thing I want to do is
bring up a playground that I
have using Create ML, and this
playground will just load.
In this case, this is my product
word tagger.
It'll load the training data,
create a word tagger from it,
and write it out to disk.
So let me just fire that off,
and let it start running.
It's loaded the data, and so
under the hood, we automatically
handle all of the tokenization,
the feature extraction.
We do the training.
This is a fairly small model, so
it doesn't take all that long to
train, and I have it set to
automatically write my model out
to my desktop, and there it is.
All right.
So that's one model.
Now I have another playground
here that's set up to train my
text classifier.
As you can see, it looks very
similar.
Load the training data, create a
text classifier from it, and
write it out to disk.
So I start that off.
And again, automatically natural
language is loading all the
data, tokenizing it, extracting
features from it.
This one is a bit larger model.
It takes a couple minutes to
train.
So let's just let that go, and
in the meantime, take a look at
some of the code we have to use
these at run time.
So I've written two very small
classes to do what I need to do
at run time.
The first one uses the text
classifier by finding that model
in my apps resources and
creating an NL model for it.
And then when I run across an
article, I just ask the model
for a predicted label for that
article, and that's really all
there is to it.
Slightly more code for use of my
word tagger.
So as you saw before, I have a
custom tag scheme for my product
name recognition, and the only
tag I'm really interested in is
the product tag.
So I create a custom tag for
that.
Again, I have to find the model
in my bundles resources, create
an NL model for it, and then
create an NLTagger, and this
NLTagger I'm specifying two
schemes.
The first is the built-in name
type scheme to do name identity
recognition, and the second one
is my custom product tag scheme,
and they'll both function in
exactly the same way.
And then I just have to tell
that tagger to use my custom
model for my custom scheme.
Now if I supported multiple
languages, I might have more
than one model in here for this
scheme.
And then what I'm going to do is
highlight text in this article
that is located, determined to
be a name of one sort or
another.
So I'm going to get a mutable
attributed string, and I'm going
to add some attributes to it.
So I'll take this string of that
mutable attributed string,
attach that to my tagger, and
then I'm going to do a couple of
enumerations over tags.
The first one uses the built-in
name-type scheme for name
identity recognition of people,
places, and organizations, and
if I find something that's
tagged as a person or place or
organization, then I'm going to
add an attribute to the
attributed string that will give
it some color.
And then we can do exactly the
same thing with our custom
model.
We're going to enumerate using
our custom product tag scheme,
and in that case, if we find
something that's labeled with
our custom product tag, then I
can add color to it in exactly
the same way.
So you can use custom models
with Natural Language API just
in the same way that you use
built-in models.
Now, let's go back to our
playground, and we see that the
model training has finished, and
in fact there are now two models
showing up on my desktop.
So all I need to do is drag
those into my application.
Let's take this one and drag it
right in.
Okay. And let's take this one
and drag it in, and Xcode will
automatically compile these and
include them in my application.
So all I have to do is build and
run it.
And let's hide that.
Here's my new application, and
you'll notice that my list of
articles is all neatly sorted
automatically by topic, and if I
go in and take a look at one of
these articles, you'll notice
that names are highlighted in
it, and you can see, using our
built-in name identity
recognition, we highlight names
of people, places, and
organizations, but if you look a
little further, you can see that
it has used our custom product
tagger to highlight the names of
products like iPad, MacBook,
iPad mini, and so forth.
So this shows how easy it is to
train your own custom models and
to use them with the natural
language APIs.
[ Applause ]
So now I'm going to turn things
back over to Vivek to talk about
some important considerations
for training models.
[ Applause ]
Thank you, Doug, for telling us
how to use these custom NLP
models.
We are really excited to sort of
have a very tight integration of
natural language with Create ML
and the Core ML [inaudible], and
we hope that you do some really
unbelievable things with this
new API.
So I'd like to shift attention
now again and talk about
performance.
So as I mentioned before,
Natural Language is available
across all Apple platforms, and
it also offers you what we call
as standardized text processing.
So let's take a moment again to
understand what we mean by this.
Now if you were to look at a
conventional machine learning
pipeline that didn't use Create
ML, where would you start?
You would start with some amount
of training data.
You would take this training
data.
You would tokenize this data.
You'd probably extract some
features.
This is really important for
languages like Chinese and
Japanese where tokenization is
very important.
You would throw that into your
favorite machine learning
toolkit, and you'd get a machine
learning model out of it.
Now in order to use that machine
learning model on an Apple
device, you'd have to convert
that into a Core ML model.
So what would you do?
You would use a Core ML
converter to do this.
This is sort of the training
procedure in order to get from
data to a model and deploy it on
an Apple device.
Now, at inference time, what you
do is you drop the model in your
app, but that's not it.
You also have to make sure that
you write the code for
tokenization and feature
extraction that is consistent
with what happened at training
time.
It's a lot of effort because you
have to think about maximizing
the fidelity of your model.
It's absolutely important that
the tokenization featured
extraction is identical at both
training and inference time.
But now with the use of Natural
Language, you can completely
obviate this.
So if you look at the sequence
at training time, you have
training data.
You just pass it to Create ML
through the APIs that we've
discussed so far.
Create ML calls Natural Language
under the hood, which does the
tokenization feature extraction,
chooses the machine learning
library, does all the work, and
returns a model which is a Core
ML model.
Now at inference time, what you
do is you still drop this model
in your app, but you don't have
to worry about tokenization
feature extraction or anything
else.
In fact, you don't have to write
a single line of code because
Natural Language does all of
that for you.
You just focus on your app and
your task and simply drag and
drop the model in.
The other aspect of Natural
Language as I mentioned before
is it's optimized for Apple
hardware and for model sizes.
So let's look at this through a
couple of examples.
So Doug talked about named
entity recognition and chunking,
and here are two different
benchmarks.
So these are models that we
built using an open source tool
kit called CRF Suite, and
through Natural Language.
The models were built from
identical training data and
tested on identical test data.
The same sort of features were
used.
The accuracy obtained by both
these models is the same.
But you look at the model sizes
that Natural Language is able to
generate.
It's simply just about 1.4
megabytes of data size, model
size for named entity
recognition and 1.8 megabytes
for chunking.
That saves you an enormous
amount of space within your app
to do other things.
In terms of machine learning
algorithms, we support two
different options.
We can specify this for text
classification.
So for text classification, we
have two different choices.
One is maxEnt, which is an
abbreviation for Maximum
Entropy.
In NLP, we call maxEnt is
essentially a multinomial
logistic regression model.
We just call it Maximum Entropy
in NLP feed.
The other one is CRF, which is
an abbreviation for Conditional
Random Feed.
The choice of these two
algorithms really depends upon
your task.
So we encourage you to try both
these options, build the models.
Now in terms of word tagging,
that is one default option,
which is a conditional random
feed.
When you instantiate an ML word
tagger, specify data to it, the
default model that you get is a
conditional random feed.
Now as I mentioned, the choice
of these algorithms really
depends on your task, but what
I'd like to emphasize is sort of
draw [inaudible] between your
conventional development
process.
So when you have an idea for an
app, you go through a
development cycle, right.
So you can think of machine
learning to be a very similar
sort of a work flow.
Where do you start, you start
with data, and then you have
data, you have to ask a couple
of questions.
You have to validate your
training data.
You have to make sure that there
are no spurious examples in your
data, and it's not tainted.
Once you do that, you can
inspect the number of training
instances per class.
Let's say that your training a
sentiment classification model,
and you have a thousand examples
for positive sentiment, you have
five examples for negative
sentiment.
You can't train a robust model
that can determine or
distinguish between those two
classes.
You have to make sure that the
training samples for each of
those classes are reasonably
balanced.
So once you do that with data,
the next step is training.
As I mentioned before, our
recommendation is that you run
the different options that are
available and figure out what is
good, but how do you define what
is good?
You have to evaluate the model
in order to figure out what
suits your application.
So the next step here in the
work flow is evaluation.
Evaluation in convention
[inaudible] for machine learning
is that when you procure your
training data, you split your
data into training set, into a
validation set, and into a test
set, and you typically tune the
parameters of the algorithm
using the validation set, and
you test it on the test set.
So we encourage you to do the
same thing, apply the same sort
of guidelines that have stood
machine learning in good stead
for a long time.
The other thing that we also
encourage you to do is test on
out-of-domain data.
What do I mean by this?
So when you have an idea for an
app, you think of a certain type
of data that is going to be
ingested by your machine
learning model.
Now let's say you're building an
app for hotel reviews, and you
want to classify hotel reviews
into different sorts of ratings.
And the user throws a data that
is completely out of domain.
Perhaps it's something to do
with a restaurant review or a
movie review, is your model
robust enough to handle it.
That's a question that you ought
to ask yourself.
And the final step is well in a
conventional development
workflow you write patches, you
fix bugs, and you update your
app.
How do you do that with machine
learning?
Well, the way to do that or fix
issues with machine learning is
to find out where your models do
not perform well, and you have
to supplement it with the right
sort of data.
By adding data and retraining
your model, you can essentially
get a new model out.
So it's, as I mentioned, it's
very similar to sort of the
development workflow, and they
are very [inaudible].
So you can think of it as part
of your fabric if you're
employing machine learning
models as part of your app, you
can just combine it with the
word process itself.
The last thing I'd like to
emphasize here is privacy.
So everything that you saw in
this session, all of the machine
learning and Natural Language
processing happens completely on
device.
So we at Apple take privacy
really seriously, and this is a
remarkable opportunity to use
machine learning completely on
device to protect user's
privacy.
So in that vein, Natural
Language is another step towards
privacy preserving machine
learning but in this case apply
to NLP.
So in summary, we talked about a
new framework called Natural
Language framework.
It's tightly integrated with the
Apple machine learning
[inaudible].
You can now train models using
Create ML and then use those
models either with the Core ML
APIs or with Natural Language.
The models that we generate
using Natural Language and the
APIs are highly performed and
optimized on Apple hardware
across all the platforms.
And finally, it supports privacy
because all of the machine
learning in NLP happens on
user's device.
So there's more information
here.
We have a Natural Language lab
tomorrow, so we encourage you to
try out these APIs and come talk
to us and ask us questions about
where you'd like enhancements or
perhaps some sort of
consultation with respect to
your app.
We also have a machine learning
get together, and there's a
subsequent [inaudible] Create ML
lab that's happening right now.
So you can continue coming and
talking to us as part of that
lab.
Thank you for your attention.
Thanks.
[ Applause ]