[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Welcome, and hello.
I'm Ben Chester, a software
engineer on the Wallet and Apple
Pay team.
And, I'm here today to talk to
you about how to create great
customer experiences using
Wallet and Apple Pay.
And to do that, we're going to
cover four topics, and see a
fantastic demo from my
colleague.
Firstly, we're going to cover
some of the key things that have
happened in the last year.
Secondly, how to create great
experiences with Apple Pay,
using some of the new
enhancements we're announcing
today.
Thirdly, how to get the most
from passes.
There's some updates to designs,
and some new changes you can
adopt for richer content.
Finally, we will talk about
digital to physical commerce.
And, to do that I'm going to
show you an example that we use
every day at Apple Park, the
Caffe Mac's app, and some
others.
So, let me first start by
telling you about Apple Pay
Cash.
Apple Pay Cash makes it easy to
get paid, and pay friends and
family using iMessage.
Now, you can pay in-store, with
apps, and on the web.
And, it's available in the U.S.
Most importantly for you, ensure
you accept Discover debit in
your apps, and with your payment
processor, so you can take Apple
Pay Cash.
Another feature that we
announced last year, that is
even a greater option, is inline
setup.
Now, inline setup lets your
users with no cards set up one,
and then return to the purchase
in one step.
All you have to do is always
show the Apple Pay button if the
device supports it.
If the user has no cards, you
can use the Set Up with Apple
Pay button, shown here, to make
it even clearer to the user.
Now, when the user taps that
button, the setup flow is
presented inside of your app,
which reduces the risk of users
leaving your experience.
And, this is commonly known as
abandonment.
And, to support this, no
additional work is required from
you.
Once the card is set up, it
returns the user to the purchase
immediately.
We even automatically activate
the card via SMS.
Now, even with all of this, it's
still faster than manual entry.
And, you should adopt this in
your apps, if you haven't
already, for a great user
experience.
That's not the only feature we
announced in the last year.
To help with faster checkout, we
also introduced error handling,
and that's been great for
developers.
Error handling gives you control
over nonfatal errors in the
Apple Pay Sheet.
And, this allows you to provide
your own custom error messages
to the user for billing and
shipping issues.
And, that's so they can more
easily resolve those issues, and
get back to purchasing.
And, that's great for higher
conversion.
Now, some tips for error
handling.
One thing we want to make clear,
is that it's still important to
expect fuzzy data.
The user has one set of data in
Apple Pay, and that's shared
across many apps and websites.
And, we don't want the user--
don't want to force the user to
conform to everybody's
individual business logic, as
that requires the user to
reenter information, which just
increases friction, and will
reduce your overall conversion
rate.
Instead, you should do your best
to accept a range of inputs.
For example, Zip and Zip + 4.
And, infer what details you can
from other fields such as city
and state from Zip.
Now, that's not all the features
that we announced.
We also launched in some new
countries.
And, you may remember this slide
from last year.
Well, this year, we're
introducing the following
countries, and we're also coming
to Norway and Poland soon.
Now, that's a great range.
But, one country I want to talk
about in particular, is China.
This year, we've taken Express
Transit to China, launching with
Beijing Transit, and Shanghai
Transit.
Now, this works fantastically.
You can buy a card directly from
Wallet, and get going
straightaway.
But, Transit is not limited to
China alone.
You can use Apple Pay to ride
throughout the world, anywhere
credit and debit cards are
accepted, such as Moscow and
London.
Well, that's it from updates
from the last year.
Let's talk about creating great
Apple Pay experiences.
What is a great experience with
Apple Pay?
Well, it's one that is easier,
by allowing the user to checkout
as early as possible, with what
we call upstreaming.
It's one that is faster, by
making Apple Pay the default
payment option, with what we
call defaulting.
And, clearer by making the Apple
Pay flow as simple as possible,
with what we call streamlining.
Now, I want to go through each
of these, starting with
streamlining.
Here we see a fantastic example
of streamlining.
The Apple Pay button is directly
placed on the product page.
And, this makes it so easy, as
Apple Pay is [inaudible] the
user's flow as possible.
Now, if your experience instead
is focused on multi-item
checkout, then placing the Apple
Pay directly on a product page
might not work so best for you.
Instead, you should focus on
Express Checkout.
In this example, the customer
has the option to checkout with
Apple Pay right from the basket,
and the user should be able to
reach this checkout from
anywhere in your flow.
And, you can combine both of
these experiences for the best
results, if that does make sense
for you.
Whenever you use this Apple Pay
button, it's critical to use the
one provided in the SDK.
Let me tell you why.
Well, it's localized in all
device languages.
And, it's available in a number
of styles and colors.
It scales across all the
supported devices, and any
changes that we make, you're
going to get for free in the
future.
It's also supported all the way
back to iOS 8.3, and WebKit 10.1
on iOS, and macOS 10.12.1.
However, we're heard that the
button does not always fit all
of your needs, and so today,
we're announcing three new types
in iOS 12.
And, I want to show you them
now.
The first one is Book with Apple
Pay.
Now, you should use this when
booking a hotel, or with a
ride-sharing service, for
example.
Simply pass the new Book type to
start using it.
Secondly, Subscribe with Apple
Pay.
Use this for subscription-based
purchases.
Pass the subscribe type.
And, thirdly, Check out with
Apple Pay.
This is best used if you have
multiple references to checkout
on the same page.
Now, this really makes it clear
to the user exactly which
checkout performs Apple Pay.
That's not all the changes to
the button.
You know that we love rounded
corners and continuous curves,
but we understand that not
everybody shares exactly the
same feelings, and so this year,
we're allowing you to control
the corner edits of the button.
You can configure this however
you see fit to match existing
styles of your apps or websites.
If you want square corners,
simply set the button radius to
0.
And, if you set no value, our
existing corner radius will be
used.
Now, similarly, on older
versions, the button will
fallback to using the current
rounded corner radius, ignoring
any value that you've set.
The new types and corner radius
are available in iOS 12 today.
And, they're coming to WebKit in
a future release.
Most importantly, fallback to
using older types on unsupported
versions.
Consider that cascade.
Using the new types will help
your customers purchase more
easily and clearer than ever
before.
Now, the placement and use of
the Apple Pay button is one way
to make checkout easier.
But, that benefit to customer
experience can be multiplied if
you combine this with guest
checkout.
Now, you should think about
guest checkout as your user's
first experience.
Now, blocking first-time
purchase increases friction,
which can lead to abandonment,
as we described earlier.
The user should want to create
an account with you, not have it
forced upon them.
Apple Pay offers you a great way
to do this.
You can use data from the Apple
Pay sheet post-purchase to make
account creation easy.
I want to show you an example of
that.
As soon as the purchase is
complete, and the confirmation
is displayed, account creation
is now offered.
User's email address from the
Apple Pay transaction has been
used, and all the user has to do
is enter a password to confirm
the creation of the account.
You can make this even easier,
using password AutoFill, and the
enhancements that we've added in
iOS 12.
So, that's everything for
upstreaming.
Now, let's cover making things
faster with defaulting.
Most important thing about
defaulting is that your users
will look for and expect Apple
Pay.
So, you should make purchasing
faster by setting Apple Pay as
the default option.
And, Apple Pay is a great
default option, because it has
the user's most up-to-date
customer information.
Even if the user has no card set
up in Apple Pay, as we showed
earlier, it still makes a great
option.
Let's see an example of
defaulting in action.
Here we see Apple Pay as the
default option right at the top,
and the Buy with Apple Pay
button is clearly visible, and
easily reachable by the user.
If you apply these guidelines,
you can make it faster than ever
for your users to checkout with
Apple Pay.
So, that's easier and faster
ways, but let's look at how to
make things clearer with
Streamlining.
Most important piece of
information about Streamlining
for you, is to prefer customer
information from Apple Pay.
Users have this data already set
up, and you can make their
experience clearer by using it.
When you request user's data,
it's important to only request
relevant fields.
Any additional fields that you
add will only make things more
difficult.
If data is needed that Apple Pay
does not support, you should
collect this before checkout
begins.
For example, the number of items
of a particular product, or a
voucher code.
Now, this year, we've helped to
streamline the Apple Pay
experience even further, by
making two changes.
The first one I want to talk
about is zero total support, and
I want to show you why that's
important.
Here we see the Apple Pay sheet
with a discount being applied,
and the total is above zero.
But, if that discount had
brought that all the way down to
zero, we've previously not been
able to present this sheet.
Well, now we do.
You can see the discount has
brought the total to zero.
Apple Pay sheet can still be
used to collect the necessary
shipping details, and other
information you need for the
purchase.
And, zero totals also work well
with subscriptions.
If the introductory month is
free, you can make this clear to
the user with a zero total.
Now, remember, it's important to
clearly state the price of the
subscription, as well as the
promotional discount they can
receive.
Zero total support is available
in iOS 12 today.
And, it's coming to WebKit in a
future release.
Make sure to fallback to
existing behavior on older
versions, where zero total is
not supported.
Now, the second way we have made
the experience more streamlined
in iOS 12, is with three new
supported networks.
And, this means you can filter
the cards in the Apple Pay sheet
more granularly.
And, there are three new
networks: Electron, Maestro, and
VPay.
It's important for the best
possible experience to accept as
many networks as you can.
These are available in iOS 12,
and coming to WebKit in the
future.
So, we've covered ways to make
things easier, faster, and
clearer with Apple Pay.
I hope you will try these all
out, and make your experiences
better than ever, using our new
enhancements.
One final topic I want to cover
is Apple Pay on the web, and the
WC3 Payment Request API.
Apple worked closely with a W3C
working group over the past few
years to help develop the
Payment Request API.
Now, that it's announced, you
may be wondering if you should
be using that, or our existing
Apple Pay JavaScript API.
Let's compare the benefits of
using one over the other.
The Payment Request API is a
cross browser solution, however,
it's important to know that
Apple Pay is only supported on
Safari.
If you choose the Payment
Request API, you do miss out on
some of the following features.
Error handling with custom error
messaging, as I showed you
earlier.
But also, automatic selection of
affiliated and cobranded cards.
And, therefore, your ability to
adjust prices of the user's
selection of these cards.
In markets and regions where
it's important, phonetic name
collection is also not
supported.
And, the Apple Pay JavaScript
API has a wider range of
support, going back to iOS 10,
and macOS 10.12.
Now, you should evaluate what
makes sense for you.
And, if you choose the Payment
Request API, consider using the
Apple Pay JavaScript API as a
fallback for older clients.
To make it even easier to get
started with the Apple Pay
JavaScript API, today we're
launching a demo page.
Let me show you that.
The demo page walks you through
all the steps required to get
set up.
And, it all starts with the
Apple Pay button.
You can configure sizes, and
styles, and locale, and see how
they change in real time.
The code required to drill the
button is dynamically updated
below.
And the page even allows you to
test out the Apple Pay purchase
flow.
Simply configure the JSON in the
request inside the page, and the
Apple Pay button there will be
used to present the payment
sheet.
The results of the authorization
and success or failure are
displayed to you directly.
Now, it's important to note,
your cards will not be charged
when you do this.
It's a great resource to get
started, and I hope you try it
out.
The demo page is available here
online today.
And, that's everything we have
for covering Apple Pay today.
So, now I want to move on to
talking about getting the most
from passes.
Passes are where it all began
for us, and they hold a very
special place in our hearts.
And, we have some fantastic
improvements I'm going to tell
you about.
But first, I just wanted to
recap what makes passes so
special.
They are so easy to use
contactlessly or with a bar
code.
And, they're synced across all
your devices using iCloud.
And, we're able to intelligently
show them on the lock screen and
in Search for quick access.
And, they continue that seamless
Apple Pay experience into the
physical world, which works
great for tickets, movie passes.
Those are great reasons why you
should use passes.
But, how do you get the most
from passes for your users?
Well, to do that we're going to
cover four topics.
And, we're going to start by
talking about adding passes to
Wallet.
And, we have some best practices
that you can follow.
Secondly, making passes look
great.
There's some new design options,
and some tips for making passes
work across all your devices.
Thirdly, rich pass content.
New ways to make your passes
more deeply integrate with the
system.
And, finally, contactless
passes, and how you can get
started.
So, let's begin with adding
passes to Wallet.
Many of you have seen or
experienced the full model UI
that was presented to add
passes.
But, there's a better way.
For almost all situations, we
recommend using our automatic
pass adding API.
To use this, simply call the
addPasses function in
PKPassLibrary, with the array of
passes you intend to add.
Now, this presents a simple
alert to the user, requesting
them to add or to review those
passes.
And, that's much less friction
compared to the full-screen
model UI.
And, the user still has the
option to review the passes in
full.
And, you should handle that in
the completion, and present that
viewController if requested.
In the demo you're going to see
later, you'll see how this
improves the experience.
So, let me tell you about some
other best practices to follow
for adding passes.
Now, we suggest adding passes
that were created outside of
your experience, when the user
enters the app for the first
time, if they're coming from an
unsupported platform.
They've not previously had the
opportunity to add those passes,
and that's a great time to offer
it to them.
And, you should add related
passes to Wallet in a group, to
reduce the friction.
And, you can make it easy for
people to quickly add passes
that they do not have from your
order history views, or previous
transactions, for example.
And, from those same views, if
your user has a pass in Wallet
already, you should link them
directly to it.
So that no matter where the user
starts their journey, in Wallet,
or your experience, they can get
to the pass.
If you follow all these tips,
and use automatic pass adding,
your users will love passes.
But, how do you make a pass that
looks great?
Most important information for
you is that the pass fields that
you display to the user should
have the relevant and critical
information on them.
And, there're things that the
user definitely needs.
And, you can make them stand out
by using vibrant colors.
And, you should design a pass
that looks great across all your
devices.
Now, to do that, you want to
avoid reproducing existing
passes, physical ones.
We have some great templates,
and layout options to make these
fields stand out and make sure
that your entire audience can
work with these passes as
they're accessible.
And, secondly don't encode user
information inside the strip
image that we can see here.
You should reserve that for the
fields.
That's particularly important on
Apple Watch.
Because there's no space to
display that.
And, the fields are front and
center.
Similarly, the thumbnail image
is also not displayed, and the
user cannot access the pass
details.
So, but we know sometimes
there's information that's
difficult to put all on the
front of pass.
And so, today we want to make
things a little bit easier for
you by adding additional row
support.
Let me show you that in action
first.
Here we see a new third row
enabled, showing the section and
the start number.
Now, that's a great way to layer
additional content, when your
existing information is already
a little bit long.
And, this is really easy to add
to your passes.
Let me show you how to do it
with a pass JSON.
Here we see the new row key be
using the auxiliaryFields, by
setting a 0 or a 1.
You can indicate that the field
should be split over the two
locations on the front of pass.
"Row" can only be used in the
auxiliary fields, and only for
event ticket-type passes.
We support values of 0 and 1,
and that's going to be coming to
you in a future seed.
On older versions, "row" will be
ignored.
And, in that case, auxiliary
fields will be displayed on one
row, up to a limit of 4 fields
per row.
So, make sure you consider this
when designing your passes.
And, test across supported
devices and versions.
So now, we've got passes in
Wallet, looking great.
How do we make that content even
richer?
Let's get the most from a pass.
You can include information that
the system can leverage to
provide the user enhanced
experiences.
And, one of those you may
already know about, is
relevancy.
You can add relevancy by setting
the locations, relevantText, and
relevantDate pass JSON fields.
And, this allows the system to
present the pass to the user
just at the right moment.
We handle multiple relevant
passes.
And, if you're issuing passes
for a single journey, multiple
ones, then you should make sure
to add relevancy information for
each pass.
And, allow the system to
correctly present them one at a
time to the user.
It's not a problem at all.
Now, it feels like magic when
their passes are so easy to
access.
And, to date we're looking at
making passes even richer, with
something we call semantic tags.
The fields that we showed
earlier in the pass JSON are a
great mechanism for display.
And, as the developer, you have
full control over the field
names, and the format of that
content.
However, that means it's
difficult for iOS to reason
about every field.
As everybody uses unique key and
label names.
Semantic tags changes that by
providing a structured way for
you to augment the display data
with a fixed format data.
Let me show you how easy it is
to add to an existing pass for
an upcoming film I'm going to
see.
Here we see a sample of primary,
secondary, and auxiliary fields
from the pass JSON.
This film's called "Revenge of
the Passes."
It's showing at Apple Park, and
it's running for two hours and
45 minutes in theater F5.
Now, that's all the information
I'm going to need when I get
there to see the film.
And, it's going to be readily
available to me.
So, let's take that event field
at the top, and add some
semantic tags to it.
To do that, we add a semantics
dictionary to the field.
And, inside that dictionary, you
can have relevant key names from
my documentation to provide
machine-readable content.
For example, with the movie, the
name used for display may differ
from the full official name used
internationally.
And the same might apply to your
venue name.
These should be the official
names that are different from
display.
You're also able to add
additional related data that is
not important for display, but
associated with that field.
For example, the phone number.
Now, sometimes, you have
semantic data that is not
associated with fields.
And, to capture that, we can use
a top-level semantics
dictionary.
Here, I've added a semantic tag
indicating that while this pass
is relevant, silence should be
requested.
I've also indicated the duration
of the event in seconds, and
specified the event type.
You may have seen this in the
Keynote, Siri will then be able
to offer the user the ability to
quickly enable do not disturb at
the right time.
It just works.
And, it's great for things like
movie tickets, or event passes.
Now, in summary, semantic tags
are a great way to add
machine-readable content to your
passes.
And, we have over 70 supported
transit and event tags.
All these keys will be available
in our online documentation
soon.
And, one important thing to
note, relevancy information
works in combination with
semantic tags.
And so, you should add both to
your passes for the best
experience.
Now, bringing all this together,
I want to talk to you about
contactless passes.
Contactless passes are a great
way for users to interact with
Wallet.
And, it's a much improved
experience over scanning a
barcode.
I want to show you one of our
favorite uses of contactless
passes.
Internationally renowned,
Wembley Stadium in London had
famous football players record
an advert just to show how easy
it is to use.
[ Music ]
It really couldn't be any
easier.
And, that contactless feels like
magic when you combine it with
relevancy for lock screen
access, swiping down for
notification.
Contactless passes do require an
NFC certificate to get started.
Now, you should contact us for
access if you have a great use
case.
One other important thing to
remember is that contactless
readers you select must support
Apple's value-added services
protocol.
However, that's easier than
ever.
You can find readers from any of
these companies that support
this protocol.
Now, one final use of
contactless passes you may have
seen in the Keynote, is student
ID cards.
Students will be able to use
these to access and pay anywhere
physical student ID cards are
used today, right from Wallet.
We worked closely with two
companies to bring student ID
cards to educational
institutions across the U.S. Now
for a demo of some of the
features that we've covered here
today.
I would like to welcome to the
stage, my colleague, Katie.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Ben.
Hi, my name is Katie, and I'm an
engineer on the Wallet and Apple
Pay team.
Today, I'm going to be showing
you a Swift application, where a
user can purchase an event
ticket for a party that I'm
throwing this weekend for my
team.
My colleagues will be able to
use the app in order to purchase
a ticket, and make me a little
money on the side.
This app will demonstrate two
things.
First, how to use the best
practices and new API's that Ben
had mentioned earlier in order
to create the most seamless
Wallet and Apple Pay experience.
And, second, how to structure
your pass's JSON in order to
enhance your customer's
experience.
So, let's go ahead and take a
look at this app.
So, here we're presented with a
summary about the event, a date,
a time, a location, and a cost.
Here's an example of
upstreaming, where we place the
Buy with Apple Pay button
directly on the product page.
So, let's go ahead and purchase
this ticket.
You can see, we're presented
with the Apple Pay sheet, and
this is a good example of
streamlining, asking the user
for the least amount of
information possible.
In this case, only their email
address.
So, let me go ahead and Face ID
in order to complete this
purchase.
Here, we're shown more
information about what we just
bought, about the event.
And, here at the bottom we have
a QR code, and all the way below
that, obstructed from view, is
an Add to Apple Wallet button.
You might have seen many apps in
the App Store today do something
like this, embedding a QR code
in their app.
If you have a QR code on the
front of your pass, there's no
need to embed it within your
app.
So, let's go ahead and add this
pass to Wallet.
You can see, we're presented
with the pass for the user to
review.
It has information about the
event, and a QR code.
So, let's add it.
Now, let's go over to the JSON,
and-- for this pass, and see
what changes we can make in
order to enhance the customer's
experience.
There are two major changes I
want to make here.
First, when people come to my
event, I want to check them in
using a contactless reader.
And, second, when the user gets
close to my event location, and
in this case, Discovery Meadow,
I want the pass to become
relevant on the lock screen.
So, let's first take a look at
this barcode dictionary here.
Since I'm going to be checking
people in using a contactless
reader, there's no need to have
a QR code on the front anymore.
So, let's remove this
dictionary.
And, instead, let's replace it
with an NFC dictionary.
Here, this dictionary contains
information that we've passed
from the device to the reader in
order to identify them when they
check in.
Next, let's add location data to
this pass, so it can become
relevant on the lock screen.
Here, we set a latitude, a
longitude, in this case it's
Discovery Meadow, and relevant
text that will be displayed in
the notification on the lock
screen.
Now, let's take a look at the
Swift application, in order to
see what changes we can make
there as well.
Let's first take a look at this
presentAddPass method.
This was called when we tapped
the Add to Wallet button.
Here, we got the pass from a
function we called, called
eventPass.
Let's go ahead and replace this
with our newly modified pass.
We then instantiated a
PKAddPassesViewController with
that pass, and presented it.
But, as Ben had mentioned
earlier, there's a better API we
can use in order to
automatically add passes to
Wallet.
So, let's go ahead and remove
these two lines of code, and
replace it with that API.
That API's on the PKPass
library, so let's create an
instance of that.
And, let's call the API.
The function's called addPasses.
Takes an array of passes, has a
completion handler with a
status.
And, there are three possible
statuses that can be returned.
DidAddPasses, which means the
user wants to add the pass to
Wallet.
DidCancelAddPasses, which means
the user does not want to add
the pass to Wallet.
And, shouldReviewPasses.
In this case, the user wishes to
be presented with a preview of
the pass before deciding to add
it to Wallet or not.
And, if this is the case, you
should do what we did previously
and instantiate a
PKAddPassesViewController and
present it.
Now, let's go up to the
viewDidLoad method.
As we saw, there was a QR code
here.
Again, if your pass has a QR
code on the front, there's no
need to have it in your app.
And, since our pass is now
NFC-capable, we don't need this
view anymore.
So, let's go ahead and remove
these lines of code.
Here is the PKAddPassButton, or
our Add to Wallet button.
In order to-- another way to
enhance the user's experience is
when the summary view is
presented right after they've
purchased the ticket, we
immediately ask them if they
want to add the pass to Wallet,
rather than having a button
onscreen.
Of course, you can have this Add
to Apple Wallet button somewhere
else in your app, if the user
decides to add the pass later.
So, let's go ahead and remove
this button.
And, instead, we're going to
replace it with a View in Wallet
button.
That way, the user can tap this
button, and they'll be brought
directly to a Wallet, and be
shown the pass that they just
added.
And, finally, when the view is
presented, let's immediately ask
them if they want to add the
pass.
Now, that we've made these
changes, let's deploy to the
device, and see what it looks
like.
Again, we're presented with the
same view, a summary about the
event.
I'll go ahead and purchase this
pass again.
And now, you can see we're
immediately asked if we want to
add the pass to Wallet.
And, you can see in the
background code, the QR code is
no longer there.
And, the Add to Apple Wallet
button is replaced with the View
in Wallet button.
So, I want to add this pass to
Wallet.
And, let's go ahead and view it.
You see, we're immediately taken
to the pass, and you can see the
QR code is no longer on the
front.
And, instead we have a Hold Near
Reader displayed at the bottom,
meaning that our pass is now
contactless, and I could scan it
a reader when I arrive at the
event.
Now, let's lock the device, and
since we're close to Discovery
Meadow here in San Jose, let's
see if the pass is relevant on
the lock screen.
Here's the notification for the
pass with the text that we set
in the JSON.
Let's tap our notification.
The pass is immediately
displayed, and I happen to have
a contactless reader here on
stage, so let's simulate me
arriving at the event.
And, it's as simple as that.
We hope that you can adopt these
simple changes in order to
enhance your customer's
experience when they interact
with Wallet and Apple Pay in
your app.
And now, I'll hand it back over
to Ben.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you Katie, for that
fantastic demo.
What an improvement those
changes made to the experience.
So, the final topic we want to
cover today is digital to
physical commerce.
Now, using Apple Pay is a great
way to buy, but that's not where
the user's journey ends.
It's important to carry through
that seamless experience into
the physical world.
Now, to do that, I want to show
you two examples.
Starting with the Caffe Macs
app, that's used by thousands of
employees every day at Apple
Park.
Here, I launched the app, and
I'm immediately presented with
the best offers on offer today.
It's a great way to engage me.
It doesn't require me to browse
through all the items in the
app.
You might be wondering why you
don't see the Apple Pay button
immediately.
And, that's because I'm not
inside Caffe Macs.
As soon as I get close, using
GPS and Bluetooth beacons, the
app detects that change, and the
button appears.
This allows me to buy right from
the starting page.
It's a great example of
upstreaming.
Sometimes I order more than one
thing, and Caffe Macs has me
covered.
They support both the multi-item
express checkout, as well as a
single-item purchase flow right
from the product page.
I can also check out from
anywhere in the app, using the
Pay tab below.
Now, this is a great pattern to
follow to make checkout easy.
When I'm ready to pay, I Face
ID, and I'm done.
Here, you can see that following
our guidelines, and requesting
as little information as
possible.
I'm already logged in across
multiple Apple apps, so no
additional fields are required.
However, if I wasn't, this would
be a really great place for you
to request the minimal
information to make collection
of the items easier.
Finally, a confirmation to let
me know that the order's been
done, and I should wait for a
notification.
As I walk over to the pizza
station, the notification
arrives to let me know that it's
ready.
And, when I get there, my lunch
is waiting for me.
A ticket with my name on it, and
a member of the Caffe Macs staff
confirms me by name, and I'm
away to devour my pizza.
Now, that's a great experience
from start to finish.
And, another experience that we
love is a food ordering app from
China, [Chinese spoken].
Now, they start with using the
iPhone's camera to scan a QR
code when entering the
restaurant.
And, that takes them straight to
the menu in the [Chinese spoken]
app.
They use images in their menu to
make it easy to know what you
want, and how to checkout fast.
In the checkout flow, the app
offers the user a virtual
payment credential, issued by
[Chinese spoken], which uses our
in app provisioning flow to put
a card directly into Wallet.
Now, this works great even if
the user has no cards at all, in
Wallet or otherwise.
They can set one up, and order
right away.
And, the card that's provisioned
can be used in all e-commerce,
and in-store merchants anywhere
in China that takes Apple Pay.
If you use a provisions
[inaudible] card into Wallet,
Apple Pay's the exclusive option
to checkout.
Fantastic example of defaulting.
As soon as I Face ID, the food
is ordered.
That's a fantastic experience
bringing together all of these
technologies: GPS, beacons, the
camera, in-app provisioning, and
notifications.
If you combine that with a great
physical customer experience--
you know, if you leverage
everything we've shown you here
today, you too can build digital
to physical commerce
experiences.
So, I have one piece of final
housekeeping.
If you are a payment processor,
or a merchant, most of you don't
need to worry, but you should
just check your server-side
certificate expiry dates in the
developer portal.
They are easy to renew, and you
should renew before expiry to
avoid disruption taking Apple
Pay.
That's everything we have to
talk about today.
If you want to learn more, our
online documentation can be
found here.
And, if you have any questions
about Wallet, Apple Pay, or Core
NFC, you can join us immediately
after this session in Technology
Lab 1 at 10 A.M. Thank you all
for coming today, and I hope
you've had a great WWDC.
Bye.
[ Applause ]