[ Silence ]
>> Anders Bertelrud: Welcome
to session 401, Xcode
Core Concepts.
I'm Anders and later on in
this session I'll be joined
by my colleague Rick.
So, this morning in Presidio
in the previous Xcode session
we saw what's new in Xcode 5.
And in this session I like
to talk a little bit more
about the core concepts
behind Xcode, both those in 4
and also those that are
newly expressed in Xcode 5.
And the goal is to give
you better understanding
of what you're seeing in the UI
and to make you a lot more
efficient as you're using Xcode.
So specifically we're
going to start talking
about the user interface and
the various concepts behind
that with the special
focus on navigation.
When you're working
with your code,
a lot of the times you're
going back and forth
between various source
files or UI files.
I want to make that as efficient
as possible and Xcode has a lot
of good features for that.
We're going to talk
about working effectively
with editors, with the single
editor as well as multiple ones.
We're going to talk specifically
about some of the things
in the source editor that you
can use to be more productive.
I'm going to talk a little bit
about documentation integration,
and how to customize
Xcode's behaviors.
Xcode has fairly flexible
behavior system that you can use
to really improve your workflow.
After that, my colleague Rick's
going to come up on stage
and talk about the fundamental
concepts that underlie Xcode,
the once you're manipulating
through the UI.
That includes workspaces,
projects, targets,
schemes and run destinations.
So some of this will be
familiar from Xcode 4
but there may be a lot of things
there you don't know about
and some will be new in Xcode 5.
We'll start with the UI.
This is the familiar
Xcode workspace window.
And so I won't go
into it in detail
because you all have
seen it before.
But briefly, to the left
here is the navigation area.
All of that area are
consists of different panes
that show you a different
view into your code.
I should say also on the right
there is the utility area
consisting of the inspector
on the top and library
at the bottom and in the middle
is where you do the editing,
and of course you can
close any of these panes.
So let's start by that
focusing and navigation.
So the navigator area here
on the left, the very top
of that are the selectors
for choosing
which navigator you want to see.
We'll go into each of
these in a bit more detail.
We have the project
navigator, the symbol navigator,
find, issue navigator.
The new one in Xcode 5 is the
unit test testing navigator,
debugging and related
is breakpoints and then
of course the log navigator.
So taking a closer look
at those, first of all,
I want to show that at the
bottom of most of these,
we have a filter bar that's
down there at the bottom--
it's different, slightly
different for each
of the navigators but it fills
the same function for each.
There's usually a way to create
the new entry of the content
that you're looking at,
whether that's a file
or breakpoints or any of those.
There are state filters
that are specific
to the particular
navigator you're looking at.
And then there's
usually, most of them,
have a generic text filter,
where if you know the name
or a substring of the name
of what you're looking for,
you can just type it
in and quickly narrow
down on what you're looking for.
So, looking at each
the navigators in turn,
we'll see first here with
the project navigator,
there is a recently
edited, first of all,
of course it shows you the
project contents, projects,
files, those kinds of things.
At the bottom there,
there is a recent filter
and this could be very useful
if you have a very large project
and you've been working
on a certain set of files,
you have a certain working set.
So those will show you the ones
you've been visiting recently.
The modified filter will
focus just on those things
that you modified since the
last time you checked anything
into source code or that
have interesting SCM state.
And of course there is the
filter field where you can,
in this case, we type
in the string render
and we see just the entries
that-- that contain that name.
So that's pretty simple.
Now the symbol navigator,
it shows you all kinds
of symbolic information that
we get from indexing your code.
So this includes of course
classes, methods, enumerations,
all those kinds of things.
There are filters there to
let you focus just on your own
or the ones that are
in the system as well.
The find navigator is where
you do workspace wide searching
of either regular plain text
strings or regular expressions.
And so-- one of the things
that you can do here is to go
into replace modes, you could do
search or you could do replace.
And as you saw yesterday we
in Xcode 5 we streamlined the
UI here to make it a lot easier
to get at these various things.
You can actually delete search
results, as you go through them,
and that doesn't delete them
from your code, it just takes it
out of the list of the
ones you're operating on.
There's also a scope field
and what that lets you do is
to narrow down the
search or replace
on just a particular
part of your workspace.
Now that could be either
a subtree or subfolder
or a project, or you could
define your own filters
that define a set of files
such as all header
files or all nib files.
The issue navigator
shows you issues
that Xcode has discovered
with your project.
So this could be,
of course, warnings
and errors form the
compiler or linker,
but also static analysis
results.
And also Xcode itself, you--
before you build will check
for certain consistency issues,
such as if you don't have
the right SDK installed
that you'll need
for the project,
you'll see that right away.
And sometimes, if Xcode detects
a modernization suggestion,
it will actually tell
you here as well.
So that's a good
place to check and try
to keep this as empty
as possible.
The test navigator
is new in Xcode 5
and this shows your unit tests
and that also let's you create
new ones from here and run them,
and there's a whole session
about that coming up and so,
so I won't say much more about
that here, that's on Thursday.
The debug navigator is of course
where you see the current state
of your program, that's where we
have the new gauges in Xcode 5
and there's a whole session on
that as well, so I will skip
over that one as well because
there's a lot more to talk
about in this session.
That debugging session
is on Wednesday.
The breakpoint navigator
is closely related
to the debug navigator, and
unlike the debug navigator,
this is one where you
can create content even
if your program is not running.
So for example, you can
create new breakpoints,
new symbolic breakpoints or
just breakpoints in your code.
One of the new things
in Xcode 5 is
that this pane shows you
the resolved breakpoints
of any symbolic ones you have.
So you can enter
symbolic breakpoints
for a certain method name and
then you can see all the places
that match that in the code and,
and click on them to
go directly there.
And of course the
activity log navigator,
that shows SCM activity, it
shows you build, warnings
and errors and those
kinds of things.
And in Xcode 5 it also shows
you the diagnostics and logs
that you get from your
Xcode service bots.
There's a whole session on that
called "Continuous Integration
in Xcode 5" and that's going to
be this afternoon at Presidio.
So, because these are
very commonly used
and very useful different
entry points into your code,
they have very convenient
keyboard shortcuts.
So control simply 1 through
8 will put the cursor
in the navigator, switch to
the right one, put the cursor
in there so you can use the
arrow keys to go up and down
and then quickly go
to the file you want.
So even if your hands are on
the keyboard, your text's--
you're looking at your text,
this is the-- the
way to do that.
Let me just very
quickly go there.
So let's talk a little
bit about editors
and working effectively
with editors.
We've seen now how to navigate
between the different content
and get different
files into the editor.
So at the top of the editor,
on top of every editor,
there's a jump bar
as we call it,
and it has various components.
So, there's the-- the
related files menu,
I'm sure you've used before
but I hopefully I can--
show some, some extra
tricks on how to use that.
There's back and forth buttons,
each editor works a little bit
like web browser in the
sense that there's a history,
you go back and forth
not only between files
but also the locations
within the particular file.
The location of the file in
the workspace does two things.
It-- it tells you what file
you're editing especially useful
if you have multiple
files with the same name,
but also it lets you access any
of the other files
reachable from your workspace.
And on the-- right here is
the issue mini navigator.
If you have any issues at the
issue pane that are associated
with files, you can use the
arrow keys to go back and forth
between them or pop that menu
and just cycle through the,
the issues and fix them.
So, the-- starting off from the
left here, we can hit control 1
or we go, we click
on the, the menu.
We get to the related
files menu.
And when Xcode indexes
your project it knows a lot
about each file and how that
can be related to the other one,
so obviously there
is a recent menu.
Counterparts include most
obviously if you're looking
at the implementation you can
see the header, vice versa,
superclasses, pretty
straightforward, categories,
and those kinds of things.
Now, there's also a convenient
way to get to any other file
that this file includes
or vice versa to get
to any other includers
of this file.
That's great for a header
when you're wondering
which other files
include it and you want
to go quickly between them.
And then of course,
new in Xcode 5 is
that you can get
to tests as well.
At the bottom there are
controls to get to preprocess
and assembly language
outputs of your current file.
And when you do that you get
a preview of the assembler
and you can pick if
you have let's say code
that compiles both for iOS
and for OS X, you can pick
which CPU you want the
assembler output for.
The back and forth buttons
are pretty straightforward.
I won't spend a lot
of time on those.
But there are keyboard
equivalents for each
of these and, and so that
will conveniently get you
up to the menu.
The menu that shows you the
entire workspace can be quite
big but it uses submenus to let
you navigate really to any file
at all that you can
reach from the workspace,
so that can be fairly
convenient.
And then finally, if you--
if you hit Control 5,
you get to the menu that
shows just the files.
Very often the other file you're
looking to go to is up here
of the one that you're already
viewing and so control 5 put you
on that menu, you can use
the arrow keys and return key
to quickly go to any
one of those files.
And control 6 pulls down to
Symbol menu which is, well,
shows you all the
classes and methods.
And one of the tricks
that actually works
with all these menus
is type-aheads.
You can just start typing
when you're looking at any
of these menus and it
will quickly filter
down to exactly what you're
looking for and that can be--
that actually works in all of
them and that can be a great way
to just very quickly get
to the menu you want.
So, we've looked a little
bit about the jump bar
at the top of editors.
So let's talk about the
assistant editor, when you open
up Xcode by default, you get
just the single standard editor,
and whenever you choose
a new thing to look
at though navigation, then
the content is replaced.
Now, the assistant
editor is a secondary
or it can even be
tertiary that opens up
and it will track the
contents of the primary editor.
And so this is excellent for
looking at auxiliary content.
And one of the things that you
might not know is that you can--
you have several
options for how to lay
out the assistant editors.
They can stack from
top to bottom,
or right to left, et cetera.
So with the Assistant
Editor, how do you invoke it?
One of the ways you can
invoke that is most obviously
with the tool bar and you see
here the highlighted button
there, it gets you into standard
editor mode, just clicking
on the assistant
editor button put you
on assistant editor mode.
You can conveniently access
any kind of SCM information
about the current file as well.
And for each of this there's,
there's key equivalents you can
see in here, command Option,
command Shift, et cetera.
There's a whole session on SCM
and Xcode and that's going to be
on Friday in Pacific Heights
and that will talk a lot more
about the functionality that you
get underneath that, that mode.
Going back to the
Assistant Mode here,
regardless of how you invoke it.
What happens when you invoke
it is you get a second editor
that tracks and by default it
will track whatever is most
appropriate as a counterpart to
the file and the primary editor.
Xcode knows things like
header files being associated
with implementation files.
It also knows for example that
a vertex shader is associated
with a fragment shader.
So when you choose
counterparts here,
it will go between the
various, various files
and when you switch a file,
the assistant editor tracks.
This is particularly useful
when you have contents
such as a nib file.
So if you're looking, for
example, at a view controller,
you can see that
the corresponding UI
in the right hand side there.
And then what happens
when you're looking
in the assistant editor
is you may very well want
to actually focus on that for
a bit so you can choose the--
to make that the
primary content.
And what happens in that case is
that the assistant content
becomes the primary content,
and now the assistant
editor is available
to show you related
content to that.
So that way you can sort
of navigate back and forth
in your graph of connectedness
between your files.
In this case, as you
click in the nib file,
you can see the source
files that are related
to the various doc-- various
objects in your nib file.
And you'll notice that the
Assistant menu now has changed
to show you entries that are
relevant to the nib file.
So you can very easily,
for example, go through all
of the different
actions that are,
that are presented
in this nib file.
In activating the assistant
editor, how do you do that?
Well one is of course, you can
use the button in the tool bar,
but there's a very useful
thing throughout Xcode,
and that is the Option key where
when you use the Option key,
and combine that with
other modes of navigation,
instead of putting the source
file into the primary editor,
it'll open up an assistant,
and this could be very useful.
It exists in a variety
of places.
So for example, command click
on a symbol will navigate
to the source of that symbol
to-- to where it's defined.
If you also hold down the Option
key, it will do the same thing
but open up an assistant editor.
And you can do the same thing
when you click on a File
and then any of the navigators,
hold on the Option key
and it will instead put that
content in the assistant.
And that can be very useful
when you're navigating
and you don't actually want to
focus on what it is that's--
that you're seeing, you
just want to keep it
up as auxiliary content
to maybe for reference.
And in addition to that, if
you want even more power,
if you hold down the Shift
key in addition you can get
to the navigation chooser.
You can also get to it from
the menu, the Open in menu.
But again, Command,
Option, Shift will bring
up the navigation chooser.
This is a HUD that lets you
use arrow keys and return key
to really do anything you want.
You can put the content
in a new tab,
you could add a new
assistant editor
or you can even create
a new tab,
it will put in an existing tab
or put content in a new window.
This is very customizable
and the user,
perhaps you can set exactly
what happens when you hold
on the option key, when you
double click, et cetera.
So if you haven't customized
this you may want to take a look
at that and see if you--
find a better workflow for
you with these options.
All right, so another way
to navigate is open quickly,
and I'm sure many
of you use this.
Command, Shift, O,
brings up open quickly,
and here you simply type
the name or a part of a file
or a symbol and Xcode
narrows down the list.
And as you notice, you
actually don't have
to type the contiguous range.
Very often if you just remember
the first parts of various,
of the subwords,
you could type that.
And very quickly get to
where you want to go.
And also the Option
key works here too,
so if you just hit return now
or just select this then
you'll be replacing the content
of your primary editor.
If you hold down the
Option key as well,
it'll open up assistant editor.
So let me show you few things
about the source editor.
So that's couple things
about the assistant editor
and the key takeaway
there is the,
the power of the Option key,
it can really, really help you
with your workflow there.
With the source editor,
there are couple of things--
there a lot of features, but
a couple of things I want
to call out in particular.
It's very common to want to
rename all the local variables,
a-- a local variable,
all the occurrences
of a local variable to,
to have a single name.
So, you can do that by
editing each occurrence of it,
but a better way is to
do Edit All in Scope
and there's a menu item for that
but there's also
command, Control E.
And when you do that, what
Xcode does is to take what's
under this-- the cursor, and
there's actually a submenu
that shows up underneath
an arrow there.
You can-- so there's
variety of ways to invoke it.
And then as you just type,
Xcode will replace all the
locations of that same symbol.
And it's not purely a
textual replacement.
It uses the index and it
knows that two variables
with the same name
are actually different
if they're in different scopes.
So that-- that can
be a really great way
to rename a variable to,
to have a better name
if you picked the wrong
one the first time around.
Another very useful
feature is Code Snippets.
So, very often when you're
coding, you come to a point
where you say, "Well
there's a sort of,
the sort of pattern
here of function call
or a loop that I want to use."
And Xcode has a fairly large
library built in Code Snippets
for common idioms into
various frameworks.
One way to instantiate it
is to just drag and drop.
And then what you get is you get
tokens for where you're going
to fill in your own content.
And you can just fill that in
and then just have your
own-- your own code there.
But very often, you will have
your own code where you want
to create your own
shortcuts for it.
So you can also create custom
Code Snippets, and to do that,
you just select a bunch of
code and then you drag it over
and drop, and you
see that it shows
up right there on
the-- on the side.
A popover comes up and
it will let you edit any
of the content in here.
So there are menus to let
you choose the platform
and the scope and the language,
that's pretty straightforward.
You edit the contents of it and
I want to call out one thing
in particular, when you edit the
contents, you can use the syntax
that uses angle brackets and
hash marks to surround parts
of your text that
you want to tokenize.
So those then become tokens when
you instantiate the Code Snippet
that can be easily replaced.
That turns into a token, and
then you can also crucially,
you can set a code completion
default because as fun as it is
to drag code snippets,
you probably don't want
to keep the utility area open,
and certainly you don't want
to reach for the mouse in order
to do instantiate
a code snippet.
So, by associating a substring
here, now it becomes avail--
and I'm hitting OK, I'm done.
Then it becomes available when
you go down and put your cursor
in the code, and you
can instantiate it.
And when you start typing,
code completion will
include that code snippet.
And then when you
instantiate it, it shows up
and you can just replace it.
So, with that I'd like to invite
my colleague Rick on stage
to show you some
of this in action.
>> Rick Ballard:
OK, thanks Anders.
So, right now I'm going to
take you through a quick demo
of using some of the features
that Anders just talked
about to work efficiently
in Xcode.
All right, so, I've
got my project here
and I have a problem
I want to investigate.
So, first of all
I want to go look
at the method where
the problem is.
So, as Anders told you, you
can just use Command, Shift,
and O to bring up Open Quickly
and start typing the name
of any symbol in your workspace
and we'll find it via the index.
So, in this case, I'm going to
start typing part of shape class
and it found my method,
register shape class with tag,
and I just hit Return
and here's the method
that I want to take a look at.
So, this method is dispatching
something to a concurrent queue.
And the problem I have is
that one of the callers
of this method is passing nil
for one of the parameters.
So, this is assert is firing.
Now normally I'd just look
at the backtrace of my assert
to see who called
this the wrong way.
But since this is dispatched
to a concurrent queue,
that backtrace just
shows dispatch machinery
and I can't see who's calling
my method with a bad parameter.
So, I'm going to use the
power of the assistant editor
and our callers functionality
to track
down who might be
causing this here.
So, first of all I'm
going to go ahead
and select the assistant editor
in upper right-hand corner
and I can go and see a bunch
of different related content
in the assistant editor.
In this case I'm going to
go take a look at callers,
and here Xcode through its
index has found everything
in this workspace that
calls this method,
there are three callers.
So, now I can easily
just select one of them
and here I can see this method
is definitely not passing nil
for that parameter.
So, this is not the problem.
So to go to the next
one, I'm actually going
to use a keyboard shortcut now.
If I use control 4 it will
pop-up the assistant menu again.
And I can just use
the Arrow keys
and select the next caller here,
and I see this one also is not
passing nil for that parameter.
So, I'm going to do
that one more time,
I'll select the last
caller and this one is--
has forgotten to pass a tag.
So, there's my problem.
So, I can just say
fill in this--
fill in this tag and
I fix that problem.
OK, I'm going to go back
to my standard editor
so you can see well here.
And the next problem I want
to solve is I have this property
isLoaded here and I maybe want
to give that a bit more
of a descriptive name.
That property reflects
whether my cache is loaded.
So, I think I actually want
to call it, isCacheLoaded.
So to rename a method,
normally I could use--
to use Xcode's refactoring
feature to rename a method
and it would rename that method
and all callers of that method.
But in this case, this property
is, key-value observed by some
of the callers and
so this method name
or this property name just
shows up in string values
to key-value observing
so the rename refactoring
isn't sufficient.
So, for this case, I'm actually
going to use a textual find
and replace in order
to rename this method.
So first of all I'm going
to go to the find navigator,
command 3 will bring
that up easily.
And I'm going to
select the word "Loaded"
that I'm going to replace here.
Command E will put that
in the find pasteboard.
So, you see it's showing up here
in the upper left-hand corner.
And if I hit Return, I can find
all instances of the word loaded
in source code in my
workspace, just like that.
So, I actually want to
do a replacement here.
So, I'm going to choose
replace then I want
to replace the word
Loaded with cacheLoaded.
So, if I hit replace on
that it will go ahead
and make this change.
But before I do that,
I ought to make sure
that all these instances
of the word loaded are actually
references to my property name
and not that word showing
up somewhere else
in my source code.
So, if I start flipping through
these, I see, here's a case
where that property is
being key-value observed.
Here-- here is that
key path again.
Actually, almost of these are
my property, but there's one
that isn't and that's the
underlying shape cache
isLoaded property.
I'm not renaming that.
So, I don't want my find and
replace to touch that one.
So as Anders said, you can
actually delete find results
out of the find navigator.
So, with this selected, if
I just press the Delete key,
it deleted that find result.
And now when I do my batch
replace, it's not going
to touch that one case.
So, I can just replace
the instances
of the string that I want to.
So, I'm going to say
replace all, I'm not going
to use snapshots at the moment.
And now, it's gone ahead
and renamed our property
to isCacheLoaded.
All right, there's one more
thing I want to show you.
I have a method that I want to
validate that some other methods
that I call are doing the
right with change management.
So, first of all
I'm going to go back
to the project navigator
to find this file.
I could use open quickly
again, but I'm going
to show you a different way.
Down in the lower left, if I
select the recent files filter,
you'll see just the files that
I've been editing recently.
And this provides a
really nice working set.
If I'm going back and forth
between a few files
I edit frequently,
I can just see them all here
and have them all
immediately accessible.
So, in this case the file I
want to edit is SKTDocument.
And now, I need to find
the method I'm looking
for so I'm going to use control
6 to bring up the symbol pop-up.
And with type-ahead, I can
just start typing what I'm
looking for.
So, I'm going to
say readFromData.
Here it is, there's the
method I want, I select that,
and here's the method I
want to take a look at.
So, down here this method
is removing some graphics
and then inserting
some graphics,
and I want to make
sure that both
of these are doing
the right thing.
So, if I command click on this
symbol it would jump right
to that method and I
could see what it's doing.
But in this case, I actually
want to see my code side
by side, so I can see that
it's all coordinating properly,
so to use that I'm going to
use the assistant editor.
So as Anders said any
navigation that you can do
if you add the option key,
it will send that navigation
to the assistant editor.
So, instead of command
clicking on this,
I'm going to command
option click on it
and that will automatically
open up the assistant editor
and you can see here's
the method
that I want to take a look at.
So, that's great.
I also want to look at
insertGraphics at the same time.
So, I'm actually going to open
up another assistant
editor to do that.
So, Anders mentioned that
Option, Shift, Navigation brings
up the navigation
chooser and let you choose
where your concept will go.
So, I'm going to Command, Option
Shift, click on this method.
There's my navigation chooser,
I can just go down and tell it
that I want to open a new
assistant editor, hit Return,
and here's this method
opening in a new--
you open in a new
assistant editor.
So, I can go down here and
see that my remove method,
before it does the remove,
it stops observing graphics.
My insert method, after
it does the insert,
it starts observing graphics.
So, this looks like it's
all behaving correctly
and works the way I want.
So, that's just a quick example
of how you can use
Xcode's navigation features
and our assistant editor
to build really efficient
nice workflows.
Let's turn it back
over to Anders.
>> Anders Bertelrud: So,
let's talk a little bit
about documentation integration.
Xcode 4 had good
documentation integration,
and in Xcode 5 it's even better.
One of the ways, of course,
when you want to look
at documentation is you're
looking at your code,
you have your hands
on the keyboard,
and you may want information
about a certain method.
So, in Xcode, we
provide documentation
with the command completion.
So, when you go to
complete code,
you can now get information
about the item under
your selection.
If you have more than one
as you arrow up and down,
you get a short summary.
This is great if you
don't know exactly
which method you're using,
that you want to use,
then you can get
a summary of it.
Another thing you can
do is to option click
and that will get you,
instead of command click goes
to the definition, option click
will get your documentation
about the symbol under there.
And as you can see, we
have complete documentation
about the symbol without even
having to open up a utility area
or documentation area.
That's great when you just want
to know some more information
about a particular method
that you see being used,
method or function or
enumeration, et cetera.
Sometimes though
you want to look
at documentation a little
bit more permanently
or less transiently, so what
you can do there is to open
up the right side of the utility
area there, and then keep
that open, and as you
move the cursor around,
the quick help will
show you the information
about whatever is
currently under your cursor.
So as you use arrow
keys up and down
for example the content
there will change.
So, that's all great.
That's for the built-in
documentation for iOS,
for OS X, SDKs, etceteras.
So, what about your own code?
Well, this is what you see
if you haven't told Xcode
anything else, all it knows is
where you declare it which would
be in a header file usually.
But, as you may have seen
in the previous sessions,
in Xcode 5, you can do better.
So, this is how your
declaration looks
without any other adornment
and that's the help you get.
You sort of get what
you put into it.
If you put some comments
in, for regular comments,
you can put some special
annotations in there,
Xcode will parse that, in this
case we're using doxygen type
tags there, and then Xcode
can actually show a pop-up
that will give you a
lot more information.
The same amount of
information that you get
for the built-in SDKs.
So, in this case for example,
you see how the various parts
of your comment translate to
the various parts of the pop-up.
And you can get more information
about the syntax,
at doxygen.org.
So, now if you go back
to our source code,
when we try to use
code completion
on our own method instead
of just the header we
get full documentation
and of course we get the same
thing with the option click
for the pop-over, and we get
the same thing in the quick help
on the right side of the screen.
So, that way, you can
really make your own code
for your own sake and the
sake of your teammates be
as well documented
as Apple's APIs are.
Let's talk a little bit more
about the documentation window.
You've seen this one
before I think also
in the Intro to Xcode 5.
In Xcode 5, we've pulled
the documentation viewer
out of the organizer and put
it into its own window which--
and along with the new great
multi windows full-screen
support can be a great
way to put your doc
on one window, et cetera.
The documentation viewer now
let's you look at the content
and also the Table of
Contents on the right
for whatever document
you're looking at.
And also whenever you see
anything that you want
to highlight that's
particularly relevant
to what you were looking at
or what you need to work on,
you just click on the Bookmark
icon and then that entry shows
up in the bookmark
pane on the left
where you can very
quickly access any part
of the documentation
whether it's a method
or conceptual documentation
or anything like that.
And of course, you can
close both of those sidebars
to see the full documentation
experience when you really want
to read a particular document.
Finally, I want to talk a
little about and this is--
finally you have
UI part of this.
I want to talk about how you
can customize Xcode's behaviors
to increase your efficiency.
So Xcode has a lot of
filters-- features built in,
and there are also
a lot of triggers
that you can associate
custom behavior with.
So on the left side here,
this is in the PrefPane,
and you may have seen
this before, you may not.
In the PrefPane, there are
a bunch of built-in triggers
of various kinds when your
program hits a breakpoint,
when your program crashes, when
you check something into SCM,
you can associate those with
the actions on the right.
And so there are
several built-in actions.
One of the ones I want to point
out which you might not be aware
of is one that works in
conjunction with tabs.
I didn't talk a lot
about the tabs,
but we actually have talked
about them a lot in past years
and there are videos from
previous WWDCs going into detail
about how you can use those.
One of the things you can
do is give a name to a tab,
and then when a certain trigger
occurs, you can cause that tab
with a certain name to be
opened in a separate window
or in the same window,
et cetera.
This is great for
combining with things like,
oh there was console
output, let me go to the Tab
that I've named Console.
So, if you like working
in the tab format--
with a tab workflow, that's
a great way to set it up.
You could also create
your own custom actions,
your custom triggers
and associate a key
equivalent with those.
So then, obviously that
triggers whenever you hit
that key combination.
And that's very useful not only
for invoking the built-in
behaviors that Xcode has,
but also for invoking
custom behaviors.
You can choose any shell script
that you want to have run
and associate that with
any action including the
Command key.
So, the script can get
past certain information
about the context like the
file you're looking at.
So, this can be a great way
to invoke custom scripts,
really those power users you
want to do custom operations
when you hit ceratin keys.
And so, with that, that
was a quick view of the UI.
I'd like to hand it back to Rick
who's going to talk about some
of the underlying
concept of Xcode.
>> Rick Ballard: Thanks, Anders.
So, that's an introduction
to Xcode user interface.
Let's talk about the underlying
conceptual model in Xcode
that you want to know about
to get things done day to day.
After this section,
you should come away
with a few important takeaways.
You should understand how set up
your own workspace with projects
and targets, how to
configure your settings
to produce the products
that you want to produce,
how to use schemes to perform
actions on those products
like running in the debugger,
testing your unit tests,
profiling for performance,
statically analyzing
your source code,
and archiving your
product for distribution.
And you should come away
with the better understanding
of Xcode's underlying conceptual
model which will help you feel
like you know what
you're doing in Xcode.
So, the fundamental
concepts we're going to go
over today are workspaces,
projects
and the build configurations
they contain, targets
and the build settings and
build phases that they contain,
schemes, and finally
run destinations.
Let's get started
with workspaces.
Workspaces are collections of
files and projects with state.
So, a workspace contains a
set of related Xcode projects
that you want to work
with at the same time,
along with any other related
files that you want to have
like todos and notes
that go along with it.
Your workspace provides
repository for state.
So that means things like
the user interface state.
What windows and tabs
did you have opened
and what files are they showing?
It means what breakpoints
do you have set
and other related state,
all get saved per workspace.
Your workspace also
provides a unique location
for your build products.
So, all the build products
produced by targets and projects
in one workspace will go to
that workspace's unique location
and won't get mixed up
with the build products
from another workspace.
Finally, your workspace
provides a symbol index
of all the symbols
in that workspace.
So, anything, any method, any
class, any symbols you have,
in any projects in that
workspace, you can get to easily
from anywhere else
in the workspace
with our features
like open quickly.
So, when should you actually
create your own explicit
workspace document?
Well, anytime you have
a set of Xcode projects
that you use together,
it generally makes sense
to create a workspace
document, put those projects
in the document and
work with that workspace
when you're working with them.
Another important
reason to think
about workspaces is what we
call implicit dependencies.
So, you can make targets
explicitly depend on each other,
but you don't actually
have to do that.
If you have an application and
it links against the library
and you put the project
that builds the application
in the same workspace with the
project that builds the library,
Xcode will notice that implicit
dependency and make that happen
so that whenever you build
the application target,
it will build the library
target first automatically
so the application can link
against the built library.
So, you can use workspaces
to put things in together
when you want to detect
those implicit dependencies.
The last thing to know about
workspaces is in Xcode,
even if you haven't created an
explicit workspace document,
you always have a workspace.
Xcode projects, like if you
open a bare Xcode project,
it will act as its
own implicit workspace
and provide a unique
location for build products,
saved state, and so forth.
So, anything I say about
workspaces applies to working
with bare Xcode projects
as well.
So, let's talk about projects.
Your Xcode projects are
collection of files, targets,
schemes, and build
configurations.
So, a project contains file
references to source files
and resource files that you
want to use, a set of targets
which process those
files in order
to produce your build
products, a set of schemes
which will tell those targets
to build their products
and then perform actions on
the product of these targets,
and a set of build
configurations which allow you
to vary your build settings.
So, build configurations
are build setting variants.
All your settings
normally have a value,
but when you have build
configurations you can vary
their value across
those configurations.
So, by default out of the
box, we give you debug
and release build configurations
and that's all most
of you will need.
You generally just have
two modes, I'm, you know,
working in the debugger or
I'm going to release my app.
Most settings don't
actually need to vary it all.
You generally just
need one value.
But there's some that you do
like your optimization level.
When you're debugging your code,
you don't want your
code to be optimized.
When you're releasing to the
App store you definitely do.
So, that's when you use
build configurations.
Finally, you can create your own
build configurations if you need
to vary your build settings
for another purpose.
But, most of you are
probably going to be just fine
with just debug and release.
You can get your
build configurations
and your other project
settings in the project editor.
You first select the project
in the project navigator
on the left.
And then from the project
editor pop-up, you make sure
that the project is selected.
This gives you the
project editor on the right
which has some common
project settings and this is
where you define your
build configurations.
Let's talk about targets.
Targets are the instructions
for building one build product.
So, your targets can--
will reference some or all
of the all source files
and resource files in
that target's project.
And the target contains
a set of build phases.
The build phases are the
high level sequence of steps
that the target is going to take
when it produces
your build product.
There's also a set
of build rules
that determine how the compile
sources build phase will compile
your sources.
You notice a build rules
tab in the target editor,
but most of you don't
need to mess with this.
And finally, a set of build
settings will define pretty much
every aspect of how that
build process works.
Targets can also depend on
one or more other targets
and a target you depend on will
be built first automatically
whenever your target is built.
So, let's talk about
target build phases.
Build phases again are the
high level sequence of steps
that your target will take
when producing a product.
So, some of the common
reasons why you might want
to go edit the build
phases are--
you might want to set per
file compiler build settings.
You might want to add
resources to your product
or configure exactly
where inside your product
those resources go.
You might want to make a target
depend on another target.
You might want run a script
while building in order
to do just about anything
else that isn't covered
by the built-in behavior.
You get at your build
phases in the target editor.
So, from the project
editor pop-up,
make sure that your target is
selected that you want to edit,
and you get the target
editor on the right.
And this-- In the general
tab, we'll show some
of the common target settings
you might want to get at.
If you select the
build phases tab,
we'll show you the high
level sequence of steps
that your target is going to
take when building your product.
So, let's go through
this briefly.
The Target Dependencies
phase lists all the targets
that your target depends on
and you can add and
remove them here.
The Compile Sources phase
shows all the source files
that your target is
going to compile.
If you want to set per
file compiler flags
like maybe you want to turn off
ARC for just one of your files,
you can do that on the
Compile Sources phase.
The Link Binaries with Libraries
phase lets you setup what
libraries and frameworks your
target's product is going
to link against.
If your target produces
a framework on OS X,
you can control which headers
get copied into that framework
with the Copy Headers
build phase.
If your target produces any
sort of bundle type output
like an application bundle,
you can copy resources
in to your bundle with
the Copy Resources phase
and by default this
will copy your resources
into the resource's
subdirectory of the bundle.
But if you want to copy files
anywhere else into your product,
you can setup custom
copy file phases as well.
This allows you to specify where
you want the file to be copied.
And for example, here I've got
a helper tool and I'm copying it
into the executables
directory of my bundle
so that my application can
launch its helper tool whenever
it needs.
Finally, anything else
you want to do as part
of the build process, you
can do with shell scripts
with the run script build phase.
They can be created and
dragged to reorder them.
We'll provide the build
settings for the target
in the environment of your
scripts so it can do things
like find where your target's
product has been placed
and manipulate it.
Let's talk about
build settings now.
Build settings are
the set of values
that control exactly how
your product is built.
So, some common reasons to want
to go change your build
settings are you might want
to rename your product,
it's time to ship
and you're renaming
your application.
There's a build setting
for that.
You might want to set
what SDK you're targeting
or change the preprocessor
defines that the compiler passes
to outsource files
when it compiles.
You might want to
update your warning flags
to configure just what warnings
you get, and there are many,
many more reasons to go
in to the build settings.
So, let's take a look.
If you select the build settings
tab from the target editor,
you'll see the list of all
the build settings available.
There's a basic tab
you can select
to just see the most
common ones,
but here I'm showing
you all build settings,
and they're categorized as well.
You notice that most of these
build settings only have a
single value that's because
they don't need to vary.
But, there are some
like optimization level,
that vary across
build configurations.
So, there's a different value
for debug versus release.
There's actually another axis
on which you can vary
your build settings,
that you can make your build
settings have different values
per architecture or per SDK.
And to do that, you just hover
the mouse over one of these rows
and a little plus button
will appear allowing you
to vary your build settings
along another access.
So, this is the build settings
that are set in the target.
There's actually an inheritance
flow of build settings however.
If you select the
levels tab at the top,
it will show that to you.
So, the project also has
a build settings tab,
even if the project doesn't
directly produce anything,
any build settings you set on
the project will be inherited
by all targets in that project.
So, it provides a good
way to set uniform values
across multiple targets.
In the levels mode, we'll
show you that inheritance.
On the right, you'll
see the default value
for every build setting
that would be used
if you didn't customize it.
To the left of that are
all the build settings
that are set in the project.
So, these will be inherited by
all targets in that project.
Next come, the build
setting values
that you've set specifically
in this one target,
and those will override
the project build settings.
You'll also notice that
there are green boxes drawn
around some of these cells.
We draw a green box to show you
exactly where the final value
from each build setting
is being taken from.
So, you can see that
at a glance.
Finally, on the far left,
you see the result value
for every build setting
that will actually get
used when you build.
All right, let's
talk about schemes.
Schemes are the instructions
for building a set of targets
to produce a product and
then performing an action
on that product.
We support scheme actions
for running on the debugger,
profiling for performance,
testing your unit tests,
statically analyzing your source
code, and archiving your product
for distribution
to the App store
or to just save a freeze-dried
copy of your product.
For each of those actions
the scheme allows you
to specify the set of
targets that you want to build
when you're performing
that action,
and the build configuration
that this target should build
with from-- when you're
going to perform that action.
To get at your schemes
you're going to go
to the upper left-hand corner
of the workspace window
to the scheme pop-up.
If you just close
this, you'll see a list
of the schemes available
to you in your workspace.
And you can choose to
edit scheme here to bring
up the scheme pop-up on the
currently selected scheme.
The scheme pop-up
is where you go
to edit all the settings
for that scheme.
To perform a scheme action,
you can use the run button
in the upper left-hand corner
of the workspace window
or the product menu
which offers all of them.
So, here you can see
there's a run, test, profile,
analyze, and archive command.
There are also subcommands for
building for specific actions
without actually
performing that action,
and for performing an action
without building if you want
to just use your last built copy
that you built for that action.
So, that's what your
schemes are.
Let's talk about
where they come from.
Out of the box, we
will automatically try
to create the schemes
we think you want and so
that means the first time you
open a project or workspace
or whenever you create a
new project that has targets
or a new target, we'll create
a scheme for every target
that we see so that you
have at least one scheme
that will build every target.
Now, I said every target,
that's not quite true
if you have unit
test bundle targets.
Instead of putting those
tests in their own scheme,
we'll try to put
them in the scheme
of the product they go with.
So, if your tests
test an application,
in that application scheme's
test action we'll add the test
bundle target.
Likewise, if you
create new test bundles,
you probably don't want separate
schemes for them, you can delete
that scheme if we create it and
instead add your test bundle
to the test action of
whatever it is it tests.
These schemes that we
create automatically
for you are per user.
So, every user will get their
own copy of these schemes.
Finally, you should feel free
to delete any of the schemes
that we create that
you don't want,
because you can manually create
them again anytime you want
later from the scheme
management sheet.
And you might also find that
you want to create new schemes
to support custom workflows
with run script scheme actions,
and I'll talk about
that in a moment.
Let's talk about why
you might want to go
to the scheme editing sheet
to actually change settings.
So, first of all, you might want
to change the build
configuration that's being used
to build your targets when
performing one of your actions.
You might want to change
which unit tests get run
when you perform the test action
and you can also perform your
tests in the test navigator one
by one or as a suite or
a bundle if you want now.
But, when you want to configure
which tests get run standard
every time you test your scheme,
you do that on the test action.
You can also set arguments
and environment variables
that get passed to your App when
it's running in the debugger
or being profiled or get
passed to your unit test,
and that's done in the
scheme editor as well.
We support a bunch
of diagnostics.
There's a bunch of checkboxes in
the run action that allows you
to easily turn on things like
malloc stack logging or zombies
without having to remember the
underlying environment variable
that controls it.
And there are many other options
that you'll see when you go
to the scheme editing sheet.
We also have a more
detailed walkthrough of them
in last year's presentation
on understanding schemes.
So, if you bring up the
scheme editing sheet,
you'll see that on the
left we have a row for each
of the scheme actions
we support.
And there's also a row for the
build action or for building.
Building is not actually
an action.
Building is a step that
happens before each
of the other scheme actions.
So, when you perform an action
usually you build the prod--
or the targets for that action
and then perform that action.
You'll also see there's
a row of checkboxes here,
these determines which targets
gets built for which action.
And this is notable in
particular for the test action.
There's no reason to
build your unit test
if you're not going to test.
So, the test bundle,
test bundle is only built
for the test action by default
and you can configure
this further.
Also I mentioned,
you notice some
of these checkboxes
are disabled that means
that that target is explicitly
being used by that action.
So, if you wanted to uncheck
this target you'd have
to go tell the action not
to use its product anymore.
You'll notice that there's no
build configuration in this
in the build tab and that's
because you set the build
configuration per scheme action.
So, if you select
another action like test,
you'll see that each action has
a build configuration pop-up.
So, for most scheme
actions you usually want
to use the debug
build configuration.
Say, when you're
running on a debugger
or performing your unit test,
but when you're archiving
for distribution, you want
to use the release build
configuration and so we set
that up by default
to do that for you.
We also support additional
scheme action
as I alluded to before.
If you disclose the disclosure
arrow to the left of any
of these actions or
before the build step,
you can set pre-imposed actions.
It will run before
or after that action
or before or after the build.
We support send e-mail
as one of these actions,
but more usefully there's
a run script action.
So, you can set up
custom schemes
to run any script you want to
support your custom workflows.
This is especially useful
with our continuous
integration features.
You can for example have
a post-archive script
which copies your built
archive to some shared servers.
So, everytime the bot produces
an archive, you put it somewhere
where everyone can
get at it easily.
The archive action provides
some things in the environment
to your script to tell it
where to find that product
and you can additionally
set a target
to provide its build settings in
the environment to your script.
The last thing I want to mention
here is, why you would use this
versus a run script
build phase in a target?
Well, if your script
is an integral part
of producing the products of the
target, that probably belongs
as a run script build
phase in the target.
So, no matter which scheme
is building that target
that script gets run and the
product gets produced correctly.
If on the other hand your script
is part of a custom workflow,
that probably belongs
in the scheme.
So that you can have
different schemes
with different custom
workflows or have a scheme
that doesn't run it
when you don't want to.
So, that's how to
edit your schemes.
Let's talk about
how to manage them.
In the scheme pop-up
in the upper left,
there's a Manage Schemes
option and if you choose this,
it will bring up the scheme
management sheet giving you all
the schemes in your workspace
and projects and a list
of settings you can change.
So, let's talk about these.
First of all, there's
a shared checkbox
for each of these schemes.
Now, I said before that every
scheme we give you is per user,
just for you, but sometimes
you might have authored the
perfect scheme.
It's got just the targets
that you want to build
and the right arguments
and environment variables
being passed when you run
in the debugger, and
you want to share this
with your coworkers 'cause
everybody wants to use this.
So, if you click the
shared checkbox here
that scheme will actually be
moved to a shared location
within the project or workspace
bundle, and everybody else
who works with that project
or workspace will get a
copy of that scheme too.
This also means that any
edits that anyone makes
that scheme will be
shared with everybody,
because it's a one
shared copy of the scheme.
You know, some times if you work
on a big team and have a lot
of shared schemes, you might
have some that you don't care
about and don't want cluttering
up your scheme pop-up.
For example the QA team might
have some special schemes
that they use for
custom workflows,
but you don't always
want to be wading
through those when
you're working.
So, we have a show
checkbox on the left
and if you uncheck this,
that scheme just won't show
up for you in the
scheme pop-up anymore,
but that won't affect
anybody else.
Anybody who's sharing that
scheme will still be able
to use it and this
checkbox is per user.
Let's talk a little bit
about where these schemes
actually are stored.
Actually before that, when
you have a shared scheme,
you may sometimes want to make
some temporary one-off changes
like you want to
enable a diagnostic
or add an additional
command line argument.
But if you do that to a
shared scheme it will show
up for everybody and that's
not always what you want.
So, in that case we
generally recommend
that you create a duplicate of
that scheme that shared scheme,
with the Duplicate command,
and make your modifications
in your own per-user
copy of that scheme.
When you're done with that
per-user copy, you can delete it
to go-- go back to
using the shared scheme.
So, now let's talk about
where exactly these schemes
are stored.
Every scheme is actually
stored in its own separate file
so that you can manage it
easily in source control.
And that scheme file is
stored inside a project
or workspace wrapper.
So, that container column
here shows you which project
or workspace wrapper each
scheme file is stored in.
And you can bring up
a menu here to change
where you want to
store that scheme.
This is important to think
about when you're working
with source control.
So, under source control,
you'll see inside a project
or workspace wrapper, there's
a separate shared data section
and user data section for
the data that's shared
between all users or the
data that's per user to you.
In the shared data section,
you'll see any schemes
that you've chosen to share,
and so generally you want
to commit this to source
control so that anybody else
in your team who
checks out your project
or workspace will actually get
a copy of that shared scheme.
In the per-user section, you see
all your own personal schemes,
as well as the scheme management
property list that records
which schemes you've
chosen to show and hide
and what order you want them to
show up in, in the scheme pop-up
since you can drag
to reorder them
in the scheme management sheet.
You might often want to check
in your own schemes here
as well just so you
can track changes
and have those personal schemes
available to you if you set
up any custom settings, whenever
you check out that project
or workspace somewhere else.
There's one more thing I
want to talk about today
and that's run destinations.
Run destinations are the devices
on which you can
perform scheme actions.
So, the run destinations we
give you are all the devices
that you want to
build for and run on,
and we let you choose among
all plugged in iOS devices
which are configured
for development,
all available simulators,
and the local Mac.
But of course we'll
only give you choices
of those run destinations which
are compatible with the targets
in your schemes,
Deployment Target setting,
and Base SDK setting.
You can get at the
run destinations
in the upper left-hand corner
of the workspace window,
just to right of
the scheme pop-up.
And if you disclose the run
destination pop-up you'll see
all the destinations that are
available to run on, again,
those that are compatible
with your Deployment
Target and Base SDK.
Here, I have a couple iOS
devices and several simulators.
If you, through the
download PrefPane in Xcode,
choose to install
older simulators
like you install
the iOS 6 simulator,
we'll give you those
choices as well as long
as your target is compatible.
So, you'd also say, you
have to have your target--
deployment target set to 6.0,
and with that simulator
installed now we give you choice
of which OS you want to simulate
when you're choosing
your run destination.
So that about wraps it up
for the fundamental concepts.
We've talked about
workspaces, projects, targets,
schemes, and run destinations.
After today's talk, I hope you
have a few useful takeaways.
You should feel comfortable
navigating
and editing efficiently
in Xcode.
You should know how to
integrate your own documentation
in Xcode's help and code
completion using the
doxygen format.
You should understand how to
customize Xcode's behavior,
so the UI behaves
just the way you want.
You should know how to create
and configure your own
workspaces, projects,
and targets and set their
settings appropriately.
And you should understand
how to manage
and share your schemes
with your teammates.
If you have more questions
I highly encourage you
to contact Dave Delong
who's our App Frameworks
and Developer Tools Evangelist.
We also have documentation
on Xcode
at developer.apple.com/xcode
as your jumping off point.
And if you haven't used it
already the Apple dev forums are
great place to come and
discuss and ask question
about the new versions of
Xcode or existing features.
That's at devforums.apple.com.
We have some more sessions about
Xcode coming up for you today.
I encourage you to take a
look at these and go to any
that strike your fancy.
We've got a lot of great
information for you.
[ Silence ]