[ Applause ]
>> How you guys doing?
Oh, come on.
You guys aren't [noise]
yeah, here we go.
I'm about to say like this
is a 10:15 session, right?
You guys are way more
awake than the 9 o'clock.
All right!
My name is Kevin Cathey, I'm one
of the Interface
Builder Engineers.
And, later my co-worker
Tony is going to be joining
up on stage taking the reins.
And, what we're going to
be talking about today is,
hence the title,
Auto Layout in Xcode.
But before I talk about
Auto Layout in Xcode,
I just want to take a
brief kind of crash course
into what Auto Layout is.
In case you're new to the
technology, new to the platform.
So let's do that real quick.
If I were to define Auto Layout
in a sentence, which I've done,
is that it is a constraint-based
descriptive layout system.
That was helpful.
So let's look at
what that means.
So I have an interface here
and I want to describe it once.
But I wanted to look good in
both portrait and landscape.
So what are some ways that
I can describe the interface
like I have here?
OK. One way I could do it would
be with the Hard-Coded Layout.
But, when I rotate my device,
if I keep my frame origin fixed
like that, you know,
139,270, then it's going to be
in the wrong spot when
I rotate my device.
So clearly, that's
not what we want.
So what's another way that we
could describe this interface?
Well, if I were to go
like to the white board
and like describe it to
someone, I might use terms like,
the control is centered
vertically in my container or,
to fix the distance
from the right edge,
and this is exactly
what Auto Layout is.
What Auto Layout is, is
it's taking this kind
of white board human
readable descriptions
and its codifying them
into these objects
that we call constraints.
Now, what the automatic
part is of Auto Layout is
that you provide the
constraints for us
and then we automatically
determine those frames based
upon the constraints.
Now, this is really
cool and really powerful
for a couple of reasons.
So, like I mentioned, first
of all, it's relational.
I'm just describing it how you
would describe it to someone
if you were just
explaining it to them
in the hallway or
on a white board.
And this relationship-based
layout is also going
to benefit us in other ways
too, especially when things
around us start changing.
This is the fun part
of writing code, right?
So, for example, let's talk
about metrics for a second.
I already talked about
rotation where the size
of container is changing
based upon the orientation
of our device or the think about
screen sizes, the difference
between a retina 3 and a half
inch and a retina 4 inch.
Or as we've been talking
about so far with this WWDC,
the differences between
iOS 6 and iOS 7
where not only do we have
changes in the metrics
of controls like UI
switch and UI slider,
but we also have a great
new dynamic text feature
where the user can
actually change the size
of the font on the fly.
So, using Auto Layout and using
relationships to describe things
like spacings, alignments, equal
sizes, these are the things
that are going to translate
regardless of what the size
of the container is, so
the size of the control,
the size of your contents.
So, let's talk about content.
So, Localization is a really
common place that this comes up.
Now you guys are all
localizing applications, right?
I can just assume you are.
I'll take it by the yes's
in several languages
that you are, great!
If you're not, then this is a
great time to start doing so,
'cause not only it will
benefit you for Localization
but also all of the things
I've been talking about.
So let's talk about
expressiveness.
With Auto Layout,
you can do things
that just weren't
possible before
without writing a lot of code.
And as we all know, writing
code is writing bugs,
less code equals more
awesome most of the time.
So with Auto Layout, you
can express really powerful
relationships, and
if you're using Xcode
in Interface Builder, you can
express these really powerful
relationships again, without
writing a single line of code,
and that is just a huge win.
So, as we've kind of been
saying so far with WWDC 2012,
this is a great time to
start adopting Auto Layout.
And so you might be wondering,
well, how do I do that?
I don't even know
where to start.
So, the first place to start
is with Interface Builder.
If you guys are using Interface
Builder, the first step that I
like to recommend is that
you go in Interface Builder
and you upgrade your documents
to start using Auto Layout
and you add constraints.
Now, let me pause here
and mention something
that I think it's
really critical to talk
about when it comes to some
of these new technologies.
Auto Layout can be
adopted incrementally.
It's not an all or
nothing thing.
You don't have to turn
it on for you whole app,
make it work all at once, right?
We all have deadlines.
And, sometimes the task
of adopting a new technology
looks daunting given a deadline.
But, with Auto Layout and
many of our new technologies,
with iOS 7 and OS X Mavericks,
is that you can adopt them
incrementally, bit by bit.
So, with Auto Layout,
the kind of granularity
for this is per view controller
or per Interface
Builder document.
And you can add just that one
piece in to use Auto Layout,
get it to work and
move on to the next.
You might only get two or
three view controllers working,
the place is what makes the
most sense then say, "You know,
I have to ship," great.
After the release, come
back, and keep moving on.
So I just want to make sure
that's really clear as we go on.
Now, a lot of us do things
outside of Interface Builder
with code, we add
extra subviews,
make little adjustments
here and there.
And this is the last part of
adopting Auto Layout is to go
to those places where you're
adding subviews dynamically
at runtime and you'll need
to update those call sites
to be aware of Auto Layout.
So previously, with the springs
and struts system you would
do things like setFrame,
addSubview, things like that.
You'll continue to
call addSubview,
but instead of calling
setFrame, now what you want
to do is either add constraints
or modify those constraints.
Now, the risk of being overly
complicated too quickly,
I'm going to point out one thing
that I want you to be aware
of as you're adopting
Auto Layout
and this property called
translatesAutoresizing
MaskIntoConstraints.
What this does is it just
tells the system, "Hey,
I want you to help me by
generating constraints
that exactly mimic
the Autoresizing Mask.
So go back to this idea
of adopting incrementally.
In code, you can actually
get down to the level
of adopting it per view.
Now if you want to add your
own constraints, you're going
to want to have
translatesAutoresizing
MaskIntoConstraints turned to
"No," the default is "Yes."
If you use Interface Builder,
don't worry we'll
handle all for you.
But as you're adding
subviews and code,
you want to make sure you
turn that off if you want
to add your own constraints.
All right!
That was like the 3-minute crash
course into what Auto Layout is.
If you want to know more,
if you're still confused
at this point, you can go
check out these sessions
from the previous WWDC, there's
three great sessions here.
So if you're watching
the videos,
hit the spacebar,
go check this out.
If you're in the
audience, well buckle up.
All right!
So let's talk a little
about kind
of how Auto Layout
has come to be.
So you may know in 2011, we
first introduced Auto Layout,
it was brand new for the
Mac, brand new for Xcode,
and it was all about helping you
create Auto Layout interfaces
quickly, with the
Visual Format Language
and with the Interface Builder's
automatic constraint addition.
Now last year, it was all
about helping you build
Auto Layout interfaces
in more places, bringing
Auto Layout to iOS.
Now, it's been really cool
to get to work with you guys
over the last two years.
I've had a chance
to meet many of you.
And man, you guys are
doing some cool stuff,
like some really
custom cool stuff.
I just think it's awesome.
And so, what we're going to do
this year is we want to put you
in the driver seat when
it comes to Auto Layout.
And so, with Xcode 5 where we're
introducing a completely new
workflow for working with
Auto Layout in Xcode,
that will give you both kind
of broad painting strokes
for working with Auto Layout,
but also that really
fine-tune grained control
that will help you
accomplish and build those apps
that are just fantastic.
Now, as we talk about phases
of development, right,
we're adding features
that are going to help you
in every phase of development.
What are some of those
different phases?
Well, we all start here, right?
Initial Layout, and this is
just where you're dragging stuff
out for the first time, you
want to get stuff to show up.
At this point, I mean I'm not
really thinking about rotation
or localization, I'm just
pretty much concerned with--
can I remember how to
connect to a database
and can I populate my UI label,
that's pretty much what I'm
concerned at this point,
and getting things up and
running as quick as possible.
But then, eventually, I
do want start thinking
about how is my application
going to adopt when I rotate,
change devices, change
localizations?
And this is in an
Auto Layout world
where we start adding
constraints.
And then we all go through the
inevitable Debug cycle, well,
except here at Apple 'cause
we don't have any bugs.
No, I'm just kidding.
So we all go through
that Debug cycle,
we identified problems
and fix them.
And then we kind of push
our interfaces often
to this Maintenance Mode, right,
I may make a few tweaks here
and there, but generally we're
not touching our interface
for probably quite a while.
And it's really important
in this phase
that when you're making those
single edits to your document,
that things aren't changing
that you're not aware of.
And this is last arrow that kind
of connects maintenance
and Initial Layout.
And you can think about this
when you start your next version
of your app, you
shift from version 1,
you shift to version--
and I'm going
to start working on version 2.
Your marketing guy comes
in and says, "Great,
let's change the whole thing."
Awesome! So then, you need
a chance and some tools
to help you start over
with some of your layout.
So what Tony and I are going
to show you today is how
with Xcode 5, we've added
features to help you
with each one of these phases.
So what we're going to do
is we're just going to walk
through each one of
these one by one.
So let's start with, at the
beginning, Initial Layout.
Now, again, this is just when
you're first adding views,
positioning, resizing,
I mean the stuff--
you guys got the stuff,
this stuff was easy.
And again, when you're working
in the space, you're not
yet thinking about
how it's going
to react the changes around you.
So, with Xcode 5,
when you add a view,
you get to add constraints
when you're ready.
Interface Builder is not
going to add any constraints
when you first add a view, you
get to decide when that's best.
[ Applause ]
So then, you add a view, you
don't add any constraints,
and you build and run.
Well, what do you
expect to happen?
With Xcode 5, if you
haven't added any constraints
to the view yet, we will at
Build Time add fix position
and size constraints, so
that you can experiment very,
very quickly without
having to think
about constraints again
until you're ready.
Now, what this allows you
to do is this allows you
to separate your Layout
and Interface Builder
with your layout at runtime.
What you are dragging around and
resizing an Interface Builder,
could be independent of how
you're thinking about things
at runtime and then
you get to decide
when you want to sync that up.
You might say, "OK,
I want my constraints
to reflect what I have
in Interface Builder,"
or you might say,
" You know what,
I don't want Interface Builder
to reflect what my
constraints at."
And we've added features that
give you the precise control
over when you want to do that
and how you want to do that.
Now again, at this
point, I'm still thinking
of my interface as
a static entity.
But eventually, I want to start
thinking about how does it react
to changes, and this is when
we start adding constraints.
We've added a lot of new ways
to add constraints with Xcode 5.
And really, I think, the best
way to show you is with a demo.
So let's do that now.
So all the features I'm
going to show you work
with both iOS and OS X.
But what we're going to
do is we're going to look
at just an iOS application here.
And this is an app that you've
seen in a couple of sessions,
I believe, it's our
adventure game.
And what we're going to do is
we're going add a Front End UI
to this to kind of navigate
around some of the things
like a creating a new game,
loading a game, things
like that.
All right, so let's
get started here.
What we're going to do is we're
going to build a splash screen
by adding some buttons here.
So what I can do is I can
just-- here is my library,
I'm just going to drag
out a button and drop it,
and again the first thing you're
going to notice by zooming here
with Interface Builder
is waiting
to add constraints
until I'm ready.
All right, so, my artwork is
going to send me a designer.
My designer is going
to send me some artwork
so in the meantime
I'm just going to fill
in with a background color,
just a placeholder
background color here.
I want to call this,
if I double-click, I
can edit the title.
I'm going to call
this "New Game."
And I can just position
this, resize this,
and it just works
just how I expect.
Again, let's see, load game,
and then the most important part
for us as developers,
the credits.
And then, whoops, I
didn't mean to do that.
And let's resize this, position
them, all right, we're good.
Now, I'm going to
build and run this.
Again, I haven't added
a single constraint yet,
but my document's
using Auto Layout.
And you'll see when I build
and run my application
and it shows up,
it's going to show
up exactly how it looks
in interface builder.
And these are those constraints
that we add at Build Time
so that you can build
run your application
and quickly experiment
with what you're doing.
We'll even tag those
constraints at runtime so that,
if you start getting
log messages and stuff,
you can see exactly what object
what Nib file those constraints
came from right at runtime.
All right!
So you can see the effect
of our fixed position
and size constraints
when I rotate my device.
Well, that's clearly
not I want to happen.
So let's go back to Xcode and
let's add some constraints.
I'm going to show you three
ways in this demo to--
new ways to add constraints.
You've already seen two
of them, and I'm going
to reiterate those first.
Let me stop this.
All right!
So the first way I'm going to
show you is via Control-Drag.
Just like you can
control drag between views
to add relationships like
actions and outlets for views,
now you can control
drag between views
to add relationships
that are constraints.
So hold Control, I
can just could drag
from this new button off
to create a leading
space to my superview.
I'm going to pause again
and point out a few things.
When you add your first
constraint to a view,
what you're telling Interface
Builder is, "Hey, I want to be
in charge of the
layout of this view,"
and now what Interface Builder
does is it starts trying
to help you, by just pointing
things out, and just making sure
that you're getting the
constraints that you want.
So there's two things I want
to point out here: First,
the constraint that I've added,
I've only added one constraint,
and the constraint that
I've added is orange,
which is indicating to me "Hey,
I still have more work to do."
The other that Interface
Builder is doing is,
it's showing me my
Runtime Layout.
Like I said, with Xcode 5, you
can have your Design Time Layout
and your Runtime Layout be
different while you're building
as you get to the
point where you want
to have the UI that you want.
And so, what Interface Builder
is showing me is, "OK, this is--
this big rectangle here is
where my Design Time Layout is,
and this dotted rectangle is
what the constraints would
generate at runtime."
And so what I can
do is if I control
and I got off the right edge,
you can see that it
jumps over that side.
So why is it-- it
actually have a height,
I haven't add any
height constraint,
why does it have a height?
And this goes to one of
the concepts in Auto Layout
that is also really
powerful, which is the idea
of the intrinsic content size.
Most views like or most controls
rather like labels, buttons,
other things like that have a
size that is like they're sized
to fit size, think about it like
the size of the text of a label,
that's a great example
of something that--
the intrinsic content size is.
So from my button, the intrinsic
content size is the size
of the text, New Game.
So in this case, the
height there is showing me,
the height of the string game.
So, Control-Drag is
context sensitive.
So based upon the views I'm
dragging between and the angle
of the line that I'm drawing,
it will give me suggestions.
So if I'm drawing out a vertical
line and some horizontal,
you can see it gives me options
for vertical or horizontal--
vertical and horizontal
constraints.
We have a top space here
and then our horizontal
constraint is centering,
so based upon that line
that I've just drawn.
So I can pick a top
space and then I'm going
to draw one more constraint here
which is the height
of my button.
Now, generally, you do not
want to add explicit width
and height constraints.
If you add an explicit
width or heights constraint,
then as the intrinsic
content size changes,
say when the font size changes
or the string inside
of it changes.
That control will
not change size
so you might get clipped text
or really awkward spaces.
Now I'm adding a height
constraint here 'cause this is a
custom button and
there's artwork
that my designer will provide
for me later, but for now,
I'm just going to add
a height constraint.
But when I got my artwork,
I would probably
want to delete this.
All right!
So just like I can create
constraints between my superview
and across myself, I can also
created them by siblings.
So to do that, I can
control drag from new game
down the load game, and you can
see I get a few more options
here, I get a vertical space, I
get some alignments on the left,
center and right, and
also some equal sizes.
So I'm going to select
vertical space.
That constraint is orange
telling me, I still got to work
to do so I'm going to add
some more constraints.
I can add them one at a time or
I can add multiple at a time.
Before I do that, I'm going
point out something else.
Well, just this little dot
right here which is telling me
that I've already added this
vertical spacing constraint.
All right!
So now I can hold
command or shift
to add multiple constraints
at once.
So I can do left and
right, I can hit return
or just click away, and it's
added those two constraints
really quickly.
And now I can finish off my view
by adding my height constraint.
Great! I've go my two
buttons done here.
Let's talk about the
third button here.
The third button you can
see here doesn't have any
constraints yet, and
it still not kind
of fixed position
and size state.
When you build and
run your application
and Interface Builder adds
those fallback constraints.
If you haven't added any
constraints yet, it's per view.
So you can as you get them
up and running, you can work
on like one part of UI, move
on to the other part of UI,
and work on it again
incrementally.
Now, I can control drag between
all my views to add constraint
which is again a really precise
and quick way to
add constraints.
But right now, I just
want to kind of get more
of a broader paint stroke.
I want Interface Builder
to give me a suggestion
of constraints that
I can work with.
So to do that, I'm going
to use the new Auto Layout Issue
Resolving Menu, and Tony's going
to talk more about this later,
but I'm just going to point
out a few things, so
let's zoom in down here
and I can pop this guy open.
It's got a bunch of
different commands here
for doing larger brush
strokes with constraints.
One of these is reset the
suggested constraints.
That will clear any
existing constraints I have
on just this view, and then
it will add some suggested
constraints for me,
that sounds great.
So I select that, and you
can see it's added the exact
constraints that I would add
with Control-Drag, left, right,
spacing, and a height
constraint, perfect.
That's exactly what I wanted.
And now, we build and run
our application, you will see
that our layout comes up,
looks great in portrait
and in landscape, well, OK,
horizontally it looks good.
We still got to work
on the vertical.
Let's go back to IB and
figure out what we need to do.
We rotate that back,
we write Xcode.
And if I select all my views, it
will show me all the constraints
for those views, and there
is my obvious constraint
that I don't want anymore
which was this top
space to my superview.
I would really like all the
buttons to stay centered.
So, with Xcode 5, it's
very easy to get rid
of a constraint I
no longer want.
I just select it
and hit the Delete.
[ Applause ]
Who knew that deleting
would be so exciting?
All right!
So let's add the constraint
that I actually want
which is our center
vertically in our container.
OK. Now we should be
good if I build and run.
It looks great in
portrait, great in landscape.
All right!
So those are the first two ways
that we can add constraints.
Control drag and the Auto
Layout issue resolving menu.
OK. Now we're going to move
on to a few more interesting
example is we're going
to combine some of the different
techniques, and I'm going
to show you the third way
that we add constraints.
So again, I can control
drag between views
to add the constraints.
I can control drag between
scenes to add actions
and it just automatically
detects the context
and it gives me what I need.
In this case, I want
to add a push segue.
Now, in my new game
view controller,
we're going to add a few
different controls here.
We're going to add one for being
able to select my character
and I want to add one for
adjusting the strategy
that I want, and then I
want a big old play button
so I can start playing my game.
Let's start with the play
button that sounds exciting.
So once again, I'm going to
drag out a button and I'm going
to give it my background
color, my design--
just for right now
until I get my artwork,
which will someday be
delivered by my designers.
I type in play here
and then let's go ahead
and position this,
resize, snap, good.
I'm going to show you the third
way now to add constraints.
Control drag offered you a
precise way to add constraints,
and you can add a few at once.
And then the Auto Layout issue
resolving menu allowed you
to do broader strokes,
and now I'm going
to show you the
constraint-addition popover
where I can kind of do a
combination of all of that.
So down here in the
bottom right of my canvas,
I have my little pin
button, I can select that
and a popover comes up.
And let me kind of
walk you through some
of the pieces of this popover.
At the top, we have
something called "Spacing
to Nearest Neighbor," OK,
what's the nearest neighbor?
The nearest neighbor
is the nearest sibling
in the direction indicated.
So the nearest neighbor
off the left edge,
the nearest sibling
off the right edge,
bottom edge, top
edge, and so on.
If there's no sibling, then
it picks the superview.
So in this case, it's
showing me that it's going
to pick the superview 20 points
away 'cause I don't have any
other siblings, and
so I can just select
that I want these
constraints just
by clicking these
little iBeams[phonetic].
So I want 20 on the leading,
trailing, and bottom edge.
And I can also add a
height constraint just
by checking height.
And then I can go ahead, add
my constraints and viola,
I have my constraints
really, really quickly.
[ Applause ]
But it gets cooler.
So like I said, Interface
Builder,
you can do your Design Time
Layout and your Runtime Layout,
they're kind of--
they're separate,
but when I add constraints
I cannot do both my Runtime
and Design Time Layout
at the same time
and let Auto Layout do
all the work for me.
So I'm going to add some buttons
to select between my archer
or my warrior characters.
Quick poll, warrior or archer?
>> Warrior.
>> Oh, that's why
it's going first.
All right!
So we're going to
add a button here
and warrior will be
our first choice here.
And then I'm going to duplicate
this by this option dragging.
I'm going to call
this my archer.
All right!
So, I want these buttons
to be the same size,
I want to have them to be space,
all space apart, space the--
my container and at the top.
Now I could position and size
these all myself right now or,
again, I can let Auto
Layout do the work for me.
So I'm going to open
up my constraint-addition
popover again,
and these text fields
are editable.
So what I can do
is punch in 20, 20,
20 and what that will do is
it will add a leading top
and trailing constraint
at 20 each.
For both of these, it will
just do it to my container
on the top, and then for
my warrior it will do it
to my superview,
and for my archer,
it will do it to the warrior.
On the trailing edge, it will
do archer to my superview
and warrior to my archer.
Kevin, you say, Kevin,
you're just going
to add two constraints
still in the middle.
When you add constraints using
the constraint-addition popover,
however, we will unique
the type of constraints
so you're only end up
adding one of that type
of constraint when
we go to add it.
Now, I can also say that I
want them to be the same width
and I can also give them a
height so my designer says,
"A hundred," I say, "Sure."
And now, I can quickly
add the constraints button
which will not touch
my Design Time Layout,
I'll just add the constraints.
Or, I can click this nifty
add and update frames button,
it will add the constraints and
then it will size in position
to views in the canvas
to match the constraints.
So I click that, boom!
Constraints and layout
all in one action.
[ Applause ]
And you could see how
this can help you get
through what you're going
for to show quickly.
You can just drag out views.
You don't really need to
[inaudible] their position,
you can add constraints
and let Auto Layout do
that work for you.
It's actually pretty cool.
All right!
So, you might be able to
tell what these pictures are,
but I'm just going to
add some labels just
so that we make sure we know
what we're looking at here.
So I'm going to add
warrior label and position
that right here, and then
I'm going to do my archer.
Let's make sure he's centered.
OK. Now I'm going to
combine techniques here
and show you how you can--
again, you can think
about layout in a way
that you want to think about it.
So I can Control-Drag
between my warrior to my--
label to my warrior image 'cause
I know I want a vertical space.
So I know I want vertical
spaces for both these labels
through their respective
buttons.
Now, I'm having stage fright
so I forget whatever
constraints I need to add.
Never fear, Interface
Builder is here to help you.
So they go to Auto Layout
resolving menu down here.
I'm going to point
out one other command
which is Add Missing Constrains.
What Add Missing Constrains
do is it will only add the
suggested constraints on
top of what you already have
so that my constraints are
no longer orange so that--
the position and the size of
my view is fully specified.
So let's click that,
and you can see
that Interface Builder
has suggested to me
to center X constraints
and that's--
that's exactly what I want.
Now, remember.
Now what you notice again is
that Interface Builder
doesn't give us any width
or height constraints,
and this goes back again
to what I was talking
about earlier
with this intrinsic
content size.
With things like labels that
have text or other things
that have text or content that
you don't want to get clipped,
you want to make sure that
the size is being driven
by the intrinsic content size,
otherwise., when I localize this
in another language and
the strings get really long
or really short, they might
start occluding, overlapping,
and I definitely
don't want that.
So that's why I don't
have any width
or height constraints
'cause that is coming
from the system for me.
All right!
So, that's an example
of kind of mixing,
mixing the different
patterns of approaches here.
And we're going to have
one more piece to our UI,
which is to allow me
to adjust my strategy.
So I'm going to add a
slider that will allow me
to either be weak or slow.
So I got a slider here.
And so based upon, you know,
how I'm feeling that day,
maybe I'm really good
at attacking my enemies,
so I'm going to be
a little stronger.
Maybe I'm really good at
running, I'm probably good
at running away and so then
I can choose to be faster.
So what I'm going to do is I'm
just going to get an initial set
of constraints here so
we're going to go back
to our menu here, and this
is speed key for this,
so you can learn that
and quickly get the constraints
suggested that you want.
And now, I got a
bunch of constraints
so let's go take a look
at what we got here.
And the way I'm going to
show you how to do that is,
in the Size Inspector you
can actually see a list
of all of your constraints.
So if I select the weak label
and open the Size Inspector
and roll over this, you
can see the constraints
that have been added
for this view.
Now, I can see that this
top space here, well,
that's not really what I wanted.
So again, it's as easy, I
can select it in the canvas,
or here I can just select it,
hit delete, and now it's gone.
So what I really want
is for my weak label
to be centered vertically
with my slider, I'm just going
to hold control, I'm going
to drag, and I'm going
to get a center Y constraint
and there now that looks great.
Let's build it and run it,
and see how it looks
after we run it.
OK, wonderful splash screen,
new game, oh it looks beautiful.
Let's rotate it and, well,
that's not exactly what I want.
We don't want that
stuff to overlap.
So I go and tell my
designer, "Hey, Mr. Designer,
this step is overlapping, I
need some more help here."
Now, he gives me one suggestion
which is to change the size
of my images here so I
say, "OK, let's do that."
So I have this two
height constraints, right,
that I've created, and I
can select both of those
and in the Attributes Inspector
I can change the value, he says,
"OK, they have to be
no smaller than 72."
Now I want to make
sure that my--
those two buttons for selecting
my character never clip, never,
never crash my slider or overlap
with my slider so I'm going
to create a constraint between
my slider and my warrior label.
Now, when I drag that horizontal
line, as I got farther
and farther away, right,
it's unclear whether
or not you want horizontal
constraints
or vertical constraints.
So again, based upon that
line or actually in this case,
we'll show you all the options
so that you can quickly create
the constraints that you want.
A little pro tip, if you
want to create both vertical
and horizontal at the same
time, just draw a diagonal line
and then you can select the
constraints that you need.
Now, I don't want it to be a
fixed-- fixed position, right?
I don't want it to
be a fixed space.
I want it to be able to be--
just make sure that they
don't run into each other.
So I'm going to change the
relation of this constraint
from a quality into
an inequality.
So, I can do that by
double-clicking the constraint.
Now this a-- this will be
available in a upcoming seed
of Xcode 5 and I'm going
to show it to you know.
So, by just like double-clicking
on the constraint I can
change the relation from equal
to greater than or equal,
and then for the constant,
I can open this up and I
can picture different kinds
of values here.
I can punch in the value
myself or I can say,
use the standard value or the
current candidate's value.
I'm going to select
standard and what this is
that will give me what the
system thinks is the best
spacing in between
these two views.
So I'm just going to use the
standard space and there we go.
Now that slider should
never get a--
never get occluded
by our warrior label.
Now, I can build,
run and preview this
or I can preview this
right inside of Xcode.
To do that I'm going
to use some--
a new feature of Xcode 5 which
is our preview assistant.
And I love tips and
tricks so I'm going
to keep giving you
guys tips and tricks.
I can quickly get to the preview
edit by opening assistant
or I can select it here.
But what I'm going to do
is I'm going to hold Option
and Shift when I select this.
And I'm going to get a little
navigator and this allows me
to target where I want to put
the thing that I'm opening.
So, this works with anything,
any file that you ever open,
any sort of link that
jumps you and opens a file,
you can hold Option and Shift
and get this little picker.
I can pick a new window,
I can pick a new tab,
I can actually pick other splits
and other tabs that are open.
Now, in this case I'm just going
to say opening the assistant.
And I'm going to select
that and you're going
to see it's open the
same view over here
but now I can change attributes
about this view to preview it.
So for example, I can say,
what is it going to look
like in landscape and
you can see it's clipped.
Now, I'd been thinking to
myself, what does it look
like landscape in iOS 6?
I could change this or using
our little navigation control,
I'm going to open
a second assistant.
So, again, I'm going to come
up here, preview, hold Option
and Shift and then I can
target a new split and enter
and now I'm seeing another
view of the same view.
I can rotate this,
and set it to iOS 6.
And now I can edit in
portrait and landscape
for two operating systems.
[ Applause ]
So, this makes it really easy
to preview what you're doing.
OK, so now I'm going to show
it to you, I'm actually going
to show you one more thing too.
So, I'm actually going
to close the assistant.
We know that there's a problem
here but I actually want
to see this in my main
editor and I actually
with that problem right,
right at my fingertips.
So, to do that, I'm going
to show you what I
called simulated metrics.
And simulated metrics are
just a way for you to kind
of hint the Interface
Builder, hey at runtime.
The stuff around my
ViewController is going to look
like this and that will allow us
to give you a design experience
that matches that environment.
So I can select my
ViewController
by clicking down here.
But I'm going to show
you another tip and trick
and I love tips and tricks
and that's the ability
to select views that might
be occluded in your UI.
So, if I hold Control and
Shift or just Shift right click
over my slider here
and select I get a menu
and this menu shows me
everything under the mouse
at this point in time.
And so you can see I have my
slider, my container view,
and my ViewController and
I can just quickly select
my ViewController.
[ Applause ]
And now I'm going to change
my orientation to landscape.
Again, this is just previewing
it right here and inside
of Interface Builder and there
sure enough, there's the problem
with my warrior label.
And what's happening is all the
constraints that we've added
so far have been required.
And so, you've got
to fulfill this.
So, Auto Layout has followed
your beckoning and it's followed
that but at the cost of
clipping some of my content
and I don't want this.
So, I'm going to show you
one of the powerful things
about Auto Layout which
is called priorities.
Priorities are a way that you
can indicate the preferability
of something.
So, in this case, you know, I
want my slider to be centered
but if it's going
to clip my content,
well that's not exactly
what I want.
So, I can change the priority
of my constraint to be basically
like try to be satisfied
but if you can't be satisfied
then don't worry about it,
just get as close as you can.
So, I can select my slider and
select the horizontal, sorry,
the vertical centering
constraint, open that up.
And again, I can
punch in a value
if I know what priority
I'm going for
but I can also get
some suggestions now
with Xcode 5 by opening
the Menu.
I can choose Required,
High, Low,
or what Interface Builder would
do is actually analyzes your
interface and it looks for
that content which is clipped.
It will figure out which
constraints are involved
in clipping that label
and it will figure
out what priority needs to
be changed on that constraint
so that that label no
longer gets clipped.
And that's exactly what I want.
I select that and it moves
my slider out of the way.
[ Applause ]
And that is a brief look at
adding constraints with Xcode 5.
[ Applause ]
All right, so what did
we see in this demo?
Again, with initial layout,
this is when you're first
adding your constraints
and when you added
view, you haven't added
into constraints yet, it will
add them for you at build time
to fix that position and size.
I showed you three ways to add
constraints, using Control-Drag
for that fine control, using
the Auto Layout resolving menu
for those kind of broader brush
strokes and finally the kind
of combination of all of it
which is this constraint
addition popover.
Now, one of the things that I
did was I kind of waved my hands
over a lot of kind of debugging
and resolving some
of the issues.
So, how do you see
what's going on?
How do you identify those
problems and to do that,
I'm going to invite up my
co-worker Tony and he's going
to walk you through what
that looks like in Xcode 5.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Kevin.
Good morning.
My name is Tony Ricciardi
and I'm also an engineer
on the interface builder team.
So, Kevin just gave you
an overview of Auto Layout
and showed you how you can
get started adding constraints
to your views and
Interface Builder.
Now, I'm going to over the
next step which is debugging
and resolving any issues you
might encounter while designing
your layout.
All right, so as you add
and remove constraints
to your views, your
layout will transition
through intermediate states.
And you can think of this like
you would think of writing code.
If you were to build and
run your app in the middle
of writing a line of code,
it probably wouldn't compile
or even if it did, it probably
wouldn't do what you want
at runtime.
So, in the same way, your layout
and interface builder
won't always be
in a complete state
and ready to run.
There are three different types
of intermediate states
you'll encounter.
First you can have an ambiguous
frame which means you haven't
yet added enough information
to one of your views
to fully specify its layout.
On the other hand, you
can also add too much
in which case you might end up
with conflicting constraints.
And third, you can also
have a misplaced view
which means your view's frame
in the Interface Builder
canvas doesn't match the size
and position.
It's going to have at runtime
based on its constraints.
So, I'm going to into
little more detail in each
of these three intermediate
states
and show you few examples.
And then after that I'm
going to head over to Xcode
and show you some new
features we've added
to help you quickly diagnose
and resolve these issues.
All right, so first we
have ambiguous frames.
You can get an ambiguous
frame simply
by just not adding enough
constraints to your view.
So, if you we take my example
here with my warrior imageView,
I've added three constraints,
one for the top space,
one for the height
and one for the width.
And together these three
constraints specify its size
and its vertical position
but they live its
horizontal position ambiguous.
And you can imagine if I
were to rotate the device,
the system wouldn't
know whether I want
to keep it centered
horizontally or keep
at the same distance
from the left.
Here's a slightly more
interesting example
of ambiguity.
Let's say, now I have two labels
with a horizontal spacing
constraint between them
and I have another
constraint between each label
at the edge of each container.
When I rotate the device,
the total horizontal space
in the container grows and
one of those labels need
to be stretched to fill
in that extra space.
Without any more information
the system doesn't know
which label I want to stretch.
So, my layout is
once again ambiguous.
So you can get conflicting
constraints
by over constraining
your view and it could be
as simple as this example here.
I've added two-- two
height constraints
to my warrior imageView
saying it
to be two different
heights at the same time.
You can also get them in
slightly more subtle ways.
Let's say instead that I
have three constraints,
one for the top space,
one for the bottom space
and then one for the height.
And together they
add up to the--
the height of my screen
in landscape mode but then
when I rotate the device the--
the height of the screen grows
and now those constraints create
a conflict with the screen size.
The third type of issue is
misplaced views and this happens
when you resize or you
reposition your view
in Interface Builder without
updating its constraints.
So, let's say that now that
I have four constraints
that fully specify my imageViews
layout and it's not ambiguous,
it does not have any
conflicts but then I decided,
I really want to have
it centered vertically
in that container.
So, I just drag it down to the
center in Interface Builder
and not it's misplaced because
I still have that constraint
at the top saying it should
be 20 points from the top.
So, interface builder
doesn't automatically update
your constraints.
And that's because it doesn't
know what your intent is.
It doesn't know whether you'd--
whether I want to update
that height constraint
and just stretch it down to the
middle or that I want to get rid
of it and replace it with a
vertical centering constraint.
So, rather than pick one
of those options for you,
it just makes it really easy
to update your misplaced view.
All right, so-- so those were
the three different types
of intermediate states and we've
added a ton of new features
to Xcode to help you quickly
debug and resolve these issues.
And the best way to show
you those features are
with the demo, so I'm going
to head over to Xcode now.
OK, let's start with
top one here.
I'll select and drag
up on its [inaudible].
OK, so when I did that,
a couple things happened.
First I got that dashed
rectangle and it tells me
that my button is misplaced.
And at runtime its
frame is going to be
where you see the dashes.
Also, over here my height
constraint turned orange
and I got this little badge.
So, that tells me that it's
currently 32 point shorter
than the height of the
button in the canvas
and that it explains
why it's misplaced.
I need to update that
height constraint.
So, I could do that by selecting
the height constraint and going
over the inspector and adding
32 points to its value.
But this is a very
common type of operation.
So, we've got a short
cut for doing that.
So instead, I'm going to head
down here, and what I'm going
to do is use this command
here, Update Constraints.
So, this looks at your
selected view, and it looks
at all the constraints
that are touching it,
and it updates their values
to reflect its current
frame in the canvas.
So when I click that, it's going
to update my height constraint
over there, and you can see
now it's no longer misplaced.
All right, let's move
on to the other buttons.
I could follow the exact
same, the back exacts in step,
so I could just resize them and
update their height constraints.
But then I'd have to make sure
I made them all exactly the
same height.
So instead, what I'm going
to do is create an Equal
Heights constraint.
I'm going to Control-Drag down
here and choose Equal Heights.
So, this constraint is going to
make the system enforce the fact
that they all have
the same height.
So, I choose that,
I get a conflict.
The reason why I got a conflict
is I still have this old height
constraint here,
and it's telling me
that it's 43 points tall.
So, now I have that constraint
saying it should be 43 points,
and I also went and added
that Equal Heights constraint,
saying it should
be the same height
as the Top button
which is 75 points.
So, I need to delete
one of these constraints
to resolve this conflict.
I'm just going to delete
that old height constraint
because it's-- I don't
need that anymore.
All right, so I did that.
I got rid of the conflict, but
now my button is still misplaced
because its-- the frame in
the canvas hasn't-- has--
is no longer reflecting that
Equal Heights constraint.
So, I could resolve
this by going
into the button's size inspector
and adding 32 points
to its height.
But again, this is a very
common type of operation,
so we've added another
shortcut for doing that.
And that's over here in
the bottom of the canvas,
back in our Auto Layout menu.
So this time, I'm going
to choose Update Frames.
Update Frames resizes and
repositions your views according
to their constraints,
so it makes their frame
in the canvas match
their frame at runtime.
When I choose that, now my
button is no longer misplaced
and it's resized
just like I wanted.
All right, let's do the same
thing for the Middle button.
I'm going to start by deleting
its height constraints,
so it doesn't-- so I don't
run into that conflict.
And I'm going to
Control-Drag down and add
that Equal Heights constraint.
OK, so now my Middle
button is misplaced
because I have an updated site
and by virtue of growing taller,
it's going to push apart
those other two buttons.
So now actually if I
select these buttons,
you can see they're
all misplaced.
They're all either in the wrong
position or have the wrong set.
So, let's go back to the
menu and update their frames.
This time, I want to
point out the fact
that this menu is
divided into two halves,
so we're zooming down here.
It's divided into two halves.
On the top half, we
have command that apply
to the currently selected
view, and on the bottom half,
we have commands that
apply to all views
in the current scene
in your story board.
So in this case, I want to
choose update all the frames
in my splash screen
view controller.
So that's going to apply
that update frames command
to all three buttons at once.
When I do that, it resizes or
repositions all three buttons,
and now they're not
misplaced anymore.
[ Applause ]
OK, so you just saw a
couple different ways
to resolve misplaced views.
Now, I'm going to move
on to ambiguous frames.
And to that, I'm going
to head over here
to my load game view controller.
OK, so this is a
table view controller,
and it has a prototype cell.
That prototype cell is going
to get reused at runtime
for every saved game
that the player can load.
And the cell has a
couple of labels here,
and those represent the name,
the name of my character
and the date that I last
played with that character.
And when I select these labels,
you can see they currently don't
have any constraints on them,
so at runtime, they're going to
have fixed sizes, fixed frames,
fixed positions and sizes.
So, I want to hit Build and Run
now, and so you can take a look
at this table view without,
before I start adding
constraints.
All right, so here's our splash
screen, I'm just going to tap
on Load Game, and
here's our table view.
And so you can see all the
labels are getting clipped,
and that's because
those static sizes
that we gave them
are just too short
to fit their content at runtime.
So, let's go back to IB
and add some constraints
to let them grow dynamically.
[pause] Let's start with
our date label here.
I'm just going to
Control-Drag over
and add a leading space
constraint, that's just going
to pin it to the left
side of the cell.
And when I did that, it gave
me an orange constraint.
It's orange because my
date label is ambiguous,
and I can also see this at
the top of the canvas up here
in the-- in our mini navigator.
So, this button here
is a mini navigator
and it gives you a quick summary
of all the unresolved
issues in your document.
So when I click that, it tells
me the vertical position is
ambiguous for my date label.
So, that makes sense because
we've only added a single
horizontal constraint.
So, we need to add
more constraints
to fully specify its position.
I could keep adding
constraints to each of my labels
until they're unambiguous,
but instead I'm going
to use another shortcut.
So, when I head back to this
menu, and this time I'm going
to choose Add Missing
constraints
and Load Game Table at the cell.
So, it's going to apply
that same Add Missing
constraints command
that Kevin showed you, and
it's going to apply it to all--
both my labels at once.
So when I choose that,
my constraints turn blue
and you can see now I
have four constraints.
And these are enough to
fully specify the layout
of my two labels.
So, I got a leading
space constraint.
I got a top space constraint.
I got a baseline alignment
constraint that's going
to align the two
labels vertically.
And I got a little horizontal
spacing constraint between them.
So, you might be wondering
why I didn't get any with
or height constraints, and
that gets back to the idea
of this intrinsic content
size that we get from UILabel.
So at runtime, it's going
to infer its size based
on its content and that's
going to let it grow and resize
and our labels won't
be clipped anymore.
So, let's see what
that looks like.
[Pause] All right, so now
our labels are no longer
getting clipped.
The first two cells look
great and the third cell,
I have a character with
a really long name,
and that's just running right
off the edge of the cell,
and it's actually occluding
my disclosure indicator here.
So, what I want to do
is add a little padding
on the right side, so that
that name label gets
clipped before it runs
over in the disclosure
indicator, so let's do that.
All right, so I'll
just control-drag over
and choose trailing space.
And that gave me a bit
more padding that I wanted,
so I'm just going to double
click it and choose 40 points.
So I did that, I
got a new issue.
This is a new type of ambiguity.
And it's ambiguous
because if you add
up the 3 horizontal constraints
we have and the widths
of the two labels,
it doesn't quite add
up to the full width
of the cell.
And so one of those labels
needs to be stretched to fill
in the extra space, and I
haven't told Interface Builder
which one I want to resize yet.
For situations like this when
you encounter a new issue,
and maybe you're not
familiar with it,
you're not sure how
to resolve it.
You want to get some
suggestions on how to fix it.
You can always head over to the
Interface Builder outline view,
and get some information.
So, let's do that.
If you look here by my
load game view controller,
you can see I have
this button here.
And that's-- that indicates
that I have unresolved Auto
Layout issues in that scene.
When I click on that,
the AL view slides over
and I get a list of
the unresolved issues.
Here's telling tell me I have
content priority ambiguity.
All right, and I can find
out what content
priority ambiguity is by--
there we go, clicking
on this button here.
It gives me a detailed
explanation
of content priority ambiguity.
Oh, OK. And here in the second
paragraph, it says to fix,
I need to increase or
decrease the content priority
of my labels.
So, you could think
of content priority
as how strongly a
view wants to remain
at its intrinsic content size?
And in this case, I want my
Name label to get stretched
or clipped more easily
than my Date label.
So, I wanted the content
priority to be lower
than my Date label's
content priority.
If I click on this button
here, it gives me a suggestion
for how I might want
to fix this issue.
So, it's offering to
decrease the content priority
of my Name label.
And wants it to make--
wants to make it lower
than my Date label's priority,
and that's exactly what I want.
So, I'm just going to
choose Change Priority.
And when I did that, oh, you
can see my labels are no longer
marked as ambiguous.
They have blue constraints.
So, let's hit Build and Run
and take a look at that.
[ Pause ]
OK, there we go.
So now, it's getting clipped
with a little bit of padding,
and it's no longer occluding
that disclosure indicator.
All right, so just saw a couple
different types of ambiguity,
and I showed you a
couple of different ways
to resolve that ambiguity.
There's just one more
feature I'd like to show you
which is useful when you
defined your own custom
controlling code.
And so for this example,
let's imagine that instead
of this Date label here.
I want to use my own
custom data control
that I've implemented in code.
Actually, I already have a
scene and the story board set
up that way, so I'm going
to scroll over down here.
OK, so this is the exact same
table view only we have replaced
that Date label with UIView,
and that UIView has
its custom class set
to my date control class.
You can see when I select
it, I already have a bunch
of constraints, and I
can get more details
on those constraints in the
size inspector over here.
And in particular, I want to
point out that it has a width
and a height constraint.
So, earlier I mentioned
you don't want to add--
you don't want to add explicit
width or height constraints
to views that define
intrinsic content sizes
because then you risk clipping
or getting somewhere in padding.
And my date control does define
an intrinsic content size.
However, Interface
Builder only knows
about the built-in
system controls.
It doesn't know about this
intrinsic content size
that I have implemented in code.
And when I delete these
height constraints,
my view is ambiguous because
Interface Builder doesn't have
enough information to know
what it size should be.
So for situations like this
where you know you want
to use information at runtime to
get your intrinsic content size,
you can tell Interface
Builder, it's OK, you don't need
to warn me about an
ambiguous size, and you can do
that by giving in a placeholder
intrinsic content size.
So, I'm going to click on this
button and choose Placeholder.
And now, I've just
told Interface Builder
to use this size as my
intrinsic content size,
and it's OK if I don't have
width or height constraints.
And when I did that,
it's no longer ambiguous.
[ Applause ]
All right, so you just saw
a bunch of different ways,
a bunch of different
tools we've added
to help you resolve
Auto Layout issues.
First, you can use
the canvas decorations
to see how your view is
misplaced or ambiguous
or you can get a quick look
at all the unresolved issues
in your document using the mini
navigator, issue navigator.
If you want to quickly
update the constraints
on your misplaced view
or add constraints
to an ambiguous view, you can
use the Canvas Resolving menu
at the bottom of the canvas
or if you want some more
information about your issue,
you can always head over to the
Interface Builder outline view
to get more detailed help.
So, that wraps up
the new workflows
for Auto Layout in Xcode 5.
Before we finish, I just want
to add one quick note
on compatibility.
So all the features we discussed
today are fully compatible
with any previous OS version
that supports Auto Layout,
or we use these great features,
and you'd be using Xcode 5,
and your Interface Builder
document won't be compatible
with previous versions of Xcode.
If you really need your,
[inaudible] story board
to be backwards compatibility,
you can always downgrade it
in the File Inspector, but
then you won't have access
to these features.
And of course and along with
the new Auto Layout workflows
and of course support for iOS 7,
Xcode 5 brings along
a new readable
and diff-able XML
format for this.
[ Applause ]
If you'd like more information,
you can contact the Dev
Tools Evangelist, Dave DeLong
or you can post it
on developer forums.
We'll be having auto
or-- we also have--
we also recommend you checkout
the Auto Layout related sessions
from last year's conference, or
the Interface Builder session
for this year's conference.
And with that, thank you.