[ Silence ]
>> We have audience
participation.
Look at that!
That's great.
Yehey! [applause]
It's working together.
We have achieved
something here today.
All right.
What's new in iBooks Author?
Great. So today's agenda,
I'm going to give you a demo
of iBooks for the Mac.
It's going to be a
little bit more in depth
than what Craig showed
yesterday during the keynote,
although it showed amazing well.
They were very proud of it.
I'm going to show
you iBooks Author 2.0
as I promised I would do.
And through that you're
going to learn how
to do a few different things.
You can learn how to
create your own templates,
how to build interactive
content.
You're going to discover the
new widgets and learn how
to apply them effectively.
I'm going to show you how
to publish books directly
within iBooks Author.
It's one of the features
we added in version 2.0,
and also show you how to
version your book directly
from within iBooks Author.
And then hopefully along
the way, we're going to pick
up some skills that you
wouldn't have come here
with that will enable
you to create books
in a very efficient manner.
First, a recap.
So we launched the iBooks
Multi-Touch Experience
in January of 2012
with the intent of kind
of revolutionizing textbooks.
And our vision was
that through the iPad,
we could create a
new generation of--
new version of education
materials that did a lot more
than their printed counterparts
by making it a more
multimedia experience,
a more explorative experience
that obviously textbooks can be
in their static guise.
So this is an example of
what our textbooks look like.
You can see they're
very visually rich.
You can't tell here of course,
but they're very
touch-interactive.
These callouts, for example, the
interactive image I can interact
with and explore
different facets
of that underlying
image very easily.
So we've achieved
a few of our goals
that we'd set out to accomplish.
So far, we've got thousands
of textbooks published
to the iBooks store.
We have an excess, I think at
this point, of 22,000 titles
on the bookstore today,
Multi-Touch titles,
which includes publications
from all
of the major textbooks
publishers, Pearson,
McGraw-Hill, Houghton Mifflin,
and a bunch of independent
publishers, you may be some
of them, thousands
of those worldwide.
We've got 100 percent coverage
of the high school core,
common core curriculum
in the United States.
We have over 2,500 classrooms
in the US using these
Multi-Touch textbooks today.
And now we have books
available in the US, in Canada,
Australia, and the UK.
So really proud of our
achievements there.
And here're some examples
of the kinds of textbooks
that are being published today.
Shakespeare like you've
never known it before,
the Shakespearience.
Just give round of applause
for the Shakespeariemce
folks right now.
By making judicious use of media
and interacted experiences,
it allows you to kind of explore
and experience Shakespeare
in a way you never,
ever could before.
The Houghton Mifflin's biology,
Richard Feynman's
Six Easy Pieces,
it's-that's a bald face lie
of a title, but whatever.
Core-- Core Class Life
Science, our course E.
O.
Wilson's Life on
Earth, I could go on.
But in addition to those
educational titles,
we're seeing books in many
other categories find their way
to the iBooks store.
Publishers have found this
platform and are using it
to showcase titles that are from
different categories altogether.
So from Random House, we have
Tyler Florence's Fresh book,
which through interactive
content allows you
to explore these recipes
in kind of a different way.
They've even got smart things
like an HTML widget at the end
of the book that allows you
to calculate the ingredients
that you're going to need
given the number of servings
that you need to serve.
Jessica Alba's lifestyle
book, The Honest Life,
a book she managed to published
on her own despite my
repeated attempt to help her.
The Rolling Stones, 50-year--
50 years of the Rolling Stones,
it's an amazing multimedia
book, a great back scenes,
behind the scenes kind of
view point of the band.
Linda McCartney's photographic,
just published by Taschen,
very happy to see
that get published.
DK, one of our most prolific
publishers with amazing animals,
I think they've got-- well,
over 40 titles now around.
I might be lying about that.
Don't quote me, but
just a lot of titles.
Amongst those other
titles, we have books
that are somewhat technical in
nature which may be the kinds
of things that maybe
you're hoping to do
out there spans the
gamut from, like,
gaming guides to user guides.
Here we have a Canon
Mark 5D user guide.
I see a couple of titles
here that are going
to need updating just
based on revelations
from this very conference,
that guy notably.
But you get the picture.
If you've got something
to say and the materials
to say it with, you can
put a book together.
You can publish to
the iBookstore
and get the message out.
And now, you're not just getting
the message out on the iPad,
you're also getting
it out via the Mac.
So without further adieu, I'm
going to give you a little demo
of iBooks for the Mac.
All right, so this is my
new Mavericks desktop.
I'm going to click the shiny new
iBooks icon, up pops my Library.
Here all the books in my Library
which I can browse a
number of different ways.
It's going to point out the
buttons on the toolbar here
so everyone is familiarized
with the UI.
This is the Store button.
I dare not press it
today for this demo
but when you do click
it, we're shipping--
you'll flip over
to the iBooks store
and you'll get the
complete iBooks experience
and if you shop in context,
the same way you do
within iTunes today.
Next we have a set of tabs
that allows me to kind of look
at my books in a different way.
So I can click on
the collections tab,
see all my purchased books,
see just my textbooks,
see my fiction books, and so on.
I can view by author, I can
view by genre or I can view
in a list view which
hasn't built out yet.
Obviously the books
are all searchable.
I can sort them in
different ways,
can sort them alphabetically
which will make more sense
when I turn on the labels.
You have a number of different
options for viewing your books.
So let's get into one
of our book experiences.
The first one I'm going
to show you is Curiosity.
And this book kind
of exemplifies why we
built iBooks Author.
Because the gentleman
who published this book--
his name is Patrick Lister
is not a book publisher.
[Background Music] He's
not a book designer.
His background is
in engineering,
but he has a fondness and love
for the Mars Exploration Program
and thought he could
showcase it in a book
which he's absolutely done.
And he's created a
beautiful experience.
So there you saw the intermedia
which you may recognize
or remember from the iPad.
When it plays through, I'm
brought to the graphical table
of contents view, it's
exactly the same as the iPad
and it's a good place to call
out evidence that you built
for one platform and you get
the benefit of having it run
on multiple platforms.
So it's going to
work on the iPad.
It's going to work here.
You don't have to
do anything special.
Also the methods of
interacting with the content
on the iPad have transferred.
So here I'm using my Macbook Pro
and I've got a trackpad with it.
So if I want to swipe
through my chapters,
I can just swipe
using my fingers
on the trackpad and away I go.
I can also swipe through
the thumbnails down here
at the bottom, decide where I
want to go and just click there.
Let's start with page 1.
So here, I swiped to page 2.
There's a movie.
[Background Music] I can
play that movie in place.
[ Music ]
I can also expand that movie--
>> It was this really
amazing moment--
>> So it fills the
window if I want to make
that window larger, I can.
That's great.
You'll note here that we've
actually overtaken the
toolbar here.
So it's an edge to
edge experience--
to full bleed experience
for media.
We want it to maximize
the impact
of that media on the page.
When I'm done, I just click
Done and I'm back to the page.
An example of some beautiful
typographic treatment
that Patrick has
integrated within his book,
we're going to replicate
that later
on so I'm drawing your attention
to it, kind of right now.
Next, we have gallery.
You can swipe through the
images of the gallery in place.
I can click on individual
thumbs.
I can go full-screen.
I can do all of that stuff
and you can see the
experiences very complete.
If I pause for a
second, the UI fades away
and then you can really feel
that completeness of the image.
Scanning over on our
pages a little bit.
Here we've got a 3D
element, interact with Mars,
spin it around, which
I love to do
and of course here it's
identifying all the landing
points for the various
rovers and landers
that have spotted
Mars over the years.
Next, I want to show
you an example
of something that's
found on another page.
To get back to the graphical
table of contents view
with the trackpad,
I simply pinch,
same convention as the iPad.
And now I can scan ahead
to the next chapter,
click on the contents
of the next chapter,
and find a page that
I've bookmarked.
Here it is.
So whenever you bookmarked a
page in iBooks for the Mac,
you see a red bookmark
represented on your thumbnail.
So I want to show you this guy
'cause this is an HTML widget
that is really effectively
used and it's a good example
of when you should choose
to use HTML to have kind
of a unique experience.
So here, it's a timeline
of Mars exploration.
So I can actually scroll
down here with the trackpad,
click on an event
in the timeline
or I can use these
little previous,
next navigators to
get to a place.
It's really quite beautiful
and impactful and no reason--
well, they have every reason,
Patrick had every reason not
use a conventional widget
but rather do something
in it's own in this case.
And I hit Escape and I'm out.
So this page is bookmarked.
If I rollover the
toolbar area up here.
You'll see that we have
a few different icons
that appear within the toolbar.
I can see this page
is bookmarked.
If I click the arrow
just to the right of it,
I see that I've got some
other things earmarked.
I'm going to choose one--
actually I'm not going
to choose one right now.
Let me show you the
pop-over widget first.
So, here you can't really
tell but this is more
than just a static image.
Patrick used the pop-over widget
to provide some additional
information about the
where the world's
radio broadcast here.
So, the sidebar widget and the
pop-over widget are widgets
that are great for kind
of condensing the amount
of information that
you get on a page.
So if you have a side story
that you need to tell,
you can tell it really
well using these widgets.
I want to show that
everything is clickable.
You can click on an image,
it's brought full-screen.
You can examine it
in full glory.
Every image that we save
out in iBooks Author is
taking iPad Retina Displays
into accounts which means you
have overhead for users to kind
of zoom in and explore images,
and really get the
most from them.
All right.
So next I'm going
to switch gears
and show you another title.
No, I'm not going
to do that either.
I'm going to search
for something.
So Johannes Kepler,
who had a lot to say
about planetary motion.
In here, I mentioned a sidebar.
This is where I want
to show the sidebar.
So the sidebar here is
a scrolling sidebar,
looks and feels a lot like the
pop-over widget I just showed,
except that always occupies a
place on the page, but again,
a very great way to kind
of collapse information
within any given page.
And now I really will switch
to go show you another title.
So I click this little
Toolbar icon at the left,
it represents the Library
up comes the Library.
I'm going to close this guy.
Now I'm going to show Richard
Feynman's Six Easy Pieces,
like I told you very much a lie.
>> [Background Music] Things on
a very small scale behave-- -
>> All right.
So [inaudible] for
me the experience,
apparently Richard Feynman
was as fond of bongos
as he was theoretical physics.
Who knew? It's the
same deal once you get
into the chapter view, of
course, from scrolling ahead,
there's something I want
to show here in Chapter 2,
and I know I bookmarked
that page.
What I'm going to show you
now is two different guises
of this audio widget, which
is in fact, the media widget.
So here we see the
standard playback control
that you may remember
from version 1
of iBooks Multi-Touch Books.
So this is great for long form
audio if you have something
that users may need to
scrub through or want to zap
to a specific point within.
The scrubber is a great way to
kind of support that activity.
But that's not appropriate
for all audio links.
Here, we have another
version of the audio widget.
It's in the button the mode.
And when I click it--
>> So we gradually try to
analyze all this trying
to put together things which
at first sight look different
with the hope that we maybe
able to reduce the thing
and understand it better.
>> Obviously, you
didn't hear any of that.
But you saw the radio playback.
You saw that it was
giving you feedback
about the length of the content.
And that content was the right--
or this button interaction
was the right way
to represent audio
of that duration.
But what I really
want to show you
in this title are our
note taking features to--
so I'm going to launch our
pop-over table of contents view.
So this is another kind
of table of contents view.
You saw the graphical
table contents view.
This represents all of the
contents of your book as a list
and it's analogous
to the portrait table
of contents from the iPad.
So I can expand in chapter
and click on a location
and I'm brought to that
page within the book.
And you'll note that
down here, what appeared
in this little placard is
basically a kind of snapback UI
or history UI that would
allow me to get back
to my previous location.
So if I'm following a hyperlink,
or exploring something
in kind of a free form way.
I can get back to previous
location very quickly.
But here as I mentioned,
I want to show you our
highlights and notes.
So I have a highlight
and a corresponding note.
If I want to view the contents
of that note, I can click on it
and that note will
appear in place.
If I want to create a highlight
and a note, I can simply draw
out a selection range and then
up will pop this little
highlighting menu, and then via
that menu I can just
hit Add Note.
And there I've added my note.
There's another method
for creating a highlight
in very quick fashion, too.
That's using the
command key as modifier.
It was a shortcut rather.
And with it, I can just
simply draw out my highlight,
click on it again, change the
color, and you get the idea.
Now whenever you
resize the window,
we're trying do a
couple of smart things.
So you'll note that, when the
window is fit to the page size
and it kind of roll
over the margins,
these little page affordances,
paging affordances
appear in the page margin.
If I make the window
just a little bit larger,
you'll see that they actually
appear on the outside,
it will allow me to page.
If I make the window
larger still,
you can see that the notes are
telegraphing that they're going
to appear in the margin for me.
So if ever I need to
review my notes in context,
this is a great and efficient
way to be able to do that.
Then I can simply page through
and view all these
notes in line.
But wait, there's more.
If I make the window
larger still,
you can see that there's a
little page trying to peek
out in the background.
When the window gets big enough,
I get Two Up mode
which is awesome.
And then, of course, if you want
it all, you can have Two Up,
notes in margins and you're good
to go, making really great use
of the Mac's overall resolution
and the ability to
resize windows.
We also have a notes view.
So up here in the toolbar,
you click on the second icon
from left and it will come the
notes view or the notes panel.
And within it, I have--
or can see all of the notes
across all the chapters
in the book.
Only those chapters that
have notes are represented
in this view.
But if I want to quickly find a
note, I can scan to a location,
click this button, and,
of course, that page,
and I click this button, of
course, it's only one page away.
I will click this button
and boom, I just warped
to another part of the book.
All together, if I want to edit
a note in place, I can do this.
And I'm good to go.
And then, if I want to get
back to the previous location,
where we were before, I
click on that and there I am.
Finally, when it comes
time to review my notes
and to study the contents
preparing for a test,
we brought over the study cards
that you may remember
from the iPad.
So here's a set of study
cards that are derived
from my highlights and my notes.
There are no glossary
terms defined
for this particular book.
But if they were, they
would appear here in line
with my own notes
and highlights.
But in order to move through
the cards, I can simply swipe
with the track pad,
click to flip the card.
I've heard it said a number of
times, but I wish I had this
if when I was in school
about 20 years ago.
You can also filter these down,
so it's just your glossary terms
or highlights of any given
color, a very powerful tool
for studying and we think this
is going to be a great boon
for students who used their
Mac in studying contexts.
So that's it for our tour
of iBooks for the Mac
and to switch back to my slides.
So all of that content was
enabled with this tool,
iBooks Author, textbooks, cook
books, photography anthologies,
anything that is visual
in nature is fair game
for iBooks Author and
anything that could be extended
with media is also fair
game for iBooks Author.
So what is it?
Well, it's a tool for creating
exactly that kind of content,
it's a WYSIWYG in dragg-and-drop
editor, we try and stayed--
we stayed very true
to those kind
of interaction principles
throughout the system
and all the workflows
it supports.
So with those paradigms in mind,
you can write edit
and import text.
You can add graphics, you
can customize page layouts,
you can make the thing look and
feel exactly as you need it.
You can also create these
interactive experiences using
basic media like
images, video, and audio,
just using basic drag
and drop techniques.
It works for single publishers.
It also works for professional
publishing pipelines
where you have many
users collaborating
around a single book.
And probably, the
biggest incentive this,
of course, it's free.
We're not asking you to
shell out lots of cash.
We are however asking you to
publish to the iBooks store.
So please do that.
Why would you choose to use
this particular platform
over other competitive
choices that you may have
and that are open to you?
Well, you can create these
immersive iPad experiences
without code and
these are experiences
that are designed for the iPad.
So all of that work and
thought and experience
in designing the iPad itself is
being translated directly here.
So when we design a widget, you
can be assured that you're going
to get a very equality
experience at the end
when the users actually
interact with your content.
But we provide flexibility
for you to go out on your own
and create these great
unique experiences
like the timeline I showed
you from Patrick Lister's book
when you need to, just
using HTML widget and HTML5.
As I mentioned, it's designed
to work perfectly on the iPad.
But now, of course,
the Mac create--
wants published in
many places or have it
to be consumed to many places.
You get true layout and type
setting, so things looked
like real books but they
feel like something else.
They feel like something
it's truly interactive.
And the sum-- total of which
leads to this statement,
which is bold, but
it is my opinion.
It's the best platform
for creating interactive
media rich books,
that's out there today.
You can't do it with ePub.
You can't do it with PDF.
Of course, not in the way that
you can with iBooks Author
in the .ibooks format.
So what's new in
iBooks Author 2.0?
What kind of stuff
you're going to see today?
We introduced portrait-fixed
layout books.
Our first version of the books
where in a landscape flavor,
there was a portrait
flow mode that was kind
of an optional mode that was
enabled by turning the iPad
into a portrait orientation.
But now, portrait-fixed layout
books, you can layout something
that fills a lot
more like a book.
We have introduced two math
typesettings using LaTeX
and MathML.
We are optimizing
media automatically.
So when you drag in a piece
of media, you don't have
to precompress it, we're
going to do that for you.
We're also going to transcode
it to the right format.
So you don't run in any
glitches when you're uploading
to the iBooks store and your
content will get refused
as a result.
We've got new widgets, I
showed you the pop-over widget,
I showed you the
scrolling sidebar widget,
and the new audio widget modes.
The enhanced publishing workflow
with the support for versioning
which is very important when
you want to update your book.
Basically, we're trying
to transform people's--
I don't want to say it--
understanding of books and
make them feel more evergreen
in nature.
So like apps can be updated on
an ongoing basis and content
and new value can continue to be
added to your-- for your users.
You can do that now
with iBooks books.
And we also now support embedded
font, so you really can get
that crisp, custom look
that you're looking for.
All right.
So now on to part 2.
Let me show you how to
build this great stuff using
iBooks Author.
Now there are few points I
want to leave you with today.
Probably, the most important
of them is this, when you sit
down to write your book
or compose your book
within iBooks Author, you
really should have written your
book first.
You can sit down and
start typing away
and you can craft your book.
And you'll get there and
you'll be able to do it
with little difficulty, but it
won't put you on the great place
to make changes down the line.
So what we recommend to do
is that you do two things.
You write your book
first, your write it
with your interactive content in
mind to know what you want to do
when you sit down to compose
with in iBooks Author.
And then finally,
we ask that you--
or recommend rather that you
build your template first.
Building your template will
allow you to make those kinds
of changes late in the editorial
process when you need to.
It will help support multiuser
or collaboration workflows
when you're working with
many people, you know,
just make your life a
lot easier, trust me.
So our content here that
I'm choosing to replicate is
that Curiosity book
that we'd shown.
So in order to replicate
it, I'm going to try
and find a template here
that roughly approximates
Patrick's look and feel,
nothing is identical to it.
So up here, we have a collection
of landscape templates
which I can choose.
Down here, we have the
portrait fix layout templates
which we introduced
with version 2.0.
It's a landscape book
that we're going to create
and this is the template we're
going to chose to create it.
So when you launch a template
we're putting you in a place
where if you want to start
creating your book, you can kind
of just get under way and
start building things.
We're not going to do that
right here now that we're going
to build our template
first as I recommended.
But first, let's take a look
at the UI of iBooks Author.
So if any of you are users of
Pages, Keynote, or Numbers,
do we have those users out
there, are they out there,
and so we'd like to see.
This is going to
feel familiar, right.
It's the same framework that
you recognize from those tools.
Not only as the UI
framework the same,
the underlying objects
are the same.
So when you create a table
in Numbers and you paste it
in here, you're getting that
table, we don't support things
like computation
within those tables,
but the table will come over.
If you create graph,
any graphic elements,
in any of those applications,
you can copy and paste them here
and stuff, is just
going to work.
So going left to right
across our toolbar,
if you want to add
content to your book,
you do it by the
Add Pages button.
And as I'm rolling over
these different objects,
I'm seeing a bunch of layouts
that correspond with
these objects.
These objects are also
describing the structure
of an iBooks book.
At the highest level of the
book, there is the chapter,
beneath the chapter,
there's the section,
a section contains pages.
So here's the chapter,
it's top to your item,
second to your section,
and then finally,
discreet page layouts
which I can apply.
Be delving into that
further in just a little bit.
Next up, the View switch,
used this to turn on
or off different user interface
elements within iBooks Author.
So for example, if I
wanted to change my sidebar
to an outline view, instead of
thumbnails, I could do that.
I could turn on or off the
Format bar, but I'm going
to turn that on because
that's actually going
to help us edit more quickly.
The Orientation switch
which allows me to switch
between the portrait flow mode
that is used only on the iPad,
it's not used on iBooks
for Mac in landscape.
We won't go into that today.
I'm not going to touch
on anything having to do
with portrait flow
mode here today.
But if-- should you
want to learn more,
I recommend going back to
last year's session where I go
into great detail about how to
work with portrait flow mode,
that's available online
in the developer website.
Next up, we have a
graphic create tools,
I need text, I add a text box.
If I want to add
a graphic shape,
I can have a graphic shape,
create a table, add a chart,
you can add any of the numbers,
any of the widgets
that we shift with.
Here they are all nine of them.
I can preview.
I'll show you how to
preview a little bit later
and I can also publish,
we'll be going
through the publish
workflow in a little bit.
Finally, there's the Inspector.
Well not finally.
We also have the system edit
panels, font color and media.
We won't use those.
But the Inspector
is very important.
The Inspector is the thing that
used to edit the attributes
of any object that you
select within the canvas.
So when you're composing
things right here
and you're editing things and
you're moving stuff around,
this is where you edit the
attributes of the said things.
So it's good to get
to know the Inspector.
Now to round out our tour,
over here we have the sidebar,
it's got some special
nodes contained within it,
the top most node is our cover.
This is where we can
compose and build our cover
that will get shift out when
we go to publish our book.
And we have a spot
for Intro Media,
so that splashy video intro that
you saw for both of the books.
This is where you would add it,
just by dragging in a movie.
We have the table of contents
authoring environments,
so you can build out your
table of contents here
and create a custom
look and feel for it.
And then finally, we
have the glossary.
All right.
So let's get start--
started building.
I'm going to open another
document just for reference.
So just to remind myself,
what Patrick's book looked
like I'm going to call this
up from a time to time.
Now I should make
that a lot smaller.
All right.
So this is an example
of this very same page.
It's similar and that is
got a very full-bleed image,
but the title is
completely different.
It's got this background
element here.
We don't want any of that.
So let's go edit
it away right now.
So the first thing I'm going
to do, just because, you now,
it's my book, I want to see
what it feels like a little bit.
I'm going to drag in my
image from my chapter
and that kind of feels good.
I'm going to edit the
title, OK, the long--
Great. So it sort of feels like
my book, but not close enough.
In order to make it really look
like the book, I'm going to have
to change the layout that
this page references.
So to view my layouts, you
can do one of two ways.
You can go to the view menu
where I told you, you can turn
on or off different UI
elements and go show layouts.
Or you can simply
split this bar down.
It's just living behind
your page thumbnails.
And this little check
mark indicates
that this is the layout
that's being utilized
for this very page right now.
But there are two pages
associated with chapter
and section layouts and
I'll explain what they are.
The first page is
always the splash page.
It's the visual thing
that identifies an incoming
chapter or a section.
And then, the second page
is a body page which is used
to create all of the text
pages within that chapter
or section as the case may be.
So when you import text and
random pages are created
for you automatically, that's
the page that's being reference.
Well, here's a layout that
looks a little bit more
like the one we want.
I'm going to actually
apply it right now.
Looks a little bit better.
It's still not the
thing that we need.
So I'm going to edit
the contents
of the layout right now.
So in the Inspector,
I'm going to switch
over to the Layout tab.
And within the Layout tab,
I find the attributes
for layout objects.
Layout objects are anything
that lives inside your layout.
When I select this background
image it tells me a few
different things about
what it set up to do.
So this first check
box enables the--
well, me as the book creator
to basically edit this
content on the page.
If didn't check this box
and I apply these changes,
I would be unable to edit
or modify or even select
that thing anymore on the page.
So I'm just going
to undo that change.
It has a special tag.
This main image tag is what
we used to identify images
that will also be used in
the table of contents view.
So follow me just for a second.
If I switch over to the
table of contents view,
you can see that two
things have happened.
The background image
that we have supplied
for the chapter was used here
and the title that we entered
onto the chapter head
page is also being used
in the table of contents view.
So you might be asking yourself,
how do iBooks Author know
to make that the
title for the chapter?
It knew to make that the
title for the chapter
because it was using something
called a section title smart
field which this thing is.
It has a telltale visual
cue which is kind of hard
to see here in this display
or in this composition.
But basically, it's
a blue outline
that surrounds that word.
And what this field is used to
do is basically name the thing
that it's currently applied to.
So what we're telling
the smart field to do is
to name every chapter
it's applied to,
it either reflects the name
if you put it in somewhere
or it allows you to edit
the name directly in place.
So when I went and
edited the name here,
that's how it got all the way
over to the table
of contents view.
And if something goes
wacky in your setup,
and you should accidentally
delete this thing
and delete the other
thing, don't freak out.
You can very easily
create another one by going
to the insert panel and
selecting section title
and you're often
running yet again.
What we need to do here,
I'm going to preserve those
elements is restyle these
things, so it looks a little
bit more like Patrick's design.
He used the Avenir font,
it's going to very quickly
select the Avenir font.
And he used basically one
lockup for the chapter
and the chapter numbers.
I'm going to delete
the second thing here.
And then, I'm going to
insert another smart field
which we called the section--
numbering smart field.
The section numbering smart
field is a dynamic thing,
but you don't edit things in
it, it just reflects the title
or the name of the thing
and the number of the thing
that it is applied to.
So if I insert section
number here,
it comes up by default telling
me, "Hey, I'm Chapter 1."
But I just want it
to be a number.
So I say, hey, give
me the number only.
And then I believe Patrick
had this as an orange element,
I know full well, he
did, blind you guys.
I've applied the changes
and that we have something
that looks a lot more like
what Patrick had in his book.
So we've just finished
editing our chapter head page.
Now the body page has a
couple of different things.
You can't really
see it right now.
Down here, we've got
a page number element
and up here we've got
the body text container
which you can't see.
Now Patrick's pages
featured a black background,
I'm going to create one here by
simply adding a graphic form.
You can't see what
I'm doing here.
I'm using a hotkey to push
this object into the back.
Now I'm going to just
make the body text white.
So we can see it.
And now we have edited
the wrong thing.
That's OK.
Did anyone see me
making that mistake,
hands up if you saw me
making that mistake.
That's good eyes,
good, thank you.
Call it out next time though
'cause I get really farther.
Let's copy and paste that
stuff, add text container
because that guy
won't come over.
All right.
Now we're back on track.
OK. So we now fully edited--
sorry, don't get
confused by that again.
I was going to delete him so I
can't make the mistake again.
We've now fully edited
that body page.
So if the chapter needs to
create pages, it can do so.
And they're going to look
exactly like we need them.
Next up, we're going to
create the section page.
And one of the benefits of
working with the templates
that we've provided
as the iBooks group is
that we have done all of the
thinking around, you know,
what's the best point
size for the iPad,
what are the best page
layouts for the iPad
that give the right
proportions of white space
to the actual text content.
So it's in your best
interest that kind of work
with the layouts that we
provide and customize them
in exactly the way that
I'm showing right now.
We do this because we don't want
you putting unnecessary effort
if you are a real book
designer and you want
to completely custom, you
can go ahead and do that.
But for the rest of us,
it's nice to have
these starting places.
And that's the setup for
me saying, "Hey, don't go
and rebuild a section
from scratch the way
that we just did the chapter."
If you want to create
a new section,
you can just duplicate the
thing we've already created
which has most of the stuff
that we need and drag it
over to the section layouts area
and now we have a
new section layout.
We don't need this thing.
We will need this thing.
And we're going to need another
one of these black things.
And there you go.
Now the only problem with this
is, it's currently setup is
that that chapter-- that section
numbering field that we set up,
is currently pointing at
the chapter we want it
to actually point at a section.
So we can double-click to
edit it, specify section
and we're pretty much
good to go at this point.
Now, I'm going to remind us
again what Patrick has done
in other areas of the book.
I think, I can actually
tour that guy down.
He has these large
quotation-- sorry--
he has these quotations that are
rendered in large or in text,
orange text, do you
remember that when I showed
that in the original
run through.
I'm going to go very
quickly create that text box
to contain that quote.
But I chose a ginormous
point size.
That's pretty ginormous.
Maybe not that ginormous,
a little smaller.
There you go.
To make sure that
we can edit it later
when we're actually
composing the pages,
I mark it as editable.
And I'm going to
give a custom tag.
Now the benefit of using tag
is that when it comes time
to switch out layouts, if
you got multiple layouts
that can all be applied
in similar content.
If you tag things the same
way throughout the layouts,
they'll actually inherit the
contents between the layouts
which is kind of nice.
And then finally, there's the
attribution which I'm not going
to bother adding right now
'cause I want get underway
building our book.
But we're basically done.
We've created two layouts now
that through which we're going
to be able to compose
the rest of our chapter.
So now I can go to
our add pages menu,
add our new section layout.
Actually, I'm not
going to do that.
Do something even better.
I'm going to bring in the Pages
document that contains all
of my text for this chapter and
just drag it into the sidebar.
When I do, iBooks Author
prompts me to choose a layout
and in this way it tells iBooks
Author what level this content
is going to live at.
We want this to be a section.
It's a little bit different
from Patrick's book.
He only had chapters, but
I want to show a little bit
of the book structure
and hierarchy here.
Note also this check box.
If you have crafted--
and many people do this,
painstakingly so, if you
crafted paragraphs styles
in your document that you
want to preserve, you're going
to want to check this box.
And when you do that, all
of the incoming paragraph
styles will merge
with the paragraph
styles from the template
and you'll have them, but we're
also smart enough to recognize
when they've been
named the same.
So you won't have
duplicate paragraph styles.
We'll just keep the
ones that are incoming.
So there you have it.
We've created a run of pages all
from the layouts
that we just created.
I'm not sure how long it took
us to create those layouts,
but something in the
order of 10 to 15 minutes.
And you would also want to
create some custom page layouts
which you could apply
to your book throughout.
That's going to take
some additional time.
But suffice to say, you can do
this kind of thing very quickly.
So I'd embedded the quotations
that we need here over there.
Copy that text and just
paste it, I should have done
that attribution
as another element.
Forget that.
We're going to name
this section.
So great, it's named
on the page.
But as I mentioned, because
we're using those naming smart
field, I'm actually identifying
the components of my book.
So now if we switch back to
our table of contents view,
we can see that we have
three sections created
within our chapter, the first
of which I've actually named.
Did I actually do that?
No, I didn't.
I fell into a trap of my--
literally my own design,
literally my own designs.
It's-- I'm not proud
of this fact.
OK. So if you should see that
that blue line has gone away,
it's evidence that you've wiped
out that section
naming smart field
and you need to recreate it.
So I've just undone
that mistake.
And now we see that the thing
is kind of correctly named
and I also undo that resize
there, but there you go.
Now while we're looking at
the table of contents view,
this is the area where you can
obviously customize the table
of contents experience.
The only caveat being that
what you do for one chapter,
you do for all chapters.
So if I'm going to
delete this background
and then restyle my text and
do whatever I needed to do,
it has to work for all of
the chapters of my book
because it's going to
be shared amongst them
when the user is swiping
through in the graphical table
of contents.
The next thing that
you're going to want to do
to define the structure of
your book is through something
that we call semantic
paragraph styles.
So books have subjects
or headings contained
within things like chapters.
And you want to identify these
things to iBooks Author so that
when the user searches
for them in the book.
We can bring them
to the right place,
the places that matter--
that matter most.
There are three components
to any templates.
There're the layouts that
are contained with in it.
There are the object styles
that are preserved within it.
And then there are the
paragraph styles that it owns.
If you want to view the
paragraph styles for template,
you can do one of two ways.
You can click to view the
paragraph styles drawer
and here you can
see them all here.
Also your character styles and
list styles are preserved there.
So I'm going to apply the
heading one, paragraph style
to this text and
it's been adopted.
The font is incorrect,
so I'm going
to change it, Avenirs
I did before.
Make that a little bit smaller.
And now what we'll see--
see this little red arrow in
the paragraph styles drawer,
this indicates that
the paragraph style
that that text think it--
thinks it is, is different
than what the text
actually is right now.
We've overwritten
that paragraph style.
If we want everything to
have this new paragraph style
that we just defined, we can
select this via that menu,
redefine style from selection.
Now every time we come across
a heading that we want to apply
that style to we've got the
new style and that's great.
All right.
So how about the
interactive stuff,
we've got some content
over here.
I'm going to close my
paragraph style drawer first,
bring in some new content.
The first and most basic
of the interactive elements is
the simple and humble image.
And insert a page
break here quickly,
so we're just looking
at that image.
This image, we know
it's special,
iBooks Author doesn't
know it's special.
The way that you
make this special
so that people can actually
interact with it is you go
over here to the Widget
tab in the Inspector.
And within this Widget tab,
you'll find the attributes
of interactive things.
So there are two ways to make
this thing actually interactive,
you can add a title
to it or a caption
and that's evidence enough
that you think this is special.
So when a user taps on it, it's
going to go full-screen for them
or go to the expanded state.
You can also just check this box
which is make zoomable
in iBooks.
So if you didn't have a title or
caption, you can check this box.
And then, when a user clicks
or taps on that thing,
they'll be able to see it in
kind of an expanded state.
But I'm going to leave the
title and caption there.
Next up, I'm going
to show you another
of the version 2.0 features
which is our support
for LaTeX and MathML.
So in order to do that, I'm
going to place my cursor here,
you access the equation
input user experience
through the Insert panel,
I'm going to insert equation
and up will pop our
Equation Editor.
And I hope to God, I can
remember this equation.
So for circular pads,
the equation is something
like 2 [inaudible] 3.
There you go.
You can see this preview area
that I've successfully
entered an equation.
My mother would be
very proud of me.
If you edit it in such a way
that the equation
becomes invalid--
we just redo what I've done--
like put the hat without
completing that statement.
You can see it, it shows
as an invalid equation.
But once it's done,
I can insert it.
This is proper text.
I can edit it.
I can give it a new size.
I can send or justify it.
So real math type setting
now within iBooks Author,
also works for MathML.
Trust me. I'm not going to
show you that right now.
Next up, I want to show you
the scrolling sidebar widget.
I mentioned that's a
great way to do something
like tell a historical
aside like I'm going
to do for Johannes Kepler.
So this is very simple, just
drag in some text, boom;
drag in an image, double boom.
He's not a very happy looking
man, but he was brilliant.
You can also style this.
It's a graphic object like
any other graphic object
within iBooks Author.
So if I want to give this
a black background fill
and make my text white like the
rest of my content, I can do so.
So there you have it.
There's the scrolling
sidebar widget.
Now finally, I'm going to add
one more page which I think,
just going to add a blank page
here and add a final widget.
It's going to be the timeline
widget that we saw before.
Now the timeline widget is a
full-screen-only experience
which means that you have to
tap on the element that's shown
on the page before you can
interact with the HTML.
You can, however,
preview HTML most
of the time within
iBooks Author.
I can't do with this widget.
But if you hit Edit HTML,
you're brought to an environment
where you can actually
preview the HTML.
It's not going to work, as I
mentioned, for this widget.
You click Done when you're done.
But there's our HTML
widget in place.
Now that's our first section
of three sections built out.
I can go-- click back to
the table of contents.
Say yes, everything is
going according to plan.
I'm going to paste in our quote.
I expect you're following
along now.
So I'm going to move
a lot more quickly.
Choose that heading style that
we applied or that we created.
Oh, did I actually
ever prove to you
that we were doing something
special with that heading style?
>> Yes.
>> Did I? OK.
Did I switch over to
the sidebar to do that?
[Inaudible Response]
>> Thank you.
So let's switch to
the outline view.
You can see here,
that's the evidence
that those semantic paragraph
styles are doing their job.
So when I go to that
table of contents view,
the pop-over table of contents
view in iBooks, I'm going to see
that stuff listed there
and that's the way
that it gets there using that
semantic paragraph style.
Thank you, phantom
voice from the audience.
>> You're welcome.
[Laughter]
>> All right.
So let's add some more
interactive stuff.
We're pressed for times.
So I'm going to do this quickly.
Next up, we'll set a movie,
it's very easy to do, right?
If you got a movie,
slam it in there.
The attributes for
the movie are limited.
I can click over to
the Widget tab and see
that I have the option
to show these things.
The thumbnail-only which means
it would be just stay proxy
on the page, and
I'll click that proxy
and the movie will only
play in full-screen.
But we want it to play in place.
I can also choose the
poster frame that I want.
That's exciting enough for me.
I can choose looping
options for it.
I don't want the movie to loop.
It's a rather lengthy
movie, why would it loop.
But there I'm done with it.
Next up, I'm just going to
insert another page break
to this content appears
over there.
And I'll show you how to
configure an audio widget.
So here we have a little
audio snippet from, I believe,
the mission control commander
for the Viking missions.
He's very excited about
observing the first image
from Mars ever which this is.
Actually, it's pretty amazing.
>> How do you possibly
describe the first photograph
that a human being has ever seen
from the surface
of another planet?
>> I would say it's kind
of contrasty and maybe,
framing's not great,
but whatever.
I mean, you know, at least
proud of, you should be.
So that the way that you
define what the audio is going
to represent itself as
on the page is, again,
in the Widget tab, I can choose
to make that scrubber if I want,
but it's better left a button.
I can also make it an image.
If I wanted this whole
surface to be a tappable thing
that would play that audio
clip as Patrick has it,
I could just say,
make it an image
and then delete that image.
And now we have a clickable
thing that will play
that audio clip when the user--
well, I'll deal with that--
selects it on the page.
So not a beautiful layout there
but you kind of get the idea
and also that I'm trying to
move very quickly through this.
Galleries-- Galleries are fun.
They're probably
one of the best ways
to make your content more
interactive as evidence
by the Feynman book which
is basically just a bunch
of audio clips and images.
You know, that's all it takes
to make the experience
truly engaging.
And in case of the Feynman book,
Caltech just had all the stuff
in the archives resurrected
and give it kind of new life
by combining it with, you know,
Feynman's magnum opus
of Six Easy Pieces.
And it's pretty amazing what
it does, just through the use
of simple and basic media type.
For the gallery, you can
go to the pedantic route
of adding the gallery and
dragging the images in
or you're just drag
in the folder and,
boom, you've got gallery.
It was a folder of
images if you had a folder
of Word documents you
wouldn't have been happy.
But you can see as I'm
resizing that gallery
and making it fill the page,
that the imagery is
doing the right thing.
So we're always kind of
maximizing the content
within the available space
within that canvass space.
If I need to reorient or
reposition something on a kind
of a per image basis, I can.
But I'm pretty happy
with the way that looks.
So I'm going to leave it there.
3D content, we support 3D that
is rendered out using a kind
of standard file
format known as Collada,
it's an interchange format.
It doesn't do a lot.
But it does allow all of your--
all of the conventional 3D
authoring tools to export models
that you can use here
in iBooks Author.
This one doesn't have
a great background
for it, let's start white.
It's not going to work for
us, I'm going to quickly make
that black and it's good.
One thing I have to
show you before we wrap
up this interactive image.
So let me just create one here.
I'm not going to go to the
other section to do that.
Now, the interactive
image is one
of our most favorite widgets.
It's the one that allows you
to kind of create these very--
it's a very engaging
experience just around photos.
And what you do is
you set up callouts
to identify features
within the photos.
So I've just inserted
the interactive image.
I'm going to drag over an image.
There it is, all of the lunar
exploration rovers are there.
The little one kind of looks
like the Tech Droid
from Star Wars.
Am I allowed to say that?
I'm probably not
allowed to say that.
I said it.
In order to define a
kind of special region
within this image, I
can select the callout.
This is already got kind
of a zoom set up for it.
But I'm going to bring
this callout down here.
At least [inaudible], kind
of zoom in a little bit.
And now we've set a
view for the Sojourner.
So we can go from our
default view to that view.
So we've got a nice
interpolation.
In the interest of time,
however, I'm not going to set
up all of these callouts.
Let's just do two.
Zooming a little bit, set
the view, and now we're done.
We've set up our
interactive image.
So two things very
quickly, pop-over widget.
The pop-over widget is
a great way to supply
that secondary information
when you want the user to kind
of guess what the contents
maybe or be surprised
when the contents are revealed.
To create it, I insert one.
I drag over an image
that I want to use.
Actually, I don't want
that one, I want Sojourner.
I drag over the image that
I want to serve as kind
of the tap target, the thing
that the users going to interact
with to pop the pop-over.
I can double-click it.
There's my pop-over.
To populate it, I mean,
just drag in text,
drag another image element,
position it where I want it.
Sort of kind of-- sort
of kind of-- there we go.
Boy, it's really twitchy.
There you go.
And there we have it.
And then finally I'm going to
add a Keynote which I was hoping
to be able to show you how
to build yourself right now,
but we won't be able to do that.
After a moment of
processing that file,
keynote is actually being
prompted in the background
to create a lightweight
version of the presentation.
In order to make this look a
little bit better on the page,
I'm going to use another great
feature for reducing content,
a footprint on your pages
and that is Show
Widget As Thumbnail.
And when you click Show
Widget As Thumbnail,
that experience will be
represented by a proxy element
that you're going to tap
on before the user
goes to full-screen.
And I'm going to customize that
tap element just by dragging
in an image that I want
to service my proxy
and then I'm pretty much done.
Now two more things
before we go.
When I get to this point, I
want to understand how this--
how this-- what the end user
experience is going to be.
So I'm going to need
to preview it.
In version 1, we were able to
preview with an attached iPad.
I'm going to show you
something that nobody knows yet.
And I'm not going to
claim that we're going
to ship it anytime soon.
But I have a special build
of iBooks Author here
that will allow me to preview
to iBooks for the Mac directly.
So here I can click Preview,
iBooks Author kindly reminds me
that I can't see portrait flow
mode within iBooks for Mac.
But once it builds its
preview, we should see our book.
So here's the Keynote widget
that I was going to show you how
to create, but didn't.
Our pop-over widget with a
bit of blown layout there,
our interactive image,
and so on, you get it.
So all of the elements are here
and previewable within iBooks.
Again, I can't say when
we're going to ship this.
But we absolutely will.
Now when it comes
time to finally--
to shift your book
to the iBooks store,
you can do that directly
within iBooks Author.
So I have another file
here I'm going to open up.
I mentioned that iBooks
Author works in kind
of multiuser contexts.
So what you do in that case
is you have someone build
the chapter.
And you're like, "Great,
you got your chapter."
I'm like, "Yeah, I do."
You go, "OK, you
copy that chapter."
And then you simply paste
it where you need it.
So now we've introduced
that new chapter.
It's not in the right place.
I'm going to drag it here.
You'll notice that the whole
time that we're composing this,
this thing was reporting
that it was Chapter 1,
which in fact it was for
this particular document.
But when we've introduced
it into our new document
because we're using
those things,
the section numbering fields,
the section titling field,
this thing is now properly
numbered, Chapter 3.
And everything works within the
table of contents view as well.
When you publish, you
hit the Publish button,
iBooks Author does one thing
first, it validates your book
and make sure that
you're not going to run
into any errors with
the publishing.
Do you ever try to type
in a room with hundreds
of people looking at you?
It's not easy.
It's going to ask you, "Is this
a new book or is this an update
to a previously published book?"
It is absolutely an update.
Version 1 is up there
on the store.
Here, all I have to do is add a
new value, increment that value.
It's worth noting that you
always have to increment
that value, you can't go down.
Once you go up and when
it hits the bookstore
at a current number,
you're stuck
with that number or above it.
Another beautiful thing
we've done, sample books,
you don't need to
create one on your own.
All you have to do is pick
a chapter from your book
that you want to be the
basis of the sample.
And we'll generate the sample
that is 15 pages or 20 percent
of that chapter,
whichever comes first.
Then you export your book.
So close, there we go.
Little ding notifies me
that my book is exported.
I'm now ready to go to
iTunes producer to finalize
and ship this to the
iBooks store, again,
all from within iBooks Author.
So that's it for the session.
A few points I want to leave
you with before I get cut-off.
So as we've shown it's
now, easier than ever
to create this kind of
really interesting content.
The coding isn't required.
But if you want to
bring it, you can
and it's going to
be very effective.
Got great new widgets
that allow you
to extend the interactive
experience and make stuff
that is unique out there.
So you can publish and make
the updates to your books,
push new versions of your
books to the iBooks store.
Your end users are going to get
notified directly within iBooks
that new versions are available.
So you can continue to give
them updated experience
to troubleshoot,
extend the content,
add value overtime,
it's all up to you.
And with all these things, we
think it's possible for anyone
to become a published author.
That's it for the session.
Thank you so much
for joining us today.