[ Silence ]
>> Welcome to Designing
Accessories for iOS and OS X.
So, my name is Peter Langenfeld.
I'll be walking you guys
through the session today,
and a little bit about what
are we going to talk about.
Of course, we're going to
talk about the new features
in iOS 7 and in Mavericks.
We want to spend a
little bit of time talking
about the frameworks
that you guys can use
as application developers
to utilize accessories
and to better expand
the accessory ecosystem.
And then, of course, we
want to focus in on some
of the technologies and new
things we've done overall
and the exciting--
these exciting parts that
we think you guys have
opportunities in regarding
Wi-Fi, AirPlay, Bluetooth,
Lightning connector,
few other things
that we'll probably
touch on in between.
So, first, I want
to thank you guys,
thank you for coming today,
thank you giving me a nice crowd
to get nervous in front of.
But also thank you
for developing
such great devices
and accessories.
It really makes us excited
everyday to come in to work
and to work on the overall
accessory ecosystem,
see how many cool
things appearing
for our users to enjoy.
You know, one of the big
things that we notice working
on accessories in the
accessory ecosystem is
that you guys have really
helped our devices become a part
of people's everyday lives,
a critical part of that.
And so I want to give
you guys a few examples
of the things we find
really interesting and kind
of maybe give you some ideas
of areas you can work
on and expand on.
Of course, we always like
to see new things as well.
So health and fitness
is great area
that we've been seeing a
lot of expansion recently.
You know, in this
particular example,
we have a blood pressure cuff,
but we also have fitness
monitors, Wi-Fi scales,
things that basically
help people to keep track
of their everyday lives to
become better individuals
and to really make the
merging of the applications,
the iOS device, the Mac device,
and the accessory system meshed
into their everyday lives
and improve life in general.
And we think that's great.
We love seeing it.
Of course, we also have
some home products as well.
Here's the Nest thermostat
and it really, again,
just highlights the fact
that you can merge this
into your life, you can
utilize it, you can decide
to save some energy, you can
decide to heat up your home,
you can decide to see
how you're doing as far
as performance overall so that
you can add something more
to your overall experience
than just "Oh,
I feel cold," or "I feel hot."
You can actually see
how things are going
and we think that's great.
And then finally, fun.
Everybody likes to have fun.
We like to have fun.
And we think it's fun that you
guys have enabled things like--
they are drawn to play
kind of the interactive,
virtual reality video
games essentially.
And all of that is
enabled by accessories.
All of that is enabled
by you guys.
And it makes us excited
and thrilled to come
to work every day,
create solutions together
that we can really get
the overall consumer base
excited about.
So how do we do that?
Well, here's the
infamous super slide.
These are all the different
technologies that we support.
There's obviously many more
but we think these ones
are particularly important.
And this here, I
think, we really want
to highlight the fact that OS
X and OS 7-- iOS 7, excuse me,
work together and
as app developers
and accessory manufacturers, you
guys can support both platforms,
mostly seamlessly and really
support more consumers overall.
So we have a few actual
connectivity options listed
on the slide.
Of course, Wi-Fi, Lightning,
Bluetooth low energy are things
that we're very excited about
and are pushing forward
constantly as far
as the technology bases.
But also things such as
the 3.5-millimeter jack,
the headphone jack are
also opportunities for you
as developers to take
advantage of in both your apps
and in the overall
accessory ecosystem.
So we want to highlight
those things.
Of course, there are also the
way you access these things
from apps, the actual protocols
and the frameworks, like I said,
that are available, again,
across both OS platforms.
And so let's dive in
to a couple of these.
Let's talk a little bit about
what you can do with them
and we won't be able to
hit them all but hopefully,
we can give you some
ideas of places
where you could start developing
and getting some
exciting products going.
First up, USB Audio.
You access USB Audio
as an app developer
through the Core Audio
Framework that's both
on iOS and OS X again.
And, you know, you
can design products
that are USB 1 compliant
and we will support them.
We'd really recommend you guys
start thinking about USB 2.0
as a standard and that's on the
accessory manufacturing side.
And that's for both
input and output devices.
You know, although you
can support a number
of sampling rights on both the
physical device side and the OS,
the application side, we want
to stress that, you know,
16-bit when you're
PCM, 32, 4401,
48 kilohertz is really the
standard that we focus in on.
And so we do make
it a requirement
of all external accessories to
support those sampling rights
and we would suggest as
application manufacturers,
application developers,
you also focus
in on supporting those rights
and make sure not to block them
from requirement standpoint.
You do have access
to multichannel audio
on both sides should
you choose to use it.
And then finally, of course,
volume synchronization.
If you adjust the volume on the
OS side or you adjust the volume
on the accessory side, the
two should be synchronized.
You should get volume
increases and decreases
as the consumer really sees fit
and that's all available
to you as well.
So next up, something new.
We talked about this
a little bit yesterday
and we'll be talking about
it more throughout the week,
is game controller.
This, we think, is great.
This is something we're
really excited about.
We've decided to standardize
around the concept that iOS
and Mavericks should have a
consistent game controller
experience that you
can use in both places,
and that application
developers can utilize
to create richer,
more immersive games.
As you can see, we have a
standard game controller
and of course, we
also expand that out
to an extended game controller.
Really, the extended game
controller adds a secondary
trigger button or shoulder
button and some joysticks.
And we do have a session
later today actually
to talk a little bit more
detail about the hardware
and the software
requirements of that.
Also, reference it a little
bit later in this presentation.
But please, if you're
interested in game controller,
come to the labs, go to the
sessions, and really get
to know more about this 'cause
this is something we think is
really to make the game space
a great, a better experience
than it even is today,
and that's hard to create.
Okay. So iPod accessory
protocol.
We now refer to this
as iAP usually,
and you'll hear us
all slip in to that,
so that's what we're referring
to if we talk about it.
And the key here is it's
basically how you access a bunch
of the system services on iOS.
It's been around since we
introduced the 30-pin dock many
years ago, we've kept it around.
We continued to expand it.
We continued to think it's
a great way to interface
with accessories in
an Apple-specific way.
We've given you access
to the media library,
and what that means is you
can look at all the metadata
on the device, organize as
we organize it, and you can--
on your accessory side, you
can decide to display it
to your user in a way that
you think makes the most sense
to them and allow them to browse
and use playback
controls, et cetera.
Next up, of course,
is the accessory--
external accessory protocol,
EA as we like to call it.
It's the best way to have
an application talk directly
with your physical accessory
that you decide to design.
And the exciting
part there, I think,
is that we also have app
discovery and app launch.
So, if someone goes out
to the store and decides
to buy an accessory for the
first time, they plug it
in to their device or they
connect it to their device.
The first thing that
the device does
from a system aspect is
ask you, "Do you want
to download the app
for this device?"
It's a great feature.
It prevents people from
having to search on the store.
It prevents people
from having to look
through the manual, et cetera.
And we think people
really enjoy it
and we love the way it's working
out and we hope you guys decide
to try and exercise
that a little bit too.
The next, location information.
You can decide to expand
the location capabilities
of your device.
Finally, accessibility.
Obviously, some people, some
of our customers need some help
in using our devices and we've
made these frameworks available
to you to make sure you
can design accessories
that help them use that
and help everyone enjoy
and utilize their iOS
device to its fullest.
Many of the technologies
I've been talking about fall
under the MFi Licensing Program.
MFi is made for iPod,
iPhone and iPod.
And what does it include?
Well, it's a program that gives
you access to our connectors,
to receive a Lightning
connector.
[ Pause ]
Our headphone with remote
system which is a great way
to not only listen to the music
and audio from your devices,
both on the MAC side
and on the iOS side,
but also allows you
to use the controls.
Again, volume controls,
play/pause, all of the things
that people are used to
using on a day-to-day basis.
Finally, AirPlay
licensing, we now allow you
to create AirPlay accessories
and finally, AirPrint.
And really, the intent
here is to make sure
that there's a sense of
quality for the consumer
when they go into a store.
We keep the MFi Program
around and we allow the badge
to be used on products
that Apple
and the accessory
manufacturers have worked hard
to guarantee our solid quality
experiences for the consumer.
So, when you go shopping
for an accessory,
you know with confidence
that if I buy this accessory
and take it home, it'll
work with my device today,
and it'll also work with
my devices in the future.
If you want to join
the MFi Program,
we obviously have many
people you can talk
to in the lab sessions today.
We highly encourage
you to chat with us,
understand with it's about,
understand what you get.
Some of the highlights, you
get full technical information
of how to interface
with our devices.
You get access to all the
components, so connectors,
headphone, mic-- and
mic systems, et cetera.
All tools that we
make available as far
as developing accessories,
this will help you understand
if you're speaking the protocols
properly, if you're electrically
in sync with our specifications.
And finally, it gives you access
to the product certification
and the logos and
compatibility icons
if you pass product
certification.
So that's what I'm going to
do from a high-level overview.
Obviously, it's a complex phase.
Like I said, we definitely
have many lab sessions
that we are more than
happy and willing to talk
to you guys about this.
And, you know, I'm just
trying to highlight here
that no matter what
transport you decide to use,
you pretty much have an
option to do some sort
of communication, whether here
it's audio or communication
with apps, there's also a
number of other options we have.
So, hopefully, you guys
are getting inspired,
hopefully you guys
are getting excited
to make some accessories,
to make some apps that work
with accessories, and we would
really enjoy talking to you.
So, please come along
and ask some questions.
Let's switch gears just a little
bit and let's talk about some
of the advances we have in
specific technology areas.
First up, I'd like to
highlight wireless.
We at Apple think wireless
is a great solution,
and wireless includes
both Wi-Fi and Bluetooth,
and Bluetooth low
energy of course.
And why we like wireless so
much is that the consumer gets
to keep the device in their
pocket or in their hand,
and they don't have to worry
about walking over to it
and plugging in it or having a--
forgetting it somewhere
and leaving it.
They can just walk into the
room where these things exist
and they can start
using it seamlessly,
which we think is great.
On the Wi-Fi front, couple
of things we think you guys
should be thinking about.
On the software side, definitely
realize that networking sockets
and ports are your friends.
We have great frameworks
for dealing with both.
They're totally open.
You can determine how
you want to speak to
and communicate with
your accessory.
And I also highlight that we
have Bonjour, and I'll talk
in some more detail in a minute
but Bonjour is really the best
way we think for consumers
to be able to interact with
network devices without having
to know the technical
details of them.
On the hardware front, a couple
of things I want to stress,
and I've talked about this
in the past but hopefully,
we can all get on
board with this now.
The Wi-Fi Alliance Certification
is really important
in the Wi-Fi space.
It makes sure and ensures
that you have inoperability,
it makes sure that when your
customer brings the device,
it's not going to interfere
with other Wi-Fi devices
in their home, and it's
also going to work well
with any brand of
router and any brand
of infrastructures
that they may have.
Dual band operation I think
is also something that we
like to stress and
I realize it's--
it may seem unnecessary
on the accessory front.
But we all have more and more
RF interference in our homes.
And obviously, everything is
using the 2.4 gigahertz space.
We have Wi-Fi, we
have Bluetooth,
we have all these technologies,
ISM unlicensed band.
And so we really
want to encourage you
to give the consumer the option
to put both 2.4 and 5 gigahertz
into the device so they can use
whatever gives them the best
experience, so, to
avoid audio dropouts
and communication breakdowns
and the fact that if you walk
to one corner of your home
and your neighbor has
a strong Wi-Fi signal,
you may get more
error rate, et cetera.
If you enable the products
with dual band performance,
hopefully, we can avoid that
and we can get to a better place
as far as wireless usability and
enjoinment from our consumers.
The final two things are
really on the software front
but they're specifically
targeted towards hardware OEMs.
And so, I want to stress
quality of service, WMM,
this is an inherent
part of 802.11n.
You have to certify for it.
What I really make sure
is that high bandwidth
and high priority traffic
on the network actually gets
the priority it deserves.
So, it makes sure that you
avoid network dropouts again,
it'll make sure you,
you know, avoid glitches
in your video stream, which
is in your audio stream,
those sorts of things.
And finally, IPv6 versus IPv4.
Now that we're entering the
age of the internet of things,
the fact that everything is
connected, we're quickly going
to start running out addresses.
And so we at Apple, believe
strongly we should all be making
the transition over to IPv6
and we encourage you guys
to make sure that you have
the ability to do the same.
A little bit more on Bonjour.
So, as I mentioned before,
Bonjour is a zero-configuration
networking protocol suite.
Really, what it boils down to
from the consumer's perspective
is that use a friendly name.
So, you don't have
192.168.0.1 or 10.0.0.1
or something identifying
your product.
You name it WAMP or computer
or microphone or something
that means what it
does to the consumer
and the consumer has the
ability to rename that device
and to have the experience
to find that device
on their network just by using
the name that they can remember.
We think that's great.
No worry about IP addresses,
no worry about URLs, hopefully,
no worry about having to go
to the user manual to find
out where to find out
where they should be going
to configure things.
It should just be easy for
them to bring something home,
put it on their network
and enjoy it
with the name they recognize.
Next up is network
service discovery.
What this does is
it allows the--
well, allows applications
to filter
down what devices the consumer
sees by the actual function
that they want to provide.
So, for example for AirPlay,
we use Bonjour to make sure
to only display those devices
that support AirPlay audio
coming to them instead
of showing all the
devices on your network
that might perhaps
support something
that you're interested in.
By doing this, you give to
your consumer a much targeted,
a much more enjoyable experience
'cause they only see the things
that they need, they
only see the things
that they can use
right now for the type
of things that they want to do.
We believe so strongly in this.
We've actually made
this open source.
It's part of the
mDNSResponder project.
You can find it at the
address listed there.
We highly encourage you
to go and take a look
and if you have any
more questions
about general functionality,
obviously you can talk to us
in the accessory labs or I'm
sure you can find someone
in networking labs that can
help talk you through this
and give all of our consumers
a better or raw experience.
Configuring wi-fi accessories.
You know, I talked about this
need to make sure we get way
from forcing people to go to the
user manual and forcing people
to come home with their device,
set it up, get ready to use it,
only to realize, "Oh
wait, how do I get this
on my Wi-Fi infrastructure?"
But we took care of
this a couple years back
and we enabled Wi-Fi
information sharing.
What it does is you plug the
accessory into a physical port
or Bluetooth and then it
asks you, "Do you want
to share your networking
credentials
to your iOS device that's
already on with your accessory?"
Great, perfect.
They can say yes.
They can say no.
Great, it's all configured,
you don't have worry about it.
No manual needed.
However, we did hear from a
few people, wouldn't it be nice
if we didn't have to
include a physical port?
Wouldn't it be nice if you
can do this Wi-Fi-only?
Well, we agreed and now you can.
So, what I'm showing you
here is a Wi-Fi-only way
to configure your accessories.
Essentially, what happens on
the accessory front is it goes
into a software AP mode,
software access point mode.
And we identify it as
non-configured device.
So, up there on the screen,
you can see set up new device.
This is a very similar
system that we've had
for our AirPort products
for a while.
We've just added third parties.
So, you see Thermostat there.
So, if I select Thermostat,
I now get the option
to join the network to my
iOS device that's already on.
I can obviously show
other networks
so I can select a
different network if I like.
And then I can rename it.
If I click on the name--
accessory name section,
I can decide I want to call it
something other than Thermostat.
I want to call it, you know,
Back Bedroom Thermostat
or Garage Thermostat or
somewhere else that I want it.
Then I click Next,
voila, lo and behold,
we securely transfer all the
networking credentials including
the passwords and anything
else that user may not remember
down to the accessory.
The accessory rejoins the
target network and you're done.
We do have one more thing,
if that accessory
has an application,
we also allow you to-- the
consumer to click on Find
Out for this Accessory.
It will do a search and take
you directly to the App Store
and they can be off on their
way again without having
to open the manual,
without having
to think anymore about it.
Of course, we don't want to
leave Mavericks out of this.
So, we also have the ability
to go up to the Wi-Fi menu,
obviously you see new accessory
up there, same choices,
you select Thermostat,
or AirPort updater
program launches.
You have the ability to
select both of them there.
Again, chose your network,
rename if you so please
and you're also on
the network there.
So, whether you're
using Mavericks
or whether you're using iOS 7,
your consumer now has the
ability to get on to the network
in easy way only using Wi-Fi.
We think this is great.
It's going to be part of the MFi
Program and we're super excited
to have people come and talk to
us about how you implement this.
So please come and talk to us.
Obviously, one of the
great things this pairs
with is AirPlay Audio
and we've talked
about AirPlay Audio a
little bit in the past.
It's a third-party program.
It is part of MFi that allows
you to configure the device
and have it be part of
our AirPlay ecosystem
so you can stream audio
to the third-party device.
We have audio/video receivers,
speaker docks, television.
We have all sorts of things
in this expansive ecosystem
that allows you to listen
to your music how you
see it fit as a consumer.
But we've had one
little snuck in the past.
It's been a little
restrictive perhaps.
So I'm happy to announce
that we're also transferring
this into a more program.
We're going to look at
essentially enabling all of you
to develop and create
AirPlay accessories
on whatever platform,
on whatever hardware
platform you see fit.
It's the same program,
same product definitions,
same feature set, same terms
of compliance, same everything.
It's just that now you get
to choose whatever
hardware you would
like to enable your AirPlay
accessories and hopefully,
that will give you guys a
little bit more flexibility
and we'll expand that
ecosystem even further.
With that, thank you.
I'd like to bring in my
colleague, Brian Tucker,
to talk a little bit more
about Bluetooth and some
of the exciting things
we have there.
Thanks guys.
[Applause]
>> All right.
Thank you, Peter.
My name is Brian Tucker and
I am ultimately responsible
for Bluetooth at Apple
and that includes iOS
and now OS X Mavericks.
And I have an incredible honor,
the guys gave me the opportunity
to come up and talk about
what's next for Bluetooth,
what are we doing with
Bluetooth now, what's the state
of the union of Bluetooth?
I'm obviously very, very
passionate about this.
I've actually had the
opportunity to meet a lot of you
in the audience here today.
We do have a followup
session to this
that specifically covers Core
Bluetooth in a lot more detail.
And so what I'm going to do in
this session is give you kind
of a sneak peak at some of the
things that we've done specially
in iOS 7 to really take Core
Bluetooth to the next level.
So where's Bluetooth today?
Well, Bluetooth is
over a decade old.
In fact, it's about 12
or 13 years old now.
Core Bluetooth or Bluetooth
low energy just came
in the market a couple of
years ago, three years ago.
This marks our third iteration
of Bluetooth low
energy implementations
in Apple products,
but what's going on?
This last year was crazy.
[laughs] It was nuts.
I mean, one of things that
blew me away is in the SIG,
we saw 451 percent
increase in listed devices
for Bluetooth speakers.
I mean that's just nuts.
If you look at the
chart, it kind of grows,
and then last year, it's
just this hockey puck.
And this year is no different.
We're seeing more and
more devices get listed
in the classic Bluetooth space.
So classic Bluetooth, it
is definitely here to stay.
It is still growing
by leaps and bounds.
We want to continue to improve
that user experience
with customers.
You know, we want to do this
like make AC perform
even better,
perform better coax algorithms,
to improve audio quality
for conversational audio.
All those areas around
Core Bluetooth that are key
to the customer experience,
we want to make better.
And what we're doing with you
guys is we're updating our
Bluetooth Guidelines document
to make better suggestions
about how to implement
hands-free and HTTP devices,
as well as make improvements
on [inaudible] in OS X and iOS.
It's pretty cool.
So Bluetooth low
energy, obviously,
I just spoke of,
it's pretty new.
It's only been around
four, three years.
But what's amazing is in a few
market reports that I've read
and have been provided
to the Bluetooth SIG,
we're going to surpass a billion
Bluetooth low energy devices
this year.
That's ridiculous.
A Bluetooth-- a billion
Bluetooth low energy devices
with a technology that
realistically has only been
around for a couple of years.
That's insane.
So clearly, this
is a huge market
for you guys to step into.
And then finally, and I think
this is pretty important,
is that now every major mobile
OS manufacturer supports
Bluetooth low energy.
So I like to personally
welcome them to the pool,
the water is great,
but this is awesome
because this now gives you
the ability to truly look
at a technology across
the entire spectrum
of mobile devices.
So no longer is it just our
play, we're going to continue
to drive this market forward.
We're going to continue
to innovate in this space,
but I think it's
important to note
that everybody feels the same
way about Bluetooth low energy
that we do, which I think
is really, really cool.
So last year, I spent
some time with you guys
to talk about some use cases.
And these are the use cases
that I showed last year,
things like health care, sports
and fitness, toys, I don't know
if you guys got a
chance to catch the demo
in the keynote yesterday,
the Anki Drive demo,
really, really cool.
That is all Bluetooth
low energy.
That's an iPhone talking
to each one of those cars
with a Bluetooth low energy
link and maintaining that
and I would argue, one of the
worst wireless spaces known
to man and Bluetooth low
energy still operated,
which is remarkable.
I was happy.
[laughs] So, with these use
cases-- there are many more,
but with these use cases, we
took a look at each one of these
at the beginning of
kind of our cycle
with iOS 7 and with Mavericks.
And we wanted to kind of put
our money where our mouth is.
We wanted to say, "If these
are so important to you guys,
if we're saying that
these are super important,
then what can we do to
make these even better?"
So, I wanted to highlight a
few of these particular areas.
I'm not going to
through all of these.
I don't have enough time.
But I want to highlight a
few things that we've done
to make some of these user
experiences even better.
And the first one I want to
talk about is health care.
And like Peter said, health care
is growing by leaps and downs.
If you look at what
we're doing with LE,
we're allowing the consumer
to quantify themselves.
I'm not sure I like this
concept called quantify itself,
but the-- or the name.
I love the concept.
And the idea is that you
as a consumer can now
take active control
over your own health care.
You can monitor your
own blood glucose.
own heart rate.
I saw a product that monitors
your blood glucose level
and actually gives you real-time
body chemistry information
as you eat your food.
So, like you can go eat a bagel
and your phone will tell you,
"Dude, your blood sugar level
is spiking, you may not want
to have any carbs for lunch,"
you know, kind of thing.
And that's awesome, 'cause now
I can immediately know how the
system is operating, right?
And as an engineer, that's
huge, [inaudible], right?
And if I have data on my body,
I can make the right choices
in real-time as I go out
throughout my day, huge,
huge opportunity
here in this market.
Another area is providing
a better relationship
between the patient
and the care provider,
the nurse practitioner
or your doctor.
And connecting the device
that's on your body with the iOS
or the OS X device
and connecting
that to your doctor directly.
So now, the doctor can take
an active role in your life
without you having to be in
the hospital the whole time.
And for my parents, especially,
it even gives me the ability
to monitor their
health remotely.
They live in Arizona, I live
in California, it's just peace
of mind, but they
can still continue
to live their lives
the way they want to.
I think that's just huge.
It changes the world, right?
Another area where
we're kind of--
we put our money where
our mouth is this idea
of MFi hearing aids, or
Apple designed hearing aid
audio transport.
Now, about a year and a
half ago, we were looking
at this space and
we're like, you know,
Bluetooth is being used but
the experience is just less
than ideal.
You had to wear something
around your neck,
or you had to wear a
thing on your belt,
and it was like Bluetooth
that and magnetic inductance
to your hearing aid, or
you put it up to your ear
and it just sounded
really crappy.
And we're like, "We
can make this better."
And so, we first started looking
at Bluetooth and like, "No,
that's not going to
work, too much power,
the chips are too
expensive, they're too big."
And then we started
looking at low energy,
and I remember having
conversations
with some chip guys and they
literally laughed at us,
you know, they didn't think
that that is even possible.
But we hammered it
and we hammered it,
and we came up with
a way to push audio
down to lower energy link,
and this is Apple iP.
And we're enabling the
hearing aid market.
In fact this year, we'll
start seeing hearing aids
on the market using this
technology, and it's crazy tool.
I mean, we'll start to see this
technology in cochlear implants,
where you technically have
an audio linked directly
from your phone into your brain.
I mean, it's just
nutty technology.
And it's also a data pipe.
So, not only that we're
pushing audio to your ears
but the doctor-- you can call
up the doctor, talk to them
on the phone and they can adjust
your hearing aids over the phone
as you're talking to them,
just awesome, awesome stuff.
So this is what I
mean about kind
of putting our money
where our mouth is.
And then finally--
and this is one
of those sneak peeks
I'm giving you based
on our Core Bluetooth session,
but this idea of improved--
we improved Core
Bluetooth backgrounding.
So now with app preservation and
restoration, we give the ability
to launch apps in the
background and interact
with Bluetooth low
energy devices regardless
of the state of your
application.
So this gives a whole new
market of interaction especially
in areas of long-term care and
some of the areas I want to talk
about here in a minute.
So sports and fitness
is the next area.
Now sports and fitness seems
to be completely designed
for Bluetooth low energy.
Some of the products that
we've seen in the market
and the space, the Fitbit Flex,
a Bluetooth low energy product.
This is really cool.
It monitors your activity,
but it also monitors
your sleep cycles.
So it tells you how
well you slept,
as well as how sedentary
your life is.
As an engineer, I struggle
with this constantly.
But it says, "Get off your
butt and go exercise."
It's a great product.
This is one that I'm especially
excited about with my kids.
This is soccer ball made by
Adidas, the Adidas Smart Ball.
What's cool about this is it
has Bluetooth low energy radio
in the middle and then
sensors that spider
out to the outside of the ball.
It looks like a spider
exploded inside the ball, right?
And it is connected to the ball
and it actually monitors
the activity
of the soccer ball during use.
So it monitors how well
you're passing a ball.
How much spin you're
putting on the ball.
In fact, it a has feature
where you take a shot on goal
and if you're looking
particular curve to the shot,
it will monitor that curve
and then compare your shot
against a pro shot and it will
actually tell how well you're
doing against maybe Beckham.
And you want this, that cool,
you know, right to left curve
into the top-right or
top-left corner of the goal.
This ball will let you do that.
So for coaches, this is huge
because it gives you the data.
In addition to that in
basketball, there is a product
by 94Fifty, a smart ball that
does very similar things,
but in a basketball space.
You take a shot, it tells
you the rotation of the ball,
it tells you the shot angle
of the ball to the goal,
how well you're dribbling.
I mean, it's awesome.
And that somebody like
that's a data junky,
this is just a really, really
great way to get feedback
on how well you're doing,
as well as how well
your athletes are doing
if you're a coach.
Really, really cool.
And so, again, we feel like with
iOS 7 in the app preservation,
you can now do long-term
accessory interaction.
Now there is a lot to
be talked about in here
and a lot more detail in
the Core Bluetooth session.
Reno [phonetic] and Jason go in
this in great detail and talk
about how your apps
can really interact
with these devices
long-term always.
As long as the phone is with the
consumer, the phone can interact
with these accessories.
So the third thing is security
and security is kind
of snuck up on us.
Security has just exploded.
In fact, just recently, we're
starting to see just a ton
of products in the space that
are providing you experiences
around home similar to
the experiences you get
around your car with a
wireless remote or wireless key.
Kwikset Kevo is a similar
product, you walk up,
your phone interacts
with the door,
you touch the door
lock and it unlocks.
This is a Kickstarter,
guys, Lockitron where--
a product where it just
goes over the door lock
and it can open and
unlock the door lock.
And then just recently,
just a couple of weeks ago,
a company called August
makes up Smart Lock
that does very similar
things, beautiful product.
One of the things in their video
I thought was really cool is
this idea of being able to
share your key virtually.
So if I want to allow
my plumber, for example,
to get in my home,
let's say this Thursday
which I know I'm not going
to be there from 12 to 2,
I can send him my key and say,
"You can get into my home only
from 12 to 2" and
oh, by the way,
when he does enter the
home, his phone tells me
that he entered the
home and left the home.
It's pretty really,
really, really cool stuff.
And, again, we think
state preservation
and restoration is key here
because if the app goes away
or dies, you don't
have the ability
to unlock your door, right?
It doesn't interact
with the door
because the app is
no longer there.
And iOS doesn't a have perceived
knowledge of what it means
to interact with the door lock.
So this is really, really,
really key to this product space
and we think that this is going
to just explode this market.
Entertainment, so briefly Peter
covered this, but I just wanted
to cover a couple of
areas where entertainment
and low energy is converging.
Game controller is
obviously an area
where Bluetooth low energy
is perfect for this space.
The small data packet
sizes, the data intervals,
the connection intervals
that you can achieve
just perfectly aligned
with game controllers.
Obviously, keyboards, I'm not
sure keyboards are entertaining,
but you can connect to
keyboards maybe to play games
that are a little
bit more complicated,
and then of course,
remote controls.
Like this remote control
potentially can be LE
and probably should be LE given
that this could connect directly
to an iO-- or an Apple product.
So, what have we
done in this space?
Well, now on iOS 7, we
natively support HID
over BLE accessories.
So now, if you make
a BLE keyboard,
you can connect directly to
iOS and to OS X Mavericks.
And what's important to
note here especially, well,
in both platforms is
this is the first time
that we have supported
profiles in the LE space.
That means that device
management is now being managed
by the OS, but that doesn't
take away device management
from your apps.
So if your apps still want to
discover devices and connect
to them and interact with
them, they can totally do that.
That's totally fine.
But the case of hosted
profiles such as HID over GATT,
we now managed those
devices for you.
So we felt like it's a more
of a system level functionally
and we thought it
was important for us
to put this into the product.
And then finally, proximity,
and this has been talked
about a little bit.
I've had countless
questions, people like,
"What's this iBeacons thing?"
You know, all those
kind of stuff.
So, I wanted to briefly
talk about this.
Some of the areas
where proximity is key,
we already talked
about security,
advertising the ability
to go into a retail space,
and my phone starts to
interact with that retail space
in an advertising way.
I think Minority Report, but
hopefully not that creepy.
Location services,
obviously, if I'm up--
going up to a statue
[phonetic] and I want
that statue do tell me something
about the points of interest,
that's really interesting.
So what have we done
in this space?
Well, now, natively, we give
you the ability to do this iOS
to iOS built right
within core location.
And this is using
Bluetooth low energy.
We don't make it obvious that
it's using Bluetooth low energy.
But then you have the ability
to engage from consumer
to consumer, iOS
device to iOS device,
these proximity services.
So that's just a few areas that
we've been working on in iOS 7.
So as a review, these are some
of the new things that we talked
about here, Core Bluetooth
App Preservation Restoration.
I know it's an interesting
name, but it's really cool.
Learn about it.
It will change your life.
BLE based proximity services,
we talked about this already.
iOS hosted BLE profiles,
HID over BLE.
That should be HID over GATT.
It was the official name.
And then finally,
hearing aid support
which we think is
hugely profound
and truly does make a difference
in the world which is one
of our mission statements
in wireless software
and we think this fulfills that.
Real quick, this is kind
of our state of the union.
This is the classic Bluetooth
protocols and profiles
that we support in OS X.
You can write this
down real quick, no.
These are all available
and visible to you
in the current release
of Mavericks.
And then on the LE side, we
have a couple of new roles
on the LE side and that is
low energy peripheral role.
Apparently, we thought enough
about it to add it twice.
And-- but anyway, we did
give you the ability now
to offer up services in OS X.
And now on the iOS side,
from a Core Bluetooth--
or from a classic Bluetooth
perspective, excuse me,
these are the profiles that
we're currently supporting.
Nothing new here, just
a lot of bug fixes
and interrupt ability
changes to make our products,
our devices work better
with your products.
We also continue to support
the iPod accessory protocol
over Bluetooth and that's still
very much an active technology.
I use it every day
when I go to sleep.
And then on the LE side, we have
a couple of new things there.
As I said before, Alert
Navigation Service.
We have this new thing,
brand new called Apple
Notification Center Service.
There is also going to
be documentation posted
to the developer site very,
very soon, hopefully today.
So check it out in
there and a lot
of this information
will be on that.
And then finally, the
current time service is also
always available.
So if you have an accessory
and you want that accessory
to use an accurate
schedule or timer,
the timer in the phone is
always available to you.
So hopefully, that was a very
brief informative overview
of where Bluetooth is right
now within our OS products.
So with that, I'd like to
invite up Edwin Foo to run us
through Wired and to
continue our presentation.
Thank you.
>> All right everybody,
so you're still with us.
Thanks for holding up this
far throughout the talk.
I'm Edwin and I am going to
spend a few minutes talking
with you about some of the Wired
interfaces that are available
to accessory developers
for both iOS devices
and Macs running OS X.
Let's start with Thunderbolt.
This has been around
for a while--
a little while now
and it has worked
out really well for
us on the Macs.
Thunderbolt is a high-speed
transport that's capable
of transferring both data and
[inaudible] digital video,
namely DisplayPort, at really
high speeds and it can handle--
it can handle, actually
be daisy chained
up to six devices per
port and carry power.
It's a bit of mouthful, but
in short what this means is
that you can have high transfer
speeds, one cable from the Mac
to your Thunderbolt accessory
so there's no messed up cables.
And, of course, once your
users have multiple Thunderbolt
peripherals hooked
up to their Mac,
you still don't have a messed
up cables going from the Mac
to every single Thunderbolt
peripheral.
For applications that require
really, really high speed,
mass storage really
comes to mind as well
as digital video of course.
Thunderbolt is a great choice
and we strongly consider
that you consider using it
in accessories like that.
So how do you get started?
Well, first, there is
a certification program
for Thunderbolt.
And the reason
that certification
program is there is
that it helps ensure a really
high quality of offerings
to users and customers
out there.
They want to be able to buy
Thunderbolt peripherals,
plug them in, and
just have them work.
And that works in both
directions because it means
that as users and customers
get more comfortable
with Thunderbolt and depend on
it more and more, they'll begin
to think less and less
about buying your Thunderbolt
peripherals and wondering
if they'll work with Macs.
For those of you
who are interested
in buying device drivers
for Thunderbolt accessories,
refer to the Thunderbolt
Device Driver Programming Guide
on the Apple Developer website.
Next, I'd like to
talk about USB 3.0.
Most Macs today ship
with USB 3.0 ports.
And like Thunderbolt, USB
ports can also, of course,
provide power up to
900 milliamps of it
to your USB accessories
for power and charging.
USB throughput is
still quite fast,
although not quite
as fast Thunderbolt.
And for those of
you who are thinking
of making USB mass
storage accessories,
we definitely recommend
that instead
of using the USB
Mass Storage Class,
please consider using the
USB Attached SCSI Class.
The performance is much
better and all Macs--
most Macs especially Macs
that will be shipping
with OS X Mavericks
will support this.
And last but not least,
we definitely recommend
that you have your
USB peripherals
and accessories certified
by the USB Integrators Form.
This will guarantee that your
accessories have maximum chance
of working out of the box
without have additional--
install additional
drivers with Macs
and OS X releases down the road.
Next, I'd like to give
brief overview of Lightning.
I don't want to spend
a whole time at it
because we did talk a lot about
Lightning last fall, of course.
But to briefly summarize,
the Lightning connector
is all digital interface.
It is completely reversible
so that your users don't need
to worry about which way they're
plugging in your accessory.
And one interesting
thing about Lightning
that may not be very
obvious to most people,
but is actually felt every
single day when you plug
in your phone to charge it,
is that Lightning connectors
have a very positive insertion
and removal feel.
There was no mistaking when
your user has connected their
accessory to a phone, and
likewise, there is no mistaking
when the user is disconnected.
It sounds like a purely
mechanical [inaudible]
but it actually is--
contributes greatly
to the overall user experience.
Because if you have, I'm
sure that some of you
in the audience have
had experiences with--
dealing with connectors
that feel a little bit loose
or slipped out and the like,
and that can also sometimes
result in a poor experience.
You won't have that
with Lightning.
Lightning connectors
just stop by the end
and they start working.
Another important
feature of Lighting
which maybe is not
necessarily immediately apparent
to most people is that it
actually provides power
on both directions.
Lightning based accessories do
not just have to provide power
to the Apple devices although
of course we love getting power
so please send us all you can.
But it is also possible to draw
a power from Apple devices.
Now, we do put some limitations
on that and some requirements
because we don't want users
to be wondering why they have
this vampire essentially sucking
power out of their phone.
But for the right categories
of accessories, getting power
from an Apple device is
a very powerful feature.
It means that your accessory
doesn't have to have a battery.
It doesn't have to even have
a power supply at the box
or even a connector for
external power supply.
All you see on the accessory
is the Lightning connector.
The Lightning connector
also has--
is multifaceted in terms
of its data transmission.
That supports multiple types
of connectivity technologies
starting with USB host,
USB device, and Serial.
Now, the availability of various
accessory interface features
over these transports does
vary based on the transport.
So, we definitely do recommend
that your accessories make use
of the USB host mode
on Apple devices.
And by this, I mean
just be clear
that the Apple device is
playing the role of the USB host
and your accessory
is a USB device.
As you can see here
from the slide,
there are more features
available today
to USB host mode accessories
than to USB device
mode accessories,
and that is definitely
a trend that we expect
to see continuing forward.
We have a left out
Serial though.
Why? Well, Serial interfaces
are really, really simple
to implement and they're very,
very low cost and they're very,
very low power, kind
of going back to why--
the question about drawing
power from Apple devices.
It's something you
should definitely consider
if your accessory design falls
into that kind of category.
If your data transmission
rate is not too high
and you're drawing power from
an Apple device, you may want
to consider that interface.
I also want to talk briefly
about the headphone
with remote and mic.
One, the most obvious example of
course is the EarPods that comes
in a box of every iPhone.
Accessory headphones that
implement the headphone remote
and mic feature all have
to use a standardized
microphone and transmitter chip.
And what this means
is that they all work
with all iOS devices
and most Macs.
Applications running
on iOS devices
and on Macs can receive events
from the remote control.
So it isn't just limited
to changing the volume
and starting playback
or pausing playback.
And last but not
least, I want to bring
up the game controller
feature one more time
and I'm mentioning
specifically in the context
of Wired accessory interfaces
because we're actually
very excited
to consider what possibilities
await for both game developers
and game controller
manufacturers
when you consider the
power of tactile feedback
from the game controller
buttons combined
with the multi-touch screen tilt
and driver sensors in an iPhone.
We're really looking forward
to see what creativity
arises from all this.
And not only but the game
controller framework is going
to be standardized so that if
you're making game controllers,
you won't need to worry
about which apps your game
controller is compatible
with 'cause the answer
is all of them.
And we need to go
check the compatibility
with every single app out
there by trying that yourself.
The inverse holds true
for the game developers.
They won't need to have a
closet full of game controllers
that they keep testing
every single time.
For those of you in the
audience who are thinking
about getting involved
with this,
with the controller
manufacturing inside of things,
look for update to the
MFi accessory interface
specification coming soon.
So, for more information
about all the technologies
that we talked about
today, definitely,
feel free to contact
any of the three people,
named on this slide in addition
to visiting the Apple
Developer Forums
and contacting Apple
Developer Support.
There are a bunch of related
sessions that you may want
to pay attention to as a result
of having heard the
content mentioned here.
And with that, that
concludes the session.
Thanks for attending.
[Applause]
[ Silence ]