[ Music ]
>> Hi, everyone, my name is
Sommer Panage, and I'm
Engineering Manager on the
Accessibility Team.
I'm excited to share with you
three ways in which you can make
your apps more visually
accessible.
We will be covering Dynamic Type
as well as some great
improvements to Reduce Motion
and an API that we brought over
from Mac to iOS that we call
Differentiate Without Color.
So let's get started with
Dynamic Type.
Dynamic Type is a feature that
allows users to customize the
size of the text on their
screen.
Now for some users that might
mean smaller text and for others
that might be larger text.
Now for some larger text might
just be a preference, but for
others large text can be the
difference between being unable
to use their device and being
able to use it.
When you're implementing Dynamic
Type for your users, I'd like to
remind you of four important
principles.
First, you make as much of your
text dynamic as possible.
If the text can grow, it should grow.
Second, use as much of the
screen width as possible.
Third, don't truncate text as it
grows.
You'll want to display the same
amount of text as your default UI.
And, finally, you should scale
glyphs that appear next to text
so that your UI continues to
look balanced.
In iOS, there are 11 different
text styles that you can use
with Dynamic Type all the way
from titles down the captions
and footnotes.
To use Dynamic Type for your UI
labels, your UI text fields, and
your UI text views, you just
need to use a preferred font for
one of these text styles and
you'll want to set the adjust
font for content size categories
flag to true on those views.
This guarantees that your view
will update whenever the user
changes their font size even if
your app is in the foreground.
As of iOS 11, we made it easier
for you to use Dynamic Type with
your custom fonts as well.
You'll want to have one font and
size mapped to each of the 11
text styles that we saw
previously.
Here I create my own dictionary
of fonts for each style.
Then I can look to see if I have
a font for the given style.
If I do, then I scale it as
appropriate using UI font
metrics, and if not, then I fall
back to that preferred system
font.
As I'm doing my awesome Dynamic
Type work, I want to be able to
see it and I can now easily
preview it using the new Xcode
environments overwrites pane
seen here.
I can just slide the Dynamic
Type slider and instantly in the
simulator see the results.
Next, I'd like to talk to you
about reduced motion.
So, motion is often an exciting
and dynamic part of iOS.
We use motion in many places to
create a more immersive
experience for our customers.
However, for some users these
effects might not be desirable.
One in three people has some
form of motion sensitivity.
Now for most people this means
riding a roller coaster or maybe
reading a book in the car, but
for a small subset of people
that sensitivity could be
triggered by even looking at a
screen with motion on it.
To help iOS adapt to all
customers, we already provide a
reduced motion setting in our
accessibility settings to
disable things like weather and
parallax effects in the system.
And here's the reduce motion API
that you might already be
familiar with.
When reduced motion is on, your
app should adapt its animations
as well.
Now another motion effect is
autoplaying video.
Here we see that as we scroll
through the App Store trailers
for the featured games begin to
play.
Now while for some this might
make them want to click in and
learn more about a fun looking
game; for others this behavior
could be a bit jarring or
perhaps it could trigger some
anxiety.
So that users can decide if they
want to see autoplaying video,
we're excited to announce a new
motion setting this year for iOS
13.
Settings, accessibility, motion,
auto-play video previews.
With this setting disabled our
apps such as App Store will no
longer auto-play content like
trailers but rather they will
require user interaction to
start and stop playback.
Auto-play video previews starts
as enabled by default, but you
can turn it off at any time.
And, additionally, we've made
this public API.
If is video auto-play enabled is
false, you should also make sure
that any videos in your apps
provide a play or pause
avoidance to your users.
And, of course, always listen
for that notification to know
when you should change your
behavior.
Now if your app already provides
an in-app setting, you'll simply
want to mirror that, mirror our
global setting as your default.
However, you can still use the
setting in your app to allow
users to customize your
behavior.
Another form of motion in iOS is
a transition from one screen to
another.
Here we see the typical sliding
transition as we navigate
through our settings app.
To provide even more
fine-grained control over the
types of motion that a customer
experiences on iOS, we've
introduced an additional setting
when reduced motion is enabled
and this is called prefer
Cross-fade Transitions.
As you can see, by enabling that
setting, my lateral slides have
become dissolved transitions in
the app.
Now UIKit implements these
dissolved transitions for you
when the setting is enabled.
So as long as you're using UIKit
standard navigation or modal
presentation, you'll get this
behavior for free.
Finally, I'd like to talk to you
about Differentiate Without
Color.
So colorblindness might cause
numerous colors that appear
different to some to appear very
similar to others.
For those with deuteranopia, for
example, some reds and greens
and yellows might all look very
much the same.
To see how this might impact
users and how we're solving for
it, I'd like to show you this
little app that my colleagues
and I worked on.
So we all really like peanut
butter, and I just added a new
feature so that I can track my
personal peanut butter status.
I've added green circles to the
peanut butters that I currently
have, I've added yellow circles
to the ones where I've eaten
them before but I don't have
them right now, and I've added
red circles for the ones I
haven't tried yet.
Now if my friend wants to use
this app but they happen to be
colorblind, this might be how it
looks.
As you can see, all of the
circles kind of blend together.
Now, as of iOS 13, this user can
go over to settings,
accessibility, display in text
size and turn this on --
Differentiate Without Color.
As a developer, I can just check
should Differentiate, Without
Color and observe the
Differentiate Without Color to
change notification.
If the setting is true, any
place in my app where I use
color as the only way of
conveying information, I should
now add some additional
indicator.
For example, a shape.
So back to my peanut butter app,
when I see that the user has
turned on Differentiate Without
Color I now replace my circles
with a green check, a yellow
question mark and a red X.
So now even if the app appears
like this, we can still discern
the status of my different
peanut butters.
Now you might be thinking, hey,
Sommer, wait a minute.
The app actually just looks
better this way.
Why even bother with the plain
circle version?
And you'd be totally right.
In fact, when possible, you
should not rely on color alone
to signal meaning.
Now in the case of my peanut
butter app, that's easy.
I can just get rid of the
circles, but it's not always
that easy.
Here we see the game Causality.
The game play is actually
indicated by the color on the
screen.
Now this might not be enough
information for all users and so
the game creators provide a
colorblind mode that you see
here.
When that's enabled, the players
and the targets now have
symbolic flags above their heads
and associated.
The game designers might not
have wanted this extra symbol
noise in the original design,
but for some users this actually
is what makes the game playable.
And that's it.
With that we've seen three ways
that we can make our apps more
visually accessible to all of
our customers.
We can support all text sizes
with Dynamic Type, we can adapt
via new motion settings for our
customers that might have motion
sensitivities, and we can convey
information in different ways
when we check Differentiate
Without Color.
Thank you all so much for your
time.
[ Applause ]