[ Music ]
>> Hi, I'm Tim Horton from the
Safari and WebKit Team.
I'm here to show you how to
present rich links in your app.
In iOS 10 and macOS Sierra, we
introduced rich links in
messages as a way to make URLs
more beautiful and more useful.
In order to maximize the
benefit, we built
specializations for certain
kinds of links.
This includes things like inline
video and audio playback, a
special presentation for Tweets
including those with multiple
images and many other things
like Apple Maps links.
This year iOS 13 and macOS 10.15
bring new APIs that allow you to
present rich links in your own
apps so that you get those same
benefits with a minimal amount
of work.
In this video, we're going to
follow the development of this
very simple recipe book marking
app as we progressively adopt
features of the new link
presentation framework to go
from a bland list of URLs to a
rich grid of links like this in
no time at all.
To achieve this I'm going to
cover 3 topics.
First, how to present metadata
given a URL.
Second, how to easily present
that metadata to the user.
And third, how to use fetched
metadata to accelerate the
presentation of the new Share
Sheet experience in iOS 13.
So let's start with retrieving
metadata.
In the recipe app, let's say
that you already have some
mechanism for users to get URLs
into the app.
You could just present them in a
table and call it quits, but
URLs are not very user-friendly
and in this case, it's quite
hard to distinguish between
them.
You could instead ask the user
for a title for each link, but
we can make it even easier.
Using the new link presentation
framework it's very easy to use
the LP metadata provider class
to retrieve rich metadata from
the website.
You just pass it the URL and it
returns you an LPLinkMetadata
object with a representative
title in any media that is
available.
Let's see what this looks like.
First you create an
LPMetadataProvider and then call
startFetchingMetadata with the
URL you're interested in.
When the completion handler is
called, be sure to check the
error.
If the server doesn't respond or
is too slow or your user doesn't
have a network connection, the
metadata fetched can fail.
Finally, you use the metadata
for whatever you want.
We'll come back to this in a
moment.
Before we continue there are a
few things to keep in mind when
using metadataProvider and
LinkMetadata.
First, the resultant metadata
object can include any of a
title, icon, image or video or
none at all if the site doesn't
specify any.
It is also serializable within a
secure coding.
This is important because
LPMetadataProvider hits the
Internet to do its job and you
don't want to do that work nor
make your users pay that data
and performance cost every time
you present the same link.
You should cache retrieved
metadata locally as much as
possible.
Also, you can fetch metadata for
local file URLs in which case
the new QuickLook thumbnailing
API will be used to retrieve a
representative thumbnail for the
file, if possible.
Now let's talk about how to put
the metadata we retrieve to use
by presenting it in our app.
Once again, it's
straightforward.
You can just take the object
from earlier and create an
LPLinkView with it.
It's that simple.
Let's return to the recipe app
and put LPLinkViews inside our
table view cells.
Much better.
Now you have a very familiar
presentation that makes each
recipe easy to identify at a
glance.
LPLinkView has an intrinsic
size, but it also responds to
size that fits with the ideal
size to use given a constraining
size and we'll try to present
something reasonable when laid
out at any size.
The last thing I'm going to talk
about is how to make use of
LinkMetadata to accelerate the
presentation of the new Share
Sheet experience in iOS 13.
For existing apps that share
URLs, the Share Sheet will
automatically present a preview
of the link at the top of the
card.
However, this requires reaching
out to the server to retrieve
metadata once the Share Sheet is
presented.
So the title and icon show up
asynchronously.
Let's watch that again.
Keep a close eye on the Share
Sheet's header.
If you already have an
LPLinkMetadata object for URL,
you should just pass it to the
Share Sheet and the preview will
appear instantly without loading
from the network.
You can use the new
activityViewControllerLink
Metadata method on your
implementation of
UIActivityItemSource and just
return the metadata object.
Let's look at the difference in
our recipe app if we provide the
data that we already use in the
table view.
Much nicer.
It's also good to note that if
the user chooses to share to
messages the same metadata is
passed directly through
providing a smooth and seamless
experience with no unnecessary
loading.
One last thing.
Say your app already has a
database of recipes with titles
and images that weren't fetched
by linked presentation.
You don't have to re-fetch the
metadata from the Internet in
order to accelerate the Share
Sheet or to present a rich link.
Instead, you can just fill in
the fields of LPLinkMetadata
yourself from your pre-existing
source of data.
You simply create an
LPLinkMetadata object and fill
in at least the original URL and
URL fields plus whatever
additional information you have.
So our 3 key takeaways today are
you can use LP metadata provider
to fetch rich metadata for URL
in order to provide more context
about arbitrary URLs.
You should use LP link view to
present links in your app in a
way that is both beautiful and
consistent with the system and
you should prefetch or use
existing LPLinkMetadata to
accelerate the Share Sheet
preview in your app.
For more information visit
developer.apple.com.
Thank you for your time.