[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Good morning.
Well, Xcode 11 has a ton of new
features and improvements.
Everything the tools do is in
support of getting you from an
idea, through development to
delivering a great product.
We want the tools to make you
more productive, so you can
spend more time dreaming up and
implementing the next great
thing.
So, this year we focused on
making it more efficient and
faster for you to use the tools
we rethought some of the basic
workflows.
Let's take a look.
We'll start with a quick recap
of Xcode 10.
Now in Xcode 10, there's three
main Editor modes, Standard,
Assistant and Version, and they
live up here in the toolbar,
because they apply to the entire
windows content.
Now, the Version Editor, it's
got three modes of its own,
Comparison, Authors, and Log.
So, you've got a lot of
functionality available to you.
You just have to pick the one
thing that you're most
interested in.
Well, we heard your feedback
that you wanted more
flexibility.
And so, we, we made some
improvements.
At first, we took the Source
Control Log information, and we
moved it over to the Inspector,
where it's now available all the
time for any file.
So, you can bring it in when you
need it, without ever disrupting
what's in the main editor area.
And next, we wanted to let you
change each Editor Panes mode
independently, because we know
that different file types like
Source Code and Storyboards,
they have very different
workflows.
So we move the Assistant and the
Authors out of the main toolbar
down into each editor pane.
So, now you can choose the right
mode for each editor.
Now a lot of people use the
Assistant today to split up
their Xcode window with multiple
editors.
Well in Xcode 11, you can create
splits anytime, anywhere.
And you can split both
horizontally, as well as
vertically, all within the same
window.
So, there's a lot of added
flexibility this year which
really does make it easier than
ever to work the way that you
want.
Now there is no better way to
see this than in a demo.
So, here to show it to you now
is Brendan.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks Ken.
So, we've given Xcode a bit of a
renovation this year to give you
more control of your workspace.
One of the most visible changes,
is to the Editor Splitting and
the Assistant.
So, let me start with the
Assistant, and its new companion
mode, the SwiftUI Canvas.
Each editor has an options menu
in the top right.
This is where you control the
behavior of the editor.
I have this one set to Editor in
Canvas, which means that if
there is a SwiftUI preview to
show, Xcode will show it.
In this case, there is no
preview.
So there's nothing to see.
But if I switch over to a file
that has a preview the Canvas
appears and Xcode renders a
preview of my UI.
Now, the Assistant works the
same way.
If I switch over to the
Assistant using the options
menu, Xcode will show me the
generated interface for this
file.
But if I switch to a file that
doesn't have an Assistant, like
the project, it gets out of the
way.
There's no space wasted and
there's no need for me to spend
time manually switching modes as
I switch between files.
All right.
When I switch back to a source
file, of course, it remembers
the state I was in, the
Assistant comes back.
So, that's the Assistant, and
the SwiftUI Canvas, let's talk
about Editor Splitting.
The first thing is, it no longer
requires the Assistant.
So, let me get that out of the
way.
So, there's a few different ways
I can split this window up.
I'm going to start with the Add
Editor button, which is up here
in the corner, next to the
options menu.
When I click that, I get two
independent editors.
These editors have their own
state.
So if I want to, I can turn on
modes like Code Coverage or
Authors for each editor
individually.
The new editor is active.
So to load another file into it,
all I have to do is click on the
file.
All right.
So, I've got two editors, I've
got two files, let's add a
third.
I'm going to split the editor on
the left, so I'm going to use
the Add Editor button in the
left editor.
And I'm going to hold the option
key down, so that I can split it
in the opposite direction.
The icon rotates to show me
what's going to happen.
So, I got an editor on the
bottom, and it's active.
So, another click and I've
loaded that file.
Sometimes I want to do that the
other way around, though,
sometimes I want to click on a
file and tell Xcode where to put
it.
For that, I use the Destination
Chooser.
I'll just hold option and shift.
Click on the file that I want,
and the Destination Chooser
appears.
Now I can just hit return to
open it in the active editor.
Or I can use the arrow keys or
the mouse to insert a new editor
here, to open it in this editor,
put an editor there, over here,
whatever I want.
I can also use standard keyboard
shortcuts to do things like
switch tabs, put it somewhere
over here, or switch windows,
put it somewhere over here.
There's a lot of flexibility
here, a lot of power.
So, I'm going to put this one
down here under the Globe Scene.
Just press return.
And I've got a set of files that
I want to work with, a layout
that I like, everything's set,
but what if I want to just focus
on one of these files for a
minute.
That's what the new Focus mode
is for, each editor has a button
in the corner next to the close
button and if I click that, I
can zoom in this editor to take
over the whole window.
So, let me use that to zoom in
and talk about what's new in the
Source Editor.
So, one of my favorite new
features in the Source Editor is
the Minimap that's in the
options menu, of course.
So, I'll turn on Minimap, and
then let me make it a little bit
bigger, so you can see it.
So, the Minimap, of course, is a
bird's eye view of your code, it
shows you the contours of your
code it shows you the syntax
coloring.
And it's meant for navigation.
So, it tells you where you're
going before you get there, as
you hover over different
elements, it shows you exactly
what it is, so you know where
you're going.
It also shows you important
landmarks, like, where you have
changes in your file or where
you have breakpoints, the text
you see down here are marks that
I've inserted into my code to
organize it.
And if I click on one of those,
you can see that we render the
marks in the Minimap, and the
Source Editor the same,
including the divider lines to
help anchor you as you scroll
around.
The Minimap also shows transient
information.
So, if I do find, for instance,
Minimap shows me all of the
matches in my file and it fades
some of the other information,
so that that stands out, so you
can see exactly where you are,
and the context of your current
match.
All right.
So, that's the Minimap.
Over on the source code side,
we've made some improvements,
like new syntax coloring options
like these declarations you see
here.
And we've added new themes,
including high contrast themes
in light and dark.
And we've given documentation, a
big boost in readability.
We've restyled it, so that it
reads more like documentation
and Xcode now understands a lot
more of the structure of your
documentation to help make it
easier to maintain.
So let me give you an example.
I have here a function which is
fully documented.
But, if I add a new parameter to
this and I'll make it a double.
I'll give it a value and then
let me use my parameter down
here, so I don't get any issues.
Now, I can use the action pop
over and Add Documentation to
fill in the gaps in my code.
Best of all, it also works with
multiple cursors, so if you have
a bunch of gaps to fill it's
really easy.
All right.
So, I got my documentation.
Now, let's say hypothetically,
you're on stage in front of a
very large audience, and you've
just made a typo in your code,
and then you've used Code
Completion and Add Documentation
to spread that typo around.
Well, Edit All In Scope can now
clean up your mistakes very
quickly, your signature, your
code, and now, even the
documentation, can be fixed in
one go.
[ Applause ]
All right.
One last thing I want to show
you in the Source Editor that
I'm really excited about is an
enhancement to change bars.
So down here at the bottom of my
file I have a change that I made
earlier.
Change bars have always shown
you that a reminder of the
changes you made earlier which
lines in your file have changed.
If you hover over the change
bar, it shows you where on the
line those changes are.
But now you can click on the
change bar and there's a new
Show Change command, which shows
an Inline Diff right there in
your file.
If you hover over the bar again
you can see exactly what it
changed from what it changed to,
and it's live, so any updates
that you make will be reflected
immediately in the diff.
So that's everything I want to
show in this first editor, let
me pop back out to the big
picture again to do that I just
click the Focus button again.
And my layout comes back just
where I left it.
One last thing before I go, I
want to do a quick code review
of my changes here.
So, I'm going to click the Code
Review button, and that's going
to take the active editor and
blow it up to the full window,
so that I can concentrate on the
task at hand, just like Focus
mode.
When I'm done, I click again, my
layout comes back.
That is a quick whirlwind tour
of some of the many workflow
changes in Xcode 11.
Back to you Ken.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks Brendan.
I love that new Minimap, by the
way.
And there's so many other great
Source Editor features this year
from Spell Checking to Nested
Code Folding to Inline Diff,
just to name a few.
But one area in particular that
we focused on over the last year
is Code Completion and giving
you better results in more
places.
There's now Code Completions for
Compiler Control statements and
that never Completions work more
reliably, and in more places
like here, when you're pending
an enum to an array [applause].
All right [applause].
And there's now Code Completions
for function overload.
So these are just a few of the
many Completions we've improved
in Xcode 11.
Now, let's look at the Source
Code Editor, and workflow.
Now, this is a huge year for
Swift Package Manager.
It's been thriving since we
introduced it with tons of
packages available today, all of
which let you build on the great
work happening in the community.
The packages are a great way to
factor your own code, breaking
it up into smaller, more
testable pieces.
Well, this year, we have fully
integrated Swift Package Manager
with Xcode.
You can use packages to build
apps for all of the platforms.
[ Applause ]
And packages, get first class
integration throughout Xcode,
from Source Control integration,
to debugging, to testing,
everything that you do with
packages, it works just like
you're used to, with projects.
And Xcode makes it easy to
discover and use packages, and
then just as easy to create and
share your own with the world.
The integration with multiple
services means that you are only
ever just a few clicks away from
some awesome code.
We really think you are going to
love using Swift Packages.
And here to show you how to get
started with Swift Packages in
Xcode is Patrick.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks Ken.
Today, I'm really excited to
show you all Swift Packages in
Xcode 11.
I will be working on our travel
app, which includes a trip
planning feature.
This feature right now doesn't
have any weather information
which is a pretty important part
about any trip.
I don't want to have to reinvent
the wheel to get this
information in my app.
Lucky for me, my coworker Rhonda
told me about a package that I
could use to do just this.
So, let's add it to our project.
I'll start by navigating to the
Project Editor.
And I'll navigate to the project
where I'll see a new Swift
Packages tab.
This tab will show me any
packages that my project
currently depends on.
To add the first, I'll click the
plus button.
And because I've already logged
in with my GitHub account, I can
see all of my personal packages,
organizational packages, as well
as my starred repos right at the
top Here's that forecast package
I was talking about.
So, if I click next, Xcode will
prompt me for my version
information here, and Xcode will
automatically fill in the most
recent up-to-date version for me
to start using.
And that's what I want because I
want the most up-to-date code,
right away.
When I click next, Xcode will
resolve any dependencies that my
package may have, but because
it's this pretty simple package,
it doesn't have any
dependencies, it will resolve
right away.
Finally, I need to choose which
target to link my package
product against, and I'll choose
my app target here, and I'll
finish up.
So, that was it.
All I had to do to set up my
package in my project was to add
it to this dependency section.
[ Applause ]
And over in the project
navigator, I now have a Swift
Package dependency section,
where I can browse all of the
source of this package, just
like it were part of my project,
because it is.
Great. So, I have a pretty good
idea of where I need to
implement this functionality.
I'm going to put it right in my
Weather Fetcher Swift file here,
which currently doesn't do a
whole lot.
Now that I've configured it, I
can quickly import the forecast
module.
And I'll start by creating a
Forecast Object using the region
that was passed in.
But I just grabbed this package
on GitHub and I'm not very
familiar with the API.
I could go look at it on the
web, but because of the
first-class citizen right here
in Xcode, I can quickly jump to
its definition and start
browsing its source right away.
So, I'll scroll down a little
bit.
And this observations method
looks like what I want to use.
But I'm not familiar with this
observations structure this
type.
So I want to I want to jump in
and find out more about it as
well.
And to show off some of our new
search functionality in Xcode
11, I'll use the find navigator
by using command shift F.
And I'll navigate down to the
Forecast Package here to narrow
my search just into that
Forecast Package.
I'll search for observation, and
I'll only get results for that
package.
And it looks like it's defined
right here.
OK. So this enum looks like it
has different options for me,
like the metrics that will come
back from this API, like the
high temp, the low temp, the
precipitation, and so on.
I only want the high and low
temp for my method, so I'll go
and use those.
And I'll use command shift J, to
jump back to the project
navigator, and navigate back to
the Weather Fetcher here, and
I'll start implementing this
method.
So, I'll use my Forecast Object.
I'll pass in the date that was
passing to this method.
And like I said before I want
the high temp and the low temp.
And I'll fill in my Completion
Handler really quick, grabbing
the high and low temp out of the
results, and then calling the
completion with high and low.
I'll fill in the condition
method in a very similar way,
only grabbing the condition back
from the results.
Awesome. So, now when I build,
and run, and review the results
in the simulator, I should be
able to navigate the Plan tab
and see some weather information
in my San Francisco trip.
And it looks like I got the high
and the low and the expected
conditions.
And it looks like it's going to
rain right towards the end of my
trip, so I should probably bring
a jacket.
It was that easy to configure a
Swift Package dependency in my
project and start using it right
away.
That's the weather.
Back to you Ken.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Patrick.
Now, all of that new package
integration is built on top of
Xcode Source Control Support,
and this year we're rounding
that out with a couple more
features, starting with Git
Stash, which lets you save off a
set of your changes.
[ Applause ]
It's available right here from
the Source Control menu where
you can quickly stash your
current set of working changes.
When you want to review those
changes and pop the stash you
can do that from the Source
Control navigator.
We're also integrating
Cherry-Pick from the Source
Control history view here, or
just bring up the context menu
on a comment and choose
Cherry-Pick.
So, it makes it really easy to
move changes between branches.
And like I mentioned earlier,
you can now get the Source
Control history for any file,
anytime, with the new History
Inspector, which by the way
works great for non-tech files
too.
[ Applause ]
Yesterday you saw the
introduction of a number of new
OS features, and you can begin
adopting those today.
Once you bring your iPad app to
the Mac.
You can start customizing it
using the new Mac device here in
the Storyboards Devices bar,
makes it quick and easy to make
your app feel right at home on
the Mac, and for the new iOS
dark appearance.
This system does a lot of the
work for you.
Again, using the devices bar you
can quickly switch between light
and dark and make sure that your
app looks great.
Now, all of the new SF symbols
are fully integrated.
The options you need are right
here in the inspector, things
like having the symbol size,
track the system font size.
And then when you want to browse
all the symbols, you can do that
in the redesigned library, and
then drag them right out into
your Storyboard.
Now, for your own resources,
things like colors, and images,
Asset Catalogs, they play a
really important role.
They let you vary for things
like device type and for light
and dark.
The best part is, you don't have
to write any code to do that.
In Xcode 11, in iOS 13, you can
create your own custom symbols.
They get all the great
characteristics of the new SF
Symbols.
So, symbols, they let you
specify various sizes and
weights of artwork.
And then at runtime, the system,
it'll choose the right variant,
based on things like the users'
font size, accessibility
settings, even where the art is
used within the user interface.
So this is a really powerful new
way to create dynamic artwork.
And in Xcode 11, you can
localize assets now too.
You just select an asset, click
the Localized button and the
Attributes Inspector, and choose
the localizations that you want
to customize.
[ Applause ]
Very important stuff.
And here to show you the updated
Design tools is Lisa.
>> Thank you, Ken.
Hi, everyone.
Today, I'm excited to show you
how to adopt the new iOS 13
features, Dark mode, and SF
Symbols.
Let's work on the login view of
our travel app.
The two images here, email and
password are now using custom
images.
I would like to change to use
the SF Symbols, so that they
look great and they can work
with dynamic type.
When I browse the library
earlier, there are two images
that look nice to me.
One is called envelope the other
is lock.
So let's change to use them.
First, I'm going to click the
email icon, and open the
inspector.
In Xcode 11, in the email, in
the -- our image icons here that
I cannot only view, the image
names, but also I can see their
appearances before I choose to
use them.
So I'm [applause].
Yeah, like that too.
So, I'm going to type envelope.
Now it will show me a list of
envelope with different
appearances.
I'm going to select
envelope.fill, which looks good.
And for the symbol
configurations, I would like to
set as font, so that they can
work with dynamic type.
I can also change the font size.
Let's change to a bigger one.
Title One.
Next, I would like to do the
same for the password icon.
I'm going to type in lock and
choose lock.fill which matches
the style here.
Again, I'll set the
configuration as font.
Next, I would like to take a
look how my view looks in the
Dark mode.
From the devices bar there's a
switch I can change from light
to dark, let's do it.
Now you can see the view has
been updated.
However, this image doesn't look
right.
The handle of my suitcase
disappears.
Let's figure out what happened.
I'm switching back.
Oh, I see.
The handle is black.
So, it doesn't show very well
against the dark background.
To fix that, I would like to
provide a new variant for this
image for the Dark mode.
Luckily, I have a great designer
named At.
He has already created one image
for me to use in dark.
Let's change to use it.
I'm going to select the image.
And I can click this arrow.
It will open this image into
dark appearance.
First, let's enable the dark
appearance.
And then I can drag in the
image, created by At.
Let's change by, up to the
Storyboard.
Now, you can see in Light mode,
it is still using the original
image as expected, but when I
changed to Dark.
Now the new image has been
using, it's look good.
[ Applause ]
But At is a perfectionist, he
thought these two blue buttons,
although they look good in Light
that he feel it doesn't pop as
much as he wants in Dark.
So, instead, he wanted me to
change to use a different color
orange.
Let's figure out how to do that.
I'm going to select the button.
And now, I can see the tint
color is set to use a custom
color called Button color.
So to use a light in the Light
mode, I would like continue to
using the blue button, but
actually in the Dark mode, I
would like to change to use the
orange color, just as easy as
what I done for the image.
I'm going to open in the
inspector and enable the dark
appearance.
And for the dark appearance, I'm
going to use orange color.
Let's switch back.
Cool. I do find these two-orange
button pop more and look better
now.
Next, I would like to take a
look how my view looks at
runtime.
So, I'm going to build and run
in a simulator.
In Xcode 11, there's a new
feature called Environment
Overrides.
It is located in the Debug bar.
When I click it, it will show me
a pop over that I can change
different settings, such as
system settings and
accessibility settings.
So, I can change the interface
style from light to dark to see
how my view got updated.
I can set different
accessibility settings, for
example, the bold text.
From this overrides, it allows
me to test out my app at runtime
with these different settings,
without actually changing the
settings on my simulator or
devices.
I can --
[ Applause ]
I can also change the dynamic
type size by dragging the slider
here and you can see how the
view has been updated.
[ Applause ]
Remember earlier when I said the
SF Symbols for these two images
that I used font for their
configuration.
So, now, when I'm dragging to
set different dynamic type, they
react to it, just like text.
With very simple edits, I think
my view looks great in iOS 13.
I hope this can make your app
look great as well.
Thank you.
Give it back to Ken [applause].
>> Thanks, Lisa.
These new dark iOS apps look
fantastic.
And some of the scenarios that
your users run into on their
devices, things like networking
or thermal conditions.
Those are really hard to
reproduce.
And that makes them really hard
to debug, well, in Xcode 11 you
can change the way your device
behaves, varying things like the
network throughput, or changing
the device's thermal state.
In the devices window there's a
new Device Condition section
where you can turn on the
Network Link Conditioner and
simulate real world networking
scenarios, or you can turn on
the Thermal State Conditioner.
Change your device's thermal
state, so that it behaves like
it's warmer than it actually is.
And once you turn on one of
these conditions, you'll see an
indicator on your device, and
you can tap that indicator to
see exactly which condition is
running.
And you can stop it here, or
when you disconnect from Xcode,
it'll automatically be stopped
for you.
This is a great way to make sure
that your apps perform really
well in all conditions.
Xcode 11 continues to improve
testing this year with the
introduction of test plans.
Now test plans let you define a
set of tests that you can share
across schemes.
A test plan can have any number
of configurations that let you
say what arguments do you want
to pass or what environment
variables do you want to say,
even what sanitizers do you want
to turn on?
When you run that test plan, it
runs all the tests in all the
different configurations.
So, for example, you can have a
test plan that has
configurations for each language
your app supports.
When you run that test plan, it
runs all the tests in all the
different languages, all with
just a single action.
And, of course, test plans, they
work great with the Xcode's
server where you can run your
tests on multiple devices and
simulators, all in parallel, and
now in more configurations than
ever.
And it goes without saying,
testing, it works great for iPad
apps on the Mac, as well as
those built with SwiftUI.
And that's testing.
There are some awesome
improvements to the simulator
this year.
There were the new standalone
watch apps you can deploy
directly to the watch simulator.
No iPhone simulator needed.
[ Applause ]
But the big news this year is
that the simulator is built on
top of Metal
[ Applause ]
Yeah.
So that means that apps built
using Metal can now run in the
simulator, and they get amazing
graphics performance, and
everything that's built on top
of Metal, like UIKit, well, that
gets a whole lot faster too.
You'll see a beautiful 60 frames
per second.
And CPU use, it is reduced by up
to 90% which is really great for
battery life [applause].
Yeah.
[ Applause ]
We didn't stop there though.
Simulator Warm Boots are now up
to twice as fast too.
[ Applause ]
So, big improvements to the
simulator.
Last year we introduced, OS
Signposts and Custom
Instruments, so that you can
surface your own data up through
the tools.
Well, this year, we're bringing
hierarchy to the tracks, to make
it easier for you to explore and
correlate data.
But when you use OS Signposts
each category that you log, will
now get its own track, like
this.
Then you can pin that track and
easily correlate it to another
track, like CPU use.
We're also introducing a new
template for SwiftUI to give you
insight into how much time
you're spending building your
user interfaces in the new body
methods.
And we've completely rewritten
the Metal System Trace Template
from the ground up.
It takes advantage of the new
hierarchical tracks and it's
significantly faster, up to 10
times faster.
Now, we can't finish up here
today without talking about
SwiftUI, which really is an
amazing new way to build user
interfaces.
SwiftUI makes it seamless to
move from editing to running to
debugging.
The new previews which show you
your real UI, they make these
three things, just a single
activity.
Editing, when we see this is the
future of UI development.
So, from the new Preview mode to
the inline editors, we've
rethought how to build UI code.
And we've done that with an eye
towards efficiency and direct
manipulation, so that you can
write more code without ever
typing a character.
And there's a brand-new
documentation experience to go
with it.
And that's going to get you up
and writing code quickly.
There are great new tutorials,
all which guide and teach you,
while helping you write code.
Now, you don't need to create a
new project to get started with
previews, you can use them right
in your existing apps, just
implement the new
UIViewRepresentable protocol and
hand back one of your own views.
It's really that easy.
So, whether you have an iOS,
macOS, watchOS, or tvOS app, you
can get started today.
Well, that is a look at Xcode
11.
Thank you very much.
Have a great conference.
[ Applause ]