[ Music ]
>> Hi, my name is Eryk Vershen.
I'm an engineer on the HLS
Streaming Team.
Let's get started talking about
HLS Authoring for AirPlay 2
Video.
Ever since we introduced AirPlay
on iOS users have enjoyed
AirPlaying video to their Apple
TVs and starting this year we're
expanding that support
dramatically with AirPlay built
directly into TVs.
Apple TV and AirPlay capable TVs
both provide the highest quality
video playback experience.
You may remember that we have
some specific requirements for
content delivered to tvOS and
Apple TV.
These AirPlay capable TVs are a
new class of devices so they
have their own requirements.
We have a simple agenda.
I'll cover the new requirements
and then I'll talk about changes
we made to the validation tools
to help you check for issues.
We released a new version of the
HLS authoring specification
recently that talks about the
additional requirements for
AirPlay 2.
Here is a condensed list.
Don't worry about absorbing this
list right now.
I'll devote a whole slide to
each line item.
Let's look at the details.
You need to synchronize the
different variants.
This makes switching easier.
If these color bars represent
different variants on a
timeline, what we want to do is
make them all line up nicely.
We are recommending that you use
at least millisecond precision
and as always your video
segments should start with IDR
frames.
You also want to avoid most
changes of discontinuities.
For example, do not switch
between HEVC and H.264 or
between AAC and Dolby Digital.
These TVs aren't able to switch
as seamlessly as iOS or Apple
TV.
You can change your frame rate
but not arbitrarily.
No switching between 25 frame
per second and 30.
You also want each codec to
provide a good set of variance
on its own.
These TVs will stick with the
codec they start with.
So, in particular, don't try to
use H.264 just for low
resolution video and HEVC for
high-resolution video.
That works on other devices but
not here.
You should, of course, be using
I-frame variance.
They make fast-forward, rewind
and seeking more effective.
Because these devices don't want
to switch codecs you need to
have a set of I-frame variance
matching the codec of the normal
video.
The encryption requirements
listed here aren't really
specific to AirPlay 2, but we
wanted to call them out.
The common encryption standard
recommends 10% partial
encryption.
With FairPlay we are requiring
it; other patterns will not
work.
For sample encryption there are
two ways to market.
The CMAF way with an senc box
and the ISO base media file
format way with a pair of saio
and saiz boxes.
We prefer the second form, but
you can provide both.
Lastly, some miscellaneous
requirements.
If you want to provide HDR
content, your best bet is to
provide multiple formats.
For example, Dolby Vision and
HDR 10 as TVs may support only
one of the formats, use WebVTT
for subtitles and we are now
recommending MIME types for all
your content.
Let's go into little more detail
about that.
We've had a MIME type for HLS
playlist for a long time.
The MIME types we are suggesting
for video and audio are what you
might expect.
Notice we are using text/plain
for WebVTT even though the
WebVTT spec says text/VTT.
However, the text VTT type was
not registered with the IANA and
will be rejected by some
clients.
So use text/plain instead.
Here's a list of some of the
less common MIME types.
Now the last 2 on this list are
not applicable to AirPlay 2
content.
I've listed them because we are
recommending MIME types for all
content not just AirPlay 2.
Let's turn to how you can check
your streams.
Remember that there are two
tools for HLS validation.
These tools are complementary.
Mediastreamvalidator is checking
against the HLS specification.
HLSreport on the other hand is
checking against the authoring
specification.
You should always be using both
tools.
I suggest you make a script that
runs them as a pair.
We've made an important change
to HLSreport.
Formerly you had to run it
multiple times with the dash os
option if you wanted to check
the rules for iOS and TVOS.
Now it checks all rule sets by
default including the rules for
AirPlay 2.
The rule set option is there to
modify the sets you check but
most of you won't need to use
it.
And while the OS option does
still work, you should stop
using it.
Let's look at how the output
from HLSreport has changed.
Notice that the title line now
shows all the rule sets that
were checked.
The rules portion is now grouped
into sections for each rule set.
Here we have the general
requirements.
There can be Must Fix and Should
Fix subsections for each rule
set.
Now farther down in the output
we have the iOS requirements.
I want you to notice that rule
10 above here the last general
rule is marked as Should Fix.
Whereas here in the AirPlay 2
section the same rule is a Must
Fix.
If there are no rule violations
for a section or subsection,
then that section or subsection
is dropped.
For example, this stream has no
Should F ixes for AirPlay 2.
The main points to take away are
we added new requirements for
AirPlay 2 devices.
Remember to use HLSreport so you
check against the authoring
specification.
And HLSreport now checks all
rule sets by default.
This is session 507 so you know
where to go for more info.
We'll have links there to the
authoring specification to the
tools and to other information
about HLS.
Thanks for your attention.
Have a great rest of the
conference.