[ Music ]
>> Hello and welcome to our
session about audio API updates.
My name is Peter Vasil and I am
a software engineer in the Core
Audio team.
Let's start with what's new in
AVAudioEngine.
We have added a couple of
enhancements and new API's to
AVAudioEngine.
We now have a voice processing
support.
We have added two new nodes,
AVAudioSourceNode and
AVAudiSinkNode.
And we have made some
improvements to special audio
rendering.
Now let's dive into the details.
AVAudioEngine now has a voice
processing mode.
The main use case for the mode
is echo cancellation in
voiceover IP applications.
What does this mean?
When enabled, extra signal
processing is applied on the
incoming audio and any audio
that is coming from the device
is taken out.
This requires that both input
and output nodes are in the
voice processing mode.
Therefore, when enabling the
mode on either of the I/O nodes,
the engine takes care that both
I/O nodes exist and that they
are switched to the voice
processing mode.
Voice processing is only
available when rendering to an
audio device, not a manual
rendering mode.
To enable or disable voice
processing, we can use set voice
processing enabled on either the
input or output node.
Voice processing cannot be
enabled dynamically, which means
the engine needs to be in a stop
state when enabling the mode.
The AVEchoTouch sample code
project demonstrates how to use
voice processing with
AVAudioEngine in detail.
Let's look at the new nodes in
AVAudioEngine: AVAudioSourceNode
and AVAudioSinkNode.
Both nodes wrap a user-defined
block that allows users to send
or receive audio from
AVAudioEngine.
When rendering to an audio
device, the block operates under
real-time constraints which
means that within the block
there shouldn't be any blocking
cause like memory allocations,
call to dispatch or blocking on
a mutex.
With AVAudioSourceNode, we pass
a render block to the node which
sends audio data to its output.
This makes it very easy to
create generator nodes without
having to implement a full audio
unit and wrap it with
AVAudioUnit.
The node can be used in both
real-time and manual rendering
mode.
AVAudioSourceNode supports
linear PCM conversions such as
sample rate or bit depth
conversions.
And has one output but no
inputs.
This short code snippet shows
how to use AVAudioSourceNode.
As we can see, the block is
passed as an initializer
argument and after creating the
node it can be connected just
like any other node.
A more detailed example can be
found in our signal generator
sample code project.
Let's look at AVAudioSinkNode.
AVAudioSinkNode is a symmetrical
counterpart of
AVAudioSourceNode.
It wraps a user-defined block
that receives the input audio
from the node chain that is
connected to its input.
AVAudioSinkNode is restricted to
the input chain, in other words
it must be connected downstream
of the input node.
It does not support format
conversions.
And the format within the block
has to be the same as the
hardware input format.
The node can be useful for
voiceover IP application when
the input needs to be processed
in real time, in which case
installing a regular tap would
not be sufficient because a tap
doesn't operate in a real-time
context.
Here is a code snippet
demonstrating how to create an
AVAudioSinkNode.
It is quite similar to
AVAudioSourceNode.
The main steps to note here are
to initialize the node with a
block, attach it to the engine
and connect it to a node
downstream of the input node.
Now let's see the spatial
rendering improvements.
We have introduced an automatic
spatial rendering algorithm, and
AVAudioPlayer node now supports
specialization of multichannel
audio content.
With the automatic spatial
rendering algorithm, the most
appropriate specialization
algorithm is selected for the
current route.
This means developers don't need
to figure out what algorithms
are suitable for headphones or
different speaker
configurations.
This adds near field and
inherent rendering for
headphones and virtual surround
for built-in speakers is
available starting with iOS
devices and laptops from 2018
and newer.
Here we see the new API and the
AVAudio3DMixing protocol.
The AVAudio3DMixing rendering
algorithm ENUM has a new entry:
auto.
Additionally, we can specify the
output type with the output type
property.
With the property set to auto,
the output type can be
automatically detected in
real-time mode but not in manual
rendering mode.
With the ability to specialize
multichannel streams, we support
point source and ambience bed
rendering.
We also support channel-based
formats and high-order
Ambisonics up to the third
order.
We have added two new
specialization properties to the
AVAudio3DMixing protocol: source
mode and point source and head
mode.
Specialize if mono is legacy
behavior.
This is the same as bypass for
any multichannel stream, which
means a pass-through or down mix
to the output format.
With point source, the audio is
sum-to-mono and rendered at the
location of the player node.
And with ambiance bed, the audio
is anchored to the 3D world and
is rotatable with the player
node's position relative to the
listener orientation.
Here we see an example of
ambience bed source mode with
automatic rendering algorithm.
After setting the properties, it
is important to make sure the
format that is used for the
connection between player node
and environment node contains
the multichannel layout.
Now let's talk about what's new
in AVAudioSession.
AVAudioSession prompt style is a
hint to apps that play voice
prompts in order to modify the
style of the plate prompt.
For example, if Siri is speaking
or a phone call is ongoing,
verbal navigation prompts is a
confusing user experience.
We also don't want Siri to
record the navigation prompt.
Navigation apps for example are
encouraged to pay attention to
prompt style changes and modify
their prompts for better user
experience.
We have three prompt styles:
none, short and normal.
We can now indicate to disable
prompts completely, play
shortened prompts or play the
regular prompts.
Let's look at other
AVAudioSession enhancements.
The default policy is to mute
haptics and system sounds when
audio recording is active.
A new property allow haptics and
system sounds during recording,
allows system sounds and haptics
to play while the session is
actively using an audio input.
It can be said using the set
allowHapticsAndSystem
SoundsDuringRecording.
For more information, please
visit the developer website.
Thank you for your attention.