[ Music ]
>> Hello. I'm Jonathan Davis,
web technologies evangelist for
the Safari and WebKit teams.
Welcome to Understanding CPU
Usage with Web Inspector.
We all know that battery life is
important to users and you
probably instinctively know the
web browser is one of the
most-used apps on our devices.
But beyond that, web content is
also incorporated into many
popular iOS and macOS apps.
That means web content
significantly affects battery
life for users.
So making it power-efficient has
a big impact.
Safari and WebKit already
provide features to
automatically save power for
users when possible, such as
throttling timers when a webpage
is in the background.
And with support for content
blocker extensions, users can
automatically block loading
unwanted content that's often
just junk slowing down their
browser, or worse, tracking
them.
But even with the built-in
power-saving features in Safari,
there's a lot left in the hands
of web developers.
So it's an opportunity for all
of us to improve performance and
build a power-efficient web for
users.
The good news is that everything
you know about good performance
practices on the web also apply
as best practices for saving
power.
So all of the things we've heard
about improving page load time,
optimizing JavaScript, and using
CSS animations and transitions
really help with battery life.
Whether you're experienced with
all the best practices for
performance on the web or just
starting out, I'm going to show
you a powerful new tool in Web
Inspector that's going to give
you superpowers for finding
where performance can be
improved to save battery life.
It's called the CPU Usage
Timeline.
And it's new in Web Inspector in
Safari 13 for macOS.
It provides a window into power
use that makes it easy to see
the impact of behaviors that
contribute to high CPU usage.
Today I'm going to show you how
to work with a new CPU Usage
Timeline, discover power issues
through CPU usage, and then I'll
briefly go over some strategies
for improving power savings in
your web-based projects.
Now before you can use the new
timeline, you'll need to enable
the Develop menu to access Web
Inspector.
Just load up Safari preferences
and click on Advanced.
And click to enable the Show
Develop Menu in Menu Bar option.
Now just load up a webpage and
open Web Inspector from the
Develop menu.
Or use the keyboard shortcut
Command-Option-I.
I am going to use the new CPU
Usage Timeline to look for where
we can improve power on
WebKit.org.
The homepage is pretty simple
but it should be interesting
because it still has some
dynamic things happening like
this subtle logo animation in
the background.
With Web Inspector open, click
over to the Timelines tab.
In the upper left is a list of
different timelines.
There's a bunch of other
timelines you can use, but the
defaults will work great to look
for ways to improve CPU usage.
To start a recording, you can
click the red Record button or
press the space bar.
But I'm going to click the
Reload button, which will
automatically start a recording
and capture page load, too.
When looking at CPU usage, it's
important to remember you'll
want to record at least 15
seconds in order to get useful
measurements.
So I'll let this recording go a
bit beyond that to capture
enough data.
Now I'll scroll over the
timeline to zoom out a bit so I
can see everything.
Clicking on the CPU timeline,
you can see details about CPU
usage of the page.
At a glance, I can tell the page
does a pretty good job of
keeping energy use low.
The quick load time helps a lot
and when the page becomes idle,
the timeline shows the page as
basically doing nothing.
This is great because it means
users can stay on the page all
day and the CPU drops to a very
low power state with negligible
battery drain caused by the web
content.
The Main Thread is where a lot
of interesting work happens for
web content.
The Main Thread chart shows
different categories of work
done on the Main Thread
including JavaScript processing,
painting, layout and things in
service of layout like style
recalculation.
Based on this, we can see that
most of the time working was
spent on painting.
In the middle of the indicator
is the time it took for the Main
Thread to complete its work.
The entire recording was about
20 seconds but the Main Thread
only took about 100 milliseconds
to complete its work.
Below the Main Thread chart is a
detailed breakdown of the CPU
usage across all of the threads
involved in doing work for the
web content.
I can take a closer look at this
by clicking and dragging in the
timeline to select just the time
range where the work is being
done.
And just under the CPU usage
graph, in this thin strip, is
the Main Thread Indicator, which
shows categories of work that
were happening on the Main
Thread at different points in
time.
In this area of growing
activity, there were some layout
events in red, followed by
significant painting work, just
like in the chart above, but
showing when it happened.
The Energy Impact Gauge really
brings it all together though.
It provides a score based on the
total average usage across all
CPU cores for the selected time
range.
The Energy Impact Gauge really
brings it all together though.
It provides a score based on the
total average usage across all
CPU cores for the selected time
range.
The Energy Impact Gauge is
interactive and as a total
average will change depending on
the time range selected.
For the page load period, the
gauge shows medium energy
impact.
But loading is expensive in
terms of power so that's
expected.
At least it stayed out of the
high range.
That would have indicated a
problem.
Double-clicking the Timeline
area to select the entire
recording shows the overall
average CPU is low.
I can click and drag the
timeline to select a slice of
time out of the recording and
watch the average change.
Now when I click to grab the
selection and slide it to a
period where the page goes idle,
the energy impact drops to low.
That's really great.
When the page is idle, we don't
want to be costing the user lots
of power for content they're not
actively using.
The CPU use was in the low range
while idle, even with the
rotating logo animation
happening in the background.
That's because it's using a
simple CSS animation that makes
it really cheap to animate, but
it still gives the page a nice
visual impact.
WebKit.org is doing great so
far, but when you're looking for
power issues, looking at loading
and idle are good starts.
To cover all the bases, we need
to capture some interactivity
too.
The WebKit Feature Status page
is a great way to stay up to
date for WebKit support for your
favorite web features.
It allows you to filter and
search and that's perfect for
capturing interaction.
I'm going to record a timeline
and interact with the page in
some ways.
I'll just scroll down to the
bottom and then all the way back
up to the top.
And then I'll do a quick search
and click on some things here
and there.
And again, we should at least
capture 15 seconds.
Since we're on a new page, we
should capture some period of
idle too.
I'm going to let this continue
recording to get enough idle
time captured.
Okay, that looks pretty good.
Now I'm going to select the
entire recording and scroll to
zoom out of the timeline a bit
so we can see everything.
And click to look at the CPU
Usage Details.
Let's start digging into these
areas starting with loading.
The page managed to stay out of
the high range during the quick
load time, so we're okay there.
Now let's look at this range of
interactivity.
The energy impact stays in the
medium range even with all of
these things happening.
But you can tell form the
JavaScript and Events Timeline,
there's a lot of script firing
while scrolling and interacting.
We definitely want to avoid
doing any extra CPU work while
scrolling, since it's very
expensive to scroll.
Let's see if we need to be doing
that work or not.
The Statistics and Sources
sections tell the story.
There were over 1,200 entries
into JavaScript for the selected
time in the recording; 596
Request Animation Frame timers
fired, and there are 647 scroll
events.
Now I know that reducing timers
and staying off of scrolling is
better for performance, but we
need to look at the code to know
if it's necessary or can be
improved.
In the statistics area, you can
click on the timers or events to
filter the sources on the right
to the code that triggered it.
And clicking the source takes
you right to the code in the
JavaScript debugger.
Ah, okay.
It looks like the Request
Animation Frame timer is calling
Update Images, which iterates
over all of the images and
checks if they are in view.
And if so, it loads them.
It's a pretty basic Lazy Loaded
images pattern.
But this dimmed out code in the
debugger tells us In View and
Load Image are never called.
Even though we scrolled the
entire page to the bottom and
back up to the top, it makes
sense though because there's
basically no images on the page.
So the Lazy Loading image code
shouldn't be firing at all on
this page.
Let's switch back to the code.
The images and the event
handlers are set up here.
So looking at the code, it's
just always setting up the event
handlers for scroll and resize
all of the time.
To keep that from happening, we
just need to add a conditional
guard.
There, let's try that.
Okay, so let's capture a
timeline with a fix in place.
I'll click back over to the
Timelines tab, start a new
recording and I'll do some quick
scrolling.
You can already see there are no
JavaScript entries showing up in
the timeline.
It's all just paints.
So our guard is working to
prevent extra JavaScript work
while scrolling on a page
without any Lazy Loaded images.
The energy impact has been
reduced and all of the Main
Thread work is paints for
scrolling.
But we need to make sure that
the pages that should be using
Lazy Loaded images are still
working.
Again with the fix in place,
I'll record a new timeline on a
page with a motion mark logo
image at the bottom that should
use the Lazy Loader.
Perfect.
The motion mark image loaded in.
I'm going to scroll to get some
CPU measurements of the new
behavior and click the CPU
timelines to see where we're at.
So we've reduced the timer and
events to just the pages where
it's necessary.
That's great.
But there's still a lot of
entries into script when
scrolling on pages with a Lazy
Loaded image.
There's an API available in
Safari that we can use to take
this solution a step further.
We can replace the Request
Animation Frame implementation
to use Intersection Observer
instead.
Intersection Observer can tell
when an element comes into view,
so you can limit your work to
just when it's visible.
And as soon as it goes out of
view, you can stop the work to
get back to a low CPU power
state and save power.
So with the Intersection
Observer implementation, let's
record another timeline and do
some scrolling to see how this
solution performs.
And as I begin scrolling,
there's just a single entry into
JavaScript.
And for the rest of the time,
it's just painting while I
scroll.
So in the end we went from 16.3%
down to 9.5% average CPU usage
with the Intersection Observer
solution.
Every little bit helps and
that's a really nice
improvement.
So there are lots of ways to
save power in web content.
Use the CPU Usage Timeline to
investigate web content for ways
to improve during interactivity
and when the page is idle.
Remember that reducing CPU usage
saves energy and reduces battery
drain for users.
CSS animations and transitions
can provide dynamic visuals
without the power cost.
And try to avoid doing work
while scrolling.
Use the Intersection Observer
API instead.
Users want an engaging, dynamic
experience with web content, but
the best version of those
experiences use the least amount
of CPU possible.
There are a lot more
power-saving tips for web
development on the WebKit Blog.
Check out the links in the
Resources section associated
with this video.
We hope you'll try using these
tools on your web content and
use the advice in this video as
some starting places for your
investigations on how to make
your web content power
efficient, and join us in
helping the web become more
powerful by using less power.