[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Hey, everyone.
My name is Michael Brennan.
I'm a software engineer here at
Apple working on Core ML.
And I'm thrilled to be able to
share with you some of the
amazing new features we've
introduced this year for Core ML
3.
Core ML makes it as easy as
possible to seamlessly integrate
machine learning into your
application allowing you to
create a wide variety of novel
and compelling experiences.
At the center of all of this is
the model itself.
You can get a model from a
number of supported training
libraries by converting them
using the converters we have as
a part of our Core ML tools
which we provide.
And with the addition of the new
Create ML app, we've made it
even easier than before to get a
model.
So in this session we're going
to cover a number of topics from
personalizing those models on
device to additional support
we've added for neural networks
and even more.
So let's get started by talking
a little bit about personalizing
your models on-device.
Traditionally, these models are
either bundled with or
downloaded to your application.
And once on your device are
completely mutable being
optimized heavily for
performance within your app.
The great thing about
associating a model with your
app is it means you can provide
the same great experience across
all of your users.
But each user is unique.
They each have their own
specialized needs, their own
individual ways of interacting
with your application.
I think this creates an
opportunity.
What if each user could get a
model personalized specifically
for them?
Well, let's look at the case of
one user on how to do this.
We can take data from that user,
set up some sort of cloud
service, send that data to that
cloud service, and in the cloud
create that new model
personalized on that data which
will then deploy back to that
user.
This creates a number of
challenges, both to you, the
developers, and to our users.
For you, it creates the
challenge of added expenses with
making these cloud services
managing that service and
creating an infrastructure that
could scale to million of users.
And for the user, obviously they
have to expose all their data.
It's unwanted.
It's invasive.
They have to expose this and
send it up to the cloud where
it'll be managed by some other
party.
On Core ML 3, you can do this
kind of personalization all on
device.
[ Applause ]
Simply take that general model
and with the data the users
created or regenerated, you can
personalize that model with that
data for that user.
This means that the data stays
private.
It never leaves the device.
This means there's no need for a
server to do this kind of
interactivity.
And this means you can do it
anywhere.
You're not tying your users down
to Wi-Fi or some data plan just
to update their model.
Before we continue, let's look
inside one of these models and
see what's there today.
Currently, your model consists
of mostly parameters, things
like the weights of the layers
if it's a neural network for
example.
And some metadata describing
things like licensing and
authors, as well as an
interface.
And this where your app concerns
itself with.
It describes how you can
interact with this model.
On Core ML 3, we've added a new
set of parameters to help
updating.
It describes what parts of the
model are updatable and how it's
updatable.
We've added a new update
interface your app can leverage
to make these updates happen.
This means that all the
functionality is accessed
directly through that interface.
We encapsulate away a lot of
those heavy details and it's all
contained within that one model
file.
So just like in making a
prediction, we supply a set of
inputs and you get a
corresponding set of outputs.
Making an update is easy, you
just supply a set of training
examples and you'll get out a
new variant of that model that
was fit or fine-tuned to that
data.
For Core ML 3, we support making
updatable models of nearest
neighbor classifiers as well as
neural networks.
And we're going to support
embedding an updatable model
within your pipeline, meaning
your pipelines are updatable
too.
And with that, I think we should
see this in action.
So I'd like to hand it over to
my colleague Anil Katti.
Anil.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Michael.
Hello. Today I show how I build
an experience that was
customized for my users using
model personalization.
For this I have an app that
helps teachers grade students'
homework.
I added a cool new feature to
this app using model
personalization.
But before we talk about the
feature, let's see what the app
does first.
Let me switch over to the demo
screen.
Great. So here's the app.
It's called a Personalized
Grading App.
What it allows you to do is take
a picture of the homework and
start grading the way our
teacher would on a sheet of
paper.
You'd mark something as correct
like that and something as wrong
like that.
It's pretty straightforward.
Pretty simple.
The app uses PencilKit to
capture the input and the
pretrained Core ML model to
recognize the grading samples.
Now recently, I added a new
feature that allows teachers
give something special for the
kids for encouragement.
And that is stickers.
Kids absolutely love collecting
stickers on their homework.
So we thought it might be a
really nice enhancement to the
app if they could allow-- if we
could allow them to give
stickers.
So to give a sticker, I could
tap on this plus button up here.
Scroll through the list of
stickers, maybe pick one, and
drag it to the right location
[inaudible].
This works.
But I think we can make the flow
even better and absolutely
magical for our users.
Let's think about it a little
bit.
The user is only using an Apple
Pencil for grading.
How cool would it be if they
could quickly sketch something
anywhere on the entire screen
and the app automatically pick
the right sticker of the correct
size and place it at the right
location for them.
Well, we can definitely do
something like that with machine
learning, right?
So let's explore some options.
Let me switch over to the
slides.
Well, some of you who have
already worked on Core ML might
be thinking, well, we could
actually pre-train a model that
can recognize stickers and ship
it as part of the app.
Well, we could do that but there
are a few issues with this
approach.
For one, there are a lot of
stickers out there and we might
have to collect a lot of
training data in order to
pre-train these models, although
a particular user might only be
interested in a small subset of
these stickers.
Second, how does this pretrained
model work if I plan to
introduce a bunch of new
stickers in the future?
Well, I might have to re-train
the model and ship it as an app
update or maybe allow the app to
download it.
Lastly, and I think this is the
most crucial point, how does
this pretrained model work for
different users?
Different users have different
ways of sketching.
If I went out and I asked a
hundred different people to
quickly sketch this mind-blowing
sticker, I'll get at least 50
different answers.
Now, it's truly mind-blowing how
different people are.
So what should the app do in
this case?
Should we-- Should the app train
the users on how to sketch
something, or should the users
train the app, enhance the model
how to recognize your sketches?
Well, that's exactly what model
personalization is all about.
What I did was use model
personalization to train-- to
define a model using the data
that I collected about the
user-- from the user to suit
their needs.
Let me show how that translates
to user experience.
I'll switch back to the demo
screen to continue my grading.
So the third answer-- third
question there is pretty tricky
for kindergarten care, but I
think Jane got it spot on.
There are four triangles in that
diagram.
So, good job, Jane.
Well, now I want to give her a
sticker to recognize the
attention to detail, but I want
to do it by quickly sketching
something.
Let's try doing that.
So the app seems to tell me that
it could not recognize what I
sketch, which is pretty fair
because this is the first time
I'm using this app.
So let me try to add a sticker,
but this time I'll say I want to
create a shortcut, right.
And I'll pick the same sticker
that I used last time.
So now the app is asking me to
give an example of how I would
sketch this particular sticker.
It doesn't have to be perfect.
It doesn't even have to resemble
the sticker.
It's just my own representation
of how I would want to sketch
that sticker, right?
So I'll just use a single star
to represent that particular
sticker.
The app asked me for a couple of
more examples, which is pretty
fair, and it just took a few
seconds but now it looks like
the app-- the shortcut has been
registered.
Now I see the sticker as well as
examples I provided in the
screen.
Before I go back, let me add one
more sticker to my library.
So, there was this really nice
high five sticker that I wanted
to use, which is right here.
I wonder what I should use as
shortcut for this.
I wanted-- I want something that
is easy to remember, easy to
sketch.
How about the number 5, which
kind of says high five?
Great. So just two more examples
and I'm done.
Let's go back to the screen and
try giving that sticker that
Jane has been desperately
waiting for.
Isn't that cool?
[ Applause ]
I'm so glad I didn't have the go
through the sticker picker and
move the sticker around and all
those mess.
Great. For the next one-- yeah,
that's right as well.
So let me give another small
star there.
I'm super happy with the way the
app behaves, so a big high five
at the top.
How about that?
[ Applause ]
So this was just an example.
You guys can think about really
amazing experiences that you can
kind of solve using this new
feature.
So before I wrap up, let me
quickly go with the things that
I had to do in order to
implement this feature.
So the first thing I had to do
was import an updatable Core ML
model into my project.
And this is how it looks in
Xcode.
Since I was trying to
personalize the model by adding
new stickers or classes, using
the nearest neighbor classifier
made a lot of sense, although
that is a pretrained neural
network feature extractor, that
is filling in into the nearest
neighbor classifier to help
improve the prediction
efficiency and robustness.
But that's it, you don't have to
worry about any of model details
since Core ML abstracts the way
all the model details from the
API surface.
You can use this model for
prediction.
There is no change there.
In Xcode you will see the
prediction inputs and outputs
like before.
But what's new this year is an
update section.
This describes the set of
inputs, yeah, this model
requires for personalization.
And as expected, it requires a
sticker which is a grayscale
image, and a corresponding
sketch which is a grayscale
sticker which serves as a true
label in order to personalize.
In terms of code, you may recall
that Core ML auto-generates a
set of classes to help you with
the prediction.
And now it generates new class
that helps you provide the
training data in a [inaudible]
manner.
If you peek into this class,
you'll see a set of properties
which are in line with what you
saw in Xcode, right?
So we see the sketch and the
sticker here.
So once you have collected all
the training data from the user
that is required to personalize
a model for-- or for the user,
the actual personalization
itself can happen in three easy
steps.
First, you need to get the
updatable model URL that you
could get either from the bundle
or from a previous snapshot of
the updated model.
Next, you would prepare the
training data in the expected
format.
For this, you could either use
the origin rated class that I
showed or build a feature
provider of your own.
And lastly, you would kick off
an update task.
Once the update is complete,
completion handler gets invoked
which provides you the updated
model that you can use for
predictions immediately.
It's that simple.
I can't wait to see all the cool
things that you will build on
top of this in your apps and
frameworks.
With that, let me hand it back
to Michael to recap and cover
some more complex scenarios and
model personalization.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> All right.
Thanks, Anil.
So just a recap, Anil just
showed us, we took our base
model and we tried to make a
personal experience out of that
by supplying some drawings which
were just beautiful to our model
and seeing what we got as an
output.
Initially, we didn't get much.
That's because internally, even
though we have that pretrained
neural network, it feeds into a
K-nearest neighbor base
classifier which is actually
empty.
It has no neighbors to classify
on.
So we actually update this and
give us some neighbors.
Well, as Anil showed us, we took
our training data, the stickers
we chose and the drawings we
drew to correspond with that,
and we feed those along with our
base model, with that updatable
K-nearest neighbor base model in
it to our update task.
And this gives us that new
variant of our model.
And this new variant can more
reliably recognize what it was
trained on while internally the
only thing that's changed was
that updatable K-nearest
neighbor base model.
So let's look at the ML update
task class, which we've
introduced this year to help
with managing these update
processes.
So it has a state associated
with it where it's at in the
process as well as the ability
to resume and cancel that task.
And to construct one you just
pass in that base URL for your
model along with configuration
and the training data.
And as Anil showed, you need to
pass in a completion handler as
well.
As completion handler, we'll
call when you're done with the
update task and it gives you an
update context.
And you can use this to write
out that model when you're done
with your update, to make
predictions on it, and query
other parts of that task which
allows us to get part of this
update context.
In code, as Anil showed us,
really straightforward to
implement.
You just construct an
MLupdateTask provided that URL,
your configuration, and your
completion handler, which here
we use to check for accuracy,
retain the model outside the
scope of this block and save out
that model.
This is great.
It works really well and it got
us through this demo.
But what about the more complex
use cases, right?
What about neural networks?
Well, a neural network in its
simplest case is just a
collection of layers, each with
some inputs and some weights
that it uses in combination to
create an output.
To adjust that output, we'll
need to adjust the weights in
those layers.
And to do that, we need to mark
these layers as updatable.
And we need some way of telling
it by how much our output was
off.
If we expected a star smiley
face and we got a high five, we
need to correct for that.
And that's going to be done to
our loss functions, which
describes that delta there.
And finally we need to provide
this to our optimizer.
And this takes that loss, our
output, and it figures out by
how much to actually adjust the
weights in these layers.
On Core ML 3, we support
updating of convolution and
fully collect-- fully connected
layers as well as having the
ability to back-propagate
through many more.
And we support categorical
cross-entropy and mean squared
error loss types.
In addition, we support
stochastic gradient descent and
Adam optimization strategies.
This is awesome, right?
But there's other parameters
associated with neural networks,
like learning rate and the
number of epoch to run for.
This is all are going to be
encapsulated within that model.
We understand that some of you
may want to change that at
runtime though.
And you can do that.
By overriding the update
parameters dictionary and your
model configuration, you can
override those values within,
using MLParameterKey and just
specifying values for them,
giving you a lot of flexibility
here.
In addition, if you're wondering
what parameters are actually
embedded within my model anyway,
you can check out the parameter
section of that model view in
Xcode and it will give you
details for the values of those
parameters as well as what
parameters are actually defined
within that model.
You may want more flexibility
than the API we showed earlier
and we provide that.
In your MLUpdateTask, you can
provide an
MLupdateProgressHandler instead
of the completion handler and
supply progress handlers and
that completion handler that
will allow you to key in
specific events.
So when your training began or
when an epoch ended, we'll call
your progress handler and we'll
provide you that update context
just as we did in the completion
handler.
In addition, we'll tell you what
event caused us to call that
callback as well as giving you
key metrics, so you can query
for your training loss as each
mini batch or each epoch gets
processed.
And in code, still really
straightforward.
You construct this
MLupdateProgressHandler, tell it
what events you're interested
in, and supply a block to be
called.
In addition, you'll just provide
the completion handler there as
well and the MLUpdateTask you
just provide the set of progress
handlers.
So we've talked about how to
update your models and what it
means to update them.
Well, we haven't really
discussed yet so far is when
it's appropriate to do that.
Now, on the grading app we
showed earlier, we're doing it
the second he interacted with
the app and drew a drawing.
And we took that data and sent
it off to the model.
But that may not be appropriate.
What if you have thousands or
millions of data points?
And what if your model's
incredibly complicated?
Well, I'm thrilled to say that
using the BackgroundTask
framework will allot several
minutes of runtime to your
application.
Even if the user isn't using
your app or even if they're not
interacting with the device, you
just use the BGTaskScheduler and
make a BGProcessingTaskRequest
and we'll give you several
minutes to do further updates
and further computations.
And to see more about this--
Yeah
[ Applause ]
It's great.
And to see more about this, I
highly recommend you check out
Advances in App Background
Execution.
In addition, how do you get an
updatable model?
Well, as we talked about earlier
in the session, you can get a
model by converting them from a
number of supported training
libraries, that story has not
changed.
You simply pass the respect
trainable flag in when you're
converting your model and it'll
take those trainable parameters
- the things like what
optimization strategy you want,
what layers are updatable -- and
we'll take that and embed that
within your model.
And then the rest of it, it's
just as what it was before.
And for those of you who want to
modify the model itself
directly, that's still fully
supported as well.
So we've talked about how to
make a more personal experience
for a user in your application,
using on-device model
personalization, and you can do
that through our new flexible
yet simple API.
It's great.
You can do this completely
on-device.
And with that, I'd like to hand
it over to my colleague Aseem
Wadhwa to tell you more about
some of the amazing new features
we've added this year for neural
networks.
[ Applause ]
>> OK. So I'm very excited to
talk about what's new in Core ML
this year for neural networks.
But before we jump into that, I
do want to spend a few minutes
talking about neural networks in
general.
Well, we all know that neural
networks are great at solving
challenging task, such as
understanding the content of an
image or a document or an audio
clip.
And we can use this capability
to build some amazing apps
around them.
Now, if you look inside a neural
network and try to see its
structure, we can maybe get a
better understanding about it.
So let's try to do that.
But instead of looking from a
point of view of a researcher,
let's try a different
perspective.
Let's try to look at it from a
programmer's perspective.
So if you visualize inside a
Core ML model, what we see is
something like a graph.
And if you look closely, we
realize that graph is just
another representation of a
program.
Let's look at it again.
So here is a very simple code
snippet that we all understand.
And here is its corresponding
graph representation.
So as you might have noticed
that the operations in the code
have become these notes in the
graph and the readable such as
X, Y, Z, are these edges in the
graph.
Now, if you go back to a neural
network graph and now show a
corresponding code snippet, it
looks pretty similar to what we
had before.
But there are a couple of
differences I want to point out.
One, instead of those simple
numeric variables, we now have
these multidimensional variables
that have couple of attributes.
So it has an attribute called
shape and something called rank,
which is a number of dimensions
that it has.
And the second thing is the
functions operating on these
multidimensional variables are
now these specialized math
functions, which is sometimes
called as layers or operations.
So if you really look at the
neural network, we see that it's
essentially either a graph or a
program that involves these very
large multidimensional variables
and these very heavy
mathematical functions.
So essentially it's a very
compute and memory intensive
program.
And the nice thing about Core ML
is that it encapsulates all
these complexity into a single
file format, which the Core ML
framework and then sort of
optimize and execute very
efficiently.
So if we go back last year and
see what we had in Core ML 2,
well, we could easily represent
straight-line code using acyclic
graphs.
And we had about 40 different
layer types using which we could
represent most of the common
convolutional and recurrent
architectures.
So what's new this year?
Well, as you might have noticed
with my analogy to program, we
all know that code can be much
more complex than simple
straight-line code, right?
For instance, it's quite common
to use a control flow like a
branch as shown in the code
snippet here.
And now, in Core ML 3, what's
new is that we can represent the
same concept of a branch within
the neural network
specification.
[ Applause ]
So another common form of
control flow is obviously loops,
and that too can be really
easily expressed within a Core
ML network.
Moving on to another complex
feature of code, something we do
often when we're writing a
dynamic code is allocate memory
at runtime.
As shown in this code snippet,
we are allocating a memory that
depends on the input of the
program so it can change at
runtime.
Now we can do exactly the same
in Core ML this year using what
we call dynamic layers, which
allows us to change the shape of
the multi array based on the
input of the graph.
So you might be thinking that
why are we adding sort of these
new complex code constructs
within the Core ML graph, and
the answer is simple, because
neural networks research is
actively exploring these ideas
to make even more powerful
neural networks.
In fact, many state of the art
neural networks sort of-- have
some sort of control flow built
into them.
Another aspect that researchers
are constantly exploring is sort
of new operations.
And for that, we have added lots
of new layers to Core ML this
year.
Not only have we made the
existing layers more generic but
we have added lots of new basic
mathematical operations.
So, if you come across a new
layer, it's highly likely that
it can be expressed in terms of
the layers that are there in
Core ML 3.
[ Applause ]
So with all these features of
control flow, dynamic behavior,
and new layers, the Core ML
model has become much more
expressive than before.
And the great part of it is that
most of the popular
architectures out there can now
be easily expressed in the Core
ML format.
So as you can see on this slide,
we have listed a few of those.
And the ones highlighted have
really come in the last few
months and they're really
pushing the boundaries of
machine learning research.
And now you can easily express
them in Core ML and integrate
them in your apps.
So that's great.
[ Applause ]
So now you might be wondering
that how do I make use of these
new features within a Core ML
model.
Well, the answer is same as it
was last year.
There are two options to build a
Core ML model.
One, since Core ML is an open
source Protobuf specification,
we can always specify a model
programmatically using any
programming language of your
choice.
So that option is always
available to us.
But in the majority of the
cases, we like to use converters
that can automatically do that
for us by translating a graph
from a different representation
into the Core ML representation.
So let's look at both of these
approaches a little bit in
detail.
So here I'm showing a simple
neural network and how it can be
easily expressed using Core ML
tools, which is a simple Python
wrapper around the Protobuf
specification.
I personally like this approach,
especially when I'm converting a
model whose architecture I
understand well.
And if I have the pretrained
weights available to me in a
nice data such as numbered
arrays.
Having said that, neural
networks are often much more
complex, and we are better off
using converters and we have a
few of them.
So we have a few converters
available on GitHub using which
you can target most of the
machine learning frameworks out
there.
And the great news is that with
the backing of Core ML 3
specification, all these
converters are getting updated
and much more robust.
So, for some of you who have
used our converters in the past,
you might have come across some
error messages like this, like
maybe it's complaining about a
missing layer or a missing
attribute in the layer.
Now, all of this will go away as
the converters are updated and
they make full use of the Core
ML 3 specification.
[ Applause ]
So, we went through a lot of
slides.
Now it's time to look at the
model in action.
And for that, I'll invite my
friend Allen.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you.
Thank you, Aseem.
Hi. I'm Allen.
Today, I'm going to show you how
to use the new features in Core
ML 3 to bring state of the art
machine learning models for
natural language processing into
our apps.
So, I love reading about
history.
Whenever I come across some
interesting articles about
history, I often have some
questions on top of my head and
I really like to get answers for
that.
But sometimes I'm just
impatient.
I don't want to read through the
entire article.
So, wouldn't it be nice if I can
build an app that scan through
the document and then give the
answers for me?
So then I started out build this
app with the new features in
Core ML 3.
And let me show you.
OK. So, here's my app.
As you can see, it shows article
about history of a company
called NeXT.
So, as you can see, this is a
long article, and I certainly
don't have time to go through
it.
And I have some questions about
So let me just ask this app.
Let's try my first question.
Who started NeXT?
>> Steve Jobs.
[ Applause ]
>> OK. I think that's right.
Let me try another one.
Where was the main office
located?
>> Redwood City, California
[ Applause ]
>> Now I also have a question
that I'm very interested in.
Let me try that.
How much were engineers paid?
>> Seventy-five thousand or
$50,000 [applause].
>> Interesting.
[ Applause ]
So, isn't this cool?
So now, let's get deeper into it
and see what the app really
does.
So, the central piece of this
app is a state of the art
machine learning model called
Bidirectional Encoder
Representation from
Transformers.
And this is a very long name.
So, let's just call it the BERT
model as other researchers do.
So, what does BERT model do?
Well, it is actually a-- it's
actually a neural network that
can perform multiple tasks for
natural language understanding.
But what's inside the BERT
model?
A bunch of modules.
And what's inside these modules?
Layers, many, many layers.
So you can see, it's rather
complicated, but with the new
features and tools in Core ML 3,
I can easily bring this model
into my app.
But first, the question is, how
do I get the model?
Well, you can get a model on our
model gallery website, or you
can-- if you like, you can train
a model and then convert it.
For example, the other night I
trained my BERT model with
TensorFlow.
And here is a screenshot of my
workspace.
Sorry for me being very messy
with my workspace.
But to use new Core ML
converter, I just need to export
a model into the Protobuf format
right here.
And after that, all I need to do
is to type three lines of Python
code.
Import TF Core ML converter,
call the convert function, and
then save out as an ML model.
So as you can see, it's rather
easy to bring a model into the
app.
But to use the app for a
question and answering, there
are few more steps and I like to
explain a little further.
So to use the Q and A model, I
need to prepare a question and a
paragraph and then separate them
as work tokens.
What the model will predict is
the location of the answer
that's in the paragraph.
Think of it as a highlighter as
you just saw in the demo.
So from there, I can start
building up my app.
The model itself does not make
the app.
And in addition to that, I also
utilize many features from other
frameworks that makes this app.
For example, I use the
speech-to-text API from speech
framework to translate my voice
into text.
I use natural language API to
help me build the tokenizer.
And finally, I use the
text-to-speech API from the
AVFoundation to play out the
audio of an answer.
So, all these components
utilizes machine learning
on-device, so that to use this
app, no internet access is
required.
[ Applause ]
Thank you.
Just think about how much more
possibility of new ideas and new
user experience you can bring
into our app.
That's all.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> OK. Thank you, Allen.
OK. So before we conclude the
session, I want to highlight
three more features that we
added this year in Core ML that
I'm sure a lot of Core ML users
will find really useful.
So let's look at the first one.
So consider a scenario shown in
the slide, let's say we have two
models that classify different
breeds of animal.
And if you look inside, both
these models are pipeline models
that share a common feature
extractor.
Now this happens quite often.
It's quite common to share-- to
train deep neural network to get
features and those features can
be fed to different neural
networks.
So actually in the slide, we
note that we are using multiple
copies of the same model within
these two pipelines.
Now this is clearly not
efficient.
To get rid of this inefficiency,
we are launching a new model
type called linked model, as
shown here.
So just see, the idea is quite
simple.
Linked model is simply a
reference to a model sitting at
desk.
And this really makes it easy to
share a model across different
models.
Another way I like to think
about linked model is it behaves
like linking to a dynamic
library.
And it has only a couple of
parameters.
One, the name of the model that
it's linking to and a search
path.
So this would be very useful
for-- when we are using
updatable models or pipelines.
Let's look at the next feature.
Let's say you have a Core ML
model that takes an image as an
input.
Now as of now, Core ML expects
the image to be in the form of a
CVPixelBuffer.
But what happens if your image
is coming from a different
source and it's in a different
format?
Now, in most of the cases, you
could use the vision framework
so you can invoke Core ML via
the VNCoreMLRequest class.
And this has the advantage that
vision can handle many different
formats of images for us, and
they can also do preprocessing
like image scaling and cropping,
et cetera.
In some cases, though, we might
have to call the Core ML API
directly, for instance when we
are trying to invoke the update
APIs.
For such cases, we have launched
a couple of new initializer
methods, I showed on the slide.
So now we can directly get an
image from a URL or a CGimage.
[ Applause ]
So this should make it really
convenient to use images with
Core ML.
Moving on to the last feature I
want to highlight.
So there's a class in Core ML
API called MLModelConfiguration.
And it can be used to constrain
the set of devices on which a
Core ML model can execute.
For example, the default value
that the [inaudible] takes is
called all which gives all the
computer devices available
including the neural engine.
Now we have added a couple of
more options to this class.
The first one is the ability to
specify preferred metal device
on which the model can execute.
So as you can imagine, this
would be really useful if you
are running a Core ML model on a
Mac which can have many
different GPUs attached to it.
The other option that we've
added this called low precision
accumulation.
And the idea here is that if
your model is learning on the
GPU, instead of doing
accumulation in float32, that
happens in float60.
Now this can offer some really
nice speed enhancement for your
model.
But whenever we reduce the
precision, always remember to
check the accuracy of the model,
which might degrade or not
degrade, depending on the model
type.
So always try to experiment
whenever you vary the precision
of the model.
So I would highly encourage you
to go and try out this option to
see if it helps with your model.
OK. So, we talked about a lot of
stuff in this session.
Let briefly summarize it for
you.
We discussed how it's really
easy to make a personalized
experience for our users by
updating the Core ML model
on-device.
We discussed how we have added
many more features to our
specification and now we can
bring the state of the art
neural network architectures
into our apps.
And we talk about a few
convenience APIs and options
around GPU.
Here are a few sessions that you
might find interesting and
related to the session.
And thank you.
[ Applause ]