[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Hello, everybody.
My name is Gokul and together
with my colleagues Dima and
Jonathan, we are really excited
to tell you all about Sign In
with Apple.
I will start with an overview of
the key features of Sign In with
Apple, then Dima will talk
through how you can integrate
this into your native app.
Jonathan will demo that live
here.
And finally, we'll discuss
cross-platform and close out
with some best practices.
Sign In with Apple is fast, easy
account setup and sign in for
your application.
It is secure and it's private,
both for your users and for your
privacy.
It's not Apple's business to
know how you engage with your
users in your app.
So you can implement Sign In
with Apple with confidence that
Apple simply won't track any of
that.
Let's take a quick look at the
experience when your user taps
on that button.
They see a sheet pre-filled with
information that you request,
like name and email.
The user can make a choice on
which email they want to share.
They tap Continue and that's it.
They are signed into your
application.
Your app gets a unique, stable
ID, a name and a verified email
address that you can reach for
the user.
And best of all, this is a
secure two-factor authenticated
account for the user in your
app.
It's that easy.
And even better, this all works
seamlessly across all of the
user's devices.
On a new device, a simple tap
gets them going with the same
account as before in your app
and ready to fully engage again.
Very fast, very easy.
So Sign In with Apple provides
really streamlined account setup
experience for your app.
Notice there are no cumbersome
forms to fill out.
Just a simple tap.
Users downloaded your app from
the Store using their Apple ID
already.
And Sign In with Apple helps
them engage fully with just a
tap in your app.
You also get a verified email
address that you can use to
communicate with the user.
Now this is the email address
that Apple uses for its
communication.
So no need to do these
cumbersome round trips of
sending email and having users
click on links.
Apple has already done that work
for you.
Sign In with Apple provides you
instantly with an email that
just works.
No additional verification
required.
Now some users may feel less
comfortable sharing their real
email address.
And you may end up with some
fake emails that don't work.
And Sign In with Apple helps you
with that.
Hide My Email option enables
these users to share a hidden
email address that routes to
their verified email inbox.
This is great.
Now this is enabled through
Apple's Private Email Relay
system that forwards the email
to the verified email for the
user and it can handle replies
too.
So it works both ways.
And you can use this for any
kind of business communication
for your app.
Apple does not retain any
messages once they're delivered
to the user's inbox.
In summary, a verified email
that works available instantly
to your app.
With Sign In with Apple there
are no new passwords to remember
or forget.
So it's already more secure.
Even better, every account that
your app receives is two-factor
authentication protected.
This is just the best account
for your app.
No password, two-factor
authentication, no cost to you
and no added friction to the
user.
Great built-in security with
Sign In with Apple.
Now combatting account fraud in
your systems is a difficult
problem, and Apple is in a
unique position to help.
Sign In with Apple includes a
new privacy-friendly way for you
to gain confidence that the user
on your app is indeed real.
It combines sophisticated
on-device intelligence with
account information, and
abstracts that into a single
bit: real user or unknown.
Real users, give them the red
carpet treatment in your app
they deserve.
This is a high confidence
indicator.
If you receive unknown, it could
be a user, it could be a bot.
Treat this user like you would
treat any other new account in
your system where you don't have
enough information to make a
decision.
So this is the real user
indicator helping you fight
account fraud.
Finally, Sign In with Apple is
cross-platform.
The API is available on all
Apple platforms: iOS, MacOS,
WatchOS, tvOS.
The sign-in experience is
tailored on each platform for
ease of use.
The JavaScript API enables you
to use Sign In with Apple on the
web as well as other platforms
like Windows or Android.
We'll talk about this in more
detail later.
[ Applause ]
Streamlined account setup,
verified email address, built-in
security, anti-fraud and
cross-platform.
That's a very quick summary of
the key features of Sign In with
Apple.
Next, Dima's going to join me
onstage to talk through how you
can integrate this into your
native app.
Dima?
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Gokul.
Hi, folks.
So you've seen this great
feature.
What does it actually take to
integrate into your app?
There are four key things that
your app needs to do to hit the
ground running.
First, Auto Sign In with
Apple-branded button.
Then configure and perform an
authorization request.
After the user sees the Sign In
with Apple UI and after a quick
FaceID check, the results of the
authorization will be returned
back to your app.
At this point you need to verify
the results with the Apple ID
servers and create an account in
your system.
Last but not least, the
credential state may change
after it is returned to your app
and your application needs to
handle those state changes
gracefully.
First, let's look into the Sign
In with Apple button.
With only a couple lines of
code, you can add an
AuthorizationAppleIDButton to
your app.
Once you initialize it, add an
action.
And that's all you need to do.
The button supports several
different customizations to fit
your app's design.
Different visual styles and
different labels are available.
Apps that currently use valid
APIs will find this very
familiar.
Next, once the user performs the
action, you need to configure a
request and perform
authorization.
Here's how you do it.
With only one line of code, you
initialize an Apple ID
Authorization request.
This is all your app needs to
create an account in your
system.
Optionally, if your app requires
this for the best user
experience, you can set
requestedScopes for full name
and email.
You should only request this
information if it's truly
required for your app and err on
the side of minimum amount of
information.
Once the request is configured,
initialize
AuthorizationController, set the
delegates to get the results
back into your app.
And last but not least, perform
the request.
Once you perform the request,
this will initiate an
authorization UI to be presented
to the user.
After a quick FaceID check, an
authorization result will be
returned to your app.
Let's talk about handling these
results.
Through an
AuthorizationController
didCompleteWithAuthorization
method, you will get an
authorization object.
This object has a credential
property of type
AppleIDCredential.
You should check that this is
actually an AppleIDCredential
before processing that.
This object has all the
information that is required to
create an account in your
system.
If the user cancels the request
or any other error occurs, we
will let your app know through
the didCompleteWithError
callback.
Both of these delegate callbacks
are guaranteed to be made on
your app's main queue.
So let's dive deeper into the
results that we will give to
your app.
First, the user identifier.
This is a unique, stable,
team-scoped user identifier.
This is great.
You can use it to retrieve
information from your user
systems across different
platforms, different systems,
the web, Android.
It remains stable across all of
them.
And it is associated with your
developer team.
This is the key to your user.
Next, we will return
verification data, an identity
token and authorization code.
A short-lived token that you can
use with Apple ID servers to
exchange for a refresh token.
If you integrate with existing
auth systems, adapting Sign In
with Apple will be very
familiar.
Optionally, we will return
account information if you
requested it, a name and a
verified email.
And since the email is verified
by Apple, your apps no longer
need to perform any sort of
verification after we have shown
it to you.
Lastly, a real user indicator,
as was mentioned earlier.
Use this to streamline your
sign-in experience.
So now you've created an account
in your system.
As the user uses Apple devices
in your app, the credential
state may change.
And you need to handle those
scenarios gracefully.
The user may stop using Apple ID
with an app.
They may sign out of the device.
Events like this should be
handled gracefully.
To allow this, authentication
services framework exposes a
fast API to allow you to query
this state.
Using the user identifier that
was previously returned through
an Apple ID Credential, you can
check GetCredentialState call to
get the state of the current
Apple ID Credential.
It's a very fast API call.
It can return three things.
We may tell you the user is
authorized, and you should let
them continue using your app.
The credential may be revoked.
You should sign the user out of
your app on this device and
optionally guide them to sign
back in again.
NotFound means that the user has
not previously established the
relationship through Sign In
with Apple.
This API is very fast.
You should call it on your app's
launch to make sure that you
provide a tailored experience
for each of these states.
Additionally, we expose a
notification through
NotificationCenter to let you
know when this credential state
changed to revoked.
Sign the user out on this device
and optionally guide them to
sign back in again.
Now the user has established the
relationship with your app,
they're using the app, they
create an account.
Inevitably they'll get another
device and they'll want to use
your app again.
Let's talk about that and how
Sign In with Apple helps you
there.
When a user comes back to your
app on a new device, they will
get a one tap sign in
experience.
After a quick FaceID check,
they're back into your app.
In addition to that, we know you
have existing accounts in your
systems.
So now we support iCloud
Keychain passwords through the
same API.
You should request
authentication with both Apple
ID and iCloud Keychain requests.
The user will be offered to
continue using their existing
credential, whichever they have.
And if an error is returned,
show your regular sign-in flows.
For best user experience, your
app should call into this
startup function if it does not
have an existing local account.
So let's look at how easy it is
to implement this.
First, initialize a request
array with an Apple ID
authorization request and an
Apple ID password request.
That's it.
It's that simple.
Pass the request array and
perform the request.
If an existing Sign In with
Apple connection exists, an
AppleIDCredential will be
returned to your app.
If the user has a stored iCloud
Keychain password, that
credential will be returned to
your app.
You should use the credential
that you get from this API to
sign the user in.
If the user has no existing
credentials, the API will return
an error immediately and you
should show your standard login
flows.
By performing these requests on
startup, you will prevent
account duplication within your
systems and streamline the user
experience of getting back into
your app and start to use it.
Now I'd like to call Jonathan
onstage to demo how easy it is
to build this.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Dima.
Good morning, everyone.
Sign In with Apple simplifies
how users create an account or
sign into an app while
maintaining strong account
security.
Password autofill and automatic
strong passwords enables you to
do some of this already.
Sign In with Apple improves upon
them further and you can
integrate with password autofill
passwords using the same native
API as Sign In with Apple.
I'm going to take you through
three topics to get your users
signed into your app using their
Apple ID.
First, I'll add the Sign In with
Apple button to a login form.
Then I'm going to show you how
to implement the Quick Sign In
flow which allows users to sign
into existing credentials using
just one tap.
Last, I'll show you how to check
the credential status of a user
identifier after app launch to
ensure your users are properly
signed in.
To show you all this, I have a
test app.
It's called Juice.
Here you can see a typical login
form with the email and
password.
We're going to add another
option below it, Sign In with
Apple.
So let's get going.
We have one prerequisite to
fulfill in our project settings
and that's to add the Sign In
with Apple capability.
So in your project settings,
you'll want to select your
application and go to the Sign
In and Capabilities section.
I've already added the Sign In
with Apple capability here.
To add it in your app, go ahead
and click on the Capability
button and then search for Sign
In with Apple.
When you do this, Xcode is going
to add the appropriate entry
into your app's entitlement
file.
This will then check that you've
added the Sign In with Apple
capability to your Apple ID in
the Developer Portal.
If you haven't done so already,
you'll want to go ahead and sign
into the Developer Portal and
make sure that you've added this
capability.
So while here, I'd like to
highlight the Associated Domains
Capability seen over here.
This will make sure that you get
passwords back in your
credential and presented to the
user when you make an
ASAuthorizationPassword request.
I'll show you how to add one of
those requests later in the
demo.
If you want your password
request to provide exactly the
right credentials, refer to the
2017 session Password Autofill
for Apps, as well as Thursday's
session What's New in
Authentication.
So I'm going to head back to
Xcode and we're going to take a
look at the Juice app.
As you can see, this is just a
simple demo app to highlight
some of the key features of this
API.
Below this or label I have a
Stack View that is called Login
Provider Stack View.
This is where we're going to add
the Sign In with Apple button.
Adding the Sign In with Apple
button will be accomplished in
three steps.
First, I'll add the Sign In with
Apple button to our Provider
Stack View.
Then I'm going to define a
function that will create and
perform the request when the
button is tapped.
And then last, we'll adopt the
necessary authentication
services protocols which will
provide us with results.
So let's get started by adding
the Sign In with Apple button to
our UI and to do that let's take
a look at the
LoginViewController Swift file.
So we'll be working with the
AuthenticationServices module,
so we'll go ahead and import
that here.
So here I've defined a function
called setupProviderLoginView,
and it's initializing the
ASAuthorizationAppleIDButton.
It's then adding the
handleAuthorizationAppleID
ButtonPress function that I've
stubbed out over here as its
action.
And then I add the button to the
loginProviderStackView which
will then show it in our UI.
Just above, I'm overriding the
viewDidLoad function so that
this way we'll go ahead and call
setupProviderLoginView and that
will get added.
So I'll go ahead and run the
app.
And great, the button is now
visible in our UI.
But it's not really doing
anything, so let's jump to step
two which is define the action
for our button.
All right, let's talk about what
this function is doing.
So what we're doing is we're
initializing an
ASAuthorizationAppleID request
using the AppleIDProvider and
then we're setting its
requestedScopes property to an
array that contains the full
name and email scope.
This part is critical.
The user will be asked to share
information depending on what
scopes you set here.
The information is then returned
to your Apple ID Credential --
in your Apple ID Credential.
You should only request what you
actually need.
So let's go back to our button's
action.
So we initialize a controller
using the request that I've
inserted into an array, and then
we set the delegate and
presentationContextProvider to
self.
We then call performRequest.
So now that we've defined the
action, let's go ahead and run
the app.
Tap the Sign In with Apple
button.
And as you can see, the UI is
asking for the requested scopes
which we set in our request.
I'm going to cancel for now.
So remember this delegate in the
presentationContextProvider?
We're going to have to formally
adopt the authenticationServices
protocol that's required for
this.
I stubbed it out below.
So the ASAuthorizationController
delegate has two functions: one
that returns an authorization
and one that returns an error.
Let's go ahead and we'll define
AuthorizationController
didCompleteWithAuthorization.
So what we're doing here is
we're checking the authorization
that comes back.
We'll check the credential of
the authorization.
And then in the case in which
it's an appleIdCredential, we're
going to set a constant user
identifier to the user property
of the credential.
For demo purposes, we then save
the user identifier in the
keychain so we can use it later.
I'll also have the
ResultViewController that will
go ahead and take care of some
of the boilerplate of handling
some of the properties of the
appleIdCredential.
So just below this, just below
what we've defined, we have the
didCompleteWithError function
and this will get called in the
case in which the flow doesn't
complete or there is no
credentials.
Lastly, we have one more
protocol and it's
ASAuthorizationController
PresentationContextProviding.
This defines a function
presentationAnchor for
controller.
And what this requires us to do
is return the window in which
we'd like Authentication
Services to display the UI.
So let's run the app.
Tap the button and share email.
And authenticate with just one
tap.
So the service in here seems to
be giving me a bit of a problem,
but I've got a backup video that
will show you what is supposed
to happen.
So here we are.
We are sharing the email and
then the ResultViewController
will then display the results
right there.
And as you can see, we have a
user identifier, the full name
and email address.
[ Applause ]
Okay, well, actually it looks
like this has worked.
Okay, there we go.
[ Applause ]
All right, so let's get back on
topic.
So to recap, we've added a Sign
In with Apple button to our UI,
we defined the button's action
and the required functions of
the authentication services
protocol that return results and
specify where UI should be
shown.
So now that we've covered
account creation with the Sign
In with Apple button, let's work
on getting our users signed in
quickly.
To do this, we'll define a
function that will display UI to
our users in a case in which
they have an existing
credential.
So this can be either an AppleID
or an iCloud Keychain password
using the app's authorized
domains.
So here I'm defining the
performExistingAccountSetup
Flows function.
So here we have an array that
contains both an Apple ID
request and a password request
using the respective providers.
We then initialize an
authorization controller using
those requests, set the delegate
and the
presentationContextProvider like
we did before, and then call
performRequest.
So we've added one more type of
credential request to our
controller and that is the
password request.
We will want to handle this type
of result in our delegate, so
let's go ahead and do that now.
So we're setting a case for the
ASPasswordCredential.
So in this case, the
ASPasswordCredential has a user
and a password property.
In this case, when it gets
returned to you, you'll want to
go ahead and authenticate
against your servers and you
don't even need to show any UI
to your users.
So there's one last step and
that's to actually call the
performExistingAccountSetup
Flows function.
I'm going to head back up to the
class.
I'm going to override
viewDidAppear to call
performExistingAccountSetup
Flows.
Let's run the app.
And as you can see, the user is
presented with existing
credentials when we show the
loginViewController.
That's our QuickSigninFlow.
So we've just implemented the
QuickSigninFlow, so let's move
on to our last topic which is
checking the credential status
of an AppleID user identifier.
Earlier in this demo we saved
the user identifier to the
keychain during account
creation.
Using this identifier, we can
check the state of the sign in
to ensure that our user is
properly authenticated.
We'll do this in our
AppDelegate.
And I head over to the
AppDelegate file.
And I'm going to remove this.
So first we're checking to see
if the keychain has the user
identifier in it.
If it does, we're going to
initialize
ASAuthorizationAppleIDProvider,
and then using the
AppleIDProvider we'll call
credentials a state passing the
user identifier.
So we're going to get three
different -- we have three
different types of cases.
One is authorized and in this
case you can just assume that
the user is properly
authenticated and you can
continue your normal app
operations.
In the case in which it's
revoked, you want to call your
existing sign out logic and then
you can fall through to notFound
case which is to show the
LoginViewController.
So I'm going to go ahead and run
the app.
And as you can see, the user
identifier is presented in the
ResultViewController because in
this case the user is already
authorized.
The ResultViewController is the
initial view controller in the
storyboard.
So that's it.
Pretty easy, right?
[ Applause ]
So I've just shown you how to
add the Sign In with Apple
button to your login form, how
to implement a QuickSigninFlow
to get users signed in with an
existing credential, and then
how to check the credential
status using the user identifier
to make sure users are
authenticated with your app.
With that, I'll hand it back
over to Gokul who'll cover
multiplatform topics.
Gokul?
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Jonathan.
We just saw Jonathan start with
a test app, add a button, handle
requests and responses and
finally handle existing
accounts.
All easy to implement and a
great experience for users.
So that was a very quick demo.
Let's talk about cross-platform.
Cross-platform's important and
it's enabled through a simple
JavaScript library.
Using this library, you can
enable your users to sign in
with Apple on any platform like
Windows or Android.
And clicking the familiar Sign
In with Apple button will
redirect to Apple where your
user can enter the Apple ID and
sign in.
Once they sign in, it redirects
back.
Both the calls and information
you receive back are very
similar to the native API.
You get the ID, the token or
even the name or email if you
request it.
And once you get back the ID and
the token, you can convert this
to an app session in your app.
Best of all, support for this is
built right into Safari.
So when your user clicks that
button, Safari will bring up a
native Apple Pay-like sheet.
Your user can simply TouchID and
they're instantly signed in and
using your website super-fast,
and what a great experience.
So it's built right into Safari.
Integrating with a JavaScript
library is just four easy steps.
You start with including the
JavaScript library in your HTML
as shown.
A simple div renders the button.
You can style it with many
parameters to customize the fit
to your site.
Configure it with parameters
like whether you want name,
email and your redirect URI.
And finally, when the user
completes sign in, the results
are posted back to your redirect
URI with form-encoded values.
You validate the token, the auth
code and convert it to an
application session.
And you decide how long you want
the session to live.
So that's a very quick look at
cross-platform support with
JavaScript library.
Finally, let's just go through
some best practices to observe
when integrating with Sign In
with Apple.
Here are some general guidelines
to follow.
As stated in the App Store
guidelines, unless your app
requires significant
account-based features, let
people use it without a login.
For example, you can guide the
user to sign in with Apple after
they've made a purchase so you
can tie their purchase to an
account that they can easily get
back to later.
If you just need a unique
identifier to identify the user,
don't collect name or email.
You don't need it.
And if you do collect email
through Sign In with Apple, make
sure that you respect the user's
choice.
And here are some additional
best practices to keep in mind
when integrating with the API.
When your app first starts up,
use the API to check for
existing accounts.
This allows the user to quickly
get going with an account they
already have with your app,
whether it's iCloud Keychain
password or an existing Apple
account.
And you don't have any duplicate
accounts in your app.
Plan to provide the best
experience for users that return
real user indicator.
If it returns unknown, treat
them like you would any new
account in your system.
Use the Button API to draw the
button.
And when you draw the button
with the API, wire it to the
Apple ID Provider in your code.
And finally, once users use Sign
In with Apple, they will expect
to see it on all platforms that
your app is on.
So implement it across all of
your platforms.
So that's a quick look at best
practices.
In summary, Sign In with Apple
is fast, easy account setup and
sign in for your app.
Streamlined, one-tap account
setup with no cumbersome forms.
Verified email address that
instantly works and you can use
for any communication.
Built-in security with no new
passwords and two-factor
authentication for every
account.
Real user indicator to help you
combat account fraud.
And cross-platform support so
your users can benefit from Sign
In with Apple on every platform
that your app is on.
Please join us at our lab at
10:00 where we're happy to
answer any questions you may
have.
There's more in the
authentication services
framework to help you help your
users with signing in and
dealing with their passwords.
See the What's New in
Authentication session tomorrow
to learn more.
And Sign In with Apple works
great with independent Watch
apps.
Please tune in to Independent
Watch Apps on the WWDC app to
learn more.
That's all.
Thank you for joining us.
Have a wonderful conference.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]