[ Music ]
>> Hello, my name is Simon
Gladman, and I'm with the Vector
and Numerics group.
In this presentation, I'll be
talking about two topics.
First, our new Swift overlay for
Accelerate and second, measuring
Accelerate's performance using a
LINPACK Benchmark.
Before we dive into the Swift
overlay, let's recap exactly
what the Accelerate framework
is.
The primary purpose of
Accelerate is to provide
thousands of low-level math
primitives that run on a CPU and
support image and signal
processing, vector arithmetic,
linear algebra, and machine
learning.
Most of these primitives are
hand-tuned to the micro
architecture of the processor.
This means we get excellent
performance and this performance
translates directly into energy
savings.
So if you're an app developer
and you use the Accelerate
framework, not only will your
application run faster but
you'll also use less battery
life.
We provide these primitives
across all of Apple's platforms.
This includes not only macOS and
iOS but watchOS and tvOS as
well.
This means your users are going
to have an overall better
experience.
Accelerate's libraries are
immensely powerful but up until
now, their interfaces weren't
that friendly to Swift
developers.
We've looked at four libraries
and created new Swift-friendly
APIs to make using Accelerate
and Swift projects really easy.
The four libraries we focused on
are vDSP that provides digital
signal processing routines
including arithmetic on large
vectors, Fourier transforms,
biquadratic filtering, and
powerful type conversion.
vForce that provides arithmetic
and transcendental functions
including trig and logarithmic
routines,
Quadrature that's dedicated to
the numerical integration of
functions, and vImage that
provides a huge selection of
image-processing functions and
integrates easily with Core
Graphics and Core Video.
Accelerate gets its performance
benefits by using vectorization.
To understand vectorization,
let's first look at a simple
calculation over the elements of
an array using Scalar Code.
If, for example, you're writing
code that multiplies each
element of one array with the
corresponding element in another
and you're using a for-loop,
each pair of elements are
separately loaded, multiplied
together, and the results
stored.
So, after the first elements in
A and B are multiplied together
to calculate the first element
in C, the second pair are
processed, then the third, and
finally the fourth.
However, if you're processing
the elements of an array using
Accelerate, your calculation is
performed on Single Instruction
Multiple Data or SIMD registers.
These registers can perform the
same instruction on multiple
items of data by packing those
multiple items into a single
register.
For example, a single 128-bit
register can actually store
432-bit floating point values.
So a vectorized multiply
operation can simultaneously
multiply four pairs of elements
at a time.
This means that not only will
the task be quicker, it will
also be significantly more
energy-efficient.
The multiply function we just
looked at is part of
Accelerate's Digital Signal
Processing library, vDSP.
So let's begin by looking at how
the new Swift API simplifies
using vDSP.
vDSP provides vectorized Digital
Signal Processing functions
including Fourier transforms,
biquadratic filtering,
convolution, and correlation.
Furthermore, vDSP also provides
some powerful, more general
functions including element-wise
arithmetic and type conversion.
So, even if you don't have an
immediate need to, for example,
compute the coherence of two
signals, you may find that
vDSP's general computation
routines offer a solution to
improve your app's performance.
Let's take a look at some basic
arithmetic.
An example could be, given four
arrays of single precision
values, you need to calculate
the element-wise sum of two of
the arrays, the element-wise
difference of the other two, and
multiply those results with each
other.
Using a for-loop is a perfectly
reasonable solution to this
problem and calculates the
expected results.
Here's how you'd perform that
calculation using vDSP's classic
API.
Using vDSP is approximately
three times faster than the
for-loop.
Here's the same computation
using our new Swift API for
vDSP.
We're exposing the new
Swift-friendly functions for a
vDSP namespace and you can see
the function and parameter names
explain the operation.
Because the new functions work
with familiar types including
arrays and array slices rather
than pointers, you no longer
need to explicitly pass the
count, so the entire function
call is clearer and more
concise.
Passing uninitialized result
array offers the best
performance and you can
obviously reuse that array in
other operations for further
performance benefits.
However, we're also providing
self-allocating functions.
These make use of Swift's new
ability to access an array's
uninitialized buffer to return
the result of a computation.
Although not quite as fast as
passing existing storage, it's
still faster than the Scalar
approach and, in some cases,
will simplify your code.
Another common task that vDSP
can vectorize is type
conversion.
This example converts an array
containing double-precision
values to 16-bit unsigned
integer values rounding towards
zero.
The Scalar version uses map with
explicit rounding.
Again, this is a perfectly
reasonable technique to use but
vDSP can vectorize this task to
improve performance.
In this example, vDSP is
approximately four times faster
than the previous Scalar
implementation.
The new Swift version of the
vDSP function offers a clear
interface.
The function excepts the source
array, the integer type you want
to convert each element to, and
an enumeration to specify the
rounding.
vDSP provides Fourier transforms
for transforming one-dimensional
and two-dimensional data between
the time domain and the
frequency domain.
A forward Fourier transform of a
signal decomposes it into its
component sign waves.
That's the frequency domain
representation.
Conversely, an inverse transform
without frequency domain
representation recreates the
original signal and that's the
time domain representation.
Fourier transforms have many
uses in both signal and image
processing.
For example, once an audio
signal has been Fourier
transformed, you can easily
reduce or increase to certain
frequencies to equalize the
audio.
The classic API is reasonably
easy to follow if you're
familiar with it.
You begin by creating a setup
object specifying the number of
elements you want to transform
and the direction.
Then, after creating two arrays
to receive the result, you call
the execute function.
Once you're done, you need to
remember to destroy the setup to
free the resources allocated to
it.
The new API simplifies the
instantiation of the setup
object.
And the transform itself is a
method with parameter names on
the DFT instance.
And now, you don't need to worry
about freeing the resources, we
do that for you.
And much like the vDSP functions
we've looked at, there's a
self-allocating version of the
transform function that creates
and returns the result arrays
for you.
If you work with audio data, you
may be familiar with biquadratic
or biquad filtering.
Biquad filters can be used to
equalize audio to shape the
frequency response, allowing you
to, for example, remove either
low or high frequencies.
vDSP's biquad feature operates
on single and multichannel
signals and uses a set of
individual filter objects called
sections.
The filters are cascaded, that
is, they are set up in a
sequence and the entire signal
passes through each filter in
turn.
The filters are defined by a
series of coefficients that plug
into the equation shown here.
In this example, these values
form a low-pass filter, that is,
a filter that reduces high
frequencies.
Here's the code using vDSP's
classic API to create the biquad
setup using the coefficients
from the previous slide.
And here's the code to apply
that biquad filter to an array
named signal returning the
result to an array named output.
Here's the code using vDSP's
classic API to create the biquad
setup using the coefficients
from the previous slide.
And here's the code to apply
that biquad filter to an array
named signal returning the
result to an array named output.
Let's look at the same
functionality implemented with
the new API.
As you can see, the new API
vastly simplifies the duration
of the biquad structure.
You simply pass the coefficients
to the biquad initializer and
specify the number of channels
and sections.
Applying the biquad filter to a
signal is a single function
code.
Now, let's look at the new API
we've created for Accelerate's
library for fast, mathematical
operations on larger arrays,
vForce.
vForce provides the
transcendental functions not
included in vDSP.
These include exponential,
logarithmic, and trig
operations.
A typical example of vForce
would be to calculate the square
root of each element in a large
array.
The Scalar version of this code
could use map.
vForce provides a vectorized
function to calculate the square
roots that in some situations
can be up to 10 times faster
than the Scalar implementation.
The new Swift overlay offers an
API that's consistent with the
new-
vForce provides a vectorized
function to calculate the square
roots that in some situations
can be up to 10 times faster
than the Scalar implementation.
The new Swift overlay offers an
API that's consistent with the
new vDSP functions and provides
the performance and energy
efficiency benefits of
vectorization.
And much like we've seen
earlier, there's a
self-allocating version that
returns an array containing the
square roots of each element in
the supplied array.
Next, we'll take a look at the
new API we've created for
Quadrature.
Quadrature is a historic term
for determining the area under a
curve.
It provides an approximation of
the definite integrate of a
function over a finite or
infinite interval.
In this example, we'll use
Quadrature to approximate the
area of a semicircle shown here
in green by integrating the
function shown.
Much like the biquad code for
vDSP, there's a fair amount of
code required to use the
existing Quadrature API.
The first step is to define a
structure that describes a
function to integrate.
The second step is to define the
integration options including
the integration algorithm.
Finally, with the function and
options defined, you can perform
the integration using the
Quadrature integrate function.
The new API simplifies the code.
One great advantage is that you
can specify the integrand, that
is, the function to be
integrated as a trade enclosure
rather than as a C function
pointer.
This means you can easily pass
values into the integrand.
Also note that integrators are
now enumerations with associated
values so there's no need to
supply unnecessary points for
interval or maximum intervals
here.
For example, you can pass the
enumeration for the globally
adaptive integrator specifying
the points for interval and
maximum intervals.
Now, let's look at the new API
we've created for Accelerate's
image processing library,
vImage.
vImage is a library containing a
rich collection of image
processing tools.
It's designed to work seamlessly
with both Core Graphics and Core
Video.
It includes operations such as
alpha blending, format
conversions, histogram
operations, convolution,
geometry, and morphology.
Our new Swift API introduces
lots of new features that make
using vImage and Swift easier
and more concise.
We've implemented Flags as an
option set.
vImage functions throw Swift
errors and we've hidden some of
the requirements from usability
and working with unmanaged
types.
If you work with Core Graphics
images, there's a common
workflow to get that image data
into a vImage buffer.
First, you need to create a
description of the CG images
format, then instantiate a
vImage buffer, initialize that
buffer from the image, and
finally check for errors in a
non-Swift way.
And that's a lot of boilerplate
code for a common operation.
The new API wraps up all of that
code into a single throwable
initializer.
However, since we're going to
use a CG images format later,
here's a similar functionality
implemented in two steps with a
new API.
We've added a new initializer to
CG image format using a CGImage
and an alternative buffer
initializer that accepts the
CGImage and an explicit format
description.
Once you are finished working
with the buffer, here's the
classic vImage function to
create a CGImage from the
buffer's contents.
And our new API simplifies that
operation too with a new create
CGImage method that uses the
format we just generated from
the image.
One important use case of vImage
is converting between different
domains and different formats.
vImage's any-to-any converters
can convert between Core Video
and Core Graphics and convert
between different Core Graphics
formats.
For example, you've might want
to convert a CMYK Core Graphics
image to RGB.
The existing API to create a
converter accepts the source and
destination formats for the
conversion and returns an
unmanaged converter.
You take the managed reference
of the converter and pass that
to the function that does the
conversion.
Our new API adds a new static
make function to the existing
converter type that returns a
converter instance.
The conversion is done with a
convert method on the converter
instance.
Finally, let's look at working
with Core Video image formats.
In a typical example, you may
want to create an image format
description from a Core Video
pixel buffer and calculate its
channel count.
Here's the code required by the
classic vImage API to create an
image format description from a
pixel buffer and get its channel
count.
The new API provides the same
functionality in two lines of
code.
You create an instance of a Core
Video image format from a pixel
buffer using a new static make
function and simply access its
channel count as a property.
That was a quick tour of a
fraction of the new API.
Let's now take a look at LINPACK
Benchmark and see just how much
faster and more energy-efficient
Accelerate can be.
The LINPACK Benchmark came out
of the LINPACK library which
started as a set of routines for
providing fast computational
linear algebra.
This was later subsumed by a
library called LAPACK which
stands for Linear Algebra
Package.
LAPACK was developed to take
advantage of these new things at
the time called caches.
LAPACK is comprised of many
blocked algorithms.
These algorithms are built into
another library called BLAS
which stands for Basic Linear
Algebra Subroutines.
We'll talk more about BLAS later
in this presentation.
For now, keep in mind that the
LINPACK Benchmark runs on top of
LAPACK which runs on top of
BLASS.
The LINPACK Benchmark measures
how quickly a platform can solve
a general system of linear
equations.
It is comprised of two steps,
the matrix factorizations step
followed by the back solve step.
By fixing the algorithm, we're
able to see how well different
platforms are at running that
algorithm.
This provides us with a method
of comparing different
platforms.
The LINPACK Benchmark had
evolved over time.
Originally, it solved a
100-by-100 system and later a
1000-by-1000 system.
The variant most often used
today is a no holds barred
variant, where the problem size
can be as large as you want.
This is the variant we will be
running today.
The LINPACK Benchmark measures
how quickly a platform can solve
a general system of linear
equations.
It is comprised of two steps,
the matrix factorization steps
followed by the back solve step.
By fixing the algorithm, we're
able to see how well different
platforms are at running the
algorithm.
This provides us with a method
of comparing different
platforms.
The LINPACK Benchmark has
evolved over time.
Originally, it solved a
100-by-100 system and later a
1000-by-1000 system.
The variant most often used
today is the no holds barred
variant where the problem size
can be as large as you want.
This is the variant we will be
running today.
The LINPACK Benchmark measures
how quickly a platform can solve
a general system of linear
equations.
It is comprised of two steps,
the matrix factorization steps
followed by a back solve step.
By fixing the algorithm, we're
able to see how well different
platforms are at running the
algorithm.
This provides us with a method
of comparing different
platforms.
The LINPACK Benchmark has
evolved over time.
Originally, it solved a
100-by-100 system and later a
1000-by-1000 system.
The variant most often used
today is the no holds barred
variant where the problem size
can be as large as you want.
This is the variant we will be
running today.
We are now going to compare
LINPACK performance on an iPhone
XS.
At the top, in orange, we are
going to run an unoptimized
LINPACK.
This LINPACK Benchmark does not
make use of the Accelerate
framework.
It relies on software that is
not tuned to the processor it is
running on.
Let's see what that looks like.
We are now going to compare that
with using the Accelerate
framework, that is, we're going
to run the same benchmark on the
same platform but using the
Accelerate framework which is
tuned to the platform.
We can see that by using the
Accelerate framework, we are
over 24 times faster.
This will not only save time but
also energy which improves
battery life.
We are now going to shift gears
and take a look at the primary
workhorse routine for the
LINPACK Benchmark called GEMM.
As I mentioned earlier, LINPACK
which runs on LAPACK is built on
top of BLAS.
Within BLAS is a routine called
GEMM which stands for General
Matrix Multiply.
This routine is used to
implement several other blocked
routines in BLAS which are used
inside the blocked algorithms at
LAPACK, most notably the matrix
factorization and solve
routines.
Because of this, GEMM is
sometimes used as a proxy for
performance.
For this presentation, we are
specifically going to look at
the single precision variant of
GEMM.
Here, we're going to compare the
performance of the Eigen library
with that of Accelerate.
Both the Eigen library and the
Accelerate framework will run on
top of an iPhone XS.
Both will be performing a single
precision matrix multiply.
Let's see how well Eigen does.
Eigen tops out at about 51
gigaflops.
Now, let's see how well
Accelerate does.
We can see that the Accelerate
framework is almost two and a
half times faster than Eigen on
the same platform.
This is because the Accelerate
framework is hand-tuned to the
platform, allowing us to fully
take advantage of what the
platform can offer.
So, if you're a developer, using
accelerate in your app will
offer better performance.
This performance translates into
less energy, which means better
battery life and an overall
better experience for your
users.
In summary, Accelerate provides
functions for performing large
scale mathematical computations
and image calculations that are
fast and energy-efficient.
And now, we've added a
Swift-friendly API that makes
Accelerate's libraries super
easy to work with so your users
will benefit from that
performance and energy
efficiency.
Please visit our site where we
have samples, articles, and
extensive reference material
that covers the entire
Accelerate framework.
Thank you very much.