[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Hi, everyone.
I'm so excited that you're able
to join us today.
I'm Kayur and I'm here with some
amazing designers, Rubii and
Cas.
And we're so excited to talk to
you today about design and
machine learning.
You see, at Apple, we've been
thinking about design and
machine learning for some time
now.
And when we think about and we
talk about machine learning, we
talk about all the amazing
technological advances in speech
recognition and computer vision.
We talk about deep neural nets.
We talk about custom processing
for on-device machine learning.
We talk about all these things
because we care about products
and we know that many of the
products that we build today and
many of the products and
experiences that we want to
build in the future would not be
possible without machine
learning.
Let's take a look at some of the
products.
AirPods.
AirPods allow you to summon Siri
to control your device with your
voice.
You can easily change your music
or answer a call all when your
hands are busy and when you
can't really look at the screen.
This AirPods experience would
not be possible without machine
learning and it would not be
possible without Siri.
Machine learning allows us to
create Face ID which provides
fast secure authentication for
your iOS devices.
And we use machine learning in
ways that you may not expect,
subtle ways that improve your
experience with your devices.
We use machine learning to
invisibly improve your typing
experience.
We increase or decrease the
target tap area for keyboard
buttons based on the word you're
most likely to type.
Machine learning applications
are diverse.
They're not just about voice
assistance or recommending
content or self-driving cars,
machine learning applications
are as diverse as any
application of software
engineering.
They can make existing products
better or enable new products
that enrich the human
experience.
And inside Apple, we've been
talking about and thinking about
what makes a great machine
learning product for some time
now.
And to go into this in more
detail, let's dive into a single
experience, Photos.
Photos uses machine learning in
a variety of ways.
Machine learning helps people
create albums, edit photos and
search for specific memories.
Speaking of memories, recently I
was looking for this memory.
This is Angie.
She's a friend of the family and
this picture was taken from a
hike a few years ago.
I felt nostalgic and wanted to
share the picture with some
friends who were already there.
Until very recently, finding a
specific picture was painful.
I'd have to sift through
thousands of pictures, try and
remember where I was or when I
took the picture.
I would've given up.
Finding a picture used to be a
barrier to me engaging with my
memories and sharing them with
my family.
In iOS X, Apple introduced a new
search experience that could
like inside a picture and
detect, among other things,
dogs.
And over the years, we've been
making this experience better.
Here's what the experience looks
like now.
I tap on the Search box.
I type in dog.
And I get a list of pictures
with dogs.
I can then select the picture I
was looking for and share it.
Easy peasy.
Searching for pictures based on
what's in a picture changes how
we engage with our memories.
It's something we take for
granted.
In fact, it's such a great
experience it's hard to remember
a time before we had this
capability.
It's well designed.
And there's a lot of interface
work that goes into making this
experience.
Photos suggest categories you
can search for, it
auto-completes searches and it
connects search results to
Moments but designing this
experience is more than just
designing a grid view in the
Search field.
If we just looked at the
interface, we'd miss the most
important parts of the search
experience, the results being
outputted into categories that
people can search for.
These aspects of the experience
should be designed.
We get to decide which
categories are included and we
decide the level of quality we
want for each category.
We've realized that to build a
good machine learning
experience, we have to design
more than just the interface.
What do we mean?
Well, when most people think
about design, they think about
the interface, how the product
looks and feels, the flow of the
experience.
With machine learning, we have
to design how the product works.
Now we know that many of you in
the design and developer
community have some machine
learning experience.
You could create a search
experience from scratch but to
get everyone on the same page,
let's look at how machine
learning for photo search works.
Deep within the logic of Photos
is a function that takes a
picture and detects if that
picture contains any of the
categories it can recognize.
In our case, it recognizes that
this picture of Angie has a dog
in it.
In traditional programming, we
would have to create the
function by writing code to tell
the computer what to do.
Our code would have to work for
a variety of different breeds,
different scenarios, different
photo resolutions because their
customers are diverse and so are
their dogs.
And we wouldn't want a search
for dogs to be littered with
pictures of other animals.
Our code would have to
differentiate between dogs and
similar animals, like this hyena
which looks like a dog but you
should not have as a pet.
Writing code that generalizes
the countless variations of dogs
in photos would be impossible.
And dogs are just one of
thousands of categories that
Photos can recognize.
There're experiences we want to
create where we can't just tell
the computer what to do.
And for many of these
experiences, we can use machine
learning to teach a computer
what to do.
We teach by providing examples.
If we wanted to distinguish
pictures of dogs from pictures
that do not contain dogs, we
have to provide pictures with
dogs and pictures without dogs.
Machine learning learns a
function that we can later use
in our app.
This function can take this
picture of Angie and understand
that it's a picture of a dog.
We call this function a model
and a model is what makes the
Photos Search experience work.
This model can generalize two
pictures that it's never seen
before.
It can recognize different dog
species and differentiate dogs
from other animals and objects.
Models are central to the
machine learning experience.
Every product or experience that
depends on machine learning
depends on a model.
Siri has a model that converts
your voice to text.
And the keyboard has a model
that infers the key you meant to
type based on the letters you've
already typed and your typing
history.
To design a great machine
learning experience, we have to
design both how it works and how
it looks and feels.
We have to design both the model
and the interface.
In this talk, we'll cover both.
Creating a model can be
complicated.
You have to make a lot of
decisions about algorithms and
parameters and frameworks.
And all of these decisions
affect what the model does and,
therefore, the experience.
Machine learning decisions are
all design decisions but not all
of them are effective places for
design input.
We choose a few places where we
think design can have the most
impact.
We talk about the need to design
what we use to teach the
computer.
This is the data.
And we also talk about how we
design what we evaluate and
these are the metrics.
Along with the model, we do need
to design the interface.
We have to design what the model
outputs and how those model's
outputs are presented to people.
We also have to design how
people interact with the model
and, if appropriate, provide
input to improve the model.
Rubii and Cas will talk about
that later.
So let's start.
Let's talk about the data.
To recognize dogs in pictures,
we used machine learning to
create a model using examples.
Those examples are called data.
And to build a good search
experience, you need a lot of
diverse data.
You need photos of the
categories that you want people
to be able to search for.
You need to provide plenty of
pictures of dogs and of other
animals to ensure the search
experience doesn't show random
animals when you're searching
for dogs.
And a good search experience
needs to support thousands of
categories that cover the
objects and events people want
to search for.
And for each of those
categories, you'll need data.
If you want to support a new
category, you'll need data.
If you want to improve an
existing category, you will need
data.
Choosing data is key to
designing the experience.
Data determines the behavior of
a model.
It's easily the most important
decision you'll make when
creating your model.
And if you don't have data that
captures an important scenario,
it's unlikely that your model's
going to work well in that
scenario.
And since data determines the
behavior of the model, and since
the behavior of the model
determines the experience, data
needs to be designed to reflect
good values in the best interest
of your customers.
To understand this better, let's
look at an example.
Let's look at Portrait mode.
Portrait mode uses machine
learning to detect faces and
segment your body from the
background.
Historically, face recognition
hasn't worked well for people of
color.
At Apple, we want to make sure
our experiences are inclusive.
So our design and engineering
teams gather data from across
different races, different
cultures, and different
scenarios.
We built a dataset that matched
the experience we wanted to
create.
We collected data intentionally.
When collecting data, it's
important to ask questions.
Who is collecting the data?
What data are they collecting?
And how are they doing it?
Data bias can seep into your
dataset in a variety of ways.
And data bias extends beyond
fairness.
You should strive to be fair and
inclusive.
Those are good values.
But you should also see how data
collection might skew away from
other design intents.
If you're creating a fun or
enriching experience, you should
sample data for fun, enriching
experiences.
If your product is going to be
used outdoors, you should sample
from scenarios that are
outdoors.
It's tempting to disconnect from
this decision and make decisions
about data collection that just
sample the data from your
existing customers and get a
uniform sample of the world from
other mechanisms but you can't
just reflect the world.
Reflecting the world can
reinforce systemic biases.
You shouldn't optimize for the
customers you have.
You should optimize for the
customers you want.
You shouldn't reflect the world
as it is.
You should reflect a better
world, that world that you want
it to be.
Collecting data is a way to
design experiences and great
experiences often change the
world.
They don't just reflect what
already exists.
So how do we put this into
practice?
We'll start by collecting data
intentionally.
Understand the experience you're
trying to create and think about
what you'll need to make that
experience work.
If specific scenarios are
important, spend more time and
ensure you collect data for
those scenarios.
Spending time up front
collecting the right data can
save time and effort and money
later.
Make sure you test for biases.
Analyze your dataset.
Catalogue your assumptions about
who will use your product and
how it will be used.
Think of ways your data might be
biased towards or against
certain populations or certain
experiences.
Update data as products change.
Product specifications change
the more you learn about your
customers or the market or what
you want to actually create.
You need to change your data to
match.
You may not need to collect more
data.
You may get rid of concepts that
are not important but you must
routinely align your data with
your product goals.
And beware of standard datasets.
Academic or industry benchmark
datasets might be a great way to
start to get some knowledge
about how machine learning
works.
It might be a great way to ramp
up your product development
process.
But they're not designed to
represent real experiences,
especially your experience.
Before you start using an
off-the-shelf dataset, think
about what the data covers and
doesn't cover.
Spend time augmenting the data
to match your needs.
Spending time thinking about
cataloguing and critically
collecting data can help you
align what you want your product
to be and what machine learning
can provide.
So, we just talked about data,
which is what you use to teach a
model.
Next, let's talk about how you
evaluate your model.
This is done through metrics.
You evaluate your model by
testing it.
In the Photo Search example,
you'd give it pictures of
animals and your model would
predict what's in the pictures.
And once it's done, you can
compare how many times it was
correct and how many times it
was incorrect.
Here, we see that the model gave
the correct prediction 75% of
the time.
This is a metric and a metric
like this will define how
successful your model is and,
therefore, whether it's ready to
use or whether you have to go
back to the drawing board and
improve it.
Models can be evaluated in many
ways.
You could look at how fast the
model works or how many
categories it can support.
You can balance all of these
together and find the right set
of metrics for your problem.
Designing metrics define how the
model will work and, therefore,
how the experience will work but
ultimately you get to decide.
Metrics encode what you think a
good experience is.
They define what you care about
and what you can ignore.
If part of the experience is not
measured, it may be sacrificed
for something that is.
And as a consequence, your
metrics reflect your values.
Let's look at an example.
Let's look at Face ID.
Face ID uses machine learning to
detect your face to unlock your
device.
And behind Face ID are a number
of design intents.
The most important is Face ID
needs to be secure.
Our customers trust us with some
of their most private data.
There are many metrics that we
use to track different aspects
of security.
One key metric was the chance
that a random person could find
your phone, pick it up and
unlock it.
We tracked this metric and
worked hard to reduce this
chance.
At launch, we knew that there
was a one-in-a-million chance
that a random person could
unlock your phone using Face ID.
And since Face ID was a new
experience, we needed to
communicate this to our
customers.
That way they understood that we
cared about their data and they
could actually trust Face ID.
But one in a million doesn't
tell the whole story.
Each failure is a person, a
scenario, an experience that we
have to think about and address.
Say you're me.
I'm your average run-of-the-mill
Apple employee and recently I
had a run-in with the new
MacBook Pro.
Due to a small mishap, I
accidentally opened up a portal
to another timeline.
Now I have to routinely fight
off my mirror universe nemesis.
I obviously don't want him
accessing secret Apple data, so
I have to rely on a pass code.
And people like me with similar
looking family members or evil
twins need to take the same
precautions.
As Apple, we also talked about
this limitation.
We dedicated time in a keynote
because it's important that our
customers understand and take
steps to secure their data.
It's important for you to
understand and communicate
limitations to unpack aggregate
statistics.
Not all mistakes are equal.
Mistakes in machine learning are
inevitable.
Few models work 100% of the
time.
When you start, you may not
understand all the limitations.
That's OK.
It's an iterative process.
But over time, you need to build
a better understanding of what
is and is not possible.
Mistakes don't mean you can't
create an experience that people
love.
If you understand mistakes, you
can account for them either by
creating new models, improving
the product or clearly
communicating technical
limitations.
And remember that metrics are
proxies for what we actually
care about.
Metrics provide numbers, a sense
of scientific accuracy, and it's
easy to get caught up in numbers
and improving them but we
ultimately care about abstract
concepts.
These things are hard to measure
like good experiences, happy
customers and strong brands.
Let's look at an example.
To understand metrics as
proxies, let's talk about the
App Store.
The App Store uses machine
learning to recommend new apps
based on what you've downloaded.
And at first approximation, the
amount of time a person spends
in the app might be a good
measure.
Right?
Afterall, the more time you
spend doing something, the more
you like it.
And if the App Store is purely
driven by metrics and models,
people would see apps that are
very similar to the apps they
currently use.
I like playing games.
So my top recommended apps are
all games.
And for a while, I might like
those recommendations but over
time, I'd feel boxed in because
I care about more than just
games.
People have diverse interests
and tastes.
The amount of time I spend in an
app may not indicate how much I
value it.
The App Store makes an editorial
content with recommendations.
This allows people to explore a
diverse set of applications and
experiences that they may not
normally see if they just got
their top recommendations.
Editorial content is a way to
address limitations of metrics
and recommendations.
But as you deploy your products
and learn more about customer
needs, what you care about
evolves.
You can evolve your metrics to
match.
For example, you can bake
diversity into your metrics.
You can measure when people
engage with diverse content and
actively create models that
balance the quality and
diversity of apps that people
engage in.
You should ensure that your
metrics still track what you
care about: a good experience,
happy and fulfilled customers
and strong brands.
But to do that, you need to
question metrics to ensure
they're relevant.
In your day to day, you can put
this into practice.
You can try to understand
mistakes because not all
mistakes are equal.
Group failure cases into
categories and scenarios.
This will help you understand
how important each scenario is.
Decide if it's best handled by a
non-ML approach like improving
the design or if you actually
need to build a better model.
And design for failure
scenarios.
When storyboarding or sketching
out an experience, don't just
sketch out what happens if
things go well.
Sketch out what happens if
something goes wrong.
This will help you emphasize
what your customers might
experience.
Spend time evaluating the
The metric will give you an
objective value for how well
your model is working.
Remember, the model is not the
experience.
The actual experience is the
So try to measure that
experience.
Run user studies.
Build demos.
Talk to your customers.
Read forums.
If the experience is bad and the
metric says it's good, your
metric is probably wrong.
If the experience seems the same
the metric says it's getting
better, your metric is likely
wrong.
And over time, evolve your
metrics.
Question and assess the
effectiveness of your metrics
constantly.
The more you rely on something,
the more you should question it.
Ultimately, your metrics reflect
your values.
And if you want to align your
metrics with your values, you
have to think carefully,
critically and continuously
about what is and is not
measured.
We just talked about metrics
which is how you understand if
the model is good, how you
evaluate a model.
Next, let's talk about the
interface.
Designing metrics in data is key
to designing how your model
behaves.
But we also have to figure out
how do we surface the model in
the interface.
And to do that, I'll hand it
over to Rubii and Cas to talk
more about outputs/inputs.
Thank you so much.
[ Applause ]
>> As Kayur has shown, there's a
lot that goes into creating the
underlying machine learning
system that powers an
experience.
But we also need to design
interfaces that allow people to
interact with the experience in
an intuitive way.
The interface can translate
results from a model to outputs
that people can actually
interact with.
The feedback we collect from
these interactions are inputs we
can use to future improve the
experience.
We've created a set of patterns
in the human interface
guidelines to help you design
output and inputs.
Cas and I will go in-depth
through some of them to help you
understand how they apply to the
experience you're building.
First let's talk about outputs.
Outputs can be more than just
predictions.
They're a design medium that can
augment an experience into
something that feels more
contextual and seamlessly
helpful.
There are four types of outputs
we'll discuss.
Multiple options allow you to
present a diverse set of outputs
to people.
Attributions are explanations
that help people understand more
about how your app makes
decisions.
Confidence is a measurement of
certainty for an output.
And limitations occurs when
there's a mismatch between
people's mental model of a
feature and what the feature can
actually do.
Let's start with multiple
options.
As I had mentioned, multiple
options allow people to choose
from among the results a feature
generates.
What does this actually mean?
Well it's often tempting to only
reveal the best option that was
created by your model.
That's often not the best
experience.
Let me show you an example from
the real world.
Last weekend I wanted to take a
short trip and I asked my
colleagues what's the best way
to get between San Francisco and
Napa.
Depending on the person and the
time of day that I asked, the
answers varied.
Sometimes they would say take
the I-80.
the 101.
This is because route prediction
is a complex task with a lot of
different variables that might
constantly be changing.
There might be traffic or
construction or even car
accidents.
Given all of that information,
in Maps we try to predict the
best route possible but
sometimes a single option is not
enough.
We can't know everything that a
particular person may care
about.
They may prefer scenic routes or
routes without tolls or routes
not along highways.
Providing a set of meaningfully
different routes can help people
navigate the gap between their
preferences and what a model can
realistically predict.
Here, Maps gives us three
distinctly different routes: One
that goes to the North Bay and
two that go to the East Bay.
This can give people a sense of
control over how to get to their
final destination.
Whenever possible, you should
prefer diverse options that
encapsulate a meaningful
selection of choices.
People might also be using Maps
while on the go and some of the
options might appear very
similar which makes it difficult
for people to quickly choose the
route.
We can also use attributions to
help people differentiate
between the options and make a
choice faster.
Here, we show you whether a
route requires a toll, which
highway it goes through and we
even highlight each path on the
map making it easier to find
that perfect scenic waterfront
drive.
These small summaries are a
great tool to help people
differentiate between a broad
selection of options at a quick
glance and easily make a
selection while on the go.
Now I know Maps is an obvious
example for presenting options
because it's reacting to very
explicit input.
I know where I am, where I want
to go and I'm expecting a list
of options that can get me
there.
But multiple options can also be
useful for features that are
proactively surfacing
suggestions or it might be more
ambiguous what my current intent
and context is.
Let's talk about the watch.
When I start the day every
morning, I might want to check
the weather, see my first
appointment and see reminders of
what I need to do that day.
Siri watch face allows me to
customize up to 19 different
data sources that I might want
to get information from
including weather, calendar, and
reminders.
You can even choose to see
information from third-party
apps.
Now information from 19
different apps is a lot to look
at on such a small screen.
That's why Siri chooses to
surface a smaller selection of
options based on time, location,
and what I've previously
interacted with.
Since my watch knows it's
morning time, I'm at home, and
in the past I've always selected
the option to turn on the lights
at the certain time.
It'll surface this as a top
suggestion every morning.
Siri can understand my usage
history to help me automate this
mundane task without having to
scroll through this long list of
options when I first wake up.
This makes getting up in the
morning so much more effortless
for someone who's not a morning
person, like me.
This is important because every
time someone selects an option,
they're actually giving you
valuable implicit feedback that
you can use to make sure the
most relevant option is always
ranked at the top.
If you learn from their
selection, you'll be able to
surface better suggestions over
time.
Now remember when we talked
about Maps and how attributions
can be used to differentiate
routes?
Attributions can actually be
used for so much more than that.
Attributions are explanations
that help people understand more
about how your app makes
decisions.
Within the App Store, we use
attributions to explain how
recommendations are created.
This helps people understand why
they might be seeing certain
suggestions and how their data
is being used.
But let's say the App Store is
showing me some recommendations
because I downloaded a cooking
app.
Now I might have downloaded an
app to cook but that doesn't
necessarily mean I'm into
cooking.
Neither does it mean that I love
that particular app.
Therefore, when using
attributions to explain
suggestions, you should relate
to objective facts rather than
subjective taste.
Here, we simply state that these
suggestions are because you've
downloaded the "New York Times"
Cooking app.
We can never have a complete
picture of someone's taste and
preferences because they might
evolve on a daily basis.
People might also share an
account with their friends and
family; therefore, profiling
them makes them feel confused
and boxed in.
You should avoid profiling
people by not using language
that implies understanding or
judgment of their emotions and
preferences.
We can also use attributions to
help people understand the
trustworthiness of a result.
I'm an astronomy enthusiast and
I wanted to see which planet was
visible in the sky tonight.
So I asked Siri, "When can you
see Jupiter?"
Siri tells me when the event
will happen but also gives me
more information from Wolfram
Alpha.
This helps me understand that
it's a reliable prediction
because Wolfram Alpha is a
well-known knowledge engine.
This is really important when it
comes to displaying predictions
where the trustworthiness of the
source really matters like
scientific information or
election results.
Cite data sources so people can
determine how reliable a certain
prediction might be.
Now attributions can be used for
more than just explaining
personalization or predictions.
We can also use it to
communicate confidence.
Let's look at the App Store
again and see how we really try
to avoid technical jargon here.
For example, we could've said
these apps are an 85% match for
you but it's really difficult to
understand what 85% mean.
That number might also mean
different things to different
people.
That's why we try to use a more
understandable explanation such
as recommendations based on apps
you've downloaded.
That 85% I mentioned is a
measurement of confidence or how
certain the model is that you'll
like the recommendations.
Confidence is what you get from
a machine learning model but
it's important to translate it
into something more
understandable for people.
Sometimes it's OK to directly
display confidence.
The Weather app gives you
information that it's going to
rain but it also gives you a
percentage for how likely it's
going to rain.
Now you might think what kind of
a decision should I make based
on this 30% chance.
Is it worth bringing my
umbrella?
It's unclear.
But we've been conditioned to
understand this percentage over
time.
And while numbers are
appropriate for statistical
predictions such as weather,
sports results or election
predictions, it might not work
in other situations.
This is Hopper.
It's an app that helps you book
cheaper flights.
It uses confidence to tell
people whether the fare will go
up or down.
And we don't expect people to
grapple with percentages here
because in this context,
percentages are difficult to
interpret.
Seeing a 65% chance the price
will go down is not really
actionable.
How is 65% different than 70%?
The way Hopper presents
confidence is by giving you
actual suggestions for actions
you should take, whether you
should wait or buy now.
It also provides additional
context such as how much money
you're going to save and the
optimal time range to book a
flight.
These additional explanations
help people make a more informed
decision.
When confidence is used
appropriately, it can make an
experience feel so much more
human.
Most of the time you should
prefer to translate confidence
into easy-to-understand terms to
help people make a decision.
So by this point, you probably
understand that confidence can
be a great tool to help people
estimate how risky a certain
decision might be but there are
cases where this doesn't work.
For example, if I ask you how
long it would take for me to get
between here and San Francisco
and you replied, "I'm 72%
confident you'll get there at
1:30."
That would be pretty confusing.
How can I be sure what time I'll
actually get home?
A better way is to provide a
range in the prediction.
With ride sharing, it's often
difficult to pinpoint an exact
arrival time since there might
be traffic or the driver might
pick up more riders.
Lyft help people estimate when
they will arrive at their
destination before they book a
ride by providing a range about
the time the driver will pick
you up and the time you will
arrive at the airport.
These ranges help me have a
realistic expectation of when
I'll actually get home.
Range can be a great tool to
help people estimate how risky a
certain decision might be.
Now these are all good examples
of how to display confidence but
what do you do when there is low
confidence and the model doesn't
have enough information to
actually take an action?
In a lot of cases, we can
actually ask people for help.
For example, the Photos app can
automatically recognize people
in order to make searching for
their pictures easier.
When Photos has low confidence
who is in a picture, it will ask
people to confirm additional
photos of that person before
automatically labeling them.
Asking for confirmation is
important because it'd be
annoying if I saw pictures that
were marked as me that weren't
photos of me at all.
With every photo I mark as me,
Photos become better at
recognizing who I am.
This is an example of a
limitation that the facial
recognition in Photos has,
which also brings me to our last
output pattern.
So what actually is a
limitation?
A limitation is that when
there's a mismatch between
people's mental model of a
feature and what the feature can
actually do.
I might expect Photos to always
know who I am even though it
can't do that yet because a
photo might be blurry or taken
in low light or not in focus.
Every feature has limitations
whether by design, capability,
or circumstance.
You have to strengthen people's
trust in your app by
acknowledging its limitations
and teaching people how to work
with them.
Now Memoji is one of my favorite
features but people might not
understand that it won't work in
certain scenarios, whether your
face is not in view, something
is covering the camera, or
you're in a dark room.
Every time this limitation
occurs, we instantly show these
inline coaching tips to help
people move past the limitation
and successfully use the
feature.
Explaining the limitations when
they happen help people learn to
avoid these situations in the
future.
People might lose trust in your
feature if limitations are not
appropriately addressed.
You should take care to manage
people's expectations of what a
feature can actually do and
guide people to move past
limitations.
Another way to help people move
past limitations is to suggest
alternative ways to accomplish
their goals.
In order to do this right, you
need to understand the goal well
enough to suggest alternatives
that actually make sense.
For example, if people ask Siri
to set a timer on a Mac, it
can't perform the action because
timers aren't available at
MacOS.
Instead of simply replying, "I
can't do it," which is kind of
frustrating, Siri suggests
setting a reminder instead.
This suggestion actually makes
sense because Siri understands
that the goal is to receive an
alert at a certain time and
setting a reminder accomplishes
the same goal as setting a
timer.
When possible, suggest
alternatives that can help
people accomplish their goals.
I hope these patterns have given
you some ideas on different
outputs that you can get from a
machine learning model.
But you have to remember that
outputs are a design medium.
By understanding the types of
outputs that are available, you
can choose outputs that align
with the experience you want to
build and not just rely on
standard outputs from the model.
We should respect people's
agency and time by choosing
outputs that are easy to
understand and effortlessly
helpful.
As you've seen, there are many
different ways to translate
outputs from the model to the
interface.
But of course, outputs aren't
static.
They're dynamic and constantly
update based on inputs.
People interact with the
experience through inputs and
now Cas will tell you all about
how to design for inputs.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> So Rubii showed a range of
outputs that people can interact
with on the interface and these
interactions serve as inputs
that we can use to collect
feedback for information from
people so we can improve our
experience.
These are the four inputs we
will discuss.
Calibration helps you get
essential information for
someone to engage in your
experience.
Calibration allows you to
collect important information
from interactions someone has
with your experience.
Explicit feedback also allows
you to collect information but
this time by asking specific
questions about the results
you're showing.
And corrections allow people to
fix a mistake a model has made
by using familiar interfaces.
So let's start with calibration.
As I just said, calibrations
allow people to provide
essential information for them
to engage in your experience.
We can use calibration for
example to collect biometric
data or data about your
surroundings.
Let me give an example.
Let's look at HomeCourt.
HomeCourt is an app that helps
you become a better basketball
player.
It uses machine learning to
analyze images from the camera
and detect for example how
accurately you take shots at the
hoop.
In order to do so, the camera
needs to be calibrated so it can
detect you, the hoop and the
court.
And HomeCourt has done an
amazing job at doing this fast
and intuitively.
You simply point the
front-facing camera to the hoop
and it immediately detects it by
putting a wide square around it.
It then asks you to make one
shot and from then on, you're
good to go and it will start
counting your shots.
What's remarkable here is what
HomeCourt is not asking you to
do.
For example, you don't have to
draw lines around the hoop or
the court.
It doesn't ask for confirmation
on whether it got the hoop right
or wrong.
And you don't need to take shots
from multiple angles.
Calibration also happens in some
of Apple's products, for example
when you set up Face ID.
Face ID uses calibration to only
collect essential information.
It asks you to scan your face
twice and from then on, it is
set up and it will always keep
working regardless of whether
you might start to wear glasses
or change your hairstyle.
So when you're using
calibration, try to be quick and
effortless and only ask for
essential information and, when
possible, try to avoid the need
for multiple calibrations.
Once you're setting up Face ID,
we help you along the way.
We start with an introduction
that clearly states why your
phone needs to scan your face.
And we do this by explaining
both how it works and what it
will allow you to do.
Throughout the process, we
always give you a sense of
progress.
Here, we fill out the lines
around your face.
And if this progress might
stall, we make sure you never
get stuck and we provide
guidance to help you move
forward.
Here, we point arrows that point
in which way to look.
And at the end, we give the
notion of success.
We tell you the work is done and
the feature can be used now.
So always provide help by
introducing, guiding and
confirming the calibration.
Of course, Face ID collects a
lot of sensitive information.
And so to respect your privacy,
we give you a way to edit or
remove this information in
Settings.
So when possible, allow people
to update their information.
Now as I said before, Face ID
asks for just one calibration
and from then on, it will keep
working regardless of whether
you might start to wear glasses,
change your hairstyle, maybe
wear a hat or a scarf sometimes
or even as your face changes as
you become older.
This was a big challenge when we
designed Face ID.
It would've been a lot easier to
occasionally ask to recalibrate
your face so your iPhone or iPad
could keep recognizing you.
But who would like to rescan
their face each time they change
their hairstyle?
So instead of asking for
multiple calibrations, Face ID
collects implicit feedback to
update the information about
your face each time you use Face
ID.
And that brings us to our next
pattern which is implicit
feedback.
Implicit feedback is information
that arises from the
interactions people have with
your app and that information
can be used to improve the model
and your feature.
A very common example of using
implicit feedback is
personalization.
For example, Siri personalizes
the search experiences on iOS
based on how you use your
device.
When you trigger the Search bar
on your Home screen, Siri
presents a range of apps you
might want to use.
Which apps appear here depends
on the implicit feedback you
give to Siri.
These might be apps you
frequently used, maybe ones
you've just used or ones you use
typically at this time of day.
For example in the car, I might
get Maps so I can get directions
or music and podcasts so I have
something to listen to.
At work, I might get apps that
help me at a meeting like Notes
or Reminders and at home, I
might get Messages to text
friends or family or suggestions
to check my activity or news.
Based on how I use these apps,
Siri tries to identify my intent
so it can surface apps to help
me achieve that intent.
So when you're using implicit
feedback, strive to identify
people's intent by looking at
how they interact with your
feature.
Over time, Siri will get better
at understanding my intent and,
apart from just showing apps as
a suggestion, it might also
start suggesting shortcuts of
actions I frequently perform.
For example in the car, I might
get directions to places I
frequently visit or the location
of my next meeting.
At work, I might get shortcuts
to my meeting notes or my work
reminders.
And at home, I might get
shortcuts to turn on the lights
or message or FaceTime my
closest friends and family.
These shortcuts appear after a
few days or weeks.
The more specific they are, the
more certain Siri needs to be
about my intent.
As I said, these shortcuts are
based on implicit feedback, so
it might take a while for Siri
to be certain enough about a
suggestion and that's OK.
It's better to be patient and
become certain of a suggestion
than to be quick and show an
unhelpful suggestion.
So bear in mind that implicit
feedback can be slow but it also
can be more accurate over time.
Now these suggestions can appear
on the Lock screen and it might
be that they contain some
sensitive information.
For example, it might show an
event you want to keep as a
surprise or notes you might want
to keep secret.
To respect people's privacy, we
added settings for you to
control which app and which app
shortcuts can appear in Search.
So respect people's privacy and
give them full control over
their information.
Treat it privately and securely.
So implicit feedback is a great
tool for personalization but you
can also use it for some maybe
less obvious purposes, for
example simply making a
direction faster or more
accurate.
One good example has been with
us since the beginning of iOS
and that's the keyboard.
Each key on the keyboard has a
touch area and the keyboard uses
machine learning to optimize
these touch areas based on what
you type.
Each touch area might become
bigger or smaller depending on
the word you're typing or the
way your fingers are positioned
on the keyboard.
Now notice that we're not
visibly making these buttons any
bigger or smaller.
The keyboard always appears in
the same way.
But over time, the keyboard
might start to feel more
accurate and more personalized
to you.
So use implicit feedback to make
your interactions more accurate
and delightful.
One last example are the Siri
suggestions in Safari.
Safari uses machine learning to
collect links from messages,
mail, your reading lists, your
iCloud tabs, and other places.
And hopefully these suggestions
are good and they help you
discover interesting content
from your friends and family or
ones you've saved yourself.
Occasionally, though, you might
get suggestions you'd rather not
see, maybe an article you're not
interested in or a source you
don't really trust.
If all of these suggestions turn
out to be unhelpful, you might
start losing trust in the
suggestions or even worse, start
to lose trust in Safari.
And that is obviously something
we would like to avoid.
Rubii talked about attribution
that can really help here in
explaining why we're showing
these suggestions but we also
want to make sure you can
control these suggestions so you
can get rid of the ones you
don't want to see and make sure
they don't appear again.
And that brings us to our next
pattern which is explicit
feedback.
Explicit feedback allows your
app to collect information by
asking specific questions about
your results.
In the previous example, it
would be great if I could get
feedback on these suggestions
that I don't want to see and
that way the model can learn and
can avoid showing similar
suggestions in the future.
So how do I design these
feedback actions?
Here are two actions that
frequently appear when we're
using explicit feedback: the
heart and the heart with a
strikethrough.
Now seeing these as buttons
leaves a lot of room for
interpretation.
It's unclear what will happen
when I press one of these even
if I add labels like Love or
Dislike.
Let's say I want to get feedback
on the third article here.
I can bring up the Action menu
and I can see the action Love.
That leaves a lot of room for
interpretation.
Does this mean I have to love
every article that I like?
Positive explicit feedback
implies additional work.
People might think they have to
give positive explicit feedback
to every article they like just
to get more good suggestions.
So we actually recommend to
prioritize negative feedback
over positive.
Positive feedback can better be
inferred through implicit
signals, for example me reading
the article, bookmarking it or
sharing it.
So instead of showing both Love
and Dislike, we can actually
only show Dislike.
But still, that leaves a lot of
room for interpretation.
If I dislike an article, am I
disliking the article, the
author, the source, the person
who sent it to me, or maybe even
the app in which I received it?
It's still difficult to
understand what will happen when
I tap Dislike.
Words like "suggest less" or
"hide the suggestion" make it
much easier to understand what
will happen when I tap such a
button.
To give people even more
control, we can allow them to
select exactly what they like to
see less, for example less of
the source, the person who sent
it to me or the app in which I
received it.
So when using explicit feedback,
clearly describe the option and
its consequences.
Use words that describe what
will happen.
And when possible, provide
different options to better
understand the user's
preference.
And of course, when I select one
of these options, the interface
should immediately reflect my
choice and hide the suggestions
that match my preference.
So always act immediately and
persistently when the user gives
explicit feedback.
So you've seen that explicit
feedback allows us to correct
suggestions that might be wrong,
unwanted or inappropriate.
But for some machine learning
features, using explicit
feedback might not be the right
choice or might not even be
possible.
Here's Angie again, the dog from
our friends.
She's often the main topic in
our group conversation.
Now the keyboard uses machine
learning to suggest corrections
of what I'm typing.
And when I initially type the
word "Angie," it wanted to
correct it to the word "angle."
Now that's obviously wrong but
using explicit feedback here
seems a little bit off.
Let's say I can bring up a
contextual menu here.
This doesn't feel very intuitive
and it doesn't really allow me
to say what I actually meant.
Instead, I can simply select the
words and correct the suggestion
the keyboard has made by
retyping it and this time the
keyboard will not autocorrect
it.
The keyboard learned from my
correction and the next time I
type in Angie, it knows I'm
referring to a name and not the
word "angle."
This is the most obvious example
of our last pattern which is
corrections.
Corrections allow people to fix
a mistake a model has made by
using known tasks.
And with known tasks, I'll
explain what that means.
In the previous example, you've
seen that we corrected this
using standard text controls.
There was no new interface that
we showed here.
Everybody knows how to do this
since this is how the keyboard's
always worked.
Corrections are, therefore, an
amazing pattern to optimize your
results without feeling like
extra work.
Let me give another example.
Photos uses machine learning to
optimize your pictures.
It can help find to the right
rotation or cropping your
pictures could take.
The way Photos suggest these
croppings or rotations is quite
subtle.
When you go into Edit mode and
select Rotation or Cropping
tool, photos will crop or rotate
the picture for you.
Now it doesn't apply the
rotation or cropping, it simply
suggests it as a starting point.
If you like what Photos has
done, you can simply tap Done
and the rotation or cropping is
applied.
But if you'd like to change what
Photos has suggested, you can
simply use the slider at the
bottom to rotate or drag the
corners to crop.
So these are great examples of
corrections.
We show you familiar controls
and we learn from the
corrections you make.
So that concludes the last
pattern.
Allow corrections through
familiar ways.
This makes it easy and fast for
somebody to correct.
Provide immediate value when
somebody makes a correction.
As we saw with the text
correction, the keyboard won't
autocorrect things that we
typed.
And use corrections as implicit
feedback.
Corrections work great as
implicit feedback to improve
your machine learning results.
So those are all the interface
patterns we wanted to show you
today.
As you can see, many of these
patterns leverage existing
interface elements we've had for
a long time.
Machine learning, therefore, is
an elevation of what we've been
doing all along.
These patterns are not
necessarily new but they are
applied in a new context.
And whenever we choose our
patterns, we have to make sure
we respect people's work.
Adding additional attribution or
additional feedback actions asks
even more information for
someone to parse and that
invades their attention and
might distract them from their
task at hand.
So choose your patterns with
people in mind first.
So designing a machine learning
experience is not just
outputting your results in an
interface.
The way we select our data,
metrics, inputs and outputs
plays a very important role in
making these experiences
understandable, intuitive and
delightful.
Now to end our talk, I want to
go back to something that Kayur
said in the beginning.
Apple uses machine learning to
create products and experiences
we could never create before,
products and experiences we
really care about.
You've seen examples of how
machine learning helps us manage
our attention, on how it allows
us to give you better
recommendations, on how it can
present contextual information
at the right time, and how we
can automate mundane tasks so
you can focus on what matters.
But machine learning can help us
achieve much more than that.
Apple has always used technology
to empower everyone and machine
learning only elevates that
capability.
It can empower us to be healthy
by measuring our activity and
our steps.
Machine learning allows us to be
more inclusive by leveraging our
communication, for example by
adding voice control to the
camera so a blind person can see
what they're holding or it can
know when their loved ones are
in frame.
Machine learning helps us to be
safe by detecting problems with
our heart by measuring our heart
beats or an ECG.
And lastly, it can allow us to
be creative by seeing the world
in a whole new way, for example
by letting a known tool like a
pencil do magic things on
screen.
So you can see when we align the
we create with the values we
uphold, we can create
experiences that really elevate
the best of humanity.
That's everything we had in
store for you and we hope we've
given you plenty of inspiration,
insight into designing great
machine learning experiences.
All the patterns we talked about
and more are available on the
Human Interface Guidelines as a
beta.
There are still a few more talks
this afternoon about machine
learning and all of us will be
available in the coming hour at
the User Interface Design Lab to
answer any questions you might
have.
So make sure to come by and say
hi.
Thank you all for attending and
enjoy the last day of WWDC.
[ Applause ]