[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Hello. My name is Ian and I
am an engineer on the Shortcuts
Team.
Today I'm going to talk to you
about how users can build their
own shortcuts and how you can
ensure that they have the best
possible experience.
I'm going to cover three topics
today.
First, intents from your app can
now be editable by the user as
actions.
I'm going to walk you through
the parts of an action and show
how users can configure them
inside of their Shortcuts.
You've built great Shortcuts and
we want to make sure that you
can get them in front of your
users, as well.
I'm going to talk about some
ways that you can showcase the
Shortcuts from your app using
Add to Siri and other APIs.
And later on, we're going to
build a multistep shortcut and
make actions that work great
with others by using input and
output.
Let's get started.
I have an app called Soup Chef.
And as you know, it's a super
way to order clam chowder or
tomato soup for delivery and
pickup.
And Soup Chef has made an intent
for ordering soup.
So, here's that inside of the
Shortcuts Editor, where actions
are configured.
Every action can have parameters
that can be edited by the user.
And these parameters were
defined inside of the Intent
definition file.
Until the user enters a value,
parameters show the display
name.
And because this display name
can sometimes be shown as a
title in configuration UI, make
sure that the display name is
always capitalized.
The parameter summary is a
sentence that's shown to the
user that describes what the
shortcut will do when it's run.
Summaries should read like a
sentence and start with a verb.
There's no need to write the
name of your app in the summary
because it will be displayed at
the top of the action alongside
your app's icon.
Try to keep the summary short
and only include the parameters
that must be filled out for the
action to be functional.
And whichever parameters you
don't include the summary will
be displayed underneath Show
More which the user can expand
while editing to modify the
values in the remaining
parameters.
Parameter summaries are defined
in the Shortcuts app section in
the Intent editor Xcode.
Soup Chef has multiple different
summaries.
One for ordering pickup and the
other for ordering delivery.
So, as the user changes between
pickup and delivery inside of
the action, the parameter
summary will update based on the
different values that the user
has entered.
So, your app knows best about
what the user does and when.
So, we think the most relevant
place to create shortcuts is
right inside of your app.
Here we are inside of Soup Chef
and someone just ordered some
tomato soup with cheese.
And this is a great time to
present an Add to Siri button
because the user just performed
an action that they're very
likely to repeat.
So, to do that, Soup Chef placed
the order information into an
intent and then, placed the Add
to Siri button into the UI.
When the user taps on that
button, the app lets them create
a shortcut by showing the Add to
Siri View Controller.
The API to do this has not
changed since iOS 12 but this
year, we've expanded what users
can do inside of the View
Controller.
So, let's look at what's new.
First, and instead of having to
say the phrase to save the
shortcut, users can now just
type it or use dictation.
Your app should be prefilling
this value by setting the
suggestedInvocationPhrase
property of your intent.
Try to keep this phrase short
and descriptive about the kind
of action that the user just
did.
And because the user will be
able to say this to Siri, it
should also be easy to speak and
remember.
Underneath that is the Do
section, which will show the
user a preview of what this
shortcut will do when it's run.
Make sure to put as much
information as possible into the
intent about what the user just
did.
This will ensure that your app
can order the soup again without
having to ask too many follow-up
questions.
And if you've made your intent
configurable, the user can tap
on this, customize the shortcut,
and change the values that were
prefilled by, by you.
And once the user is done, they
will tap the Add to Siri button
and return back to your app.
And later on, they can go into
the Shortcuts app where they can
view, edit, and run the shortcut
that they've made.
So, now let's take a look at
some places in the Shortcuts app
where you can make your
shortcuts discoverable, as well.
Many first-time users will start
off in the right-most tab which
is the Gallery.
Here is where we suggest
prebuilt shortcuts.
In iOS 13, we added a new
section to the Gallery and it
has suggested shortcuts from the
apps that are frequently used on
your device.
Now, your app's suggested
shortcuts have the possibility
of being prominently featured in
the Gallery depending on how
frequently the user interacts
with your app.
Your app can influence the
suggestions that are displayed
in the Gallery in two different
ways.
First, you can explicitly set a
list of suggested shortcuts and
you can use the
INVoiceShortcutCenter to do
this.
You can update this as often as
you'd like as you learn more
about your user's habits and
preferences.
And we also populate this list
with recent or frequently used
actions that the user has done
inside of your app.
Now, how does the Shortcuts app
know what the user does inside
of your app?
In previous years, we've
introduced the concept of
Donation.
Now, Donation allows you to tell
the system about things that the
user does so that the system can
later suggest them at a relevant
time.
You can create a, you can donate
by creating an INInteraction and
putting a filled out intent
about what the user just did
into there.
And then, later call the Donate
method.
Not only does Donate allow your
shortcuts to appear in the
Gallery, but it also enables
private on-device Siri
suggestions in places like the
Lock Screen or Spotlight Search.
If you'd like to know more
information about how
suggestions from Donations work
across the system, I encourage
that you watch our talks from
WWDC 2018.
Now, another time that users
might be creating and
discovering your shortcuts is
when building a new shortcut
inside of the app.
You'll see all of the possible
actions that can be added into
the shortcut in the Shortcuts
editor.
There's categories across the
top which contain hundreds of
built-in actions for things like
playing media, adding reminders,
and also scripting actions like
Loops and If statements.
Next, is a list of suggested
actions.
And these suggestions are based
also on device usage which
includes actions from
third-party apps.
Since I order soup a lot, Soup
Chef's action is right here at
the top.
So, how did Soup Chef get all of
these soup options to show up?
Well, there were two easy steps
to get this to work.
The first thing is to select
which of the parameters is the
key parameter.
Your key parameter should be the
one that's most identifiable to
the user.
And Soup Chef picked the soup
type as the parameter because
that's the most useful to the
user, more than quantity or
toppings.
And the second step is to Donate
every time the user performs
that action inside of your app,
if you're already donating via
the INVoiceShortcutCenter or via
INInteraction, then there's no
additional work required by your
app.
As long as your donation has a
value set for that key
parameter, we can show it inside
of suggestions.
Also, don't forget to include an
image for your key parameter
when donating.
If you don't provide an image,
then your app's icon will be
displayed in the list, instead.
And additionally, if you're
looking for a list of all of the
actions from your app that's
donated or not, you can tap on
the app's section to see them
all.
Now, let's switch gears and
build a shortcut with a set of
actions that work great together
by using input and output.
I have another app called
StickyNote.
And StickyNote's a notetaking
app where I write down things
that I need to do.
StickyNote has a whole bunch of
actions.
And most importantly, it has an
action where I can search for
notes by name.
And then, once a note is found,
there are other actions that can
manipulate that note such as
inserting text into the note or
deleting it.
In iOS 13, we now allow actions
from your apps to output
information for others to use.
So, the Find StickyNote action
can output a StickyNote with an
identifier, name, content, and
the last date that it was
modified.
I want to be able to chain two
shortcuts together and find a
note and then, add information
into that note.
So, the note would be the output
of the first action and I'm
passing it as input to the
second.
So, let's take a look at how to
set up your action to produce
output.
First, we'll click on the plus
button at the bottom left to add
a new type representing what a
StickyNote is.
Types already have an identifier
and the Display Name.
But the note has content and a
date that it was last modified.
So, we'll add those as
properties so the user can
access all of that information.
Next, we'll select the response.
And the response is the object
representing the result of the
intent.
We will add a note property,
selecting the new type that we
just made.
And finally, we'll select that
property from the Output
dropdown.
So, if your response has
multiple properties, you need to
pick a single one from that
Output dropdown.
And this lets you control what
information other actions can
see.
So, now that our action has
output, I can add one action and
after the other and select the
found note as the note that I
want to add text to.
But for actions to work really
great together, it would be nice
if the note could automatically
be filled in to the second
action, so I don't have to
select it from the first every
single time.
So, if you need your actions to
work great together and fill
output from one into the input
of another, you need to select
one of your parameters as the
input parameter.
Here we are looking at that Add
Text to Note action.
And we'll select the note as the
input parameter.
So, now when I add the second
action, the Add Text to Note
action, that note is already
filled in to the note parameter
from the first action.
So, adding inputs and outputs
allows users to create multiple
step shortcuts using your
actions that work great
together.
So, let's take a look at the
things that we covered today.
First, we walked through the
components of a Shortcuts action
and how users can configure one.
Next, we looked at the various
ways that users can discover
your actions.
And we started inside of your
app using the Add to Siri
experience.
And next, we walked through the
Gallery and the Editor inside of
the Shortcuts app and talked
about how to make your actions
discoverable there, as well.
And finally, we explored how to
make your actions work great
together taking input and
produce output.
The Soup Chef app is available
as sample code.
So, be sure to check that out if
you want to see more about how
all of this works.
We also had a session earlier
this week where we covered more
about how these can be used to
power follow-up questions in
Siri.
Thanks for attending.
[ Applause ]