>>>TIM COOK:
Good morning!
Good morning.
Thanks for joining us.
And welcome to San Francisco.
Welcome to WWDC 2015.
Although we may not
have any -- thank you --
high-flying trapeze acts, we
do have a lot of great things
to talk about this morning.
This developer conference
continues to be the epicenter
of change for not only
Apple, but the industry.
This is our 26th WWDC.
We have attendees today
from over 70 countries,
and 80 percent are here
for the very first time.
[Applause]
This is our most
global conference ever.
And a special shout-out for
our 350 scholarship winners.
[Cheers and applause]
These guys are unbelievable.
I spent some time
with them yesterday.
Our youngest scholarship
winner is a 12-year-old girl
from New York.
She is going to have a
fantastic future ahead.
[Applause]
We've got over a hundred
sessions planned for you
and over 150 labs so that
you can get your hands
on our latest technologies.
And we've got over a thousand
Apple engineers to answer just
about any question
that you might have.
Now, we've got a lot more
people that would have liked
to have been here this
morning, but unfortunately,
we just can't fit any
more in, as you can tell.
And so for the first time,
we're not only live
streaming the Keynote,
but we are live streaming
30 sessions
of the conference as well.
[Applause]
Now, before we get right to
the show, I'd like to bring
up something that I saw on
the news just a few days ago.
This is Brandon Moss of
the Cleveland Indians,
and he hit his 100th career
home run last Tuesday.
Obviously, it's a huge milestone
if you are a baseball player.
Not a lot of people do this.
And you can imagine how much
that ball would mean
to him to have it.
It turns out the ball was hit
into the Indians' bull pen,
and his teammates decided to
play a bit of a prank on him.
They decided to hold
it for ransom.
And this is the list of
things they asked for.
[Laughter] Apple Watches,
iPads, MacBook Airs, iPhones.
It's unbelievable.
It's a shopping list
for the Apple Store.
[Applause]
Now, Brandon would have
had to raid an Apple Store
to get that ball back.
That didn't seem quite right
to us, and so what we're going
to do is we're going
to pay the ransom.
And I have the ball right here.
[Applause]
We are giving the ball to
Brandon, and we are going
to give everything his
teammates asked for to them
so everybody is happy.
So congratulations, Brandon,
on a hundred home runs,
and good luck on
the next hundred.
[Applause]
Now, we've got a
jam-packed morning for you.
We are going to get
started with OS X.
We are bringing a whole bunch
of new great capabilities
to the Macintosh.
And next we've got a
great update for iOS,
the world's most advanced
mobile operating system.
And today we're bringing
native apps
to the Watch with a new version.
[Applause]
With a new version
of the watchOS,
which gives the developers
even more time
to create even greater
apps for the Watch
that will change the world.
Now, all three of these
ecosystems together provide
incredible opportunities
for developers
and unbelievable
possibilities for users.
So we are very excited
about this.
There's a lot here, and
so I am going to dispense
with my normal updates other
than to tell you
everything's going great.
[Laughter]
[Applause]
And I'd like to bring
out my friend
and colleague Craig Federighi to
take you through OS X and iOS.
Craig.
[Applause]
>> CRAIG FEDERIGHI:
Good morning!
It's fantastic to be
with you here at WWDC.
The team has been doing
some amazing work this year,
and I am thrilled to be able
to share it with you today.
We are going to start with OS X.
Now, our current release,
Yosemite, is a big, bold,
beautiful release
with a gorgeous new UI
and breakthrough features like
Continuity that let you work
across your devices
like never before.
Now, the adoption rate for
Yosemite is just incredible.
In fact, over 55 percent
of active Mac users are
running our latest update,
and this is just unprecedented
in the history of our industry.
[Laughter] In fact, Yosemite
has the fastest adoption rate
for any PC operating
system ever.
So thank you.
[Applause]
So for our next big release of
OS X, we knew we wanted to build
on those strengths of Yosemite
with some really great
refinements and advances.
The only real question, of
course, was what to call it.
So we had to once again turn to
our crack Apple Marketing Team.
Now, in typical California
fashion, they started
with a project kickoff meeting.
[Laughter]
And then headed immediately
into a team building off site.
[Laughter]
Now, of course they are in their
traditional Apple Marketing
Free-Bottom Fridays attire.
They say it's all
part of their process.
I am not sure I get it.
Ultimately, this
didn't yield any names,
so they called in a consultant.
[Laughter]
He told them the answer
was to be found within.
Not within themselves,
but within Yosemite.
And so the new name for
OS X is OS X El Capitan.
[Applause]
For El Capitan, we focused
in two major areas --
experience and performance.
For experience, we've made
Spotlight more expressive,
more powerful, and more
knowledgeable than ever.
We've made big enhancements
to the apps you use most,
and we made some real great
advancements in the area
of how you manage
windows on the system.
But rather than just talk about
it, I'd like to show it to you,
so let's start with
a demo right now.
[Applause]
Now, your first task, of
course, in a demonstration
or whenever you wake your
Mac, is finding the cursor,
and El Capitan makes
this easier than ever.
I just do that little
shake we all normally do,
and there it is.
It comes right out to greet you.
It's really handy.
[Applause]
Now, we brought other great
gestures to the system.
I am just going to
go here in Mail.
I have a message here from Eddy.
Looks like -- well, now --
[Laughter] -- that's a keeper.
So I can actually mark
it unread to keep it just
by swiping two fingers across
the trackpad just like that.
And this one I'd kind of like
to delete, so I am just going
to swipe it away just like that.
So some real nice
little gestures.
Let's move on now to Safari.
Now, in Safari, I have some
sites that I like to keep
around because I refer to them
on and off throughout the day,
and now in Safari, I can pin
those sites just like this.
So there's -- I am going to
pin my Twitter site here.
And of course I have been
following the Warriors.
Go Warriors, we are
going to get it done.
[Applause]
Just like that.
Now, Pinned Sites have a
lot of special properties.
For one, if I close this
window and reopen it,
you see that my Pinned
Sites are all right there,
and they load instantly.
Now, Pinned Sites also behave
differently when I follow links,
so I am just going
to click on one here,
and you notice it opens in a new
tab, but my pinned site remains.
Now I am going to open
up a couple more links.
This one, let's see, this one.
I will take a quick look.
This one looks like some
kind of presentation video.
This one is about the Giants.
Have you ever had
this happen to you?
You are like, Where is
this audio coming from?
Now with just a tap,
you can mute it or find
out where it came from and
shut it down just like that.
[Applause]
So I am interested in
seeing this Giants game,
and now Spotlight can
actually help me out there.
So I am just going to do a
search for the SF Giants,
and we see right now I
get current game scores,
upcoming games.
Looks like the game I want
to go to is on Friday,
so I can just search
for weather on Friday.
See we get the weather.
We can even resize the Spotlight
panel and move it around.
I mean, there's innovation; huh?
[Laughter] But I can also
express myself in my own words
in Spotlight searches now, so
I can do things like slides
from Brian, and you
see I find those there.
But how about slides from
Brian about El Capitan?
You see, I find exactly what I
am looking for in my own words.
Now, this works great
in other apps as well.
Let's try it out in Mail.
So I've been really busy, of
course, the last couple of days,
so I have been getting a
little behind on my Mail.
I want to see the messages
that I've received from Phil
but that I haven't
responded to yet.
So I am just going to say
"mail I ignored from Phil."
[Laughter] There are a few,
but I will be getting back
to him right after the show.
[Laughter] So next, of course,
it's great in the Finder
as well, so if I wanted to look
at documents that I was working
on last year at this time,
I might say something like
"documents I worked
on last June."
And I find exactly
what I am looking for.
So this is really a
great way to search.
Next I want to turn to window
management, so I am just going
to run a script here that's
going to open up a whole bunch
of windows to simulate kind
of what my desktop looks
like after a day working on OS
X because it's a powerful system
and we tend to have
a lot of things open.
OS X provides some great ways
to navigate your windows,
and one of those
is Mission Control.
In El Capitan, we made
Mission Control smoother,
simpler, and faster than ever.
I am going to take three fingers
and swipe up on the trackpad.
We get this gorgeous
overview of Mission Control.
I'll just bring forward Safari.
Let's do that again
and bring up Mail.
Just like that.
Works really great.
Of course, OS X provides
great tools also
to organize your windows, and
one of those is Full Screen.
I am going to take this
window here full screen,
and I am going to reply.
Looks like there's a
message here from Eddy.
He says sorry about bailing
on the team dinner last night.
He was apparently
prepping for the Keynote.
So that's understandable.
But it looks like, actually,
I just got a new mail
from Jeff here, and now I can
just click away, and it hides,
and then -- oh, hold on.
Busted, Eddy.
So I think I'll just
drag this, actually,
right into my Compose window,
it hops up automatically,
and I can do it just like that.
It's really great.
And I can even open up
tabs in Compose as well.
It's really handy.
So this is a great way now to
work in full screen in Mail.
[Applause]
Thank you.
Now, we've done something
totally new to El Capitan,
and it's the ability
to work really easily
on two windows side by side.
So I am just going to click and
hold here on the green button.
And you see it's
prompting me to pick a side.
I will just drop it in.
And you notice I get an expose
of all my other windows.
Let me pick the new News
app, just like that.
[Applause]
Of course, I can
resize this window
to style it just the way I want.
How about that blur?
Again, innovation.
[Laughter] So, great
way to work.
Here I can drag links,
for instance,
from Safari right in here.
You notice in the new Notes app,
I get a beautiful graphical link
that gives me a nice thumbnail
that helps me identify
what I dragged in there.
I am going to drag
in some yurts.
I think yurts, first
time mentioned
on the WWDC Keynote stage.
There you go.
Got some yurts here.
Great way to work split screen.
We've also provided a really
easy way to move windows
into their own desktops.
So let me just take this window
here, I'm just going to drag it
up past the top of the screen,
and drop it in just like that.
So easy. I can also do this
to take a window full screen.
So let's take Photos, just
drop it in right here,
I took it full screen.
Check this out.
I am going to take
Messages, drop it on Photos,
and create a split
view just like that.
Totally awesome.
[Applause]
And that is a quick look
at some improvements
to the experience in El Capitan.
[Applause]
So we saw in El Capitan
a powerful form of search
in Spotlight that lets
you compose your searches
in your own words.
It knows more than ever,
can look up weather,
stocks, game scores.
We saw gestures, for instance,
just swiping to delete in Mail.
And, of course, pin
sites in Safari
and the ability to
easily mute tabs.
A great new Notes app that
supports text styling,
checklists, and graphical links.
And better window
management than ever
with a beautiful new
Mission Control interface,
easy access to your
spaces bar, and of course,
the ability to do split
view and adjust it
to see exactly what
you are looking for,
every pixel of your display
devoted to your content.
Of course, there's much more
to experience in El Capitan,
but now I want to
turn to performance.
So we've optimized performance
throughout the system.
In fact, we are seeing about
a 1.4 times acceleration
in app launching,
a 2x improvement
in the snappiness
of switching apps.
The time to get first Mail
messages, twice as fast.
Opening a PDF in preview,
four times as fast.
But we've also made deep
architectural improvements,
and that brings us to Metal.
[Applause]
Thank you.
Last year we introduced
Metal at WWDC as a way
to accelerate graphics in
high-performance games.
It takes the overhead
out of OpenGL,
providing a high-performance API
that gives the game
direct access to the power
of the underlying
graphics hardware.
Well, this year we are
bringing Metal to the Mac.
And we are doing more than that.
Because we are taking the
graphic stacks on which apps
on OS X are built, Core
Animation and Core Graphics,
and moving them from OpenGL to
run natively on top of Metal,
making everything you do faster.
We are seeing 50
percent improvements
in rendering performance
and a 40 percent reduction
in the amount of CPU
necessary to do graphics.
That means improved performance
for your applications
and better battery life.
But the benefits of
Metal don't stop there.
Metal's also great for
high-performance apps.
In fact, Metal combines
the compute power of OpenCL
and the graphics power of OpenGL
in a higher performance
API that does both.
And what we've seen from working
with early pro developers
is really phenomenal.
Adobe came in and,
in short order,
was able to deliver an
eight times improvement
in their rendering effects
inside of After Effects,
and they have been able
to take the drawing engine
in Illustrator, move it on top
of Metal, and take kinds of UI
that previously was
noninteractive,
like zoom of extremely
detailed drawings,
and make it completely flawless
and interactive,
thanks to Metal.
Adobe is so pleased with this
they said they are committed
to adopting Metal
on their OS X apps,
seeing performance
increases up to 8x.
They are excited
about what it can do
for their Creative Cloud users.
Of course, Metal is
also fantastic for games
with a 10x improvement.
That's ten times improvement
in drawing performance.
So we brought in Epic to
see what they could do
in short order, and the
results are really phenomenal.
I'd like to welcome to
the stage Josh Adams
and Billy Bramer
for a quick demo.
[Applause]
>> Thank you,
Craig.
Thank you very much for
having us here today.
So last year Metal
revolutionized graphics on iOS,
and now Apple's amazed us again
by bringing Metal to the Mac.
Of course, this is
great news for games,
but also for the tools that
we use to make those games.
Here you are seeing Epic's
upcoming multiplayer title
Fortnite, running
entirely on Metal.
We are modifying it directly
within the Unreal Engine,
a development tool that powers
many of today's best games.
It's quite a bit going
on in this scene, though,
so let's break it down.
First, there are
64 different layers
of rendering effects,
and that's a lot.
All combining together, though,
to produce what you
see on the scene today.
If we go into a simple wireframe
mode, you can see the thousands
of building blocks that
make up this world.
We can start to add in layers,
flat shading, detailed lighting,
runtime shadows, and finally
we combine them all together
to bring Fortnite's fun and
lighthearted aesthetic to life.
The interesting thing
here, though,
is that all of the effects
you are seeing are being done
completely in real-time.
Notice how the shadows and
objects interact nicely
as Josh moves the car around.
Finally, we can change the
time of day on the fly,
dramatically altering the
mood of the entire scene.
All of this is thanks to
the efficiency of Metal.
In fact, we are seeing
a 70 percent reduction
in CPUs compared to OpenGL,
enabling developers like us
to create richer 3D worlds.
Speaking of those worlds, let's
hop into the game, Fortnite.
Now, if you've ever
built a pillow fort
and battled imaginary
monsters with your friends,
you already know how
to play Fortnite.
This is the end-of-the-world
scenario you have been training
for since you were a kid.
It's a beautifully
stylized universe.
You can destroy anything
you want.
Gather resources
and build a fort.
So let's go ahead
and wreck this car.
Gather its metal.
And continue our wanton
destruction by chopping
down this tree to get
some wood for later.
Did we mention there
are purple death storms,
like this one, for instance?
We should go.
Luckily, while we were out
exploring, we found a multitude
of weapons, and this broom.
If we can just get
across the field,
our friend has been busy
building a fort across the --
did we mention the storms
are made of monsters?
We are going to need something
a bit better than this broom.
Nice! There's our friend
laying down some covering fire.
>> Hey,
look out!
>> We call that move
the power cord.
I've got a bad feeling
about this.
You are going to
need a bigger fort.
Place a trap, head inside.
Looks like an enemy has
broken into our fort.
All right.
Let's use that wood we gathered
earlier to fix this wall,
build some stairs, meet up
with our friend topside.
>> Glad you could
make it.
[Monster screaming]
>> Whether you are a
gamer or a game developer,
Metal opens new possibilities
for rich and engaging worlds.
You can download the Unreal
Engine for Mac right now,
and the Fortnite beta
for Mac starts this fall.
Thank you very much.
[Cheers and applause]
>> CRAIG FEDERIGHI:
Thank you, guys.
That was great.
We have been totally impressed
with what Epic has been able
to accomplish in
such a short time.
And this is in part because the
work they did to adopt Metal
in their rendering engines for
iOS immediately pays dividends
on OS X, and we are seeing
this with many other developers
as well who are bringing their
gaming engines immediately
to the Mac.
And pro app makers are seeing
the benefits of Metal as well,
people like The Foundry
and Autodesk.
I think we are going to
see pro users, gamers,
and all of us benefiting
from the performance
advantages of Metal.
So that is El Capitan,
improvements
to experience and performance.
Now, El Capitan is available
to all of you developers today.
[Applause]
We will be doing a public
beta once again in July,
and we will be rolling
out to everyone
with a free upgrade this fall.
And that's our update on OS X.
[Applause]
Next -- you guessed it -- iOS.
Now, our current big
release of iOS is iOS 8,
and iOS 8 was a huge release
with tons of new features
for users and a phenomenal
set of technologies
that you developers
have been able to use
to deliver all-new
experiences to the platform.
The upgrade rate for
iOS has been fantastic.
We have 83 percent of active
iPhone users currently running
the latest OS.
And this is really important
because it means not only are
they getting the most recent
features, but they're also up to
date on all the security fixes,
and you're able to
know as a developer
that you can target
all the users
with the latest and
greatest APIs.
And this is a benefit
that actually remains
really unique to iOS.
[Applause]
So we are now looking forward
to iOS 9, and as we conceived
of what we wanted to
accomplish, first and foremost,
we wanted to elevate the
foundations of the platform,
things like extending
your battery life,
improving performance,
and enhancing security
to protect customer data.
But there was more
we wanted to do.
Adding intelligence throughout
the user experience in a way
that enhances how
you use your device
but without compromising
your privacy.
Things like improving the
apps that you use most
and taking the experience of
the iPad to the next level.
I want to start today with
intelligence and Siri.
Now, Siri has quietly
become incredibly popular.
It serves over a billion
requests per week.
And this is in part because
Siri has gotten so great
at understanding
what we are saying.
In just the last year, we've
seen a 40 percent reduction
in word error rate,
down to 5 percent.
That's an industry
leading number.
And Siri is 40 percent
faster than ever
at responding to what we say.
Now, for iOS 9, Siri has a
beautiful new UI and is capable
of doing so much more.
Things like "show me photos
from Utah last August" can
instantly show you the right
photos from your photo library.
And Siri's really great
at taking reminders.
Now you can ask Siri
things like "remind me
to grab my coffee off the
roof of my car when I get in."
Because Siri knows now when
you've gotten in the car.
And of course, we often want
to take reminders about things
that we are looking at on our
device, some content inside
of our app, maybe a Safari.
Now you can say things
like "remind me about this
when I get home," and that
reminder refers right back
with a link to specifically
what you were looking
at when you took that reminder.
So Siri is a great assistant.
But the best assistants
are proactive.
And so on iOS 9, we are
bringing proactivity throughout
the system.
So say you like to run in
the morning, and when you do,
you like to listen to music.
Well, now your phone can
learn that about you,
and when you plug
in your headphones,
can offer up Now Playing
automatically right
on the Lock screen.
[Applause]
And this is all
context-sensitive to the time,
the place, and even the
devices you are connected to,
so you do the same thing in the
car later on, and it might offer
up the audio book that you
have been listening to.
Now, as a great assistant,
your iPhone can now take
invitations you receive
in your email and without you
even touching them automatically
put them on your calendar
and even give you a time
to leave reminder, taking
into account current traffic
conditions, and of course,
with just a swipe, give you
access to driving directions.
Now, have you ever had this
happen to you, you get a call,
the number looks
kind of familiar,
but you are really
not sure who it is?
As a great assistant, your
phone can now look in your email
and find out who that person
might be and suggest it
to you right on the
Incoming Call screen.
It's super handy.
[Applause]
Now, this kind of
proactivity is also great
when it comes to Search.
So now when you swipe to the
left of the Home screen to get
to Search, you see that Siri
offers great suggestions,
things like the people that you
might want to contact now based
on your upcoming meetings and
your communication patterns,
the apps that you might want
to launch based, for instance,
on what you just downloaded
from the App Store and haven't
yet tried out, or apps you
tend to use this time of day,
and also easy one-tap
links to locations
that are relevant nearby,
and even breaking news.
When it comes to Search, we
also know more than ever before.
So for instance, you can
search for sports scores.
And we now support video
search, of popular video sites
like Vivi, Vimeo, YouTube,
and the iTunes Store.
And we have these
great descriptive cards
with a Play button so
you can play directly
from your search result.
Most importantly, we now
have an API for Search.
[Applause]
So now when a user
performs a search,
we can find content behind
the apps they have installed
on the device and pull those up
in Results, and when they tap,
they are deep-linked
directly into the application.
You see for instance
here Airbnb.
They can get their result.
Of course, we even provide
a convenient backlink
so they can get right back
to their search results.
So we think these kinds
of intelligence features
really make a huge difference
in your experience in iOS.
And to show you how, I would
like to give you
a quick demo now.
So I want to take you through
a day in the life with iOS 9,
and we are going to start with
a typical day for me today.
We are going to start
in my bedroom
when I woke up in the morning.
You will notice because my phone
knows that in the morning I
like to meditate that it's
offered me a meditation app
right here in the bottom
left of the screen.
So I can just swipe up
from the bottom left,
and I am taken right
in to meditate.
Ah, this is so serene.
Well, it looks like I got
a message here from Phil.
So Phil says that he is
putting together the invite
for tonight's big karaoke
potluck, and can I still pick
up this super awesome
karaoke machine?
Well, you know, Siri actually,
when I take reminders,
is able to link me right back
to what I am looking for,
so if I want to remember to pick
this up, I can just say this
to Siri: "Remind me
about this later today."
And so Siri will put
together a reminder,
and you see the link right
back to what I am looking for.
Well, I think after all,
meditation isn't probably
for me, so maybe I'll
move on to exercise.
So I head into the home gym
here, and because my phone knows
that when I am in the home gym
and I hook up headphones and I
like to listen to music,
watch what happens when I plug
in the cord of my headphones.
Jumps right in and offers
me some energetic music.
So let's all bust a move.
I don't know what kind
of exercise we are all
doing here, but pretty good.
Looks like actually
I've got that invitation
that Phil was going to send me.
Now, normally I would have
to actually go into Mail,
look at the time, put this
on my Calendar, but in fact,
my phone has automatically
done that for me.
Let me just swipe down here
into Notifications Center,
and we will look at my
calendar for the day.
You notice it automatically has
already been added right there.
Now, if we look at
the rest of my day,
ahead I have my vocal warm-ups
for the karaoke performance,
then WWDC.
It looks like I have
a little bit of time
to prepare my dish
for the big potluck.
So I am going to head
into the kitchen now,
and let's just swipe in.
When I am looking for
recipes, for instance,
I like to go into Search.
Let's just swipe
over into Search.
We see Siri has actually already
-- before I typed a character --
made suggestions for me
for people I could contact,
for instance, like Trent
Reznor, my vocal coach.
[Laughter] So I can just tap.
Here I can call Trent up,
and he can help me tap
into my inner pain and
rage that allows me
to fuel my vocal performances.
I actually haven't been
able to find the pain
and rage, truth be told.
Also, we have all these
great apps I can run
and locations nearby -- for
instance, because it's morning,
you see coffee and tea and
breakfast places are suggested.
As well as news.
But in this case, I
actually want to do a search.
So I have some potatoes
I think I could make use
of in this recipe.
So let's just search for potato.
Here you notice I am
getting search results right
from Yummly.
Let me tap into Yummly, and you
see I am deep-linked directly
in, so I get the great view
provided by that application.
Now, potato chips aren't
exactly what I am looking for,
so I am going to hit
the Back link here,
and I can browse directly
in to another result,
Canadian Poutine.
That looks exactly like
what the doctor ordered.
Yes. Let's look at
the ingredients.
Looks like 6 tablespoons
of unsalted butter.
I am down with that.
I am going to make at
least a double batch.
So I can just use Search to do
a conversion of tablespoons,
figure out how much that is.
So that actually
is 3/4 of a cup.
I am going to round
up to an even quart
and make myself some
fine poutine.
[Laughter] So Search
is really handy,
but Siri is also
great at search.
So I want to jump
forward to later today.
When I think I will be
reminiscing about WWDC's past.
I can ask Siri to
help me with that.
Show my photos from last
June in San Francisco.
Oh, yeah, this is great,
all these photos from WWDC.
You notice now Photos in iOS
9 has this great scrubber bar
at the bottom, so
I can easily slide
through photos super
quickly, just like this.
Oh, boy, now we are
into the karaoke night.
This is some fine stuff.
Phil really does an
awesome Viking crooner.
This is good stuff.
But of course, the
king of karaoke --
[Laughter] -- Eddy Cue.
In fact, when I want to get
really pumped up and inspired
for karaoke night,
I like to turn
to my Eddy karaoke album,
so let's do that now.
Show my karaoke photos of Eddy.
Oh, that is the master at work.
Hitting -- I love this hat.
[Laughter] This is totally dope.
Great stuff.
Well, I could really look
at these just all day,
but you know, actually,
my assistant has given
me a reminder based
on traffic conditions that it's
time to leave, so I am going
to wrap up this demo of
intelligence on iOS 9.
[Cheers and applause]
So you've seen how
we've been able
to bring intelligence throughout
the experience in iOS 9,
but we do it in a way that does
not compromise your privacy.
We don't mine your email,
your photos, or your contacts
in the cloud to learn
things about you.
We honestly just
don't want to know.
All of this is done on
device, and it stays
on device, under your control.
[Cheers and applause]
And if we do have to perform
a lookup on your behalf,
for example, for current traffic
conditions, it's anonymous,
it's not associated with your
Apple ID, it's not linked
with other Apple services,
and it's not shared
with third parties.
Why would do you that?
It is in your control.
That is intelligence in iOS 9.
[Applause]
Next, let's turn to Apple Pay.
And to take you through
it, I'd like to bring
to the stage our Vice President
of our Apple Pay
business, Jennifer Bailey.
Jennifer.
[Cheers and applause]
>> JENNIFER BAILEY:
Thanks, Craig.
It's great to be here.
We have been hard at work on our
goal of replacing the wallet,
and we've got some exciting
updates for you today.
I hope you've all tried Apple
Pay with our super easy, secure,
and private way to pay.
Last year we started with credit
and debit cards, and we now have
over 2,500 banks
supporting Apple Pay.
And this fall, Discover will
bring Apple Pay to the more
than 50 million card members.
[Applause]
Popular merchants are also
expanding their acceptance
for Apple Pay, including
great retailers
who will be supporting
Apple Pay this year,
including Trader Joe's,
Baskin-Robbins, and JCPenny.
These incredible brands join
a great list of the biggest
and best merchants
supporting Apple Pay
since our launch in October.
And for you are basketball
fans, if you are lucky enough
to have finals tickets,
you will be able to pay
for all your team logo wear at
both arenas using Apple Pay.
[Applause]
Small businesses are
also important for us,
so we are working with
innovative companies like Square
to enable millions of small
businesses to accept Apple Pay.
This fall, Square will
launch a gorgeous new reader.
Preorders are starting
today on square.com,
and these will be available
in our Apple Retail
Stores starting this fall.
With fantastic support of
merchants, both large and small,
we will surpass 1 million
locations accepting Apple Pay
next month.
[Applause]
And thanks to our
amazing developers,
we have great momentum
within apps as well.
Apple Pay is so easy
to use in-app,
our developers are telling
us they are seeing more
than two times increase
in checkout rates.
And we are adding new
apps with Apple Pay
to the App Store every day.
Here are some of the latest,
representing a great range
of categories, from
Delta in travel to Etsy,
the leading crafts marketplace.
These apps join an incredible
group that are redefining new
and simpler ways to pay.
We're also excited to be
working with Pinterest.
Later this month, Pinterest
will launch Buyable Pins,
where you will be able to buy
items from thousands of stores,
including Neiman
Marcus and Macy's,
right from within the
Pinterest app using Apple Pay,
and only on iOS.
[Applause]
With the great momentum
of Apple Pay in the U.S.,
we are now excited to announce
that we are bringing
Apple Pay to the UK.
[Cheers and applause]
And it's coming next month!
[Applause]
We will launch with eight
of the most popular banks,
with more coming this fall.
With this great lineup of
banks, we will support more
than 70 percent of the credit
and debit cards in the UK.
Great merchants are also
lining up to support Apple Pay,
like Boots, Costa Coffee,
and iconic British brands,
like Marks and Spencer
and Waitrose.
We will have over 250,000
locations supporting Apple Pay
in the UK.
That's more than we
started with in the U.S.
at our initial launch.
We are also thrilled that
our customers will be able
to commute and pay
for their fares
on the London transportation
system with Apple Pay.
[Applause]
So that's Apple Pay
coming to the UK.
Now let's talk about
some of the new features
that we are adding in iOS 9.
First, you will be
able to add your store,
credit, and debit cards.
Store cards offer unique
membership benefits,
and leading retailers
like Kohl's, JCPenney,
and BJs will be the first to
offer their cards on Apple Pay.
We will also add loyalty
and rewards cards,
also with a great
lineup of merchants.
Kohl's will bring
Yes2You programs,
Walgreens their Balance Rewards
card, and for your coffee
and doughnut lovers, Dunkin'
Donuts will bring Apple Pay
to their DDPerks
beginning this fall.
[Applause]
and Apple Pay automatically
presents the right card,
so you will never miss a reward.
With the expansion of Apple
Pay and the new types of cards,
we decided it's time to
rename Passbook to Wallet.
[Applause]
One place for all your credit
and debit cards, loyalty cards,
boarding passes, and more.
We told you last year
that our ultimate goal was
to replace the wallet,
and we are well
on the way to doing just that.
We couldn't be happier with
the progress towards our vision
and with the momentum
of Apple Pay.
Thank you.
[Applause]
>> CRAIG FEDERIGHI:
So that's Apple Pay.
Let's turn now to
our enhancements
to the apps you use most, and we
are going to start with Notes.
Notes is used regularly by about
half of our users on iPhone,
and for iOS 9, we have some
really great enhancements.
It starts with how you
work with simple text.
So now Notes provides
a really handy toolbar
with formatting options,
so it's easy, for instance,
to create titles, heading
styles, numbered lists.
But of course, we all like to
create checklists in our notes,
and so Notes makes
that really easy.
And of course, you can
just check off your items
with just a tap.
Now, because a picture is
worth a thousand words,
we make it easy to get at your
camera and your camera roll
and put photos directly
in your notes.
We are also providing a great
new way to capture your ideas
by just drawing with
your finger.
We provide some great
drawing tools.
You can make sketches
with these tools
and drop them right
inside your note.
[Applause]
Now, I don't know
if you are like me,
but a lot of times the
things I want to put
on my notes are things I
am looking at that I find
in other apps -- for
instance, a web page in Safari.
So now from the Share
sheet, you can just
with a tap add a link
right back into your notes.
And we make it really
easy to find your notes.
So we organize them
by time, of course,
and now we have these
great thumbnails
to let you see your
embedded images at a glance,
but we also provide this
cool new Attachments view
that shows you all of your
photos, your maps links,
your website links, and when
you tap, you can get right back
to the note where
they came from.
Now, Notes is great
on iPhone, on iPad,
and of course, on
the Mac as well.
And all of your content is
kept up to date across all
of your devices via iCloud.
That's a quick update to Notes.
[Applause]
Next, let's turn to Maps.
We've continued to
invest heavily in Maps,
and the improvements
are really awesome.
We are seeing five billion
user requests per week.
Usage on iOS is 3.5 times higher
than for the next
leading mapping app.
Now, Maps, of course,
historically have been
focused on drivers.
They emphasize things
like freeways and roads.
But we know for a lot of our iOS
users, they are mostly focused
on public transit, and so now
we've created a great map just
for them.
[Applause] Yes, it's Transit.
[Applause]
With Transit, we provide
a map that emphasizes all
of the different transit
lines, buses, and trains,
subway stations and so forth,
and when you tap on a station,
you can see all the
lines that run through it
with their departure times.
And we do multimodal routing,
whether you are taking a train,
a subway, a bus, or a ferry.
And we provide step-by-step
directions, including time
for walking directions.
But we've taken special care
to get the details right,
the ones that matter,
with Transit.
For instance, if you take a
subway station like this one
in Columbus Circle in New York,
it's not just a point on a map.
If you look closer,
it's actually an enormous
underground structure spanning
many city blocks, and so
we carefully surveyed all
of the entrances and exits
so that we could give you
walking directions based
on the time to travel from
where you actually are.
Now, this not only saves
you a ton of walking,
but it also probably
is the difference
between catching your train
on time and being stuck.
[Applause] It's really great.
[Applause]
We've taught Siri all about
Transit, so it's effortless
to ask Siri for directions.
And we are going to be
rolling Maps out, Transit,
starting with these cities
across the world, and --
[Applause] -- with these
and 300 more in China.
[Applause]
Now, when it comes
to searching in Maps,
we are now letting
you find locations
by type nearby with just a tap.
And when you find the
location you are interested in,
the card will tell you
right away right there
in the bottom whether
they support Apple Pay.
Support those Apple
Pay merchants.
[Applause]
Maps is great on
iPhone and iPad,
and of course, the Mac as well.
And that is Maps.
[Applause]
The apps that we've chosen
to build in to iOS are there
because they represent
fundamental experiences
to living on a mobile device.
And there's been one that we've
been wanting to do for years,
something that so many of
us find ourselves wanting
to do every day on our device,
and so today I'm pleased
to announce that we are
introducing a new application,
and it's called News.
News is beautiful content
from the world's greatest
sources personalized for you.
Now, here's an article in News.
It's absolutely stunning.
Now, publishers can easily
create beautiful content using
gorgeous imagery, custom
layout, and rich typography.
But News is also interactive,
and so to give you a look
at News in action,
I'd like to invite
to the stage our Vice
President of Application,
Product Management,
Susan Prescott.
Susan.
[Cheers and applause]
>> SUSAN PRESCOTT:
Thanks, Craig.
Thank you.
I am really excited
to be the first person
to show you our new News app.
It's right here on
the Home screen.
The first thing News wants to do
is get a sense of what I like,
so it's going to
give me a short list
of really great choices
to choose from.
And you'll see as I tap,
additional recommendations come
in on the bottom to give
you even more choices.
So I read Atlantic, Wired,
New York Times, and ESPN.
I am still with you, Warriors!
And Daring Fireball.
Topics, too, like science,
baking, and travel.
I could keep going, but I
think that's a great start,
so I will tap Done.
News creates a personalized
feed called For You.
It's based on the
choices I just made,
and it's all my News
in one place.
You can see it looks great.
It's easy to scan, and it
updates every time I check News.
The articles can
come from anywhere,
but the best ones are built
in our new Apple News format,
like this Wired article
featuring Rashida Jones,
awesome in Parks &
Rec and The Office.
Look at the rich
typography, beautiful images,
and my favorite part are
the really fun animations.
It's fast and fluid.
We think this offers the best
mobile reading experience ever.
To get to the next
article, I just swipe.
It's not just great
for magazines;
it's great for newspapers too.
This is a New York Times
article, and it looks
like a New York Times article.
Swipe down, there's a photo
gallery right in line, fast,
fluid to swipe through.
Go to the next article,
this one's from Quartz,
but I am seeing it because I
said I am interested in science.
It's a pretty cool
article about a font based
on Albert Einstein's
handwriting.
The animation makes it
come to life, and frankly,
who knew he had such
neat handwriting?
It's kind of interesting.
Swipe again, and I get an
article from Bon Appetit.
Great summer recipes,
and a crazy little jiggly
thing, which is kind of fun.
[Laughter] So I am a little
busy right now, so I am going
to go ahead and bookmark
this to read later.
Now, ESPN, I love you, Steph.
[Applause]
Now, I read ESPN
for the articles,
but there's also
some beautiful --
[Laughter] -- photos and videos.
[Cheers and applause]
Some photos and videos built in.
Not so much last night.
Let's see if Steph
can make this one.
Swish. All right.
He is going to be
there for us next game.
In addition, data and stats are
part of what's fun about sports,
so of course, rich info
graphics can be part of it.
I am going to swipe
back to For You.
Now, News is smart, so the
more I read, the better it gets
at showing me stories
I am interested in.
But what if I want to
discover something new?
I can tap here in the bottom
on Explore, and Explore,
based on what I've read,
will show me new publisher
channels I might be interested
in and suggested topics.
Well, I love technology.
I am going to go
ahead and follow that.
But News keeps track of
more than a million topics.
So I can be much more
specific about my interests.
To do that, I can tap
on Search and type.
I am going to type Swift.
And I get a number of hits,
everything from Taylor Swift,
to what I was looking for,
Apple's new programming
language.
So it's a beautiful feed,
and what's really cool
about this is there are powerful
machine learning algorithms
that analyze the contents
of the articles to figure
out which stories
belong in which article.
This looks like just
what I was hoping for.
I am going to go ahead and
add Swift to my Favorites.
So let's take a look
at Favorites.
I will tap down here.
Favorites is where I can see
everything I am following,
including Swift,
which I just added.
It's a great place to
go if I want to dig
into a particular
topic or if I want
to read a newspaper
or a magazine.
Let's say today I
want to read Wired.
You can tell I am in
the Wired channel.
You see the Wired
logo at the top
and the Wired channel
starting with Top Stories.
I can swipe through and see a
collection of the all the print
and web stories built
in Apple News format,
and it looks terrific.
I am going to look
at one more story.
This is about the first
civilian artist in space.
Cool concept and really cool.
I want to show you this.
We've taken photo
galleries to the next level
with something we
call Photo Mosaics.
Look how beautiful
it looks on the page.
Stunning. And, as you'd expect,
I just tap to zoom
in on the photos.
It looks great.
We think there's never been a
more beautiful magazine reading
experience, a mobile reading
experience in general,
and this is just
one of many channels
with beautiful stories
built in Apple News format.
That is a really
quick look at News.
We can't wait to get
it in your hands.
Thank you very much.
[Cheers and applause]
>> CRAIG FEDERIGHI:
So that's News.
Stunning content.
Personalized for you.
Fantastic on iPad and
on iPhone as well.
And of course, unlike just
about any other news
aggregation service we are aware
of on the planet, News is
designed from the ground
up with your privacy in mind.
We worked with leading
publishers,
like The New York Times,
who will be delivering 33
articles daily to News users,
and ESPN, who will be
bringing the depth and range
of their phenomenal
sports reporting.
And Conde Nast, who are
bringing content from 17
of their magazines, like
Vanity Fair, Vogue, GQ,
Wired, and Bon Appetite.
And they will be joined
by many, many others read
by millions of users daily.
News isn't just for
the media titans.
Great content comes from
all kinds of sources,
and we want them all in News, so
whether it's a local newspaper,
a blog, or a special-interest
publication,
they will all be here.
We will be rolling out News
starting in the United States,
the UK, and Australia.
We think you are
really going to like it.
[Applause]
Next, let's turn to iPad.
Now, iPad is a transformational
device.
For our users in education,
business, and at home,
for many of them, their iPad
is their primary computer.
And iPads are just tremendously
powerful, so in iOS 9,
we are elevating the iPad
experience to a whole new level.
Now, it starts with
something really simple,
which is how you work with text.
That brings us to the
QuickType keyboard.
Now, in iOS 8, we
introduced the Suggestion bar
that makes it quicker
than ever to type
and enter what you
are trying to get in.
But now, in iOS 9, we've
added shortcuts to that bar,
so with just a tap, you can cut,
copy, paste, format your text,
access your attachments.
It's really handy.
But you know, what makes
a Multi-Touch keyboard
so special is that it
can be anything you want.
It can transform.
So now when you want to move
the cursor or make a selection,
you can now just put two
fingers down on the keyboard,
and it becomes a
trackpad instantly.
[Applause]
You can move the cursor,
you can make selections.
Of course, you can use
the shortcut bar to cut,
drag to a new place, and
paste, editing more quickly
than ever before and without
your fingers ever leaving the
home row.
It's really great.
[Applause]
And if you do occasionally want
to hook a physical keyboard
to your iPad as well, we
made that better than ever.
We provide a way to
discover all of the shortcuts
that can accelerate
your operations
in the applications
using the keyboard,
and we've provided
shortcuts for app switching.
This might look familiar
to some of you.
As well as to searching
in Spotlight.
So that's QuickType, but now
I want to turn to the big one,
and that's Multitasking.
[Applause]
So iPad has always supported
forms of multitasking,
like this great graphical
task switcher,
and these nice four-finger
gestures
that let you move
between applications.
But for iOS 9, we are taking
it to a whole new place,
and I'd like to show
that to you now.
[Applause]
So let's start here on my iPad.
And what I am going to
do first is double-tap
on the Home button, and you
will see our new task switcher.
It's really gorgeous.
Big, full-screen
previews of all the apps.
Just move right into
Safari like this.
But of course, often when
I am in an app like Safari,
I then just want to
quickly check my messages.
So now with just a single
finger swipe from the side,
I can slide it right in with
what we call Slide Over.
Of course, it's fully
interactive.
I can take a quick look,
maybe type a response,
put it right back,
I am back in Safari.
Do that again.
From the top, I can pull down
and bring in other applications.
So let's bring in Calendar.
Of course, fully interactive
so I can tap into another day.
Let's bring in another app.
I am going to bring
in the new Notes app.
Just like that.
Now, sometimes, of course, I
want to stay working in Notes
and Safari both at the same
time, so I can just tap here
on the divider, and
now I am in split view.
They are both completely active.
In fact, for the first time
ever, multiapp, Multi-Touch,
I can move them both
at the same time.
[Applause]
Now, Notes is actually
pinned to the side now,
so I want to show you what
happens when I switch apps.
I am just going to move
over here to Photos.
You notice now I have Photos
with Notes on the side.
This is really great if I am
taking notes while working
across a bunch of experiences.
And of course those four-finger
gestures continue to work great,
so I can swipe my way
right back into Safari.
I can follow links, of
course, from my notes.
Let me tap on this link, and you
see Safari loads it right here
on the side.
I can adjust the split.
Let me move that over
to a nice 50/50 view
with Notes and Safari.
I can tap on links
to other apps,
so let's follow a
link into Maps.
Maps -- I really want
location accuracy.
Thank you, very helpful.
Slides right in and
shows me the location.
I can follow another
link, Maps adjusts,
I am able to stay
focused right here
in these two apps side by side.
Let's say I now want to
work Notes full screen.
I can pull right
across like that
and I am in full-screen Notes.
This gives me a great
opportunity
to show you what's new with
the QuickType keyboard.
I have a to-do list
I am building here.
I am going to add an item
here to buy a new ice chest.
There we go.
On second thought, I
should probably borrow one.
I am going to take two fingers
down on the keyboard,
swipe over here.
I can reposition the
cursor like this.
Tap and make a selection.
Extend the selection.
And type "borrow."
It's really easy.
I can make bigger moves too.
I can go to the top here, maybe
select the whole sentence,
drag down, maybe do a checklist
like this, and check them off.
Just like that.
Super cool.
[Applause]
Next I want to show you
multitasking in the context
of something I think we all
do quite a bit on our iPads,
which is not that --
which is watching ESPN.
So let's bring up a video.
I am going to play right here.
Now, often when I am watching
a video, I may decide I want
to look something up
or check something
or maybe even get a
notification, and I want you
to watch what happens
when I tap.
Watch the video.
Now I have Picture in Picture.
[Applause]
So I can still listen, I
can watch my video, I can,
of course, resize the
PIP if I want, like this.
I can move it around the
screen so it's out of the way
of what I am working on.
I can even move it off the side.
Sometimes I just want to listen
for a while while I work.
Of course, it stays
with me wherever I go.
I can pull it back,
and when I am done,
just tap to put it away.
And that is Multitasking
in iOS 9.
[Applause]
So iOS 9 delivers this great
app switcher, and of course,
that's available
on iPhone as well.
On iPad, we have Slide
Over so you can bring apps
in from the side.
You can tap and enter split view
for simultaneous
live two apps up.
And of course, Picture
in Picture.
Now, we provide developer APIs
to let your apps work this way,
and the good news is that you've
already done most of that work
because if you've adopted
Auto Layout and size classes
to work great on the iPhone 6
and 6 Plus, well, that carries
over just like this onto iPad.
Twitter came in and was able
to do it just in minutes.
It was really incredible.
Now, Slide Over is available
for the iPad Air, Air 2, mini 2,
and mini 3, as is
Picture in Picture,
and our most powerful
split view is available
on our most powerful
iPad, the iPad Air 2.
That's Multitasking.
[Applause]
So we've seen some
great end-user features,
but of course, we've also
focused on the foundations.
In performance, as you saw
earlier in El Capitan with OS X,
we've taken the core frameworks
that we use for drawing
on the system, Core
Animation and Core Graphics,
and we put them on top of Metal.
We are seeing great
acceleration,
1.6 times improvements in
animations and scrolling,
and a 50 percent reduction
in CPU usage for drawing.
It's really great.
With battery life, we focused
on real-world use cases
and optimized them.
And we are seeing an addition
of one hour of typical use
on a full charge on iPhone.
[Applause]
Now, we know that for a lot
of you if you are running low
on power, you start searching
all over for switches
and turning off features
in the hope
of extending your battery
life a little bit further.
Well, now in iOS 9, we
give you a single switch
to enter what we call Low
Power mode, and it pulls levers
that you didn't even
know existed and is able
to extend battery life for
an additional three hours
of typical use on top
of that additional hour.
It's really great.
[Applause]
Now, with security, we want
to protect our users' data
on device and in the cloud,
and so we are bringing
two-factor authentication
and making it easy for everyone
to protect their data in iCloud.
And with Software Update, we
want everyone to get to iOS 9,
and so we've done major
enhancements to the architecture
for our over-the-air
updates, and we have been able
to reduce the amount of free
space you need to get to iOS 9
from the 4.6 gigs that
it took to get to iOS 8
down to just 1.3, so we
think everybody is going
to be getting to iOS 9.
[Applause]
So iOS 9, intelligence
throughout the system,
Apple Pay, enhancements to
really popular apps like Notes
and Maps, an all-new News app,
and incredible features now
for iPad with Multitasking
and QuickType, and of course,
enhancements to the foundations.
Now, iOS 9 is a great release
for our users, but once again,
it's a fantastic release
for all of you developers,
bringing a ton of new features.
You saw search extensibility.
We are adding UI
testing to Xcode.
[Cheers and applause] Yes!
We have a new technology
called App Thinning,
which optimizes your
downloads to exactly the subset
of resources needed for that
user's device, so you are able
to get -- take less
space on device.
It's really great.
Now, when it comes to gaming,
we've enhanced SpriteKit,
SceneKit, and Metal and
introduced three new frameworks,
GameplayKit to bring
artificial intelligence
with path avoid obstacle
avoidance and path finding;
Model I/O to provide
beautiful lighting
on your 3D models;
and ReplayKit.
It lets you enhance
your applications
to let users record their game
play as video and share it.
It's really great.
[Applause]
Now, HealthKit has been on
fire, so we've continued --
well, we added water,
actually, to HealthKit.
We are not trying
to put out the fire.
We are adding lots of additional
health metrics to be tracked,
for instance, hydration,
UV exposure,
and reproductive health.
Now, HomeKit has been taking off
with manufacturers
introducing HomeKit peripherals
to the market now in areas like
thermometers, locks, and lights.
And now in iOS 9, we
are adding support
for window shades,
sensors of all kinds.
For instance, carbon monoxide
sensors, motion sensors.
And we're adding support for
security systems as well.
Perhaps most importantly,
we are allowing you
to access your home remotely
and securely via iCloud.
So no matter where you
are, you can control all
of your HomeKit devices.
[Applause]
Next, CarPlay.
So CarPlay supports audio
apps and now, in iOS 9,
it also supports apps by the
automaker to control things
in your own car without
leaving the CarPlay experience.
And CarPlay is supporting
more kinds of screens,
wider aspect ratios, high DPI.
But most significantly
with CarPlay,
we are pulling the cord.
In future cars, you will
be able to get in your car
without taking your phone out of
your bag or out of your pocket
and start experiencing
CarPlay effortlessly.
It's going to be really great.
[Applause]
Finally, let's talk about Swift.
[Cheers and applause]
You all know that the growth
that Swift has been experiencing
is just unprecedented,
and we've all seen
it with the flood
of applications coming
in to the App Store.
Well, now we are stepping on
the gas this year with Swift 2.
Now, Swift was designed from
the beginning to be fast,
and we've continued to roll
out targeted optimizations all
year long, and now with Swift 2,
we have an all-new optimization
technology that's especially
great for complex applications
and object-oriented programming
that we call Whole
Module Optimization,
and the results are
really fantastic.
In addition, we are bringing
the language features
that you've asked for most,
an elegant new error
handling model,
the ability to see
your interfaces
as synthesized headers
in Xcode, and the feature
that Tim has been begging for
all year, protocol extensions.
You are all going to love it.
Now, we think Swift is the
next big programming language,
the one that we will
all be doing application
and systems programming
on for 20 years to come.
And we think Swift should be
everywhere and used by everyone,
and so we're going to be
doing something really big.
Today we are announcing that
Swift will be open source.
[Cheers and applause]
We will be rolling
out the compiler
and the standard libraries
for iOS, OS X, and Linux.
And it will all be out there
by the end of the year.
So that's Swift,
and that is iOS 9.
We are doing a developer
beta -- you guessed it --
today, and for the first
time for a major iOS release,
a public beta, so sign
up now at beta.apple.com,
and you can get the beta
when it comes out in July.
And of course, we
will be rolling it
out as a free upgrade
in the fall.
And iOS 9 will support
all of the devices
that were supported by iOS 8.
We are not dropping
any this year
because we want everyone
to get iOS 9.
[Applause]
That's iOS 9.
I really appreciate your time.
Have a fantastic conference.
Thank you.
[Cheers and applause]
>> TIM COOK: Thanks,
Craig.
iOS just keeps getting better
and better for our many hundreds
of millions of users,
and iOS 9 takes it
to an even greater level
with incredible new apps
and intelligence
built right into iOS.
And as an avid iPad user, I
am also incredibly excited
about how far it extends the
iPad experience as we continue
to lead in the post-PC era.
With El Capitan, we've
created a new version of OS X
that dramatically
improves the experience
and the user experience and the
performance of the Macintosh.
And of course, Swift.
You've just heard Swift provides
a single language for you
to create apps for
both OS X and iOS.
There's really so many
possibilities for you
to use these platforms
and these tools
to create unbelievable apps
that will impact business
and healthcare and education and
really everything in our lives.
There's seemingly no
limit to what you can do.
And of course, underpinning
this, the App Store is very key.
It's hard to believe that the
App Store was launched only
seven years ago.
It's hard to remember
a day without it.
Now, I'm happy to announce
that the App Store recently
passed a major milestone.
The App Store has passed
100 billion apps downloads.
[Applause]
The rate of growth
and the momentum is
absolutely staggering.
The industry has never seen
anything like this before.
The App Store has
forever changed software
and software distribution.
And it's also been
an economic boon.
We've now paid over $30
billion to developers.
[Applause]
The App Store continues
to be the most profitable app
marketplace on the planet.
Now, we could not be more proud
of the work that you are doing.
More and more, developers
are transforming, empowering,
and reimagining the
very important things
that we do in our daily lives.
We've made a video about
your incredible impact
and just how far you've come
in such a short period of time,
and I'd love to run
it for you now.
>> Eight years ago, when
the iPhone was launched,
it didn't have an App Store.
And there was tremendous desire
on the part of developers
and customers for Apple
to let third-party
applications be created.
We all had this dream
that apps were going
to become really important,
but it took some time
to realize how they would affect
everything that we care about,
and as that cumulative effect
appeared, then we all start
to realize, oh, my
goodness, this is bigger
than any of us imagined.
>> Apps plus handheld
devices,
I think that's a watershed
moment in civilization.
I put it up there
with the invention
of the microscope
and the telescope.
We live in a time where the most
powerful tools ever imagined
to investigate and probe
our world are in the hand
of essentially everyone.
>> If you think the Industrial
Revolution was transformational,
the App Store is way bigger.
I don't think we've seen
anything reach a mass adoption
at anything close to this pace.
It took, for example,
electricity over a hundred years
to get to its first
50 million users.
It took television 13
years, and the App Store got
to 50 million users
in only 17 months.
>> The thing the App
Store did was give each
and every developer a voice.
It's a testament that two
guys in a room working
on an idea can launch an app
and instantly have hundreds
of millions of people
very quickly.
The iPhone made photography
universally accessible.
>> I cannot think
of a single industry
that doesn't need an app.
People want data at
their fingertips.
They want personalized
experiences.
They want power over
their money.
And it's not just for banking;
it's for every industry.
The App Store has fundamentally
shifted how we all need
to deliver.
It's leveling the playing field.
>> We don't have to own
things.
We don't have to
own our own cars.
own our own music.
We can call it up
when we need it.
That's a big change, all
flowing from the idea
of not just convenience
but people building
up an infrastructure
around that.
We are now talking
not about hundreds
of people getting the benefits
of an idea, but millions.
>> If you had told me when I
was a kid that you would be able
to write an idea and then film
that idea and then distribute it
to the world on a device
that you could also put
in your pocket, I would
never have stopped laughing,
and I would have
thought you were insane.
The App Store gives
everyone access
to incredibly powerful tools,
and there's an incredible
generation of filmmakers
and storytellers to come.
>> Kids love technology,
and they love interacting
with the iPad and with apps.
That wonder and awe that gets
ignited is actually being
utilized to help
that person learn.
Certainly in education
there's so much potential
to take the classroom
with you anywhere.
>> We all know we are
in this magic moment.
There are so many incredible
apps, and they do things
for people that change
their lives.
>> Music for me,
it's like everything.
It's really special.
This amazing feeling that
music gives me, I want everyone
to have that, even if
the person cannot hear.
So the idea of the app is to
introduce music for deaf people.
I am going to put these on
your wrist, so if you play,
you can feel the vibrations.
>> I can
feel it.
>> Did you feel
that, Rob?
My dream is to bring
music to everyone.
>> It is an amazing
time to be a developer.
We are still just at the
beginning of all this,
this moment where the technology
of an iPhone and an iPad
and the Watch enable so
many incredible things.
There's so much that can
still change and evolve due
to the power of applications.
[Music]
[Applause]
>> TIM COOK: On behalf
of everyone at Apple,
we want to thank the
developer community
for everything that you've done.
Thank you.
[Applause]
You have changed so many
parts of all of our lives
and transformed the
world in the process.
Now, we want to talk about
now the next opportunity
to transform the world.
And that's the opportunity to
bring native apps to the Watch
with a new version of watchOS.
[Applause]
For us, this is a giant moment.
This is how we felt when
we launched the App Store.
Opening a new platform
to developers
to create new applications
that can really change
people's lives.
We really believe
deeply in this space.
We believe in technology
designed for the wrist.
And we believe by
opening up the platform
that you will create
new and powerful uses
that today we can
only begin to imagine.
We began making the Apple Watch
available just six weeks ago,
and it's pretty amazing that
today we're already talking
about the next version
of the watchOS.
This new version will have
great new capabilities,
and it will bring native
apps right to your wrist.
To tell you all about it, I'd
like to invite up my friend
and colleague Kevin Lynch.
Kevin.
[Cheers and applause]
>> KEVIN
LYNCH: Hi.
So we're moving really fast on
watchOS, and I am super excited
to talk with you about the
enhancements that are coming
in watchOS, as well
as the powerful new
abilities for app development.
Let's start with
the enhancements.
The enhancements include
great new Timepiece functions,
improvements in communication
as well as in Health & Fitness,
and support for the
new capabilities
in Apple Pay, Maps, and Siri.
Let's start with Timepiece.
Now, already, Apple Watch
is a really great timepiece,
the most customizable one in the
world, and a lot of that is due
to the Watch faces and
how you can change them.
We are adding some new
Watch faces in watchOS 2.
That includes a beautiful
new Photos face to be able
to select any photo you have and
create a Watch face out of it.
You can create more than one and
switch between them as you like.
Or you can select a photo album,
and every time you
raise your wrist,
you will see a different
photo from your album show up.
It's a great way of seeing
your photos throughout the day.
We went a little
further with this,
and we shot some
photos ourselves.
We did some time-lapse
photography
in some beautiful
locations around the world.
The way this works is
when you raise your wrist,
you will see this
24-hour shoot we have done
in different locations, and it
will be the current time there.
If it's in noon, you
will see noon in London.
If it's night, you'll
see Big Ben all lit up.
We've done this not
only for London,
but some other locations too.
You can choose from
Hong Kong, Mack Lake --
which a beautiful
place in the Sierras --
as well as New York,
Shanghai, and London.
It's a great way to see really
beautiful imagery, both your own
and these time-lapse
images, on your wrist.
You can customize your
Watch with these images
but you can also choose to
show the information that you
like on your Watch
face with something
in traditional Watch terms
that's called Complications.
With watchOS 2, we are really
excited to enable app developers
to make your own Complications.
[Applause]
So be able to do things
like show your flight time
from United, see the state
of your home control system,
look at the charge level
of your electric car,
or see sports scores, for
example, from the MLB app.
You can choose the
information that you most
like to see right
on your Watch face.
It's going to be
really, really cool.
And this will work not
only on the modular face
but across the others that
support Complications as well.
You will be able to choose
from a variety of templates,
and we'll make those
look beautiful in each
of the different Watch faces.
So it's going to be
a really fast way
to look at this information.
Now, we went further than this.
We thought it's really
great to be able
to see the current information,
but what about future
information,
like the weather later
today or your meeting
after the current one?
And what if you could go
forward in time and actually see
that information update
on your Watch face?
Well, we are supporting
that in watchOS 2
with something we
call Time Travel.
And you will be able to
rotate your Digital Crown,
and you can go both forward
and backward through time,
and the information will
update right on your screen.
Let's take a look here.
So I've got my meeting in
the middle there and weather
and the charge level of
the car and time in London.
When I rotate the Crown, you
can see it's changing the time
and showing me things
that are coming up.
Now, we know a really popular
one here might be the stocks
Complication, but we
haven't cracked that one yet.
We are working on it.
You can keep rotating,
keep going forward,
get all the way to tonight.
You can see I have a date
night tonight, weather is going
to be good, time in London will
be 2:00 a.m. You can see all the
information you like to see in
the time you want to look at it.
Really, really fun
way to interact
with time on your Watch.
That's Time Travel.
[Applause]
Now, we also thought, What
would be a great experience
for the Watch when it's on
your nightstand and charging?
Well, we've come up with a
new user interface for this
in watchOS 2 called
Nightstand Mode.
When you put your Watch on
its side and it's charging,
you will get this beautiful
display now of the time,
and of course, you can set
an alarm that will wake you
up in the morning, and it
will go something like this.
[Alarm tone]
So a beautiful little
bedside alarm clock now
with Apple Watch, and
the buttons on the side
and the Crown act as your
Snooze and your Off button.
A really fun way to have a
Nightstand view on your Watch.
Those are some of the great
new Timepiece functions
that are coming in watchOS 2.
Let's look at communication.
Now, already Apple
Watch is great
at communicating
with your friends.
You can just press the side
button and see your 12 friends
that you have selected.
Now, we realize that some of
you have more than 12 friends,
so now in watchOS 2, you
can have different sets
of friends you can select,
and you can add a friend right
from your Watch by
pressing the plus sign
and add a friend right there.
Isn't that cool?
[Applause]
Now, when you are
communicating with someone,
you can make a phone call or
send a message or send a drawing
with Digital Touch, and now
in watchOS 2, you will be able
to use multiple colors
in your drawings,
so you can draw a
beautiful flower
that has more than
just one color.
Even my drawings are starting
to look better now with this.
Also an email.
You can already read
email on your Watch.
With watchOS 2, you will
be able to reply to email.
[Applause]
And with the phone, you can
already take phone calls
on your Watch.
We are now going to
support FaceTime Audio,
so you will get really
high-fidelity calls right
on your wrist.
[Applause]
And with Health & Fitness,
already Apple Watch is a great
partner for Health & Fitness.
With watchOS 2, we are enabling
your favorite fitness apps
to run natively on the Watch
so you can use them wherever
you are, and your workouts
with these apps will
contribute directly
to your all-day activity,
which will be really great,
so if you go on a bike
ride, it will count.
[Applause]
We are also enabling
Siri to start workouts,
so you can just raise your
wrist and say, hey, Siri,
start a 30-minute
run in the park,
and it will start the Workout
app and get it going for you.
You can also say things like
"go for a 300-calorie bike ride"
or "go for a 5-mile run, "
and it will start the workout
for you without having to
touch the watch at all.
When you achieve something,
there are some beautiful new
achievements you will see
that look like this.
They spin right in, they're
beautiful, you can play
with them in 3D on the
Watch, they are engraved
on the back now with your
name, and you can share these
with people over Messages,
Facebook, or Twitter.
Really cool Health &
Fitness.
[Applause]
With Apple Pay, you saw some
of the great new
support we are bringing
for store cards and
rewards cards.
We are supporting
that in the Watch,
so you can select a store card
and use it right in your Watch
in a merchant terminal
just by waving it
at the store stand there.
And with Wallet coming to Watch,
all of your rewards cards
will be right there,
and you can also use those
right from your Watch
as you are doing purchases.
With Transit, we are
supporting, of course,
the mass transit capabilities
in Maps now, so you will be able
to see the transit
lines on your wrist.
You can actually see
the departure times
for different stations
you are near.
When you are navigating, you
will get step-by-step directions
about getting through the
different mass transit you use.
With Siri, we are continuing
to add new domains for Siri.
In watchOS 2, we
are enabling Siri
to get you mass transit
directions, like bus directions
to the Ferry Building,
which will look like this
and you can just
start navigating.
Or you can control things
in your home with Siri,
you can say things like "hey
Siri set the dinner scene,"
and it will talk to any
HomeKit-enabled devices
in your house and set the
lights just how you want them.
Isn't that cool?
It's going to be great.
[Applause]
Another great thing is you
can actually ask for any
of the Glances you have,
so you can say "hey, Siri,
show me the Instagram
Glance," and it will show
up right on your Watch face.
This could be a glance you
don't have currently selected.
It's a great way
to show information
from third-party apps
right there in Siri.
So those are just
some of the highlights
of what's coming in watchOS 2.
We think it's going
to be a really,
really great update
to the Watch.
Now, that's not all.
[Applause]
We also, of course, focused on
what we can do for developers,
and already, out of the gate
on day one, you can build apps
for Apple Watch using
something called WatchKit,
and that has enabled many
thousands of apps now
to be created for Apple Watch,
and these apps today function
by relying on your phone.
So you might have, for
example, an app on your Watch
and the user interface
runs on your phone
and the user interface is on
your Watch, but all the logic
for your app today
runs on your phone.
With native apps, you will
be able to move that logic
to the watch so both the
UI and the logic are there,
it will all run locally,
performance will be great,
responsiveness will be great,
it's going to be a great new
frontier for apps on Apple Watch
with native app support.
[Applause]
When you are actually wandering
away from your phone sometimes,
your apps will be able
to communicate directly
with the network with
known Wi-Fi networks,
so you can get the information
you want wherever you are
with your Watch.
[Applause]
So we heard from you as we
were working on native apps,
a lot of feature requests
of things you would
like to do on the Watch.
These are a bunch of the
things that we've heard.
So we've been listening to that.
Let's go through
some of the things
that will be possible
now in watchOS 2.
You can see how we did on this.
So one of the things we
heard was really wanted
to access the microphone
on the Watch.
So yes, in watchOS 2, you can
access the microphone right
on the Watch and bring that
audio right into your app.
[Applause]
We also heard you want to
play audio out of the speaker.
You can do that.
WatchOS 2 with native
apps, you can play back
through the Watch speaker
or you can play audio
to a Bluetooth headset
or speaker connected,
both short-form and
long-form audio.
Video. We know you
wanted to play video.
You can play back short-form
video right on the Watch face.
It looks beautiful
on the Watch display.
Access to HealthKit.
We definitely heard that.
You now will have access,
native HealthKit on the watch,
including streaming heart rate
data, so if you are doing,
for example, a bike
ride with Strava,
you can see what heart rate zone
you are in while you are biking.
[Applause]
HomeKit is natively on the Watch
so you will be able to talk
to your HomeKit devices from
your Watch and control them.
We think this is going
to be a great future
for control right
from your wrist.
You will be able to
access the Accelerometer
so you can get movement data.
So for example, from the iPING
golf app here, you can check
out your golf swing tempo
as you are swinging the golf
club with your Watch on.
Taptic Engine is one of the
things we've really done a lot
of focused work on to make it a
great experience on the wrist.
We are bringing access to
the Taptic Engine for you
for your app development.
You will be able to choose from
a range of different feelings
as well as audio that
will come out the speaker.
So for example, if I am
unlocking my car here,
I will get feedback on my
wrist, both audio and felt.
Just like that.
Another great interaction on the
Watch is using the Digital Crown
to manipulate the UI, and we are
enabling access to Digital Crown
as well with watchOS 2.
You will be able to
control custom UI element
like changing the
temperature here just
by rotating the Crown like this.
Super easy way to
interact with your Watch.
[Applause]
So we've done a great job
bringing a lot of access
to the Watch now
with native apps.
I would like to show you a
demo now with some examples.
[Applause]
So I've got a Watch here,
and I am going to put it on.
It's connected to the display
here through this little cable.
All right.
Let's start by looking at
three examples of new features
in watchOS 2, then I
will show you three apps.
Let's start with
making a photo face,
so I will press my Digital Crown
here, go to the Home screen.
There's my Photos.
You can see I've got a
bunch of photos on here.
I can zoom in with
the Crown, pan around,
and I can pick a photo
that might make a nice
Watch face like that one.
I want to zoom in and
crop it a little more.
I am going to zoom in a
little more, move it over like
that to get it just right.
I think that's going to
make a great Watch face,
so I just Force Touch,
choose Create Watch Face,
and there you go, a
beautiful new Watch face.
[Applause]
Let's look at Time Travel.
I will go over to
my modular face,
got some more information here.
I have flight times
here on United.
I can see the temperature,
my VW car's charge
level, and time in London.
So I just rotate the Crown
here, I can go forward in time.
Time is updating.
My flight is leaving,
you can see, at 1:45.
I wonder if my charge level will
be enough to get to the airport.
So if I keep going forward in
time here, we will get to 1:45,
and you can see my charge
level is just going to be great
to get to the airport.
In fact, you can keep going
and look at boarding time
and arrival time
for your flight.
So you can get a great
preview of your day just
by rotating the Crown
right on the Watch face.
It's a lot of fun.
Just press the Crown
and go back to Home.
If you get an email, you can
reply to email now in watchOS 2.
Here is an email that's
just come in from Marc.
I can reply to this by pressing
the button right below the
message, or you can
use Siri to reply
to a message right
from a notification.
If I just use Siri here,
I can reply like this.
Reply: I would love to.
So Siri is making
the message there.
It's created a response.
I just press Send, and
it now goes off to Marc.
So just by pressing the
Crown, you can use Siri
to send a message
right from your wrist.
Now, let's look at a
few third-party apps.
Let's look at the VW app you
saw on slides a second ago.
I will show you how that works.
Here it is.
Now, I can lock my car just
by pressing this
control right here.
It responds right away.
You can see the app also
opened very quickly.
And I can control
the temperature here
that we were looking at before
by just rotating the Crown.
You can see how responsive
it is as I go up and down
through temperatures here.
Really, really cool.
I will get it nice and warm for
me so when I get down there,
it will be nice and toasty.
Okay. Turn it on.
All right.
I've got confirmation
that it actually enabled
that on my car now.
Access to the mic is going
to be really helpful in apps,
and some of the apps that will
really benefit are communication
apps like We Chat.
A lot of messages sent via
WeChat are audio messages,
so let's see how that
will work with watchOS 2.
I have a message from Becky.
I can reply by pressing
the Reply button,
and you can see I've
got a microphone now
so I can do an audio response.
Let's do that.
That sounds great.
You can see as I was recording
it, it got the audio levels
of my voice and now
it sent that to Becky.
I can also reply
with stickers here.
There's different
categories of them.
With the Digital Crown now
being able to connect to the UI,
I can flip through recent
stickers, pick one quickly
that I like, and just
send that one as well.
So very fast to interact now
with all these new controls you
have available in watchOS 2.
Now, let's look at
the Vine glance.
Vine is a great example of
playing back video on the Watch,
and its format is really
perfect for the Watch face.
Here is a recent one on Vine.
So that's video playing back
right on the Watch face.
So those are just some
examples of what you can do now
with watchOS 2, and
I am super excited
to see what all you guys
do with all this stuff.
[Applause]
So some great new
enhancements coming,
as well as some super powerful
app development tools for you.
And we've been working
really hard on this,
and I am really happy to say
that this stuff is all available
to you today to start
building these native apps.
[Applause]
Just six weeks from our
launch, it's unbelievable.
Then it will be available
in the fall to everyone,
and we will work
across all the watches,
of course, and it will be free.
So this has been
a great adventure.
We are just getting
started here,
and I am really looking forward
to the journey ahead with all
of you on Apple Watch.
Thank you very much.
Back to Tim.
[Applause]
Thank you, Tim.
>> TIM COOK: Thanks,
Kevin.
We're really excited to have
Apple Watch out in the world,
and we can't wait to see
what you do with watchOS.
And we couldn't be more
excited about how developers
and users will use the powerful
ecosystems of both products
and platforms, three
amazing platforms.
The opportunities
really are limitless.
Now, before we close this
morning, we do have ...
one more thing.
[Cheers and applause]
I'd like to tell
you about something
that we've been working
really hard on
and something we are
super excited about.
You know, we love music, and
music is such an important part
of our lives and our culture.
We've had a long relationship
with music at Apple,
and music has had a very
rich history of change,
some of which we've
played a part in.
We've made a great video
about the history of music,
and I would like to play
it for you this morning.
[Music]
[Cheers and applause]
>> TIM COOK: Today we're
announcing Apple Music,
the next chapter in music, and
I know you are going to love it.
It will change the way that
you experience music forever.
To tell you more about it,
I'd like to bring up someone
who knows more about music
and the music experience
than anyone I know.
He's worked with amazing
artists from Bruce Springsteen
to John Lennon and
countless others.
We are thrilled to have him
a part of the Apple team.
Please join me in
welcoming Jimmy Iovine.
Jimmy.
[Cheers and applause]
>> JIMMY IOVINE:
Thanks, Tim.
Well, it's really
an honor to be here.
I'm here because in 2003,
the record industry was
a ball of confusion.
We had Napster, we had
LimeWire, we had BitTorrent.
This giant invader from
the north, technology.
I'm looking at my guys saying,
well, what do we do with this?
So I go up to Apple, and I
see Steve Jobs and Eddy Cue,
and they showed me something
brilliant and groundbreaking,
a simple, elegant way to
buy music online, iTunes.
I'm like, wow, the ads are real.
These guys really
do think different.
[Laughter] So they could help
move culture the same way
that art moves culture.
Technology and art can work
together, at least at Apple.
So now 2015, music industry
is a fragmented mess.
If you want to stream
music, you can go over here.
some video,
you can check some
of these places out.
If you want to follow
some artist,
there's more confusion for that.
So I reached out to Tim Cook
and Eddy Cue, and I said guys,
can we build a bigger and better
ecosystem with the elegance
and simplicity that
only Apple can do?
One complete thought
around music.
And from that, I'm
standing here today so proud
of everyone that's worked
so hard, and I am going
to introduce you to Apple Music.
[Applause]
>> Music has such
power in our lives.
The way we listen to
and experience music is
undergoing a profound change
these days.
To have access to nearly
all the music in the world
at our fingertips and in
our pockets is remarkable.
And yet there needs
to be a place
where music can be treated
less like digital bits
and more like the art it is,
with a sense of respect
and discovery.
And if that place could
actually accommodate
and support the artists
who make the music,
not just the top-tier artists,
but the kids in their
bedrooms too, provide them all
with a home and a way to
engage with their audiences,
that would be pretty great.
And that's what we set out
to do with Apple Music.
[Music]
>> On Apple Music, all the
ways you love music can now
live together.
Stream from the millions
of songs on iTunes any time
and on demand, along with
hand-picked playlists,
recommendations,
and all that's great
and breaking in music right now.
And broadcasting every day is
Apple's first 24/7 worldwide
radio station, live
in over 100 countries,
Beats 1 is anchored
by Zane Lowe in LA.
Ero Dodden in New York.
>> New York City
worldwide, this is Beats 1.
>> And me, Julie out of
London.
>> We cannot wait to play you
guys music we've got lined up.
>> And at the heart of Apple
Music, there's Connect,
where artists can share
with fans like never before.
Songs, remixes, demos,
mix tapes, photos,
videos, lyrics, soundbites.
Really, any way an artist
chooses to express themselves.
>> TRENT REZNOR:
For fans,
we tried to create a
complete experience,
by combining the catalog
of the world's music
with the music that's
not in that catalog yet,
direct from the artist to you
in a shared experience
with Beats 1.
For the artists, we've built
an ecosystem we hope can start
to provide the tools to grow,
nurture, and sustain careers.
One place, one complete
thought around music.
[Music]
[Cheers and applause]
>> JIMMY IOVINE:
Thank you.
That's Apple Music and
the great Trent Reznor.
It's all the ways you love
music all in one place.
And that place is
almost in a billion hands
around the world already.
One app, one single
app on your iPhone.
Apple Music is three things.
It's a revolutionary
music service.
Oh. A revolutionary
music service curated
by the leading music experts
who we helped hand-pick.
These people are
going to help you
with the most difficult
question in music.
When you are listening to a
playlist, what song comes next?
The only song that's
as important
as the one you are
listening to at
that moment is the
one that follows it.
Now, picture this.
You are in a special moment.
You're exercising or some
other special moment.
[Laughter] Right, Dre?
He exercises a lot.
And your heart's pumping.
And you are about
to turn up the reps.
And the next song
comes on, ehhh!
Buzz kill.
You may ask why that happened.
It happened because it
was probably programmed
by an algorithm alone.
Algorithms alone can't
do that emotional task.
You need a human touch, and
that's why at Apple Music,
we want to give you the right
song, the right playlist,
at the right moment,
all on demand.
Now, the first-ever live
24-hour worldwide radio station,
so Trent Reznor calls
me up and says I got it.
This is what we're going to do.
Let's build the first-ever
worldwide live radio station
broadcast from three cities
that plays music not based
on research, not based on
genre, not based on drum beats,
only music that is
great and feels great.
A station that has only
one master, music itself.
So I said why do artists
always have the greatest ideas
that are practically
impossible to execute?
So I said, well, wait a second.
That's why we are at Apple.
We are at Apple to help
artists' dreams be realized.
So we built the station, and
it's a music lover's dream.
If you love great music without
any restrictions, you are going
to love Apple Music's Beats 1.
Finally, Connect, a fantastic
way for established and new
and even unsigned artists
to connect directly
with music lovers anywhere.
This is going to be very
powerful for musicians.
Can you imagine being
an up-and-coming artist
and being able to
share your music
on the biggest music
platform on the world
that people already
have, Apple Music?
Remember, this is an ecosystem.
It's built to fit together.
It feeds off each other.
When you upload your music
to Apple Music, anything
can happen.
So now let me leave
the real heavy lifting
to my great friend, Eddy Cue,
and tell you how this
all works together.
[Cheers and applause]
>> EDDY CUE: Thank you,
Jimmy.
It's great to be here
this morning with you.
So Apple Music, it's a
revolutionary music service,
and it starts with My Music.
We've added some great new
features from iTunes like the
Up Next queue, and also
your recently added albums
and songs right across the top.
And all of the music
you've purchased,
along with the playlists
you've created on your Mac
or your iPhone, are right here.
Now, of course, you can
search your music library,
but now you can search and
stream the millions and millions
of songs that we have on iTunes.
Now, in addition to My Music,
when you can stream and listen
to any song you want, you
need a great place to start,
and that's why we've
created For You.
For You recommends
playlists and albums
that we think you
are going to love.
They are personalized
to your taste based
on the music you listen
to, the artists you love.
And it isn't just algorithms.
It's recommendations made by
real people who love music,
and they are our
team of experts.
Now, let's take a look at New.
Here you will discover new
artists and albums every week,
along with the top charts, and
every one of our playlists,
all human-curated, available
by genre or by activity.
So when you think
of Apple Music,
it's My Music, For You and New.
It makes it fun and easy
to experience the catalog
of the world's music.
And that is the revolutionary
music service.
Now let's talk about Radio.
The truth is Internet
radio isn't really radio.
It's just a playlist of songs.
And so we wanted to do
something really big.
We wanted to create a worldwide
live radio station broadcasting
around the globe, and we've
done that with Beats 1.
It's the world's best radio
station now meets the world's
best voice, and that's
why we've hired Zane Lowe.
Zane is a masterful interviewer
and an influential music figure
in his own right, and to tell
you more about it, here is Zane.
>> ZANE LOWE: I am a
music fan.
I play records.
What I love is watching
a group of people react
to a great record
for the first time.
When I play that record on the
radio, the audience tell me,
the time lines light up,
my friends tell me,
my phone lights up.
They love it or they hate it.
But it creates a debate.
That's what good music
on the radio does.
When Apple first asked me to be
involved in this, they told us
to put the great music in front
of the average, the unexpected,
the undiscovered, the
anticipated, the underrated.
Their words: Move the needle.
And that's what we are doing.
We have real music fans
running this place.
We have great music DJs and
incredible artists who are
in the studio right now
building real radio shows
that are going to
blow your mind.
And the only place that can
pull off an imaginative idea
as big as this -- Apple.
We are called Beats 1.
We are always on, playing
the music that we love.
[Applause]
>> EDDY CUE: So
Beats 1.
It is worldwide, it is live,
it is broadcasting 24 by 7,
and it is coming
from New York, LA,
and London, and that is Radio.
Next, we wanted to find a
way to bring fans closer
to the artists they love,
and we call it Connect.
It's a place where artists are
free to upload their music,
their videos, their photos,
all directly to a fan.
Let's take Pharrell, a favorite
musician and songwriter of mine.
He is prolific, and
he does a lot.
Let me show you how
it works with Connect.
He takes a lot of photos.
He writes a lot of lyrics.
He's experimenting and
mixing songs all the time.
Or he just has something
new and interesting to say.
All of this lives
right in Connect.
Artists can post and
publish and upload anything,
including directly to Facebook,
Twitter, and their own website,
and fans can like and
comment on those posts.
And it's not just for one
artist, but it's for all
of the artists that you love.
And to give you a
little sense of what it's
like to be an artist on Connect,
I'd like to invite
up a friend, Drake.
[Cheers and applause]
>> DRAKE:
Thank you.
I want to say, honestly, what an
honor it is to be in this room
with so many individuals
that have changed the way
in which the world
relates to technology,
so give yourselves a
round of applause, please.
[Applause]
For example, I bought this
vintage Apple employee's jacket
using a tool known in the
rap world as the Internet.
It's going to be huge this year.
It's out of this world.
He is excited, he knows about
it, that guy right there.
[Laughter] Honestly, in all
seriousness, I came here today
to share my story, about the
way technology changed what I do
for a living.
I am from Toronto, Canada.
[Cheers and applause]
[Laughter]
You know, as a kid growing up,
I always wondered if my city
or even my country would
have somebody break
into the global music
scene as a true superstar.
You know, the dream seemed
unattainable at the time.
Even myself, I tried to
do it the traditional way,
the towering New York label
buildings, the lobby littered
with other people's
accomplishments.
It's improbable to think that
every talented artist is going
to get a shot to have
their vision validated.
And then that's when
the game changed.
And we had to change it.
Myself and my team
brought our vision
and our music directly
to the people.
And that was kind of the first
time that we really got noticed.
The dream of being a new artist
like myself five years ago
and connecting directly with
an audience has never been more
close and reachable
than right now.
See, now we encourage you to
spend the time on your body
of work, spend the time on your
craft, assemble the right body
of work, and instead of
having to post your stuff
on all these different and
sometimes confusing places,
it all lives in one very simple,
very easy place,
and that is Connect.
It's right from where
you are in your city
in front of your computer.
And this approach is
how we broke in 2008,
and it has been perfected
and simplified, of course,
by the great people at Apple.
So you know, as I'm working
tirelessly on this next album,
this comes at the
perfect time for me.
Given the great success of my
last mix tape that went directly
to iTunes, this really --
I can't wait to incorporate
Apple Music
and especially Connect
into what I am doing next.
I am really excited about
what I am working on.
And as an artist, I can say for
all those kids sitting at home,
it's truly amazing to be part
of something that I believe in,
and this is something
that simplifies everything
for the modern musician
like myself
and the modern music
consumer like you.
So I hope you enjoy Apple Music.
I hope you enjoy Connect.
My name is Drake, and
thank you for your time.
Appreciate it.
[Cheers and applause]
>> EDDY CUE: Thank you,
Drake.
And that is Connect.
Now, I'd love to give you
a demo of Apple Music,
but before I start, I do want
to wish Phil Schiller
a happy birthday.
[Cheers and applause]
So let's go ahead and
launch our new Music app.
You will notice right away
it's got a brand-new UI,
much simpler to use.
Your recently added albums and
songs right across the top.
Let's play this new
song from Spoon I added.
[Music]
One of the things
you will notice,
we have a new mini
player across the bottom
that always shows
you what's playing.
If I tap on it, I
get full screen,
and I can see the
beautiful artwork,
all the playback controls.
I can just swipe down,
and it disappears.
Now, I like looking
at my music by artist.
It's really easy to do that too.
I will just tap on
Albums, switch to Artists,
and let's take a look
at Aretha Franklin.
The first thing you will notice
is we add beautiful artwork
to all the artist pages.
Notice as I swipe
up, it goes away,
and you see Aretha at the top.
No demo goes complete
without playing this song.
[Music]
Now, you not only get all of
your Aretha Franklin songs
in your music library, but
you can also tap on All,
and now you can see all of
the songs on Apple Music,
including the latest
release, what the top song is,
what the top album is.
Now, it is hard to stop this
song, but I want to keep going.
Now let's go back to my library,
and let's take a
look at my playlists.
Now, despite the game last
night, I am getting ready
for tomorrow night, and I
have already started creating
my playlist.
One of the first things you will
notice is you can add your own
artwork to your playlist.
I am going to be
doing this tonight,
getting the Warriors
ready, but let's go back.
It is karaoke night, and
these are some of the songs
that our team has to
look forward to tonight.
Let's go ahead and play that.
[Music]
Just imagine.
Now, if I tap on
the mini player,
I can see the full screen.
If I tap on the right-hand side
next to the playback controls,
I can see the complete
playlist, and it's very easy
for me to reorganize it.
Let's say I want to
move Jealous back up,
and now that will be the
next song that plays.
It's that simple.
[Applause]
Now, that's great.
The first time we go to For You,
we want to find out a little bit
about your musical
tastes, so we are going
to ask you what genres you like.
I am a big fan of rock, pop,
hip-hop, and alternative.
And now it will ask me for
some artists that I like.
Well, I love Bruce Springsteen,
so I am going to tap twice.
I like Lorde, like
Alabama Shakes.
Now we are going to take all
of this information you've
provided, along with all
of your playlists and the songs
that you've purchased on iTunes,
and we are going to make
recommendations just for you.
So here is one inspired
by Bruce Springsteen.
Here's one called
Bring the Big Rock.
Let's play that.
[Music]
That's a great Foo
Fighters song.
I can just tap and see
the rest of the songs.
Definitely going to
like this playlist.
Now, here's another
one from Pharrell.
I also get new albums
that are available to me,
and even some classic albums
that I should be listening to.
And so here are some
brand-new albums
from the artists
that I really love.
Now, here is an interesting
one, a Cuban playlist.
You might be wondering
how did that get in there?
Well, I like a lot of Latin
music, so Apple Music knows that
and is recommending
this playlist to me.
Let's take a look at it.
[Music]
Definitely gets my
Cuban blood going.
[Music]
Now, this is a playlist I
definitely want to keep,
so I am going to tap on the
plus sign, and I've added
that now to my playlist.
Now, let's take a
look at what's new.
You can see new albums
across the top.
More here, and even the
hot singles that are out.
Let's play this one from
Florence and the Machine.
[Music]
I can keep scrolling and
see some recent releases.
But of course, everyone loves
the charts, so let's go ahead
and take a look at the
charts, see the top songs.
The top albums.
And even the top music videos.
We have tens of thousands of
music videos in HD, all ad-free.
Let's take a look at this
one from Mark Ronson.
[Music]
I've got to work on some of
those moves for next year.
[Laughter] Now, sometimes
you just want to sit back
and let someone else be your
DJ, so let's go to Radio.
And to give you a little taste
of what Beats 1 is
going to sound like ...
>>
Beats 1.
Welcome our special guest,
Florence from Florence
and the Machine.
>> On paper, it sounds like
super, not how you think a rock
and roll album would be made.
>> Was that you in
your sweatpants?
>> That was me in an anorak
cycling to the studio.
>> We are looking for the
most exciting music and people
that love it in all
corners of the globe,
broadcasting to 100 countries.
That shared experience
just got so much bigger.
&gt;&gt
LA.
>> New York
City.
>>
London.
>> EDDY CUE: That's
really awesome.
Let's take a look at Connect
and see what my favorite
artists are up to.
Here's Pharrell and some
behind-the-scenes footage.
Here is Chris Cornell.
This is an interesting one.
He has posted lyrics of a new
song that's coming out before,
obviously, he's even
recorded it.
Here's Bastille.
They are working on
their next album.
Let's see what they have to say.
>> Mark is just through
here, and we are working
on a song called Blame, which
some of you might have heard
at festivals or gigs before,
but we're really excited to
have finally recorded it.
It's a song about gangsters.
And yeah, this is the riff,
which we already
have sounding great.
[Music]
>> EDDY CUE: It's great to be
able to get behind the scenes
and see what the process that
an artist uses to create a song.
As we keep going
down, here's a shot
from Alabama Shakes
a couple nights ago.
And here is a studio session,
actually, at Capital Studio A.
Those of you who know,
Capitol Studio is one
of the premier studios,
historical,
and Alabama Shakes was just
there a couple nights ago.
[Music]
>> EDDY CUE: Again,
be able
to see things you've never
been able to hear or see.
Loren Kramar, you probably
have never heard of him.
He is an unsigned artist, I
just started following him.
He has posted a new song
right up on Connect,
and I would love to play it now.
First time anyone's heard it.
[Music]
Just imagine you
are a new artist,
and look at all the
people who have been able
to hear this song right
now thanks to Connect.
[Music]
So Loren Kramar.
Remember that name.
We think he is going to
be really, really huge.
Now, of course, you can always
search for music across all
of our millions and
millions of songs.
I like to do a little
bit of stuff with Siri
because Siri has been learning
a lot more about music.
Play Born to Run.
[Music]
It's one of my favorite
songs of all time.
Let's get a little
more specific.
Play the top ten
songs in Alternative.
[Music]
If I tap on the Up Next
queue, I can see all
of the top ten songs
and what's next.
Now, I feel like reminiscing
a little, and let's go back
to my high school
days when I graduated.
Play the top song from May 1982.
[Music]
Now, that brings back some
memories, but we will leave
that for another time.
Have you ever gone to a movie
and you love the soundtrack
or the song that was on there,
but you don't know the name
or you have forgotten
about it later?
Well, it's really
easy with Siri.
Play the song from Selma.
[Music]
Let's do that again.
Play the song from Selma.
[Music]
And that is Siri, and
that is Apple Music.
[Cheers and applause]
It is a revolutionary
music service
with recommendations
just for you,
a worldwide live radio station
with the world's best DJs,
an exciting way for fans
to connect with artists,
and of course, this is joined
by the iTunes Music Store,
the best place to buy music.
Apple Music is all of
the ways you love music,
all in one place.
We are launching in over a
hundred countries later this
month with iOS 8.4 for your
iPhone, iPod touch, and iPad,
as well as a new version
of iTunes for the Mac,
a new version of
iTunes for Windows,
and Android is coming this fall.
[Cheers and applause]
Apple Music will be just $9.99
a month, the cost of an album.
We want everyone to try it,
so we are making the
first three months free.
[Applause]
Now, we want to do something
really great for families.
Today you have to buy
a music subscription
for each and every person.
Or you share an account even
though you are not supposed to.
And now all of you can't
play at the same time,
and your playlists
and recommendations
get all messed up.
Well, with Apple Music, for
just $14.99, you can have
up to six family members.
[Applause]
Everyone gets their own
account, their own library,
their own recommendations.
It's an incredible value.
And that is Apple Music.
Thank you.
Turn it back to Tim.
[Cheers and applause]
>> TIM COOK:
Thanks, Eddy.
Isn't that amazing?
We really love Apple Music,
and we hope that you do too.
And we are so excited about it,
and with all the countries
we are rolling out to,
we made a great ad to
tell the world about it.
And I'd love to run
it for you now.
>> This is Zane Lowe of
Beats 1.
We've got the whole world
locked in for this one.
Brand-new Pharrell.
[Music]
[Cheers and applause]
Now, music connects with us all
at such a deep, emotional level.
We couldn't be happier
to launch Apple Music,
and we can't wait till
you start listening to it
at the end of the month.
This has been a jam-packed
morning.
I hope you've enjoyed
it as much as we have.
We want to thank
everybody for joining us,
especially the developers,
and I'd like to recognize all
of the people in Apple, all
of our team that have worked
so hard on making
and creating all
of these products
you've seen this morning.
Thank you, guys.
[Applause]
It is an incredible privilege
of a lifetime to work with them.
Now, I've got one last thing.
Before we go, it's only
fitting to celebrate the launch
of Apple Music with an
incredible music performance
by one of the hottest new
artists in music today,
and it's not only a hot
new artist, but he's going
to do a worldwide premiere of
his newest song this morning.
Please give it up
for The Weeknd.
[Cheers and applause]
[ Background Sounds ]
[Music]
[Cheers and applause]
>> TIM COOK: Ladies and
gentlemen, The Weeknd!
[Cheers and applause]
Everybody have a great week!
It's great to be together!
[Cheers and applause]