[ Applause ]
>> Good morning and welcome.
My name is Filip.
I'm the opening act for
Bill Nye the Science Guy.
[ Laughter ]
Just kidding.
I lead the mobile apps
engineering team at Apple
and we build iOS apps
just like you guys.
Our apps get built and
submitted to the App Store.
They get approved and they
get downloaded by users
and they can get deleted too.
Of all the teams at Apple
and of all the teams
that have presented to
you at WWDC this week,
we're the most like you guys.
What we'd like to share with you
today is some situations we come
across in developing our apps.
These situations have
given rise to opportunities
where we could harness
some key iOS technologies
and create truly unique
and compelling experiences
for our users.
I'm going to show you the
features that we built
and the technologies
behind them.
As I talk about our apps,
I want you guys to think
about your own apps and
find some parallels.
And I know you can
identify with a lot
of the opportunities
we'll see today
and use these technologies
in your own apps.
We'll talk also about tips,
tricks, and best practices.
And finally, we'll end
with a demo on iBeacons.
So let's get started.
First, I'd like to
introduce the Apple Store app.
It's going to be the reference
app for this presentation.
This is an app my team builds
and you can download it
from the App Store anytime,
maybe even right now.
Let me see, who has
the app on their phone?
Oh wow, good.
Who doesn't have it?
Who is downloading right now?
[ Laughter ]
A lot of you don't
put up your hand.
Maybe you're shy.
If you're shy, you can come
on the stage with me in front
of all of you, you'll lose
your shyness very fast.
OK. So, Apple Store app
is a great way to learn
about Apple products, to
browse Apple products.
You can customize and buy.
You can also find out
about Apple retail stores,
what events are going on,
maybe book an appointment
like Genius Bar or pick
up an order you made
on the Apple Store
app at the store.
And it's this key characteristic
of the Apple Store app,
this integration with the
physical Apple Stores,
and this by the way is the Upper
West Side Store in New York.
It's going to be our
reference store for the talk.
This intersection between the
online with the Apple Store app
and the physical with the Apple
retail store gives rise to a lot
of the opportunities
we'll talk about today.
When I talk about our app in
the store, I'd like you to think
about your own situations.
So, maybe you have a
Movie app and you want
to think about movie theaters.
Maybe you have Dinner
Reservation app and you want
to think about restaurants.
Maybe you have a Travel app, you
want to think about airports.
Amusement Park app, you want--
or Museum app, you want to think
about museums and
amusement parks
or maybe your own Retail app
and your own retail stores.
For those of you who don't
have locations of interest
in your app, don't worry,
a lot of the technology we'll
talk today will still be
applicable for you guys.
So, this is my agenda
slide, it's a timeline.
And it all centers around--
and we're going to use this
timeline through the talk.
It all centers around the
fact that there's an event.
OK, it can be anything.
Dinner is on tonight.
There's a movie playing.
You're traveling
tomorrow to go on a trip.
You can even be in a game
like all the players are getting
together to play a game online.
Or it could be a sale or
a new product is launched.
So, there's this time
before the event,
what can we do in that time?
There's the event itself
when people are arriving
at your event, what
opportunities are there?
And finally, when
people are at your event
and they're spending time,
how can we enrich
the experience there?
Before we get fully started,
I want to mention the
technologies we're going to use.
We're going to start
pretty basic
and get a little more complex.
First of is Calendar Events.
Then we've got Push
Notifications,
then Core Location.
And a specific feature
of Core Location,
we call Region Monitoring.
This is also known
as Geofencing.
You might know it like that.
And finally, we're going to talk
about a new technology on iOS 7,
iBeacons and that's the
demo we'll show you.
OK. So, it's the time
before the event,
the event is coming
up, what do you do?
You tell your users about it.
To remind ourselves in the
timeline, we are now here,
right before the event.
So this is an event,
hopefully our users really care
about this.
They're excited.
When you told them about it,
they are looking forward to it.
What can you do in your apps
to keep that excitement alive
and what can you do to
remind them of the event?
I'll show you.
Through a feature in the Apple
Store app we called iPhone
upgrade notification.
Let me just set the scene.
I will have to guess that pretty
much all of you have an iPhone
or have access to an iPhone.
Those of you that have
bought it in the US,
you know that US carriers
like Sprint, AT&T, Verizon,
they subsidized the
cost of your phone
if you sign a contract
like two years.
When you want to
upgrade your phone,
depending on where you are in
that period, maybe at the end
of the two years, you get a
full discount again of 199
and the carrier will
subsidize that.
Maybe if you're midway through,
you get a partial
discount like 449.
And if you're early, maybe
you don't get a discount.
So, as a user, you might want to
get the iPhone at the best price
so you got to keep track
where you are in that contract
and when you're eligible
for that best price.
OK, so that's your event.
The event is the fact that
you can get this new product,
this iPhone at the best price.
OK, so you got to keep
track of that date
and the worse thing
is it's dynamic.
Carriers can change it.
They can pull in
the date, you know,
maybe to incentivize
you to buy early.
So what can we do in the Apple
Store app to remind users
of this event and make
this process even better?
This is the iPhone
page in our app.
You can learn about the iPhone.
You can choose the model and
the color and you can buy.
When you buy, we're going
to auto detect your carrier
and we're going to
tell you, "Hey,
we need to go query the
carrier on your behalf to find
out what your price is."
We take some info from you
that the carrier needs.
We're going to encrypt this and
we're going to send it securely.
And then, we're going
to come back
with the price for your phone.
In this case, you're eligible
for a partial discount
of 449 for the 16 gigabyte.
On April 15th, you can get
the full discount of 199
and that's all the
features used to be.
And it would be up to you
if you don't want to buy now
to come back later and go
through this process again.
Then we added Notify Me.
That's your way to say, "Hey,
Apple Store app, I don't care
about this to think
about this stuff.
You tell me when I'm eligible."
OK, we can do that.
The first way we did this
was through Calendar Events.
And we-- you tap there, we just
put an event on your calendar.
You don't have to
think about it anymore
and they'll be there for you.
Or remember, it's a dynamic date
and if the carrier
changes the date,
the Calendar Event is static.
So then we built it
using Push Notifications.
And so, if you swipe
that toggle to on,
we're going to do is we're
going to schedule a job
on our service side and query
the carrier on a regular basis
and in intelligent way and we'll
notify you the first moment
that you're eligible.
So then, on April 15th, maybe
the app is on the background,
your phone is on your pocket,
or whatever that date is,
you're going to get
something like this.
It's a push notification from
our app, "Hey, good news,
you can get the phone at
the best price right now."
You swipe in, we'll
take you to the app,
we'll show you the best price,
and you just tap to buy,
and it can ship to your house
or pick it up at the store.
And that's iPhone
upgrade notification.
So we've taken this
event, get this iPhone
and we've reminded users about
it and made the process easier.
So, we're going to talk about
the example then we talk
about the technology behind it.
First is Calendar Events.
This is simple to use
but pretty effective.
And I'm not going to
spend too much time here.
Pretty much all the
skeleton code is here.
Innermost block is where you
create the event and save it.
The outermost stuff is
little more interesting.
It handles the privacy alert.
Your app has to ask user
permission to use the calendar
and that code is going
to take care of that.
OK. Now, a little
more sophisticated,
Push Notifications.
This is the richer way to
inform users and it's dynamic.
You can have those dynamic
events 'cause your server is
going to decide when
to inform users.
It's pretty straightforward.
You register pushes-- you
register for Push with this API.
You then take the
Token with this API.
Now the token uniquely
represents your app
on this device.
Send that Token to the
server-side where you store it.
When your server decides,
"Hey, it's time to do a push,
the event is here," you send
the push to APNS via the Token
and then APNS, that's the Apple
Push Notifications Service,
they're going to target
that user by that Token.
They'll get an alert and
then if they swipe in,
your app will get woken up
and you're going to have
to handle this did receive
remote notification method.
And that's it, pretty
straightforward
but pretty powerful
way to inform users.
So we talk about the
technology behind the example.
Now, we'll do some tips, tricks,
and best practices
to use this stuff.
First one is the big no,
no and there's X over there
in case you're wondering.
And it's the red X.
And it's the only red X that
I have but it's very important
because of this kind of stuff.
How many of you can identify
what this, you know, "Hey,
you haven't used me in
two weeks or five days.
Please open me up."
Pretty annoying.
So, notify users of
events they care about,
only of events they care about.
'Cause if you don't, if you
bought at them like this,
they going to turn off,
pushes globally for your app
and you can't notify them again.
Or worse, you're going to
hold down on your app icon.
And your app icons
start jiggling.
You guys know why it
starts jiggling, right?
'Cause they're scared,
they're going to get deleted.
[ Laughter ]
[ Applause ]
And then they're going to
click that X and they're going
to delete it and never
to download it again.
So don't let it happen to you.
How do you do it?
It's so simple.
Provide an opt-in method.
Tell them or explain the value
of this feature and let them opt
in like we did with our toggle.
You might be scared, "Oh then
nobody is going to use it."
Believe me, if you explain
the value, people don't want
to think about these things.
They want to be reminded.
So, explain the value
and they'll opt
in then you know they want it.
Provide this with the
correct moment in the flow.
In our flow, remember, you
just checked your eligibility,
you gave us all the information
then we asked you to opt in.
It's a good time.
And provide some settings where
users can turn this on or off
and we'll talk more about
that in the next slide.
So do not spam.
Thank you.
OK. So, In-App Notification
settings, I'm not talking
about the settings app here,
I'm talking about settings
inside your own app.
For example, in the Apple
Store app, in our More tab,
we've got this notification
section.
You tap that, you're going
to see something like this.
This is all the notifications
we do.
The upgrade ones, we talk about
on top, then order status,
when does your order ship,
when is it delivering.
Reservations, when is your
Genius Bar reservation
coming up?
And then location-based
alerts which we'll talk
about in the next section
in Storefront Pickup.
So, this is great if
you have many types
of Push Notifications.
If you have only one,
maybe you don't need this.
But if you have many types, this
is a great way to handle it.
Why? Because it reduces
the chance
that a user will
completely turn off Push.
If they're annoyed by one
of this, they might turn
that one off and keep
the other ones on.
So, it's pretty obvious,
pretty simple,
a lot of people don't do it
but this will be the best way
to keep those pushes
that people want on.
OK. Also, consider the time
of day, very important.
So, don't send the push in
the middle of the night,
don't wake somebody up.
Don't disturb them.
Be polite basically.
This is also going
to feel like spamming
if you send it at
the wrong time.
So, consider the time of
day, consider when is best
to send this, and also,
think about time zones.
If you have a worldwide
app, you want to think
about time zones there
or even in the US,
you have multiple time zones.
One thing I recommend you
to do is create a Do Not Disturb
Time window on your server-side.
Maybe put it in your
Push Engine.
Users have the do not
disturb setting on their phone
but they might not use that
so you cannot rely on it.
So in this way, maybe in your
Push Engine, if there's a bug
or something and a request comes
in your push engine at 3 a.m.,
"Hey, send this push."
Your Push Engine can be inactive
and queue those requests
using some queuing system.
Then when it's time
to send pushes again,
the Push Engine becomes active
and it starts consuming
from the queue.
It's kind of a last
minute safety check
on your server-side.
Just the recommendation
we found pretty useful.
Final tip and trick I
wanted to talk about is
to be a good citizen and please
clean up the dead push tokens.
Users might wipe the phone,
they might delete your app,
they might turn off
pushes for your app
so then these tokens
are no longer valid.
OK? And you can send pushes
to them, nothing is going
to happen except you're going to
clog the system for valid pushes
and valid push tokens.
So please clean up.
Very easy, query the Apple Push
Notification Feedback Service
as there's where you'll
query it using SSL.
You'll get a list
of push tokens.
The list will be
cleared when you get it.
And then you parse the list
and just stop using them.
Usually that means
you delete them
on your data store or whatever.
So please, be a good citizen.
And that's it, that's the
time before the event.
And now, the events arrived,
it's here, it's today
and users are arriving.
What do you do?
Welcome them.
And in our timeline, we
are now at the event.
We're going to welcome
our users.
When I say welcome them,
I don't mean just roll
out the welcome mat.
I mean roll out the red carpet.
Make them feel like a star.
How do you do that?
I'll show you with the feature
we call Storefront Pickup.
No setting the scene now,
I'm just going straight
into this one.
Back to the Upper West Side
Apple Store and meet John.
John made an order with
the Apple Store app.
He's going to pick it up in
the Upper West Side store.
He wanted to pick
it up in the store.
When he made this order,
the Apple Store app created a
virtual perimeter, virtual fence
or region around the
Upper West Side store.
And we told iOS Core
Location, "Hey,
when John crosses this
region even if our app is
in the background or the phone
is in the pocket, wake us up,
we want to do something."
So when John crosses it,
Core Location detects that,
wakes us up, we take a
look if John has an order
and then we pop an alert.
And John sees this says "Hey
John, you're near the store,
there's an order for you here.
Do you want to pick it up?"
John says, "Yes."
And then we tell him, "OK,
one of our employees is
getting your order ready.
Just come on over."
And we send a signal to
the back of the house
where they start putting it
in a bag and getting it ready.
As John approaches
right on the front,
he's going to get
another notification.
And it's going to say, "Hey,
one of our employees, Hillary,
has your product, has your
order, and she wants to meet you
up at some location
like the entrance."
And right as John--
and so John swipes that
and goes into the app.
We'll show him a
picture of Hillary.
So, you know who she is
and can recognize her.
And then as John enters
right around the entrance,
Hillary will materialize.
More importantly, John's
[ Laughter ]
order will materialize, OK?
And it's there for John.
Now John didn't have
to go in line.
He didn't have to ask for help.
He didn't have to be bothered.
He was just coming to the store,
he got welcomed and he's there
for his important event to pick
up that phone he got
at the best price.
And there it is, that
Storefront Pickup.
So think about in
your-- thank you.
[ Applause ]
So, think about in your own
apps what you can do here.
Maybe you have a
restaurant, you can say, "Hey,
we've detected you've come
to the restaurant, welcome.
Go to the bar, we're going
to get your table ready."
And then we'll buzz you
when your table is ready
and your phone can
buzz them again.
You can eliminate those plastic,
you know those pager things
they have at the restaurant,
you can eliminate
that with your app.
So, pretty cool stuff
you can do with it.
You can welcome people to
the airport and say, "Hey,
you know-- " I don't
know if you've ever flown
from an airport like
SFO like on Friday
at 5 or 6, it's very bad."
So, you can tell him, "Hey,
here are the security lines
that are open and
here is the wait time
in each line," for example.
So, a lot of useful things
you can do with this.
What is the technology
behind this?
It's called Region Monitoring.
This is a feature
of Core Location.
You basically create regions,
latitude and longitude
and you give it a radius, right?
And then you call this API,
start monitoring for region
and then your app can
go in the background.
Core Location will monitor
in a very low power mode.
When Core Location detects
that you've crossed a boundary,
you're at the region,
you're then--
your app will wake
up and you're going
to handle these delegates
that it will call.
Finally, if you find the
reason, there's a reason
to wake the user up, they
have an order or whatever,
you then post the local
notification using these
two methods.
You can schedule one for
later, on the bottom one,
you can present one right now.
That's it.
That's all you need to do for a
pretty magical feature, right?
So, Region Monitoring.
Now, tips, tricks, and best
practices, very important.
We want to keep the battery
full so minimize battery drain.
When you're woken
up by Core Location,
you're running in
the background.
And you know and it's
not a secret that running
in the background and especially
calling the server-side,
network call is going
to use up power.
If you do this too
much, users will notice.
They will notice your battery--
They will isolate your app
and they will do that thing,
that story I told you
deleting it, right?
So, what to do?
Just-- you know, it's obvious
but minimize the background code
and wait and you employ
some safety checks.
I'll give you an example
or/and caching as well.
I'll give you an example.
You have a restaurant at the
mall or at the shop or whatever
and the user walk-in
in the mall,
it keeps crossing your fence
and the app is waking up,
he doesn't even know
it's waking up.
If you've woken up, call the
server, you got the server data
and you woken up 5, 10 minutes
later, even an hour later,
maybe that data is still
fresh and you don't need
to call again so
you save on that.
And then employ some time
stamps and things like that.
Maybe if you were
woken up 5 minutes ago
or 5 minutes before that, you
don't need to do anything again.
You've done the work you
need to do for the day
and you can just
shut down right away.
And maybe have some upper limit
of how long you can be awake
within a given day and
enforce that to make sure
that the battery doesn't drain.
Finally, I know you love
to do this, but finally,
you need to do significant
testing on features
like this both in instruments
and automated testing
but also realize nothing
will replace this --
so, load you apps up on the
phone, put in your pocket,
walk around the mall or
whatever your use case is
and actually test this.
Make sure it's not draining.
OK, related topic is privacy.
When you're monitoring
location or regions,
this arrow is going
to appear, right?
The Core Location arrow appears
on the top right
of users' devices.
They notice this thing.
And when they notice that
they think often two things.
"Hey, Mr. App, you
know where I am."
Why? Why do you need to know?
Or you're draining
my battery, right?
You're constantly
monitoring locations
so you're probably
draining my battery.
So what do you do about this?
First one is simple, be
upfront with your users,
just like the opt-in method we
did with Push Notifications.
Ask them to opt in to this.
Tell them why you're
monitoring location,
explain the value of this.
And believe me, if you
explain the value well,
they will opt in.
So they're not surprised
when they see that arrow.
And then other than the other
battery savings stuff we talked
about, monitor location
only as needed.
Minimize that arrow.
If you don't need to
monitor locations, do not.
There are three things
you can do.
First one is the solid arrow.
That means you're monitoring
a significant location change
when your app is in background.
It means if a user
moved all the way
over there significantly,
you'll wake up.
And so you'll wake
up quite often.
If you really need
to do that, do that.
Maybe you're a Sports app
and you're tracking how
far they're running,
you might need to do that.
But if you don't need to,
if you're just monitoring
static locations
like we are then use a fence
and that will use less power.
And then if you don't
need to monitor it, don't.
So if you don't have an order
with the Apple Store app,
we're not going to
fence anything
and you won't see any
arrow, and users notice this
and they appreciate that you
monitor location as needed.
Finally, a tip for you guys
who have many locations,
maybe have a chain of stores.
Remember, Core Location allows
you only 20 regions to monitor.
So you might want to be smart
about how you monitor them,
if you need to monitor
all at the same time.
So, when you start, check the
current location of the user,
monitor those around the user.
Maybe provide some
kind of zip code
or address thing they can input,
and then if they're traveling,
you can fence another area.
Then you're going to
need to update this.
For example, if they moved house
or if they're traveling
somewhere you update
and you update when
the app is awake.
When the app is awake
battery is being used anyway,
that's screen is
being used, right?
So you can do it then and
not use much more battery.
And if you really need
to, when the app is
in the background you
can update your regions
on a significant
location change.
But remember, that's the solid
arrow and you only do this
if you need to do this.
OK, so we've talked
about, you know,
telling users about events.
We've talked about
welcoming users to events.
Now the users at your event,
at your location enjoying
and spending time at your
event, what can you do
to enrich the experience?
We're coming towards the
end now of our timeline
and the user is spending
time at the location.
So, let's give them something
they will never forget.
Let's make them-- so,
OK, don't scare them
but I'm saying give them
a memorable experience
and let them get immersed
in your environment.
How you're going to do that?
I'll show you with
another feature
from the Apple Store app.
We call this In-Store Mode.
So, this is the Apple Store app
on a normal day, featured tab,
you got your featured product,
some marketing maybe
Father's Day, alright?
But when you approach a retail
store, the Upper West Side,
when you approach the
retail store with the app on
or you turn that-- bring the app
to foreground inside the retail
store, we're going to detect
that you're there
through Core Location
and will bring up this other UI.
We call this In-Store
Mode and it takes over.
And it tells you what's
happening now and it's all
about that location you're at.
On the top, it tells
you where you are
in case you didn't
know, Upper West Side.
And then from the bottom,
just got some useful things,
first is the current marketing
or events that are going on,
you can swipe through those.
You can get in to the
virtual queue, get help,
you can see who was in-- how
many people are in the queue.
You can also get support in book
a Genius Bar Appointment right
there and probably
you can use EasyPay,
a service that's only
available in the store
where you take a
product from the shelf,
with your Apple Store
app, you scan the barcode
with your camera, put in
your Apple ID password
and you bought the product.
And you walk out with
a product in your hand
and the receipt on your phone.
So, these are some very useful
services and information
that we offer right at the
store and our In-Store Mode
to enhance the user's
experience there.
The technology behind this,
this In-Location Mode
is again Core Location
and we're using it now when
the app is in the foreground
and we just trying to
get the current location.
It's an asynchronous process
so your call start updating
location and you get a callback
"did update locations"
and then you handle that.
So now, you know where
the user is and you know
where your location
of interest is.
Compare the distance.
And if it's within a
threshold, some kind of radius
where you consider someone
in the location, you pop open
that the special UI,
that's where that location.
It's that simple.
One thing I do want
to also point out,
when you use Core Location you
can adjust the desired accuracy.
This is being a good
citizen again.
So, if you're miles and miles
and miles away maybe tell Core
Location, "Hey, you don't need
to monitor with such
high accuracy.
You can monitor less accurately
and when it comes close maybe
to the mall where
your restaurant is,
start monitoring
with more accuracy.
So, it saves a little
battery with that.
So, In-Location Mode, now to
talk about some tips, tricks,
and best practices for this.
The UI is going to depend
largely on your use case,
depends on your locations,
right?
So this is the one
that's relevant to us
but there are some generic
guidelines you should follow.
First, be distinctive,
be obvious.
This UI should catch their
eye and it should be different
in your day-to-day app.
Like this, you can't
miss this, right?
And then, focus the user.
Bring front and center, those
features and that information
that matters at that location.
So, we just really fo-- we take
everything else away and focus,
you know, what's happening
now and all the services
that are offered at the store.
Finally, make sure this
UI can be dismissed
and users can access the
normal functions of your app.
For us, there's the
top right corner,
there's the small white
arrow thing, you can see it?
If you tap that,
the UI will minimize
and then you can access
the other functions
of the store-- of the app.
And just to compare the UIs,
you can see just how
different they are
when you're in that location.
Next up, remember,
your In-Location UI is probably
only relevant in your location.
Imagine if we expose,
get help, you know,
or the EasyPay stuff
at your house.
It's confusing and it
can result in bugs too.
So make sure your
UI is only there
when you're at the location.
So you get a monitor for
exit events and watch
and it'll have-- listen-- keep
listening to Core Location.
When the user has left the
location, dismiss the UI.
If the user is looking at your
In-Location UI and puts the app
to background, when they
start the app up again,
do a quick check, are
they still there or not
and then you can dismiss
the UI if they're gone.
There's one thing
to be very careful
about here, boundary conditions.
So, if that table is my
center of my location
and this is the boundary,
right, where I'm in store.
Maybe I'm right here
in Core Location says,
you're in the location,
I pop-up in the UI
and maybe I slightly move
and now I'm out the location.
I close the UI, I slightly move,
I open the UI, it's
annoying, right?
So, you don't want to do
that flashing UI to the user.
So be careful.
The big tip I give you here
is when you detect user is
in that location, maybe you have
a 50-meter radius or something.
Relax those conditions.
Increase them, make
it 100 meters.
Or maybe it's also employed
with some minimum time that has
to pass or minimum distance
they have to move for you
to dismiss this In-Location
Mode.
What you've done is you made
the In-Location feature pretty
sticky and so when--
so that you are sure
that they have left the location
when they do, otherwise,
you'll get that flashing UI.
Anyway, if you can relax
it just a little bit,
it's not going to be a problem.
You're still not going to
pop this UI at the house
or something like that.
So important tips
to remember here.
OK, we talked about Core
Location and Region Monitoring
to welcome the user to an event
and to enrich their experience.
What's next?
OK, you know, what's next but--
How can we take this to
the next level, right?
I'll show you.
With the new technology
from-- available in iOS 7,
it's a Core Location technology
and we call this iBeacons.
I'm going to show you some
examples where we use iBeacons.
I'm going to show you a little
bit about the technology.
And then we're going to show
you how to do this thing
for real in code in a demo.
Two things I want to talk about.
First is Region Monitoring,
the essence is the same except
there's one key difference
with iBeacons region
monitoring, accuracy.
See, instead of using the
traditional Cell Tower
Triangulation, GPS, and Wi-Fi,
when Core Location used to use
that to figure out if
you cross the region.
Now, Core Location tries
to look beacon signals.
Beacons are just hardware
you put out in your location
and they emit-- in
our case Bluetooth LE,
Bluetooth Low Energy.
And we quote-- and those
Bluetooth Low Energy signals can
have specific IDs.
Your app can tell Core Location,
"Hey I'm interested in ID XYZ
or 123 this Bluetooth LE ID."
When Core Location senses
that ID, it wakes your app up
and you can do something.
So, let's see how these
works in one of our examples.
I want to put aside
the Apple Store app
and I wanted to use a museum.
We're now in Paris, France.
This is the Louvre
Museum in Paris,
France and we put
beacons on the entrance.
So, when a user approaches one
of these beacons with the phone
and our app is there, Core
Location detects that,
tells our app and we can throw
up an alert and say, "Hey,
welcome to the museum.
Your guide is ready
to meet you."
User swipes in and we
show pertinent information
and tell them where
the guide is.
Now, it's similar to the other
thing we talked about, right,
the other region monitoring but
the accuracy is the difference.
You can do this right
at the door.
Maybe if you have many
entrances to the museum
or whatever big location
you have,
each one can have
its own iBeacon
and it's a much tighter
accuracy.
And you can know which
entrance the user is
for the guide to meet them.
Pretty powerful.
Now, you get see them
more interesting.
Let's talk about ranging.
In ranging, iBeacons
ranging enables the use cases
around micro-location.
We've cracked the nut on
macro-location, right?
We know you're in this room
maybe or in this building.
We know you're in a restaurant.
We know you're in
a movie theater.
We know you're in store.
We know you're in a museum.
But how cool would it
be if we know you're
at that table versus at the bar?
We know you're at that departure
gate versus this departure gate.
We know you're, you know,
in front of this shelf
instead of that shelf.
We know you're in front of this
painting instead of that statue.
And you can open up a bunch
of use cases there and only
and show some great
features that are pertinent
to the user's immediate
surroundings.
This is very powerful
and I'm going
to show you a very
simple example now.
But what's behind this is
that Core Location
not only sees a signal
but it can tell you how far away
from a signal you are
and that's the power.
This is estimated based
on signal strength
and you can get a range
basically immediate range,
10 centimeters away or so
or near range about two
to three meters away or far
range, and then you react--
your app react based on that.
So, at the museum, we've
heard of this painting right,
and we want to go
and look at it.
And we're there with our
Museum app exploring the museum
and we're constantly querying
Core Location ranging to see
if we're near an artwork
and we've put some
beacons at the artwork.
We put a Mona Lisa beacon
right on near the painting,
it's hidden, you can't see it
but it is emitting Bluetooth LE.
And as you approach with your
app, Core Location tells us
and we'll pop a special UI
to do with the Mona Lisa
and we'll tell information about
the Mona Lisa and the artist.
And whatever makes
sense for your use case,
we can expose some features
like, "Hey, do you want to buy,"
I don't know, "A print
or a Mona Lisa calendar?
Ship it to your house?"
Anything like that.
So, pretty powerful stuff
right at the Mona Lisa.
And then if you walk away,
we'll dismiss that UI.
And you maybe you walk to the
Winged Victory statue also
at the Louvre Museum, and
when you're near by there,
you detect that beacon and you
show them a different UI to do
with the Winged Victory and you
show that information there.
Have you ever been
to the museum, right?
Have you ever had
those audio tours,
have you ever had
those Walkman things?
You know what, so you don't need
that anymore, no more Walkman.
You can just use your
app as a museum guide
with this kind of stuff.
A little bit about
the technology.
[ Applause ]
Thank you.
Thank you, I appreciate that.
A little bit about
the technology.
As I said at the basis
of this is Core Location,
monitoring Bluetooth LE signals
and it can just do
Region Monitoring as well
as it can do ranging
and detect distance.
And Region Monitoring
is when your app is
in the background usually.
But for ranging, your app
needs to be in the foreground
or you can do it scan
on wake which means
when you wake your phone up
even if your app is not on,
Core Location can do
a scan for you there.
It's pretty powerful and you
can bring up a notification.
What's a beacon, you might ask?
It can be a lot of things.
Various hardware
can act as a beacon.
You can buy this third
party program, program them
to emit whatever
Bluetooth signal but also,
your iOS devices can be beacons.
So your iPads, your iPhones with
the new iOS 7 SDK, Public SDK,
you can program them to emit
whatever signal you want
and you can do that
dynamically and programatically
and vary depending
on what's happening.
So, imagine at the
museum, the painting
or the statue has a sign
like an iPad is the sign,
like a smart sign, like we have
in our retail stores maybe,
and you could tell the
information about the painting
but if it's crowded, it's
still emitting Bluetooth LE
in on your app, we can detect
that and show them whatever UI.
So, pretty powerful that you can
use iOS devices for this too.
You can try it out right now.
Finally, to remind you the big
advantage here is the accuracy
and that range that
distance awareness
that lets you do things
you could never do before.
And also worth mentioning,
one Beacon ID, you can have,
maybe have a chain and
you do want to fen--
you know, you want to fence
more than 20 locations.
Once Beacon ID can
represent-- can be one--
the beacons can be deployed
in all these locations
with the same ID.
So, one beacon ID
represents all your location
and you're no longer
bound by that limit of 20.
So, that's pretty powerful too.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
All right, so, I'm not going to
keep talking about this stuff.
I've talked enough.
Rather than talk, what we
like to do is show you
a demo on this now.
And I want to invite
Yingfeng Su.
He is the Engineering
Manager on my team.
He leads the team that actually
built all the features you
saw today.
And one of his
[ Applause ]
Thank you.
And Mathieu Roig is an
engineer on his team.
They've actually built this
Museum app, this demo app
that I showed you and they're
going to show you how this works
in code and do a demo for you.
Take it away.
>> Thank you, Filip.
Hello everyone, my
name is Yingfeng.
I'm here to show you
two exciting demos.
Both are related to the iBeacons
technology newly introduced
in iOS 7.
I'll do code walkthrough
in Xcode.
Then I'll also show you how they
actually work on a real device.
So, the first demo I'm
going to show you --
how to welcome your
customer when they arrive
at the entrance of
your location.
So, you probably think this
feature sounds complicated.
It must take a lot to
time and effort to build.
That's not necessarily the case.
So, please look-- take
a look at the screen
where I'm showing you my
Geofence Manager class.
This is where I grouped all the
Region Monitoring related code
in a one place.
There're only two methods you
need to implement in order
to make this entire thing
work, so let's take a look.
The first one is called
Register Beacon Region.
This is where you tell
iOS, "Please monitor region
for me even if my
app is not running."
So, let's take a look at
the commented code first.
So this, the commented code
shows how you are going
to do it today with iOS
6 Region Monitoring.
You need to use a latitude
and a longitude and a radius,
then you monitor that region.
What I want to show you is that
by just replacing two lines
of code, you can easily
convert a regular region
into a Beacon region which
gives you more accuracy.
And other than that,
everything else works the same.
You don't have to touch
any of your other code.
So, let's take a look.
The first line, you
need to create a UUID.
This is your way to tell
iOS just monitor signals
from my beacons.
Don't monitor someone
else's beacon.
You can use tools
like the UUIDGen
to generate a random
unique identifier.
Next line, you create a CL
Beacon Region object using
that UUID you just created.
And next, of course you need
to create the location manager
itself and assign a delegate
in order to receive
the callback.
And the last, this
is a real deal,
where you call the location
manager start monitoring API
to tell iOS to monitor
this region for you.
iOS is smart enough
to look at the type
of the region object you pass in
and determine what
technology should be used
to monitor that for you.
If you pass in a beacon type,
it will use Beacon technology
but the API is exactly the
same as you have today.
So, that's the method.
I would call this method only
at the most relevant time.
So, when user made a dinner
reservation at your restaurant,
they just reserved the
guided tour at your museum
or they placed an order and
will pick up at your store.
Those are the perfect time to
start such monitoring process.
You don't want to
do it too early.
You don't want to do it blindly
at every startup and have
that arrow show up
unnecessarily.
So now, your customer finally
comes to your location.
At the entrance, iOS detects
that the user crossed the
boundary of this region.
So, this location manager did
enter region callback will
be invoked.
Before I expand this
method, let's take a minute
to think what we are
trying to do here.
So, the ultimate
decision we want
to make is whether
it's appropriate
to post the welcome
notification to the user.
If the user's order is not
ready, it's not the time
for their dinner,
there's probably no point
to show anything to them.
However, in most of the systems
this decision can only be made
on the server-side because
the user's order status,
their reservation information,
their guided tour schedule,
those are all stored
in the server database.
Your app doesn't have that
information right away.
That does mean your
app will need
to make a server call
potentially in background
because this will wake
up your app in background
when your app is not running.
That will involve another
technology called the
Background Execution.
It's part of the iOS
multitasking and there are lots
of documentations and
sessions about that
so I won't get into the details.
I'll just show you how we use
it in our particular example.
Now, let's expand the code.
The first line is
just a sanity check
to make sure my Geofence
manager is the right object
to respond to this event.
Because the region events
are delivered to all
of the Core Location delegates
of your app, not only the one
that registers for this region.
So, you need to keep
that in mind.
The second line is just my
way of telling you, "Hey,
I'm only demonstrating
the background case."
Once you understand this,
you can easily figure
out the foreground
case on your own.
It's even simpler.
The next one is the safety
check I'm talking about.
So, imagine your location
is in the middle--
in the middle of a busy area.
Your restaurant is in
the middle of a mall.
It's totally possible
for the user
to cross the region multiple
times in a short period.
If you blindly start your app
and do all these
resource-intensive things
like making server calls every
single time the user crosses the
region, for sure
the user will notice
that their battery
drains faster than usual.
You don't want that to happen.
You want to prevent that.
So you can-- what you can
do is to use information
such as the timestamp of the
past location events to see
if enough time has elapsed
since the last time
they crossed the region.
If that's not the case,
you should tell your app
to just go back to sleep without
consuming any more resource.
That's key to saving battery.
Now, we finally enter
the real business.
First thing you need to do
is call UIApplication begin
background task API to request
additional background time
because you are going
to do a server call
and it might take a few seconds.
So, there's a lot of the
documentation for that.
There's only one thing
I want to call out is
that be a good citizen when
your app is in the background.
Implement a meaningful
expiration handler block
so that iOS can invoke
to do the cleanup work
in case your task
runs for too long.
If you don't do that iOS will
eventually terminate your app.
Now, you requested the
additional background time,
you can actually
start the server call.
This would be exactly
the same if you wanted
to do it in a foreground.
Here I'm using my Service
Manager Object to take care
of all the URL connection,
HTTP details for me.
So, what I'm doing here is
providing a completion block
that will be invoked
by my Service Manager
when the server data has
been received by the app.
So, let's take a
look on what we do.
Rule number one, for
any client-server app,
check against the error,
never ignore an error, OK.
And if you get no error and
you actually get meaningful
information from the server such
as the user's order is ready
for pick up or dinner-- the
table is ready for their dinner,
you create the
UILocalNotification object.
You fill in the details using
the information you received
from your server,
and it's very easy,
you just call this
Present method
to UIApplication
object to present that.
Also you can optionally put
a private user info where--
to your Local Notification.
So later, when you
user opens it,
you know what notification it is
and how your app should react.
That's pretty much--
we're pretty much done.
There's one last
thing you need to do.
Remember you began a
Background Task earlier.
You need to end it.
If you don't do this, your
app will be terminated
by iOS eventually.
So that's all the
code you need to add
in order to make this work.
Now, let me show you
how this actually works
on the real device.
So, I'm the visitor.
I have a guided tour booked at
the Louvre Museum for today.
As I approach-- my phone
has been in my pocket.
It's still in the locked mode
and I'm expecting a
welcome message to tell me
where I should meet
my tour guide.
So, in order to do this demo--
because I cannot move around
with this cable attached,
so I'm going to get help
from our engineer Mathieu.
Mathieu is holding an
iPhone that is programmed
to be a beacon transmitter.
He's got this little
app where he can turn on
and off different
beacon signals.
So, when he turns on the Region
Beacon it will be exactly the
same effect as if user
crossed boundary of the region.
So, let's see how it works.
Mathieu, can you tun
on the region for me?
As we can see, as soon
as Mathieu turns it on,
the notification is posted
on the user's Welcome
screen that says.
[ Applause ]
Thank you.
It gives you some
meaningful information.
If as a user, I swipe and
open, the app is launched
in foreground and you have the
freedom to do whatever you want.
So, again, this is at the
entrance of your location, OK.
So comparing to the regular
Geofence where you have today,
it probably notified
the user at parking lot.
Now with this, you can
notify them at the entrance.
So, that's my first demo.
Only two methods, it really
couldn't be any simpler.
Let's move on to the next demo.
The next demo is about
ranging use case.
So, imagine, you are the
owner of a large museum.
You have hundreds or
thousands of artwork pods
in your exhibition area.
What you can do is to attach a
beacon to each of the artworks
such that when user
is in your museum
and they're running
your Museum app,
they can get additional
information
about the artwork
they are closest to.
So, let me show you
how to do it in code.
Again, two methods.
First method is to start
to the ranging process.
This tells iOS, "I'm
ready to receive signals.
Please, monitor beacon
signals around me
and report them back to me."
So, 3 lines of code.
First thing first,
you create a UUID.
You need to use the same
UUID between your app and all
of the artwork beacons
in your museum.
Maybe you have 500 of them.
It doesn't matter.
You use all the UUID-- you used
the same UUID on all of them.
So, there's really no
practical limit for you.
And then you create a
CL Beacon Region object.
It's very similar with
the previous demo.
And the last is this time we're
calling the Start Ranging API
instead of a Start
Monitoring API because we want
to do active scanning.
So, that is it.
From now on, iOS will start
monitoring the signals
around you and then
report them back to you.
I would call this method
whenever my app goes
to the foreground and the
user is confirmed to be
within the range of
my exhibition area.
So let's take a look at the
Core Location delegate callback.
Location manager did
range Beacons in region.
This is where iOS
tells you, "I found one
or more beacons around you."
Notice that the beacons
parameter is an array
because at anytime, you can see
multiple beacons around you.
They are sorted by the
perceived distance.
So, the one that's believed
to be the closest is
at the top of the array.
So, let's expand the method
and see what we do here.
First line, I'm just trying to
use utility method to inspect
if the closest beacon is
within a desired threshold.
Here, I'm using CL
proximity near as my threshold
which represents a distance
of roughly three meters.
So, this entire line
basically means try
to find the closest beacon
that is within three meters.
If one-- the reason I make
it into utility method is
because I may want to use
it somewhere else in my app
and it makes unit test easier.
But, inside it this is really
just objectAtIndex zero,
casted back to the region and
check the proximity property.
And if one is found, I can
inspect the major value property
on the Beacon to tell
whether it's the painting
or it's a sculpture.
So, we programmed all the
artwork beacons using the
same UUID.
So you might ask, "How do I
tell whether it's a painting
or sculpture?"
There are other customizable
values on the Beacon.
They are called major
and the minor properties.
Each of them is a
16-bit integer.
So you can define
the value of them.
So, in my case I specify one
to be the Mona Lisa paining
and I used two for the
Winged Victory statue.
So, by reading the major value,
I can give a hint to my UI code,
"OK, this is Mona Lisa.
That is the Winged Victory."
So you can show different pages.
And of course if user has walked
away from the exhibition area,
this method will return nil
and we'll just dismiss the
information page we just
showed earlier.
So let me show you how this
actually works on a device.
So, I'm running my
Museum Guide app.
OK, it's the same app
and it's in foreground.
So, the ranging process
is already working.
So again, I'm going to get
help from Mathieu to turn on
and off different
artwork beacons
which is exactly the same
as if user approaches
or leaves certain artwork.
So, Mathieu, can you please turn
on the Mona Lisa beacon for me?
As we can see as soon as Mathieu
turns on the Mona Lisa beacon--
I'm not touching the
phone by the way.
[ Laughs ]
So, we are showing
an information page
about the author and
what year it was made.
You can do whatever you
like that's relevant
to this particular artwork.
Mathieu, can you please switch
to the Winged Victory statue?
So now, I walk away
from Mona Lisa
and I walk towards the
Winged Victory statue.
You can see the app
is smart enough
to swap the information page.
Now, can you turn
off everything?
So, when Mathieu turns off
everything, we are dismissing
that information page.
And the app is still ranging as
long as you are in the museum.
So, that is the end
of my both demos.
We are very excited about
these new technologies.
Everyday, we keep thinking how
we can use these technologies
to further enrich the
customer experience in our app.
I hope you like them as well and
think about how you can use them
to deliver more personalized
services to your customers.
Thank you and I'm going to
give this back to Filip.
[ Applause ]
>> OK. Hope you guys
enjoyed that demo.
It was live and you're
one of the first people
to actually see iBeacons
in action for real.
So, like Yingfeng said,
we're really excited
about this on our side.
So, I hope you guys are
too and just go out there
and build some magic
with this feature.
I'm going to summarize things up
now and as we talked about this,
some key iOS technologies,
calendar,
push calendar events
pushes Region Monitoring,
Core Location, and iBeacons.
And they're simple to
use but so effective
and you guys can make some truly
great experience with these.
So, go out there and use them
but use them wisely,
use them properly.
That's how we have tips
and tricks here for you.
Finally, if you have
been done it already,
download the Apple Store app,
you can see all this in practice
and you can pull along and
see what we do in future.
For more information, our
evangelist is Paul Marcos.
This is the Apple Store
app, the Reference app.
You can find it here or
download on the App Store
and as always the Apple
Developer Forums are there
for you.
There are some related sessions
I want to point you guys too,
Yingfeng talked about
running in the background.
You're going to find
a lot all about that
and what's new with
multitasking.
I really recommend that one
then Integrating Passbook
in Your Ecosystem, that's
another session by my team.
Well, again we approach
it from your perspective.
We've implemented the
Apple Store gift card pass.
Pretty complex pass and
we talked about how we did
that in the tips
and tricks there
so you guys can implement
your own passes.
And then, of course what's
new in Core Location.
Here, you can find out a
lot more about the iBeacons
and all the other Core Location
technology we've talked about.
With that, I want to thank you
guys for coming to this talk.
Thank you
[ Applause ]
for coming to WWDC.
Hope you had fun.