>> Good afternoon and welcome
to fixing memory issues.
My name is Kate Stone
[phonetic], and I'm responsible,
among other things,
for managing the team
that develops the
Instruments product
that hopefully you all know and
love and will learn a lot more
about in this session.
But, of course, the focus of
our session is not Instruments,
it's on your application.
So glad to see so many of you
here today because our goal is
to make your application the
best that it can possibly be.
We want applications that
are robust, that are fast,
that don't hog too many system
resources and work really well
with other applications
on the system.
So with that in mind
let's start thinking
about what could
possibly go wrong.
Your application, of
course it occupies memory.
From the very beginning
an application that's up
and running, it's
loaded into memory,
it starts executing,
starts loading data.
It starts loading more
and more and more data.
And there are a couple of
potential side effects of this.
If you get too much you start
seeing a poor user experience.
It could mean long load times.
It could mean you're
trying to get too much up
and running before the user
sees something meaningful.
It could mean you're using
so many system resources
that you wind up
swapping on an OS X system
and slowing the system down.
It could mean that when
users try to switch
to their other applications
that they find
that they've been forced out
of memory by your application.
So there are a lot of
potential down sides,
and it really behooves us to
keep things under control.
Of course, the situation
could get worse.
It could be the situation that
you're using so much memory,
so many resources on the system,
that you were forcibly
terminated.
This can happen in
a variety of ways.
We'll discuss all of them.
But in particular you
should keep in mind
that your application being
terminated aggressively while
the user is watching is only
the worst possible outcome.
It's also possible that
the user switches away
from your application,
and because you're using too
much memory the system needs
to clean that up, it discards
your application, and it's slow
to come back to your
app the next time.
And that's another form
of poor user experience.
So, again, memory is really
critical in this sense.
But it's critical in
another sense as well.
Poor management of memory
can lead to bugs that result
in the immediate crash of your
application even though your
resources may not be excessive.
So we're going to focus on all
of these problems
throughout this session.
Specifically, if you
look at our agenda,
we're going to talk a little
bit about app memory in general.
What does it look like?
How can you think about it, and
what kinds of tools do we have
to help you understand
what's going on?
We're going to talk
about the Heap,
because every memory discussion
discusses the Heap and, in fact,
that's an area where not only do
you have a lot of resource uses,
you have keys to
finding other areas
where there's memory
being occupied.
And we'll talk about
how that works.
I'll hand it over to one of
my engineers, and we'll move
on to talking about Objective-C,
challenges on that front
including retained releases
a pattern.
And, lastly, how to be a really
good citizen in the environment.
So an overview of
application memory.
Thankfully this release,
and doubtless you've seen
this numerous times before,
we now have the debug
gauges in Xcode.
The debug gauges give you
access, among other things,
to memory at a glance.
So there's a gauge that
you can move to, click on,
and you'll get an
additional report
that shows you more detail
about your application.
We've tried to break this down
to one number that's most likely
to be meaningful to you.
In this case you can think of it
as the footprint of
your application.
That one number gives
you a good indication
as you're running your app
because it's always present
in the debugger of
just what you're doing.
If you're starting to consume
more resources over time,
if something catastrophic
does occur just what point
that occurred at.
So you've got a good
indicator when you might need
to go and use Instruments.
And, indeed, there's a
handy button right there
that if you see a trend you
don't like we can go directly
to Instruments from
the debug gauge.
You need to understand that
this memory number is just one
number, and there are all
kinds of ways to measure memory
as we'll discuss again in a bit.
But Instruments is typically
traditionally focused
on the Heap.
And you may have seen situations
where your application was
summarily killed despite the
fact that your Heap
was relatively small.
It's important to know
that there's really a lot
of other memory involved
in your application
that you may not have thought
about, may not have had to worry
about or may not have had the
tools to understand before
that can take the form of code,
it could be images, media.
It could be a lot
of different things
that you haven't been
able to see before.
So the big question
is how do you get
to all of this information?
Lastly, again, this point
that your measurement will tell
you different numbers depending
on the tool you use, the
strategy that the tool uses
to find that information and
really what you're looking for.
So if you're looking for one
number that sums up everything
about your application, in
some sense you're trying
to oversimplify what's
really a fairly complex set
of subsystems operating.
So you will see that the gauge
provides you one set of numbers.
Again, it's what we think is
the most meaningful number.
But there are other numbers that
we can explore, and as we go
through Instruments you'll
see some of those as well.
So it sounds like the
right time to dive on in
and have a look at
this workflow.
I'm just going to bring
up a project here.
And this project is one that
you're probably familiar
with if not in source code
because we don't
make it available,
then because you've used it
every day at this conference.
It's the WWDC app that
you have on your devices.
Or at least it's an early
version of it with a few issues,
maybe some of them having been
introduced by us for purposes
that will become
clear on the stage.
So let's go ahead and
run that application.
So it's been deployed
to my device.
It's up and running.
And we'll see that the gauges
are providing me feedback here
about how much CPU
time I'm using,
how much memory I'm using.
And so as I exercise the
app I'm going to drill
into a particular session.
I'm going to go ahead and look
at maps, look at news, videos.
You can't see any
of this but, again,
the workflow should
be familiar to you.
And so I've come back to
the initial state I was in,
and I've seen rather a lot
of growth over that time.
So maybe I want to have a
look at that memory curve.
And it doesn't look spectacular.
It's kind of going the
wrong direction here.
There's enough information
here to know
that there's something
I should investigate,
but not enough information
to tell me what exactly
I should do.
That's the time that we might
go to profile in Instruments.
And so by simply clicking
here I get a prompt,
and I have two options
at this point.
I can choose to stop
my debug session
and hand this existing
running application off
to Instruments to investigate.
I will have missed
the opportunity then
to measure a lot of
important information
about the allocations that
have already occurred.
So when you're looking at memory
that's rarely the right option.
It's possible there
may be things
that you could learn
using that technique,
but for our purposes no.
We're going to ask to stop the
debug session, launch a new copy
of the application
inside Instruments.
And we may see here what you may
very well have run into already
if you've been experimenting
with the seed,
that in the initial seed the
handoff is not always graceful.
If you run into problems
you can stop the application
and simply start
re-recording in Instruments.
Obviously this will
be corrected.
So we've got our application up
and running under Instruments.
We're getting recordings
here of what's going
on in terms of memory
allocation.
And we're seeing a
nice allocations curve.
I mentioned before that
typically Instruments is shown
as Heap information
in allocations.
Well, if we look at some
of these numbers we would
expect then maybe to see numbers
that are smaller
than the numbers
that are being reported
by the gauge.
That's no longer the case.
My total live bytes being
reported here, 57 meg,
is actually even more than
the number reported in gauges.
And that's because
allocations has been enhanced
to show a lot more information
than we've been able
to see in the past.
In particular it's not
just Heap allocations
but all virtual memory regions
that have been allocated,
mapped into memory while
your application was running.
So if you look here specifically
we actually have a filter
that allows us to
see a blended view
of both Heap allocations
and VM allocations.
Or we can focus on just the heap
which is really just
3.6 meg in this case.
Or just the VM regions which
accounts for rather a lot
of memory in my application,
memory that you haven't been
able to see in the past.
Well, that's interesting,
what kinds of things
have we got here?
Well, if we sort by
live bytes we'll see
that we have mapped files, and I
can dive in and see specifically
which files, zoom back out,
which files have been mapped
into my application,
when they were mapped in
and get additional information.
In fact, I can find a
particular file of interest
and find the call stack
that was responsible.
What was it in my code that
caused this to be mapped in?
Interesting.
But in this particular case
what caught my eye wasn't the
mapped files.
It was all of this image IO.
So I've got image IO going on,
and as I exercise the
application in the same fashion
that I exercised it a moment
ago, we'll see that, in fact,
image IO turns out to be
a pretty substantial chunk
of what my application is doing.
In fact, it's dwarfing the
Heap memory at this point.
So optimizing for my Heap is
maybe not the most important
thing for me to consider.
Maybe I need to understand
this a little better.
And a lot of the tools
that we've used before
help me understand this.
So if I were to go into
my call trees view,
the call trees view
will show me, again,
down which paths the
allocations are occurring.
If I search for
image IO work here I can see
that there's core
animation-related things
happening that are resulting
in memory mapped operations.
And so I can actually drill down
and see the call path
that led to this.
It's interesting because I will
see there are actually also
malloc operations operating on
the Heap in the same vicinity.
In fact, if I look at this line,
we'll go up even one more level
here, 7.83 meg is being called
down this path somewhere
in code.
7.82 meg of that looks
like it's mapped memory,
memory that would
show up as VM regions
that I couldn't see before.
So I'd have this
tiny amount of memory
on the Heap that's
allocated down this same path
and represents the same
work that's allocating all
of these images.
That's what we'd like to
be able to queue in on
and understand a
lot better in order
to control the behavior
of our application.
So these are some interesting
new tools that we have.
Of course we have some
familiar tools as well.
I'm going to dig into
the library and bring
out one other familiar
favorite, VM Tracker,
and record a little bit
about the current state
of my application
from VM Tracker.
The reason I bring this up
we'll dive into in a moment,
but virtual memory is an
interesting slippery beast.
A region can represent
a lot of memory space
but have only portions of that
memory actually in active use
in physical RAM on your device.
And the VM Tracker is
one way that you can dig
in and understand this.
So the VM Tracker in this case
is showing me information like,
okay, there's this image
IO that's going on.
Of that image IO how
much of it is virtual,
how much of it is dirty and
how much of it is resident?
These are incredibly important
queues that we really need
to understand a little better
in order to see the full picture
of what's going on in
my applications memory.
I'd also like to point out that
if you've used the Instruments
from sort of a casual
perspective, you go in
and you look at the
default presentations,
you haven't really tried tuning
the way you look at things,
you might want to try
clicking on the left side
of the navigation bar here.
Because this isn't
just about navigation
in the bread crumb trail,
it's about fundamentally
different views
for the instruments
that we have.
And so for the VM Tracker one
of those handy views is the
region's map that allows me
to see where things
are laid out in memory.
So I could actually understand
my virtual memory address range,
which things are adjacent
to which other things
in case I'm overriding the
end of some buffer, et cetera.
There's a lot of good
information in here.
We won't cover it all in this
session sadly, but we are going
to focus on some of the things
that are particularly
new this time around.
[ Pause ]
So let's switch back to slides.
We talked about the fact
that virtual memory is
now more fully represented
in allocations.
And we have a lot
of familiar tools
and techniques that
we can apply.
There's one that may not be
quite so obvious, though,
this notion that there's
an efficient alternative
to running allocations on
your application as is.
If you've ever tried
using Allocations
on a particularly
large app you'll note
that it's tracking a
lot of information,
millions upon millions of
allocations and deallocations,
and bookkeeping for that
winds up actually taking a lot
of memory and a lot of time.
So if you've got an application
that you've never been able
to use Allocations on
before there's a new
interesting technique.
If you open the configuration
panel for Allocations and move
to only VM Allocation tracking,
you will lose your ability
to see the fine grained
information on the Heap,
but you can still see the
big picture in terms of VM,
and that could be a powerful
tool for applications
that previously there was no
way to get any insight into.
Because this does
give us insight
into some very interesting
things.
It gives us an idea of who
mapped files into memory,
who is responsible for
contributing to my footprint
in a way that the
Heap never could.
And, again, for page
level statistics,
so beyond the VM region
to an individual page,
a concept we'll talk about in a
moment, there's the VM Tracker
which can give me more depth.
So, sorry, built.
Virtual memory.
We've talked a lot
about virtual memory.
I pointed out concepts like
dirty memory, resident memory,
these are things that may
or may not be familiar
so let's go through
them briefly.
The notion of virtual memory
versus resident memory.
My virtual memory isn't
a logical address space
from address 0 to the
top of logical memory,
and every single process has
its own virtual memory region.
Process A may be thinking
it has memory at address 0
and process B thinks
the same thing.
And obviously they have
distinct chunks of memory.
So this is a nice
logical concept
from an application
developer's point of view.
You can pretend that
you own all of RAM,
but the reality is a little
bit more complicated than that.
All memory regions that
are reserved are allocated
on 4K page boundaries and
occupy a fixed number of pages
so you'll never share a page
with another virtual
memory region.
So the example we have up here
you'll see that we have a region
that consists of 2 pages, 8K,
another region that consists
of 3 pages, 12K, and that's
representing my virtual address
space here.
But nothing's actually
in RAM yet.
This is all just from
my application's point
of view a simplistic way
of looking at the world.
What happens is that on the
first use, whether I read
from a chunk of memory or write
to a piece of memory it winds
up being mapped into
physical memory.
We find a page that's not used
in physical memory it's unlikely
to be the first page, there's
probably an operating system up
and running at this point, but
it finds a page that's unused
and it maps it to a page
of your application.
Same thing happens again.
I find some other
page that I touch,
and these can be completely
disjoint, and these result
in physical memory coming in.
What happens is we describe
these as having become resident.
So it's still virtual
memory, we still talk about it
as virtual memory,
but only a portion
of it is actually resident in
physical RAM at any given time.
Part of the reason that I
like to draw the distinction
between these two is because
while physical memory is more
likely to be your constraint,
we've tried to illustrate this
with the shorter bar,
it's not always the case.
It's possible in an application
that you will try to map
in too many media resources
in case you ever need them.
And so despite the fact that
you've never read a single one
of them, you've exhausted
the amount of virtual memory
that the operating system
is going to allow you.
In particular on
iOS you may find
that you don't have much loaded,
but if you exhaust the virtual
memory space that we allow
for you we will simply kill
your application outright.
So it's possible to
run into that limit.
It is much more likely instead
that I'll run into limits
in terms of physical RAM.
The notion of clean
versus dirty comes up next.
What's dirty memory represent?
Well, clean pages are pages
that we can discard
at will and recreate.
What kinds of pages
can we do that with?
Well, if we've loaded
some code from Flash
or from a physical disk
drive we've loaded that in,
we know where it came from.
If we need that memory
back we can throw it away.
We can always reload
it from disk.
That memory is still
considered clean
because it can be discarded.
And this is true
of OS X and iOS.
On the other hand as
soon as I touch a page
and actually modify its contents
so that there's no longer
essentially a backup copy
that we can readily get we
consider that memory dirty.
And so basically everything
on your Heap, your Stacks,
global variables, all
of this is dirty RAM.
It's RAM that we have
to keep in memory --
sorry, information that we
have to keep in memory in order
for you to be able to
continue executing.
That's absolutely
critical for your sanity.
So what happens when
we start running low
on memory is we'll start
discarding pages that are clean.
On OS X then we will also worry
about what we can do
to swap things out.
We'll take dirty pages
and write them to disk
so we do have a backup copy
and we can reuse that memory.
At this point your system
will start to slow as it needs
to page memory in and out.
But on iOS the situation
is much more drastic.
If there's dirty memory and we
haven't got anywhere to put it
because we don't write it
to Flash, too expensive
for a variety of reasons,
we will simply terminate
your application.
So you absolutely need
to keep your dirty memory
under control especially on iOS.
So this process of swapping
gives us potential but, again,
for the vast majority of
you it's not available.
The last concept is the notion
of private memory
versus shared memory.
When I create a memory
region I can give it a name,
and by giving it a name another
process can actually use the
same physical memory and map it
into its virtual address space.
Well, as it turns out in a
lot of cases you will wind
up instead with memory that
is automatically shared,
implicitly given a name
because it's mapped to a file.
And so as soon as I map a file
if somebody maps the same file
we're now sharing that memory.
So consider an example where
I write an application.
The first thing that
happens is a piece
of code gets paged in, okay?
We hit the code off
disk, it's now mapped
into my address space.
I then go and allocate
something on the Heap,
and so I need a page that
backs some of the Heap.
And now we've got one
process up and running.
But now I launch another
instance of the same process.
It's got its own address space.
So it has a completely separate
address space that they happen
to potentially align
here, they may not.
And now it needs to load code.
Well,
because the code is coming
from a file it's actually able
to map the same chunk
of physical memory
into its virtual address space.
But then it goes to put
something on the Heap,
and because this is logically
a separate instance its data is
kept independently,
and this is separate.
This is what we call
private memory.
So often you will see a
focus on your private memory,
memory that is not potentially
shared with anyone else
because all the frameworks
are shared.
It's generally not considered
reasonable to account
against your process what you're
using from the frameworks.
And instead we want to focus
on the private dirty memory,
and that's largely what we
show you with the Xcode gauges.
So we're going to talk
about Heap memory.
What is the Heap?
Probably a familiar concept for
most of you, but if it's not,
any time you call malloc you are
allocating a chunk of memory,
and it's potentially
quite small.
This is often used for
fine grained things,
a dozen bytes or more.
But it can also be used
for fairly large things,
and it's in this managed area.
You may not have called malloc,
but if you've called alloc
or new on an Objective-C object
under the covers
that's what it's doing.
Or if you use the new operator
on a C++ object that's
what it's been doing.
And so you wind up with
these malloc zones.
The malloc memory is actually
backed by virtual memory,
so there's a virtual memory zone
that the malloc subsystem
has created for you,
and it's doing all
the bookkeeping to try
to reuse space and
use space efficiently
within that malloc region.
So if you actually
look you will see
that there is this VM
malloc region lying
around that represents the
backing store for all of this.
And typically things
that you keep
on the heap you will often
have reference counted
so that you can do fairly
sophisticated memory management.
It takes care of a lot of
interesting bookkeeping for you.
You may also wind up seeing it,
of course, allocated implicitly
by other code on your behalf.
So when I'm looking at the heap
things that I might want to keep
in mind are that
there are some types
that are more expensive
than others.
VM is about bytes.
I can look at a VM region
and say this is a couple
of megabytes, that's
actually relatively large,
but in the Heap typically,
again, things are going
to be 16 bytes, 30 bytes, it's
going to be some small amount
of memory that's reserved.
And so it's the aggregation of
a large number of these things
that gets interesting.
Why is that important?
It's important because in
practice a small object can have
a large graph of other
objects that it references.
So let's say we have,
for example here,
in our world a view
of some kind.
It actually contains
that small chunk
of memory that's actually
allocated for us here,
96 bytes in this case.
It has a layer pointer, has view
delegate pointers, has pointers
to all kinds of other objects.
And these objects
themselves occupy space.
The layer object in this
case another 32 bytes.
And this may not seem
like it's going to add
up in a hurry except that some
of those objects manage whole
VM regions behind the scenes.
So a CA layer needs to keep
its bitmap data somewhere,
and as it turns out that data
isn't always on the Heap.
In this case we've got a VM
region that could be megabytes
and megabytes of pixel data.
And so it behooves you
to understand that, yes,
what I'm looking for are these
objects that keep large graphs
of other objects
behind the scenes.
There are the obvious ones.
If I look for an NS set or
an NS dictionary I'll see
that there's a relatively
small amount
of memory attributed
to it by allocations.
But really it's holding onto
we know potentially a large
collection of objects.
And then there's the less
obvious containers, again,
UI view, view controllers
or NS image
that represent a
lot of information.
So as I showed you
earlier in the call graph
where I found one place
that creates both an object
and a VM region this is
what happens typically.
And it's when you finally
de- reference the object
that the VM region is
deallocated on your behalf.
So what can I do to investigate?
Well, as it turns out
there are a couple
of ways to think about this.
There are my classes.
My classes is a subset.
They're probably things
that hold onto large graphs.
And so if you want to just see
just your classes you should
probably prefix them
consistently.
So in this app we have
everything prefixed with WWDC.
And that means that I can
go ahead and just bring
up the allocations UI, go
ahead and click in the filter
in the upper right
corner and type my prefix.
So once we've got that
prefix typed in you'll see
that we're filtering down to
just the object whose category
here uses that prefix.
And category is the way we
divide all of the allocations
into some reasonably
observable group of objects.
And in this case it's based
on the class of the object.
So if I've used a
consistent prefix it's easy.
But we categorize
objects by things other
than just Objective-C classes.
Specifically we're much,
much better in this
release at C++ objects.
If you have a virtual
C++ class you'll find
that we categorize
those by name as well.
We also find other
things that have V tables.
We can find dispatch queues.
We can find XPC-related types.
Just try searching
for dispatch or XPC.
We can also find blocks
that have escaped the scope
and been allocated on the Heap.
Look for NS malloc
block to find those.
[ Pause ]
So when we look at Heap growth
and it's going the wrong
direction and we could sit down
and look at objects all day
long, there are a few kinds
of problems to keep in mind.
One of them is the
potential for leaked memory.
It's possible that you
have allocated an object,
you've finished using it,
you in fact no longer
have any references to it.
And this is much easier to do
without ARC than it is with ARC.
It's still possible.
If you literally
cannot get to it anymore
because there is no longer a
pointer from any active object
that you reference we
consider this memory leaked.
And Daniel will show
you a little bit later
about how exactly you
can go about tracking
down this leaked memory.
But there's some
other categories
that are much trickier
to understand.
Abandoned memory,
memory I've allocated,
I have a legitimate path to
get to it, but as it turns
out there's never going to
be a single line of code
that actually follows
that path again.
I stuck it in the global
variable during startup,
and that startup
code is the only code
that ever references it.
That memory has been abandoned.
No leak detection tool on the
planet will find it for you,
but it's still important
that you understand
that that memory
exists and is cluttering
up your user's environment.
There's also cached memory.
If you have a cache that you
stick things in you may find
that you open a document,
put the document reference
in the cache, close
the document,
and it sticks around forever.
It's really efficient to go
and reopen that document now,
but it's a shame if the user
really intends to do a lot
of other things and it's
cluttering up the world.
And in this place
maybe the right thing
to do is consider using NS
Cache to manage your chaches
so that it can handle
memory for you.
But we're going to talk
about tracking some of this
down using a technique
called generational analysis.
You may have seen this before.
Previously we referred
to it as a Heap shot.
But given that we cover more
than Heap now we've
renamed the facility.
It's about following these
steps to find our problems.
We reach a steady state.
We launch our application.
We then do something
that allocates memory,
open a document and then get
back to that steady state,
close the document and
repeat that series of steps.
And along the way we may
find something interesting.
Specifically if I repeat this
process over and over again
and every time memory
winds up accruing,
then I've got some form of
abandoned or over cached
or leaked memory going on.
So visually steady state, some
sort of intermediate state
with the document open,
back to the original state.
Now, you may find that
there's some warmup cost here.
We're loading code that
hasn't been used before.
There's some basic data
structures being set up.
Some level of warmup
cost is to be expected.
But it's on the repeated
use of this
that we wind up finding waste.
[ Pause ]
If you find that you are going
through this repeated cycle
and you're not seeing any
waste, you're getting a net 0,
you may find that you have free
memory from a heap perspective
that isn't actually free from
a virtual memory perspective.
How does that happen?
Well, it's something we refer
to as Heap fragmentation.
Specifically I have a situation
where I have a variety of pages,
and every page has
exactly one object
that I keep referencing on it.
Those pages, therefore,
are still kept in,
they're in physical memory.
And I'm now using 32
bytes of some sort
of legitimate data
occupying 4K of memory.
So what do I do about this?
How do I understand
this situation,
and how did I get there
in the first place?
Well, here's how it happens.
You go ahead and get
a malloc VM region.
This is created for you by
the malloc subsystem in order
to allocate an object.
I then allocate a
bunch of objects
and I've filled this page.
Repeat. So we allocate
a bunch more VM regions.
We fill them with a bunch
more objects, and now we're
in a perfectly reasonable
situation
where we're utilizing
all that memory.
Now we go and we free
most of those objects.
And unfortunately what happens
is we're left with objects
in the locations where
they were allocated,
pinned there occupying memory.
So if you've got a process
that allocates a lot of memory
and then releases most of it
you may be fragmenting memory.
You may not see the
memory coming back
that you would expect
from looking at the Heap.
The biggest thing you can do
about this is avoid a situation
where you have these
extreme peaks and valleys.
So go into Allocations.
This is the place where
the Heap Allocation tool,
if you're just filtering
for Heap
only and graphing the Heap,
can show you precisely how
much Heap you're using.
So we're seeing this graph
with peaks and valleys.
And that is indicative
of a potential problem.
You may never get back
the virtual memory region
that is resident from
that high water mark.
Most of the time you'll get
back a significant amount.
But be careful.
Your ideal graph looks
a lot more like this,
relatively small increases
and decreases over time
to the extent that
you can manage it.
Of course your friend
in this is auto release.
Keep in mind that
auto release is sort
of the best tool you
can possibly use here.
And what you need
to do is make sure
that you give the auto
release pool a chance to drain.
You either drain it
yourself in the course
of a long loop that's
doing a lot of operations,
or if you're doing something
on a dispatch queue you may
find it's valuable to drain it.
You need to be careful,
as always,
that auto released
objects aren't something
that you're going to reference
after the auto release
pool has been drained.
And with that I'm going to
turn it over to my engineer,
Daniel Delwood, who is going to
dive into more of the mysteries
of Objective-C, retain
release and other goodness.
Thank you, Daniel.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Kate.
So Kate went over virtual
memory from a high level
and then zoomed into
Heap memory.
And now we're going to zoom
in even further and talk
about Objective-C, your objects
and the management schemes
that you can employ.
So first of all let's start
with a brief review
of retain release.
Objective-C uses as a reference
counting ownership model.
And this means that when you
create an object the object
starts out with a
reference count of 1.
So there's two main primitives,
retain which says I want
to express ownership over
this, it bumps the retain count
and release which
releases that ownership
and decrements are
a retain count by 1.
Whenever the account drops
to 0 the object is freed back
to the malloc subsystem.
Now, the third primitive
there is auto release,
and it's important to remember
that this is just a delayed
release, and it's very useful
for things like returning
objects from functions.
Just remember, though, that
the auto release will issue
that delayed release whenever
the current auto release ends.
The rules are established,
they're easy to learn,
and here's actually a
good reference document,
the advanced memory
management guide.
I'd recommend book marking it.
It's a great place to go back
to when you're debugging issues.
The thing to remember here,
though about Objective-C's
ownership model is
that it's deterministic
and simple to learn.
Most importantly,
though, it's fast.
So what can go wrong
with this, right?
We're talking about
fixing memory issues.
Well, it's tedious.
Writing retain and
release is very error prone
when you're writing
all of this code,
and more code really
is more bugs.
And so if you write too
many retains you're going
to get objects that may not
be referenced by anything else
in your code but still
have non 0 retain counts.
Now, if you release something
too many times it will quickly
lead to crashes.
Now, the third problem
that's common
with this is retain cycles.
And this is more of
a structural problem,
more of a behavioral problem.
And it's because you
could have objects
that reference each
other, retain each other,
and if they're not
referenced by anything else
in your application
they're still going to leak,
and you need to find some
way of breaking that cycle.
Well, luckily for the
tedium it's gone now.
We have automatic
reference counting.
And the compiler is really great
about doing those retains
and releases for us.
So it's compiler assisted
convention enforcement.
It knows that whole document
I just told you about.
It knows how to do the
retain and release perfectly.
But it's still important
that you know how
that convention works
under the covers.
Because whether you're
running ARC or not,
when you're debugging
issues you need to be able
to understand all of the
data, understand what retain
and release means in
your object history.
Now, automatic reference
counting doesn't solve retain
cycles on its own because
that's not a mechanics issue,
that's a design and
behavior issue.
Luckily, though, it does
provide some very useful tools
and keywords to help fix
these including things
like zeroing weak references
where you can mark one
of the references weak and
the whole cycle will go away.
So let's talk about then
what the common problems are
under ARC and focus on
those more behavioral
structural issues.
Well, the first one
is memory growth.
And memory growth can really
come in two different forms.
The first like I talked
about is retain cycles.
And the second is
abandoned objects.
So for retain cycles the leaks
instrument actually provides a
very nice graphical
display of the cycle
so you can easily understand
what the cause is and go in
and find out where you need to
use the weak keyword and fix it.
As for abandoned objects,
what Kate was talking
about with the generational
analysis is definitely the best
way to go.
The second thing that can happen
in ARC is messaging the
deallocated objects.
Now, you might say
how is this happening
if I'm not issuing
too many releases?
Well, I'll get to
that in a little bit.
But the problem with messaging
these objects is it's very
undefined and nondeterministic
behavior.
You might way, well, it
always crashes for me,
but it really depends
on what happens
to that object once you free it.
If you return the memory to the
malloc system it doesn't have
to clear it, it doesn't
have to reuse it.
And it may still appear to be
an object, it may still respond
to messages and you won't
get a crash some of the time.
When you do get crashes, though,
things like Objective-C
message send, store strong
or it does not respond to
selector are good indicators
that this is the sort of
problem that you have.
So how do we fix that?
What tools do we have?
Well, the Zombies template
is a great way to do this,
and it uses a very age old
debugging environment variable
exposed by foundation.
And that's Zombie
enabled equals 1.
And what this does is instead
of objects being deallocated
when they're freed or when
their retain counts goes to 0,
they're changed into
Zombie objects.
So that whenever you reference
them later and use them
and send them a message
they crash.
Very deterministic behavior,
and this is what we want
when we're debugging issues.
So, again, it's deterministic
because the memory isn't
unchanged or reused.
And I want to also point
out that every Zombie object
that you leave in your process
is technically also a leak.
So you really don't want to
use this sort of debugging
at the same time that you're
looking for leaks in your code.
An important note, though,
previously this was
only available
for iOS on the iOS Simulator.
It's now available
for iOS 7 devices.
[ Applause ]
So with that I want to
show you a quick demo.
So I have here the
same WWDC app,
and I was noticing
an intermittent crash
when I was dealing with
bad network conditions.
Well, I can actually reproduce
this a lot easier just
by messing up a URL, and you'll
see what it turns out to do.
So I'm going to go ahead
and run this on my phone.
[ Pause ]
So the app comes up.
You'll have to trust me it's
looking very nice on iOS 7.
And immediately we see
this sort of thing.
Exec bad access, crash, and
if we zoom in here right
in the debugger ObjC
underscore release.
So it looks like we've
got probably a memory
management issue.
So I'm just going to
use the profile action
from the run menu,
and goes ahead builds,
pops open instruments,
and I can go ahead
and select the Zombies
template for my device.
So, again, it launches,
and we get this graph
of allocations as we'd expect.
Alright, so instruments has
detected that I have message
to Zombie, and I can get
some more information just
by hitting the arrow.
So the first thing
you'll notice here is
that my retain release
history looks a lot different
than it did in Xcode 4.
And that's because what
Instruments is doing is showing
me a pairing view of
retains and releases.
And if I turn this down you'll
see that we have malloc events,
auto release, retain release all
grouped together into one chunk.
Now the scope bar here
allows me to change my view
so I can see it by time which is
what I'm used to seeing before.
Or, I can see it again grouped
by that pairing or
bad back trace.
So the interesting part here
is that I can select each one
of these events and take a look
at the stack trace on the right.
And look through and see,
okay, what's going on here.
But Instruments has
already told me
that these are very
likely already paired.
They're already matching up.
There's probably not too many
retains, too many releases.
So the question is why is this a
message to a deallocated objects
and Objective-C store strong?
So we can just jump
right to the code.
And I'm going to open it in
Xcode so you can see it better.
And what happens,
let's see here --
[ Pause ]
What we've got --
-- is an error parameter
being returned by reference
from this process
raw data function.
So it seems like a
very standard function
for parsing a JSON response.
We've got an auto
release pool around it
because it's doing a lot
of string manipulation
and we don't want to
cause memory spikes,
and then we're passing
our error back.
So the question is why is
this crashing when we get back
to our caller of process
raw data right here.
We get the error back,
and then we're trying
to store a response
process error below.
Well, just by taking
a look at the retain
and release history we'll see
that there was auto
release going on so
that we can pass objects
back to our callers.
But then those auto release
pools actually popped somewhere
in between.
In looking at that function
that we saw there was an auto
release pool written there.
So I'll talk about this
a little bit later,
but what we really needed to
do is was use a local NS error
and get that assignment
done outside
of the auto release pool.
So, the other thing I want
to show you here is using
the leaks instrument.
I'll just go ahead
and fix that typo.
And so I could just go ahead and
profile again in instruments.
[ Pause ]
I actually want to use
the leaks template.
[ Pause ]
And Instrument starts up
with both the template
with both allocation and
leaks and starts recording.
So quickly you'll notice that
we have some leaks detected
in the background.
And I can just go ahead and use
the app a little bit and sort
of get some activity going on.
And as I scroll around it
actually is interesting to type
in that WWDC prefix and
take a look at the view here
to see anything interesting
going on in our Heap.
If we zoom in we'll even notice
that like our table cells,
there's a lot of
transient cells.
It's very likely we've
done something wrong
with cell reuse use
just by looking
at these high level statistics.
And another interesting
thing here
with the retain release
view is if I select one
of these WWDC news
objects you'll notice
that Instruments was able to
quickly pair up a whole ton
of retains and releases even
pairing together retains auto
releases and releases together.
So let's take a look
at the leaks,
and I'll remove my filter.
And I'm actually interested in
a certain reachability leak.
You'll notice that
we have a bunch
of different objects
types, NS datas,
NS arrays, network reachability.
And they're all coming from
the system configuration
system library.
So are these really
our fault or not?
Well, to see if they're
related I can go to the cycles
and roots page and
see that, yes,
the SC network reachability
is a root leak,
and that this actually leaks
an NS array which leaks a list.
So that's kind of nice.
I can focus all my efforts
in that one location.
So if I click on the network
reachability object and pull
in the extended detail view, I
notice I allocate it right here
at reachability with host name.
And in Xcode this shows up as me
using an SC network reachability
with host name, and then
I create a wrapper for it
and then I release it.
So it looks like I'm
using it fine, right?
No problem at the
allocation point.
Well, if I dive right in I again
get that retain release view,
and not many retains
and releases.
Well, I'd like to pair these up
and know which one is at fault.
So we have a nice
pairing assistant
in the bottom left
that I can bring up.
And if I select different
CF retains
and CF releases it
will suggest ones
that could be possibly
be paired to it.
So in this case I have a
CF retain and a CF release,
and these look like
they're pretty paired.
And here's my malloc that I just
looked at and that CF release
that I just saw as well
so I can pair these up.
And now I very quickly
dropped everything
out of this table except
for the CF retain that's
probably unmatched.
Double click, go to source, and
here we have the INIT [phonetic]
with reachability ref.
And so we're doing a CF retain
into the reachability ref.
And well, oops, I forgot
to write into the alloc
so that's pretty easy to go fix.
So, alright, that is showing
you the Zombies template
on an iOS device and taking
a look at a couple leaks.
[ Applause ]
So first steps in applying this
to your app I'd very
much recommend
that you switch to ARC.
It gets rid of a lot of that
code that the compiler can do
for you and do very, very well,
and also run the
static analyzer.
You may have noticed there
actually are some analyzer
warnings, and had I looked
at the analyzer I may have
fixed some of those bugs
without having to do
any run time debugging.
And that's always a lot
better if you can save time.
Another thing if
you have crashes,
the Zombies template is
a great first resort.
If it doesn't catch anything,
great, continue debugging.
But if it does then you just
saved yourself a lot of time.
For leaks the back trace of
that allocation doesn't tell the
whole story, so you can't just
stop at that top level view.
You really do need to dive down,
look at the retain
release history even
when it's an object
that's managed by ARC.
And, finally, you
could save time now
by pairing those retains and
releases with the new UI.
So there's two ways to
do it as I've showed,
the manual pairing
assistant as well
as the heuristic-based
automatic pairing.
And you can see in this
screen shot that most
of them were automatically
paired, and I've got
that assistant up
giving me suggestions.
Now, I should note that
this is actually better
if you're using ARC and if
you're using no optimization.
And so why do I mention
that specifically?
Well, because by default the
profile action that I was using
from the run menu it defaults
to the release configuration.
And release is really great
if you're doing things
like performance work
and trying to find
out how your app is
spending its time.
You really want it to behave
as much as you can the same way
as you're going to ship it.
For memory tools
and memory analysis
that additional debugging
info is actually very useful.
And so you can set it by just
using the scheme editor and so
that that profile action
translates directly
to the profile action in
the scheme and just set it
to release, or set it
to debug, I'm sorry.
So with that I want
to talk about a couple
of common Objective-C issues
that you can face even under ARC
because these are the
issues that are behavioral,
structural in your code.
And there's a lot of
really powerful keywords
that the run time provides
to solve some issues.
They're both powerful, and some
of them are a little
bit dangerous.
And so I want to go through
a couple of these so that
when you see them in your
code you hopefully won't be
surprised, and you'll be able to
more quickly get to a solution.
So the first thing
is block captures.
Now, blocks are really,
really powerful,
and you can use Objective-C
objectives, dispatch objects,
many things inside them.
And when they're copied
to the Heap for things
like dispatch A sync
or as registrations they capture
those reference objects strongly
by default.
So if you use self
it will retain self,
and when the block is
destroyed it will release self.
But instance variables are
also implicitly reference self.
So this means if you have an
under bar fu [phonetic]
it's going to reference self
and use it in that way.
So let me show you
an example here.
I'm using NS Notification
Center API.
And I'm storing the observer
token in an instance variable.
Great. So self is
retaining observer token,
and then I'm sending in a block,
and that block is
roundabout retained
by the observer token as well.
But self is retained
by that block,
and so you can really quickly
see here that this leads
to retain cycle and it's
going to cause problems.
So the solution is just
to use a weak keyword
to break these cycles.
In this case we can just
define a weakly notified self
and use it inside the block.
Now, just as a note, when you
are running non-ARC you may have
to use the under
under block keyword
to also indicate don't retain.
It means that the variable can
be modified inside the block,
but it has that additional
effect under non-ARC.
So when do you need to look for
these retain cycles in blocks?
So is it all the time
or is it just sometimes?
Well, it's mostly just
persistent relationships,
so things like I showed
you, NS notifications
or error call backs or
things that recur over time.
So things like timers,
dispatch source handlers,
and that's where you
should definitely look
to using the weak keyword.
For things like one
time executions,
enumeration of an array, of
a dictionary you don't need
to use the weak keyword.
So let's talk about
weak just a little bit.
What does weak do and what
does that mean to you?
Well, weak validates
the reference
whenever it's used.
So it checks that the object
it refers to is still alive
and hasn't entered it's
dealloc on another thread.
So if the object isn't alive you
get back nil whenever you use a
weak variable.
This means you should avoid
consecutive uses, right?
If you begin transaction
on a weak variable then
you end transaction, well,
maybe only the begin
transaction went
through because your weak
reference may return nil
on the second use.
Finally, never do an arrow
to reference with weak.
And just to show you an example
of this, I can even check
if weak object then
I'll do an access
of the weak object's delegate
by an arrow reference.
If you get back nil then you've
referenced no and crashed.
So better would be to use
the dot syntax in this case
to access a delegate,
because sending a message
to nil is just fine.
Or, you can be very explicit,
and this is actually
probably the best way to go.
Just create a strong object,
promote your weak reference
and then use the strong
object in any way you see fit.
So one final note about weak.
Since it has to validate
the reference,
it's not a free thing.
So if this is in a really,
really hot loop you may want
to think about promoting
it to strong and using that
or not using weak in
that specific instance.
Which brings us to
unsafe unretained.
This is, as the name
suggests, an unsafe keyword.
But there's some risk
and there's some reward.
What it says is ARC please don't
manage this variable at all.
There's no retain when something
is stored to the variable,
no release when nil is
stored to the variable.
Important to note, though,
is if you've got legacy code
that you've sort of by
hand migrated to ARC,
if you're using property
assign this actually means
under the covers
unsafe unretained.
And so you can very
easily get crashes
because these are
dangling references
to whatever the object is.
Also keep in mind that many
of the frameworks will have
these sort of unsafe references
to your code such as
delegates or data sources.
And if you're getting a
crash where it's trying
to send a data source
message to your object
and your object is
already deallocated,
you may have just needed to
go into your dealloc and mill
out that data source
before your object went way.
So in general I would
sort of recommend this
as last resort keyword if
you have performance issues
or you need to use it
for some other reason.
So one of the key words to talk
about here is auto releasing.
And this one actually came
up with that demo example.
So for an auto releasing
variable the object has sent a
retain and then auto release
whenever assignment happens
to it.
So out parameters are
actually auto releasing
by default like NS errors.
And this means that if there's
an auto release pool wrapping
the assignment you can get
some interesting behavior,
namely crashes.
So in this case here we have an
auto release pool wrapping our
JSON use just like that.
We take that out error and we do
the assignment inside the kit.
So the assignment to that auto
releasing variable happens
inside our auto release pool.
The instant we leave our
auto release pool, well,
now that delayed release
happens immediately,
and now what we've done is we've
returned our deallocated NS
error to our caller
causing problems.
So the fix is simple.
If you write an auto
release pool write a local.
So in this case we just
need to write a local error,
send the local error
into the API,
and then do the auto
releasing assignment outside
of the auto release
pool that we wrote.
The final keyword I want to
talk about is bridge gaps.
Now, ARC is great for
managing life cycles
at the Objective-C level, but in
most of our code we still have
to use C-based APIs like core
foundation, core graphics,
things that take
void star context.
And for dealing with
there are bridge gaps.
There's three conversion
primitives,
bridge with just this type
casting, bridge transfer
which does the release,
and if you like the syntax
of CF bridging release
better you can use that,
or bridge retain which
does a retain as well.
Although I should note here
that incorrect bridging
because it's very explicit
can lead to a crash or a leak.
So how do you use
them correctly?
Well, this is the standard
way of using these.
If you're going from CF+ 1
you use a bridge transfer,
and you really should think
about your references in terms
of where the ARC
managed object is.
But I specifically want
to call out the third cast
because this is the
most dangerous.
If you're casting from an ARC
managed reference to a void star
or a CF reference,
this effectively creates an
unsafe unretained CF reference.
So what do I mean?
Well, if I have this
in a string it's
in an ARC managed reference,
I use the bridge cast,
put it in a CF reference.
Well, now anywhere in between
here if, say, the log info goes
out of scope, I never use it
again, the compiler is free
to release that variable.
And now when I go to use it
in CFURL create, boom, right?
And now it's kind of a very
strange crash inside the kit.
So for that just switch
to the fourth one.
Use bridge retained, and just
remember to CF release it later.
So I want to briefly talk
about being a good citizen
on the platform and what sort
of testing you can do for this.
So test some real
world scenarios.
Definitely test on
constrained devices.
If you're on a MAC, low memory
systems, maybe low CPUs.
If you're on an iPhone this
is just older hardware.
Test your first install
and first launch.
If you're having to build
up a database you may have
memory spikes in that case,
and these are really
good test cases.
As well as large data sets.
Everyone wants to have really
devoted and awesome users
who use your app for years,
and it's worth testing for them
that you can handle
these big things.
Also, test background
launch on iOS 7.
And to do that you can just use
the option in the launch options
to simulate a background
fetch and off you go.
And, finally, make
sure that you test
for leaks and abandoned memory.
So under system memory pressure
we've talked about this briefly,
and I'm not going to
touch on it very much.
But when pages have
to be evicted it really is
your dirty memory that matters.
And in this case on OS X these
are compressed or saved to disk.
See this talk right here
for more information,
it's really great.
And for iOS memory
warnings are issued
and processes have terminated.
So when it comes
to memory warnings
and how you can avoid
termination,
well, don't be the biggest.
Dirty memory really
is what counts.
You can use the VM Tracker to
find out how much you're using.
And make sure you get
a chance to respond.
You're not guaranteed a memory
warning, but if you get one,
and hopefully you will, it
will arrive on the main thread.
So make sure your main thread
isn't blocked for many reasons,
also user responsiveness.
And, of course, avoid
large and rapid allocations
so the system doesn't
have to act quickly.
So these are the three best ways
to respond using
the notifications
or the APIs that get called.
And you should consider freeing
up some memory before
you enter the background.
So there's the [inaudible]
for that.
So to summarize we really want
to encourage you
to be proactive.
Start with the gauges,
use Instruments,
monitor, test and investigate.
Definitely avoid memory spikes.
This will lead to fragmentation
of your application,
and avoidance is
the best policy.
And definitely don't allow
unbounded memory growth,
you set generational analysis.
There are some great
language tools for you to use.
And I hope that you make
great effective use of them.
For more information contact
our developer tools evangelist,
Dave DeLong.
And the Apple developer
forums are great.
Here's some related sessions.
I just want to specifically call
out the Building
Efficient OS X apps
so you can get a deeper
understanding of virtual memory
and how that works
on the system.
So come see us.
We'd love to help you.
And thank you very
much for coming today.
[ Applause ]