[ Silence ]
[ Applause ]
>> Good afternoon everyone.
Welcome to Continuous
Integration in Xcode 5.
My name is Andrew Nesbitt.
I am the engineering manager
on the OS X Server
part of this feature.
So as you heard in
yesterday's platform kick off,
the theme for Xcode 5
is building better apps.
And Xcode 5 is packed, full
of amazing new features
to help you share this goal.
In this afternoon, we're going
to spend our time looking at one
of those new features in
particular and that is
of course Continuous
Integration.
And hopefully you will learn
how you can use Continuous
Integration to build
better apps.
So the lineup for this
afternoon is that we will start
out with a little bit of a
terminology refresh of the some
of the key Xcode terms
that we need to know.
And after that we'll
dig right in.
We'll start exploring the
Xcode Service and we'll talk
for a while about
configuring OS X Server
for Continuous Integration.
After that we'll do a
deep dive into Xcode 5
and the band new bots
feature that we have.
And then we'll spend some time
looking at the web application
and the feature that
we call Scoreboard.
And after that we'll finish
with some best practices
that we have learned inside
Apple for deploying the service.
So the big question is why
use Continuous Integration?
Over the years, through
many iOS and OS X releases,
we have given you an enormous
toolbox of features to use.
And you guys have definitely
arisen to the challenge
by shipping amazing
applications.
And of course, shipping
amazing applications we all know
requires testing.
And as the number of OS versions
that you target and the types
of devices that you target
skill it becomes more
and more difficult to test
your applications well.
And this is where Continuous
Integration comes into play.
Continuous Integration will
give you the opportunity
to do testing on
multiple OS versions
and multiple hardware models.
Of course, once you have
a server in the mix,
you're now in the
position to build, analyze
and test your project often.
And of course, having a server
will give you the opportunity
to catch problems quickly and
this is the key automatically.
Many of you have more than
one Mac and I'm sure a lot
of you have a Mac sitting in
your office doing nothing.
And this is a great opportunity
to put that Mac back to work.
Let the server do the
heavy-lifting of building your--
building your project
automatically.
And having a server lets you
do things that you can't do
in Xcode or that you
can't do in Xcode feasibly
and the big thing here is
the ability to gather, build,
and test history for
your project over time.
And, of course, having a server
in the mix gives you an awesome
new way to distribute builds
to your team and I see some
examples about coming up.
So to get started, let's
talk for a little second
about some terminology that
you're going to need to know.
There are three key terms.
Number one is that of a scheme.
And a scheme is a very simple
concept; it's just a recipe
for building your project.
A scheme defines what
targets you're going to build,
what dependent targets
you're going to get built,
and also what build
settings will be pass
when those targets do get built.
And because we're dealing with
the server, a server needs
to have access to this
scheme information.
And schemes are typically
personal things,
I'm sure you all have a
bunch of schemes that you set
up just the way you like them.
But we're going to use a little
extended version of the scheme
and that is of a shared scheme.
And a shared scheme is
nothing more than a scheme
that has been checked in to your
source controller repository
and shared with the
rest of your team.
So that's item number one.
Number two is that of a bot.
And a bot is a configuration
for analyzing, building, testing
and archiving your
project on a schedule.
And we'll come back to
this guy in a second.
The third item of terminology
is that of an integration.
And an integration is just
a single run of a bot.
So every time your bot
runs, your bot is said
to be performing an integration
or it is integrating.
So let's look at a little bit
more detail of surrounding bots.
So like I said, a bot
is a configuration
for building your project.
A bot defines what
we're going to build.
So there are two things here.
Firstly, it defines where
the source code lives
that we are going to build.
So what repository that
source code lives in?
How are we going to
access that repository
to get that source code?
And secondly, the project
or the workspace inside
that SCM location that
we're going to access
where that project lives?
Secondly, a bot defines when
we're going to build it.
So we have some great scheduling
options in the Xcode Service.
We have periodic options so you
can build your project hourly,
daily at a time or weekly on a
day at a time of your chosen.
We have on-commit options.
So you can build when your
source repository changes
and you can tell the server
when your source repository
changes by a heap script.
Or you can have the
server periodically checked
with your SCM server when
your source code is available,
otherwise known as pulling.
And of course there's manual.
So you will-- this will
be you will run the bot
when you feel like
running the bot.
The third slice of the
bot configuration is
that of how we're going
to build your project.
And this is composed of the
shared scheme information
that you've defined
when you set up the bot,
which scheme you'd
like us to use.
And then some options, we have
some action options available
for your bot.
So you can choose whether or
not you would like your bot
to perform static analysis,
whether or not you would
like your bot to
perform testing.
And if you are performing
testing, which devices
on which you would like
to perform testing.
And we support bot testing on
the Mac which is the server.
We support testing on
simulators, we support testing
on a single device, we support
testing on multiple devices
or any other combinations
of those settings.
Where that makes sense?
Of course.
And lastly, your bot can define
whether or not you would like us
to produce an archive.
And an archive will produce both
a package and an .xcarchive file
for a Mac project or an IPA
on an .xcarchive file
for an iOS project.
We also have some great
notification settings
for the Xcode Service.
So when you set up a bot,
you got a couple of options.
So we let you notify people, we
have checked in code to that bot
so all the source controls
submissions that have been made
since that bot last run, all
those people can get notified
and you can choose whether
to notify those people
when the bot is successful
or when the bot fails.
And you can also define
lists of e-mail addresses
for people you would
like to e-mail
on those conditions as well.
So the Xcode story can
really be thought of--
the Xcode Service story can be
thought off in two parts here.
So there is OS X Server
and we have an amazing
preview releasable OX X Server,
and of course there's Xcode 5.
So let's start by digging
in to the OS X Server
part of the story first.
So in the Mountain
Lion timeframe,
we made server an application.
No longer a server, an entirely
separate operating system
that you have to set up, Server
is just an app that you purchase
and download and install
from the Mac App Store.
And it's never been simpler to
turn your Mac into a server.
And carrying on this theme of
simplicity in the next version
of Server the pre-release
that we have available.
We have some great new features.
And one of those
is simple setup.
Simple setup takes out all
the complexities setting
up your server.
No longer will you be asked a
bunch of complicated questions
about networking configurations
or Apple ID configurations,
you're asked one question
that is an administrator
user name and password.
And once you've entered that
credential, the Server is
up to the races setting
itself up
and within seconds you
have a server available
and ready to be used.
We also have some
brand new UI in server.
Server looks great,
it's never look better
and we're actually servicing
some really useful information
that we find that people
really, really want.
Like how your service
is behaving,
how to access your service
and whether your
service is on or off.
So as an example, let's
dig in to what it takes
to set up an OS X Server.
So when you launch OS X
Server, you'll see this.
And this is the Welcome
menu for the application.
And when you click
Continue, you'll be asked
for a user name and password.
And once you type those
guys in, the Server goes off
and starts doing its thing.
And very quickly you're launched
into the OS X Server
application.
And in the left you'll
see all the services
that the OS X Server
application supports.
And on the right, you'll
see the detailed view
for those services.
So before we go any further,
you're probably all wondering
about the thing that
you're here--
you're here to hear about
which is the Xcode Service.
The Xcode Service
when it's turned
on in OS X Server will
start advertising itself
across your network and it
uses Bonjour to do that.
So any Xcode 5 user
that's sitting
within your network will see
servers that are available--
that have been available, made
available in your network.
Once the service is turned on,
it's super simple to create
and manage bots that build
both Mac and iOS projects.
And if you're a little bit
fuzzy about Access settings,
we do have some great ways
to configure that too.
You can define both who
you would like to be able
to create bots on your
server and also who you would
like to be able to view
bots on your server.
And you can set this up in
whatever way that you like,
whatever way that makes
sense for your team.
We also have some really,
really great integration
with the Apple Developer
Program.
And this means that you
can join your Server
to your existing
Apple Developer team.
And the question might be well
why I would I want to do that?
And the answer is when your
Server joins your team,
your Server has the opportunity
to request its own Mac
and iOS signing identities
and also download all
of the team provisioning
profiles
that exist for your team.
And this puts us in
a great position.
And this brings me on to my
next point which is devices.
OS X Server has great
support for devices for bots.
So once your server is a
member of a developer team,
you'll see devices
in OS X Server.
You can easily add and
remove devices both to
and from your team and of
course once you've done that,
those devices become
available when people set
up bots using Xcode 5
against your Server.
Another feature that we've been
asked for a lot in OS X Server
for the last couple of years
is source control hosting
and we are adding
this feature too.
So, OS X Server will support
Hosted Git repositories
and once they're set up
with just a few clicks,
you'll have a Hosted Git
repository that's accessible
by SSH, HTTP or HTTPS.
And equally you can lock
that repository done just
the way you like it to.
[ Applause ]
And of course, if you're
not ready to make the move
to hosting your source code
in an OS X Server just yet
or you're using an external
source control system
like your hub, then OS X Server
will equally well connect
to those repositories too.
So, we can connect to remote
SVN and remote Git repositories
and we can connect to those
repositories anonymously
with username and
password or with public,
private SSH key pair
authentication.
And it's really easy
to set that up too.
So, as an example, let me take
you through what it takes to set
up the Xcode Service
in OS X Server.
So, when you go the Xcode
Service you see this,
and this is the Xcode
Service panel
and it's split into two parts.
On the left is everything
to do with bots
and configuring your
service and on the right,
the second tab is everything
to do with hosted repositories
and remote repositories that
your server can connect to.
So, let's say we want to add our
server to our development team,
what does it take to do that?
And it's really easy.
So, to do that, we click
the Add button right here
and we'll be asked for
username and password.
And the Server will go wide
to the Apple Developer Program
and figure out which teams
this Apple ID is a member of.
And because I am just a
member of one team right now,
I'm getting this
sheet which says,
"It looks like you're
a member of a team,
would you like to join
your server to this team?"
But if you're a member
of multiple teams,
let's say you're a contractor
then you'll get a list
of all the teams that
you're a member of
and you can join your server
to one or all of those teams.
You can have as many teams as
you like with the OS X Server.
Once you've added your team,
your server will set itself up
and you see that this
server is not a member
of that development team.
The next step of course
is adding some devices,
and once you plug in devices,
devices are able to
be used for bots.
So, the server is
recognized here
that this device does not
have a development that's set
and this device is
not actually enabled
for development for my team yet.
So, I'm going to click on Use
for Development right here
and the server will
quickly and easily add
that device to my team.
And as an example, we do
support source control hosting
like I said and here's
what it takes to set
up some hosting repositories.
So we can either host
it or remote repository
and you see some more of this
in our demo in a little second.
So, that is the OS X
Server part of the story
and of course there's the
Xcode 5 part and this is
where it gets really
exciting in my opinion.
Xcode 5 is an incredible
release.
If you have not downloaded Xcode
5 yet, I suggest that you go
and do so immediately,
it's really great.
And one of the nicest
features I think
in Xcode 5 is the
Testing Edition
and the new Continuous
Integration service.
So, as you go along with the
theme of Continuous Integration
in Xcode 5, there are a
couple of things that I'd
like to draw your attention to.
Firstly, we have some great
new kind of preferences.
So, it's really easy to add
an OS X Server to Xcode 5.
You open the Preferences, type
in the username and password
or choose guest if your
server administrator set it
up that way.
And you can quickly add
your server to your Xcode.
Once you've done that, you're
in a position whereby you
can create bots for project
and workspaces that you
use in Xcode every day.
Once you create a bot, the bot
show up in the log navigator
and you see our beautiful
reports
for Build and Test history.
And these reports
are not just reports,
these are fully live
interactive reports
that have great assistant
editor support.
So, you can select things
on the left in the report
and you'll see the source code
that caused that error issue
or test failure right on the
right in the assistant editor.
And of course, this affords
you to dig in to your issues,
or errors and you're
wondering to write
where they're happening too.
So you see things going wrong
in a bot and you can play
with the source code and Xcode.
We also have great multi-device
support in the Xcode Service
and we have some
really great UI in Xcode
for looking at those results.
You can see your
test results overtime
on across multiple
devices for your bot.
And for each integration
that happens
in the server you'll also see
full commit history for all
of the commits that were
included in that build.
And you'll see all of the log
files that you're familiar
within Xcode today be
produced on the server
and sent down to the client.
You have some great
ways to view download --
view and download archives
of your project right
from within Xcode.
And we also have some really
nice source control integration
that you'll see in
our demo coming up.
So to do that, I would
like to invite Brent Shank
who is a software
engineer on the Xcode team.
To come up here and show us the
Continuous Integration service.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks a lot, Andrew.
Well, I'm really excited
to be up here today,
not just because I had
five espressos this morning
but because I love this stuff.
I love unit test and I loved it
for the first time this
Continuous Integration System
that just works.
I don't know about you but I
spend a lot of time dealing
with some-- the other
systems that are out there.
And they're great but they
can be hard to set up,
they can be hard to maintain,
what we've done is super easy
to set up, it's super powerful.
Let me show you what
it looks like in Xcode.
So, the first thing
we have to do
to get Continuous Integration
working on Xcode is we have
to tell Xcode about an OS
X Server that's running the
Continuous Integration
service, the Xcode Service.
I do that by adding an
account for an OS X Server.
And as you've heard by
now, we have three types
of accounts in Xcode 5.
There's one for your Apple ID
or Apple IDs, there's accounts
for source control repositories,
and of course there are
accounts for OS X Servers.
And I access those through the
new Accounts preference pane.
Okay, well here's our beautiful
new Accounts preference pane,
you can see there, no
accounts right now.
It's really easy to add any
of those three account types.
I'm going to own account for
an OS X Server right now.
I click the Add Server button.
And as Andrew said,
any server that's set
up on your local
network is going
to be advertised via Bonjour
and you can add it that way.
You can also add a
server by host name or IP,
and that's really good
idea if you want to able
to access it from anywhere.
I'm going to select
this one on the list.
Click Next and authenticate
and here we go.
So, I've added an account for
server, it's really easy to do.
You can add as many
servers as you want,
OS X Servers that you want here.
So, what does this
enable me to do?
Well, we have some really tight
integration of source control
with the Xcode Service
and Xcode 5.
And part of where
we surface that is
in the new checkout workflow.
That's available in the
Source Control menu.
I go there now, and
I'll click Checkout.
So, what's in this table here?
Well, this is going to
show me a repository
for every source control
account that I've added
in that preference pane.
It's also going to show me
any Hosted Git repository
for an OS X Server that
I have an account for.
So as Andrew mentioned, this is
the new feature in OS X Server
that it can Host
Git repositories.
And you can see here, these
are all repositories that are
on that server that I added.
I'm going to select
BubbleGum, click Next,
it's going to authenticate
and checkout.
So that's a really great way to
get source code for your team.
So, let's see what the state
of this project is like.
I'm going to build it, and
build failed because I need
to switch to the simulator.
I'll do that now.
The build succeeded,
this is great,
let's see how the tests look.
I'll run unit tests,
the simulator launches,
the test are going to run,
and will they succeed?
They didn't, they failed.
Well, this is good, this
is what I wanted to happen.
Well, how can we use
Continuous Integration
to figure out what went wrong?
So I just checked out this
project from source control,
I didn't make any changes.
So, this means someone else
broke this test somehow.
So, let's use Continuous
Integration in bots
to figure out what went wrong.
So, we surfaced bots
from the log navigator.
And you can see there
a couple of things here
that you haven't seen
before in Xcode; Bubblegum
and Bubblegum Nightly
are both bots.
You can set up as many bots
as you want for projects,
it's really easy to do.
I'm going to show you
the bot for Bubblegum.
I'll click on that here.
So, this is the bot report.
You can see it's really
clean, it's really beautiful
and provides a lot
of great information.
So, let's go from
top to bottom here.
At the top here, any time you
want to run an integration,
you just click Integrate Now.
No problem.
Usually, bots run out of
schedule, you configure them
to run manually,
whatever you want,
whenever you want integration,
just click that button.
This button here, it will
let you download an archive
or a product that
your bot created.
And Wi-Fi let you install it
on a device that's connected
locally, that's pretty cool.
And finally, on this menu over
here, you can edit the bot,
delete the bot, do
other things with it.
And below that, in the
status counts area,
this shows you a high
level status for your bot
for the last integration that
is the last run of your bot.
So if there are any errors or
warnings, you'll see that here.
If you chose settle the bot
from-- on static analysis,
you'll see the status
of that there.
And if the bot is running
tests, you'll see the status
of those unit tests there.
Below that in the build history
chart, you see the status
of all the integrations that are
displayed here and we show you
as many integrations
as we can show you.
So, what you want to
see here is you want
to see there is a no issues
line with the green checkmark.
That means everything went well.
You build bots and there
were no errors, warnings
or static analysis issues.
But if you do have some, that's
okay, that's what this is for,
they'll show up in
this stock bars
and these colors are obvious to
you, warnings on yellow, blue--
static analysis uses-- are in
blue and errors are in red.
And I can click this bar, I can
get a little more information
about what's going on,
and there's even a button
that will take me
to the integration summary
for this integration.
Let's keep going down.
The chart below here shows me
the status of the unit tests
for all the integrations
that are displayed here
and the goal here is to see
these full high green bars.
That means you had the
unit tests, they run
and they all run successfully.
Below that in the integration
details area, this shows you all
of the crucial information
from the logs
that were created
when this bot run.
So you made-- the only sub--
logs for the build and you may
have logs for analysis issues
or test failures
if you configure your
bot to do those things.
What's really neat
about this view is
that it's fully integrated
with all of the navigation
that you used to in Xcode.
So what does that mean?
I'll make my window a
little wider here to--
so you can see that.
So that means when I open the
assistant editor which I do
from the tool bar and this is
where I get a left side
by side editor view.
The left editor essentially
acts as the master editor
when the assistant editor is
in the Reference Files Mode.
I can click one of
these failures down here
and Xcode will take me
right to the source code
where this problem occurred.
So this is a really fast
and great way to get
to the heart of the problem.
So now we're using bot to
figure out what went wrong.
We see unit tests
here and we can dig
into the bot a little
further to diagnose the issue.
I'm pretty sure Andrew
caused this problem by one
of his classic late night
integration sessions
where he wasn't as
careful as he usually
as about checking things in.
I can explore that a little bit
more if I click the bar here--
that's never happened before.
This will jump me right
into the Integration Report
and you can see there
are four tabs here.
One of the tabs is the Commits
tab and indeed when I go
to that I see the Commit Log
for this particular integration.
And looks like Andrew is
messing with me a little bit
and he deliberately
broke this field.
I'm going to go back and I'm
just going to change this
so I know that there are
actually are five tea-flavored
colors of Bubblegum here.
So I'll just change this and
I'm going to save and I'm going
to check this in so we
can run an integration
and see what that looks like.
Fixing tests, commit.
Okay. So while that's running,
let's explore the bot
report a little bit more
and to close this is another.
So there are two tabs, there is
a Summary Tab that's we've been
looking at and there's
the Test Tab
and this is a really great view
because it shows you the history
of the unit tests for
all the integrations
that we can display here.
We can display a
lot of integrations.
You saw this this morning,
this is a really great view
because it shows you at a glance
how a particular unit test is
doing and you can see most of
mine are doing really well.
I can filter this table to show
me just the ones that failed
and if there's a particular test
that's been giving you trouble
and you know its name, you
might type that in here
and filter the table even more.
Of course, over time, your
server is going to build
up history for thousands
of integrations
and you need an ability to
go back and forth in time
to check these things out.
So you can see how this
interesting trend line here
where I had most of
my unit test breaking
and then they all got better
so I can move the loop
in this graph and I can
slope just the integrations
like here about.
And these views also integrated
with the assistant editor
so I can bring it up again
and when I select a test case,
it will show me the source code
for that particular test case.
I think that's really great.
So let's jump back to the
report for the integration.
I can also see the
latest integrations
in the log navigator.
I'm going to click
this one here.
Let's just explore
this a little more.
The Summary tab is very similar
to the Summary tab
for the bot itself.
It shows you the
high level status.
It shows you the important
integration details.
There's also the Logs tab
and that shows you the
exact same Build logs
that you would see
if you performed this
particular bot run locally,
if you perform this
build locally.
So this is really great.
You can have the server
storing these logs
for thousands of integrations.
You don't have to
store them locally.
Whenever you needed that data
and you want to look at it,
Xcode will download it
for you and that's one
of the great benefits of having
a server that's performing your
continuous integration.
But let's look at the Test tab.
Starting this is the most
exciting part of this feature.
So what you can see here,
there are four devices listed.
They're actually all
right here connected
and what this means is the Xcode
Service is running unit tests
on all these devices.
Now, think about this.
There's never been a way to
do this automatically before.
There's never been a way
for Xcode to run unit tests
on multiple iOS devices at once.
And this is a huge deal.
If you want to see how your
product performs with iOS 7,
for example, whether up
on one of your devices,
plug it into your OS X Server
that's running the continues
integration service
and you'll get
to see you get a
high level overview
of how your software is
doing on that new OS.
I think that's very cool for
people who have been writing
in the test and have
a lot of time
and energy invested in them.
This is going to immediately
add a lot of value to them.
And for those of you who
haven't been writing in a test,
I think this is a
great reason to start.
And, again, this
is all connected
with the assistant editor so
you can click Test Case and jump
to the source code
and do everything you
would expect to do.
So we've explored
the bot report,
we've explored the bot
integration report,
but what does it like
to create a new bot?
And to do that-- and I
should create a new project.
I'll show you what it looks
like from the beginning.
So, I'll put in an
Xcode project,
I would just create a simple
iOS Utility Application--
I'll just call it Demo App.
So in this Safe panel
here, you probably noticed
for a while an Xcode
4 has offered
to create a local GIT
repository for this project
and that's a really
great thing to do.
But now if you've added an
account for an OS X Server
in the Accounts Prep Pane,
it will list any server here.
And if I choose this server
which I'll do and click Create,
let me draw your attention
to the Activity View up here.
What's going to happen is
Xcode is going to create
that local GIT repository.
It's going to create the remote
GIT repository and it's going
to push it up to the server.
So now you have the
best of both worlds,
you have a local GIT
repository, your Scratch Pad
and when you're ready to show
those changes into your team,
there's already a server that's
backing up your data for you,
you push those changes up there
and your team has access to it.
This is really great.
Okay. So we created a new
project, let's create a bot.
We do that in a Product Menu,
there's a Create Bot item.
So this is a new project
so there's only one scheme.
You probably have a few schemes
in your project and in order
for the bot to build
your project,
you need to share the scheme.
We can do that automatically
for you but--
and you should keep this check
but I'm going to uncheck it
so I can show you-- I want you
to understand what this means.
I'll show you how
to do this manually.
I want this bot to run my unit
tests whenever anyone checks
in codes so we'll call that,
I'm choosing the server here
and I'll uncheck that
particular button there.
Okay. While-- We'll
keep that checks
since it will let me otherwise
but I'll still let you
know, help you out.
I want this bot to
run on Commit.
Again, you have your choice here
when you want your bot to run,
and you can edit this
at any time later.
And as Andrew said, you get to
decide what you want your bot
to do so of course your
bot is always going
to build your projects.
So you're always going to know
if there are warnings or errors,
but these three other
things are optional.
You may or may not want your
bot to run static analysis,
to perform tests or
to build archives.
In this case for this bot, I
just want it to run unit tests
so I'll uncheck these two
and we perform test
action intact there.
I'll click Next, and because
I told that I want to build--
to run unit tests,
it's going to ask me
which iOS devices I
want it to run on.
I have four here and
I think they should--
the test should be
run on all of those
but you can configure
this the way you want.
I'll click Next and, again,
so what happens by default
when the build fails
is anyone who committed
since the last integration
will get an e-mail
but you can configure
this however you want.
So it's just a few
clicks and we've created
in a bot for this project.
Yes, the bot scheme
needs to be committed.
Exactly. So what
this is all about?
Well, let's go into the manage
scheme sheet here for a second
and you can see this
check box is checked
which is a good thing
in this case.
So I need the scheme
to be shared
so that the bot can
build my product
and my default schemes are
not shared so that check box
that I left checked in
the Assistant, that's good
but if you don't do that, you
can always show your scheme
into the Manage Scheme
sheet here.
I'll click Okay and when I do
that Xcode change to the files
that are involved in the
schemes so I need to commit
and push those up to the
server and you can see here
in the Commit sheet
there's these things related
to the scheme you don't need
to worry about what they are
but you do need to do this in
order for the bot field to run.
So I've committed those
changes and I can force it
to integrate now and you can
see the integration has started.
So really easy to create a
new bot with the rich sourcing
for integration that
we have with these--
these two parts of this
system that's why it's easy
to get source control
and get source code
and to push source code
back up to the server.
And I can see here,
you can't see it
but test are already running
on these devices
which is very cool.
So with that, I'm going
to give it back to Andrew
so he can show you
more about the web UI
where we surface
all these things to.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Brent.
Could we switch back
the slides, Brent?
>> Yes.
>> Please?
You get my demo away.
Okay. So, Brent just showed
you how awesome the Continuous
Integration support
as an Xcode 5.
And just to recap what you
saw, we have a newer kind
of Preferences tab and
the Preferences pane.
So it's really easy to
add and use server kinds
to the Xcode preferences.
You can connect to
servers using username
and password or as a guest.
And once you've done
that, the server shows up.
And once you have a server,
you're now in a position
whereby you can check
out the source code that's
hosted on those servers.
Xcode will automatically figure
out what source repositories
exist on the server
and offer to check those out.
So we chose the Bubblegum,
I'm going to check it out.
And by clicking in the
log navigator on the bot,
we could see the
bot summary report.
And here you see all the
beautiful test information
for your bot.
Along the top, you see
so many kinds for errors,
issues and warnings
and test results.
In the center you see summary
grafts for your build history
and your test result history.
And at the bottom you see
some integration details
for the most recent integration.
Expanding the side bar you
see each of the integrations
that this bot has performed.
I'm looking at the test results
view, you see a beautiful graph
of your test results over time
for all of your integrations.
And of course the best way is
that we support multiple
devices.
So when you click in a
particular integration and look
at the test tab for bot
integration, you'll see all
of the tests split
out by device.
You could see which
tests are passing,
which tests are failing
on which device.
And of course we have the
assistant editor support
as well.
So when you're digging around
in the test result table,
you can see the information
of the assistant
editor on the right.
Finally, Brent showed you what
it takes to set up a new project
and host out source
code on an OS X Server.
And with just a few clicks, it
created a rebuild and it was
on the server ready for him and
the rest of his team to use.
So the last thing that
I would like to talk
about today is our
web application.
And the web application
is really designed
for everyone who's involved
in the development process
that's not necessarily living
inside Xcode all day.
And I'm sure there are lot
of people that you work
with that fall in
to this category.
There are localizers,
there are testers,
there are project
managers if you're lucky
or unlucky to have one.
But the web application
becomes a really useful feature
for those people.
The web application
will give you a view
of your project outside
of Xcode.
So Xcode will only show you bots
that are relevant for projects
and workspaces that you
currently have open.
The server will give you
a server-centric view
of these projects.
So you see a list of all the
bots that live on your server.
And you can easily add and edit
bots right from the web for all
of the repositories that your
server already knows how to talk
to so those can be
host of repositories
or remote repositories
that you've already
connected up in server app.
And once you click on a bot, you
see the same beautiful reports
that we have on Xcode.
One feature that's unique to the
web application is the archive C
and admittedly this feature
that we stole from one
of our internal systems.
And this becomes the destination
place for your tester
in the morning to go and get a
list of the most recent products
or archive for your application.
So there's obviously archive
in product downloading.
But we have some really
nice features too.
There's build flagging.
So you can flag a build as being
a great build or flag a build
as being a terrible
build depending
on your definition
of being flagged.
And of course we
support build printing.
So if you know that you
have a build that's sitting
in your list that you maybe
don't want to keep around
or that you know was a
particularly bad build,
you can instantly delete
it just with one click.
And probably my favorite feature
of the web application is
that if you point an iOS device
at the web app with one tap.
You can install a
build application
from the Xcode Service
right in your iOS device.
[ Applause ]
And then we have another great
feature that we call Scoreboard.
And you've all seen it I'm sure
but I'll save that one for demo.
So with that, let's look at the
demo of the new web application
and the Xcode Service.
So here I am in Safari
and to get
to the web application you've
got a number of options.
Inside Xcode when you're looking
at the bot we have a Gear menu
and you can click on the Gear
menu there's a handy link
in there and it takes
you right to the web app.
If you have a host name for
your server and that may be,
you know, a local host name
for your server, you can visit
that hosting and it will take
you right to this web app.
And also if you're in
server app, we have a link
that takes you right
to the web app too.
So this is the bot list
for the web application.
And you'll see that we have
an alphanumeric sorted list
of the bots down the left
and you see some great
information for those bots.
We see we have a number of bots
here and a number of states.
Some bots are succeeding,
some bots are queued ready
to be built, some bots
are failing tests,
some bots actually have
catastrophic build failures
right now.
Along the top you see some
summary information for the bots
that are running on your server.
So the most recent bot that
Brent actually just created
in run, we could see
it has zero errors,
warnings, or analysis issues.
The Bubblegum Nightly
bot just kicked off
and on the right you can see
that we have handy download
links for the Bubblegum bot too.
So let's click on the
Bubblegum bot and explore
that in a little
bit more detail.
So here you see we
have the same reports
that you see inside of Xcode.
We have five great
tabs along the top,
they give you summary
information,
information about your Tests,
information about your Commits,
your Logs and of course the
Archives page which is unique
to the web application.
I can click around and just
like in Xcode I can see
the full test history
for my project right
here on the web browser.
And I can scroll back in
time just like in Xcode
to select any range of
test brought up that I'd
like to explore a
little bit more.
So you can see here
that our project went
through a particularly
rough patch of having a lot
of failing test and then
we slowly brought that back
in to zero again which is great.
That's exactly what
we wanted to do.
We have the Commits tabs and the
Logs tab which I'll skip over,
and I'll go straight
to the Archives tab
because that's the most
interesting part of this--
part of the web application.
So the Archives tab is a time
sorted list of the products
and the archives for all the
bots that live on your server.
And each bot has its
own Archive's page.
You can see that on the left
we have some great flag icons.
So I know that yesterday's
build was a great build.
We shipped the build for
WWDC of the Bubblegum app
and we know it was good so
I'm going to mark that one
as a flag build,
such a great build.
And also if have
build here that I know
that the day before yesterday
was maybe not a great build.
I can easily click the
trashcan here and just delete
that build with one click.
The other feature that we have
in the web application
is Scoreboard.
And Scoreboard is designed
for the big screen TV
or spare monitor presentation
of all the bots in your server.
So if you have an open
area in your workspace,
like a coffee area or you have
some space in your development
and this is a perfect candidate
for mounting a display in a wall
and having some fun with bots.
We do this at Apple
and this is great.
So there are two ways
to get into Scoreboard.
First, I can click on the
navigation icon right here
and you can see we
have a Scoreboard link.
But we love Scoreboard so much
that we give Scoreboard its
own top level navigation item.
And right here beside the Plus
icon I can click on Scoreboard.
And you can see this takes me
into Scoreboard for this server.
So right now we have
a number of bots
and those bots are
sorted by name.
On the left you see we
have a list of the bots
and all their states and on
the right we have a huge card
with some great information
about this bot.
Along the top you see huge kinds
for the errors, issues, warnings
and test succeeds or fails.
You see a list of the
commits that contributed
to that integration and we just
cycle through those commits.
And at the bottom you see the
device information for the tests
that we run for this button.
And as we cycle to the next bot,
you'll see some information.
And it looks like for this
bot, a number of tests were run
and at the bottom we
have a bunch of devices
on which those tests run.
And it seems like Brent kicked
off the Bubblegum bot just
before he left the stage.
And that bot just
succeeded and we can see
that that has one analysis
issue and 27 passing test
across the four devices that
are connected to our server.
This was great.
So let's switch back to slides.
So that's the web application.
The web application is designed
for everyone who is not inside
of Xcode including developers
you may be away from Xcode
at any particular time.
You see the full list of bots
that exist on your server
and you can sort and filter
that list of bots really easily.
You see the same rich reports
that you see inside of Xcode.
And of course you can dig and
drill through test history
for your product just
by scrolling a graft
box three times.
And of course we have
the Archives page.
And the Archives page is
a great way to ship builds
to the rest of your team.
Or to have one place the
people and your team can go
to every morning to download the
latest build of your project.
And, so these builds
can be flagged
or deleted at your choosing.
And of course we have
the Scoreboard feature.
And Scoreboard is great.
I would encourage you all
to set up a spare display
in your development room or if
you like, Brent and his bedroom.
And, you know, have
some fun with bot
so that makes it really fun.
So I did have some best
practices that I'd like to pass
on based on our internal
usage of the Xcode Service
with our small and
large development teams.
The first is that
if you're sitting
in the audience here thinking
yeah you know, this is well
and good, this works great for,
you know, the small iOS app
or the small mac or the apps
that are showing on stage
or any app apart from my app,
maybe your source code
is structured in a weird
and wacky way where you have to
check out multiple nested copies
of source code or you have
multiple cross reference Xcode
project files or you know,
something pretty normal,
then you'll be glad to hear
that the Xcode Service
actually supports bots
that are configured
against multiple source
control repositories.
And the answer that I would have
for you for that questions is
to structure your code in
workspaces and if you think
about this, this is the best way
that the server is going to be
in a position where it can
reassemble your source code
in a way that we can
build it the same way
that you build the
source code locally.
The second is more of a security
best practice and that is
if you are connecting
your OS X Server
to existing remote repositories
with SVN or Git repositories,
I would strongly encourage
you to use role accounts
for those repositories.
That's just generally
a good practice.
You don't necessarily want to be
entering your personal username
and password onto the server and
having the server check out code
as you that's why role
accounts were invented,
they're really good
for that purpose.
And also I would
also encourage you
to use SSH public/private
key pair authentication
and the OS X Server that
makes it really easy
to generate new public/private
key pairs and with one click,
copy the public key right to
your clipboard so you can paste
into websites like
GitHub in just a second.
The third best practice
that I have is actually
just some suggested bots.
These are bots that
we set up that we find
to be really, really useful.
So the first of those
is a non-commit bot
and this one is fairly obvious
one but if you think about it,
you will have the
supply in sitting
in your office that's doing
building, that's doing testing,
that's running static
analysis for your code base
and running your tests for every
source control change that's
made and that's a
really awesome feature.
And if you have a
slightly larger project,
you can adapt this
concept and say you would
like to have a bot that's
doing this work every hour
or once a day, that's a
really good thing to have.
The second is a Nightly
bot, Nightly bots are great.
Nightly bots can build and
archive your project just
in the same way you do locally
and it will produce a signed Mac
or a signed iOS Application
that your testers can come
in the morning and click
in one link on the web app
and download a build
ready to be tested.
So this is great.
And the third is if you are like
my team, we recently switched
to Git and we're a little
branch happy right now
so we branch for everything.
And if you branch a lot then
bots are a perfect candidate
for branching.
They're so light weight and
it's a great way to continue
to reap the benefits
of Continuous Integration
while you're using a
branching workflow.
So when you cut yourself
a branch for a feature,
create yourself a bunch of
bots and you're ready to go.
[ Applause ]
So the next question is, how
do you get these features?
And I'm guessing a lot
of you have already gone
and figured this out but let's
go through it just in case.
So the best way is to go to
developer.apple.com today
and you're going to
need three things.
The first thing is you
will need the preview list
of OS X Mavericks.
After that, you'll need the
preview the list of OS X Server
and OS X Server requires
some of the technologies
that shipping is part of
OS X Mavericks so you need
to be running server
on a Mavericks machine.
And after that, you need to
get yourself a copy of Xcode 5
and Xcode 5 will run happily
on Mountain Lion and Mavericks
and Xcode 5 will also run
happily on the same machine
or a separate machine from
the server if you want
to run a bot server locally,
that's perfectly fine.
After that, you can join
your existing ADC teams today
if you're a team agent or
team admin with no changes.
Just enter your Apple
ID and password,
your server will join your team
and everything is set to go.
And, of course, once
you've done that,
your server will obtain
signing certificates,
special signing certificates
for the server.
Your server will obtain
provisioning profiles
for all the devices that have
been registered for your team
and you can just plug the
devices that you already have
into your server and everything
will be ready and just work.
So you can quickly build iOS
projects just by plugging
in devices and entering
your Apple ID.
So, in summary, I hope--
today you've seen that the
Xcode Service and OS X Server
and Xcode 5 is really designed
to help you build better apps.
It's super simple to set up and
once you've set up these bots,
you can build and you can
catch build issues, errors,
run static analysis regularly
and importantly run your tests
and run your tests on simulators
on the Mac or run your test
in single or multiple threaded
devices to your server.
And the value of a server
is really keeping history
around for your project.
This is not something that
you can feasibly do locally
when you're running
Xcode, so being able
to keep all the build logs,
all the build products
and all the results
for your builds back
through time is a really
great asset for your team.
You'll be easily able to
distribute builds to your team
and the integration
with Xcode is amazing.
You'll have fully deep
integration in the IDE
with the Xcode Service
and of course
for everyone who's
not living in Xcode,
there's the web application and
of course there's Scoreboard
for the big screen television
presentation of the stuff.
So there are a couple
of related sessions
that I would highly encourage
you guys to go along and attend.
So later in the week we have
a dedicated testing session
for Xcode 5.
We'll be looking at some
of the really great new
testing features including some
of the integration with bots
and also there's a dedicated
source control session later
in the week too.
So with that, I would like to
thank you for you afternoon
and I hope you have a good week.
[ Applause ]
[ Silence ]