[ Silence ]
[ Applause ]
>> OK, thank you.
So, good afternoon.
My name is Thomas Goossens.
And I'm here to talk
about Scene Kit.
So Scene Kit is a framework that
was introduced last year at WWDC
and it is available on
OS X since Mountain Lion.
And the goal of this framework
is to simplify the integration
of 3D in applications.
And they can be whatever
applications like presentations,
UI, games, slideshows, data
visualizations, et cetera.
Scene Kit is built on top of
OpenGL to leverage the GPU
and it can collaborate with
other graphic technologies
like Core Image, Core
Animation, and GLKit
and then I'll talk
about that later.
Scene Kit is a high
level Objective-C API.
And basically, it
exposes a scene graph
and I will introduce what
it means right after.
For OS X Mavericks, we
introduce 20 great new features.
We will present some of them
later in this presentation.
But I will first start
with a quick recap
of Scene Kit's basics.
So for this presentation, I will
start by introducing the concept
of a scene graph, sorry.
And especially, how the scene
graph look like in Scene Kit.
Then I will show the
basics and usual steps
to start an application
that uses Scene Kit.
Then a section on
the different ways
to extend Scene Kit with OpenGL.
Then we will present some
of the new features
we have in Mavericks.
And we will conclude
with some techniques
and notes about performance.
So let's start with
the scene graph.
The scene graph approach
is the main difference
with an API like OpenGL.
With OpenGL, you call
some draw commands
and set some draw states for
every object you want to render,
one by one and you redo
this at every frame.
Scene Kit is a more declarative
API where you set up a scene,
set up some properties
of your scene
and then you let the framework
manage the rendering for you.
So the top level object
of the scene graph is
the scene represented
by the SCNScene class
and basically a scene
has a root node.
A node represents a
location in 3D space.
A node may have some child
nodes to build a hierarchy
and each node is relative
to its parent node.
So it's like layers that are
relative to their super layers
or views that are relative
to their super views.
Then a node by itself
doesn't represent anything.
I mean nothing that can
be rendered to the screen.
It's just a position on which
you can attach some attributes.
So attributes you can
attach are the following.
You can attach a geometry,
a camera, and a light.
You can share attributes
to multiple nodes.
The typical usage
is to, for example,
if you want to show the same
object to multiple locations
in your scene, you simply
attach the same geometry
to multiple nodes.
So let's get a quick
overview of these attributes.
The geometry first.
A geometry represents a surface
that can be rendered
to the screen.
It is made of triangles
that are connected together
to build the surface.
The triangles are
connected to vertices
and the vertices
may have a normal
that indicates the
direction of the surface.
And Scene Kit uses it to compute
the lighting for example.
Then the geometry may have
some texture coordinates
that control how images are
mapped onto the surface.
And to finish a geometry
has some materials
that control the final
appearance of your surface.
Including the colors
and textures.
Note that a geometry has
an array of materials
because sometimes, the geometry
is split into several elements.
For example, this teapot
here has four elements
and you can have a different
material for each element.
The second attribute are lights.
A SCNLight represents a light
source in your 3D scene.
There are different types
of lights to illuminate
from a point, in the
direction, with a cone,
or equally in every direction
with the ambient light.
To add a light to your scene,
simply set a light instance
to your node with the
light property of the node.
And then this light will
illuminate the entire scene
from this node and not only
the node it is attached to.
The last attributes are cameras.
A node with a camera
represents a point of view
that can be used
to render a scene.
So when you set up a scene, you
place your objects in 3D space
with the X, Y, Z coordinates.
And then you are free
to render that scene
from any point of view.
So to do this, you add
some nodes to your scene
and you attach a camera to it.
Then to select a point of view,
simply set one of these nodes
as the point of view
of your view
as the pointOfView property.
And for example, that's what I
do here, I added multiple nodes
to this scene and I can switch
to another point of view
like this one, or
yet another one.
Then a camera has
several parameters
to control how a scene is
projected to the screen.
For example, the field of
view, if you want to increase
or decrease a perspective.
So for example, here is
a narrow field of view,
so almost no perspective and
here is a wide field of view
with a strong perspective.
So to sum up, a scene is made of
nodes that can have child nodes.
Then these nodes just
represent locations
and you can attach
attributes to them.
For example, a geometry,
if I want to render
something to the screen.
Then I can configure the
materials of my geometries
to customize the appearance.
And I can attach
other attributes
like for example here, I
attach a light to the sun
to illuminate from the sun.
So you know-- with this
you know everything
about the models of Scene Kit.
Now, let's see how to start
an application that uses it.
So the first thing you will need
to do is to render somewhere.
And for this, Scene Kit provides
a SCNView if you want to render
into a view, a SCNLayer if you
want to render into a layer
and a SCNRenderer if
you want to render
into an offscreen framebuffer.
So let's consider the simplest
and fastest which is a SCNView.
To create a SCNView, simply
drag and drop the SCNView object
from the library of
Interface Builder.
Drag this to your user
interface and you are done.
Once you have your view ready,
you will need a scene
to put into.
And to create a scene,
you have two options.
You can create everything
programmatically.
Or you can load a
scene from a file.
So let's see the first option.
So to create a scene
programmatically,
Scene Kit provides a set of
built-in primitives like a cube,
a plain sphere, et cetera that
you can create and configure
with simple parameters
like width, length, height,
corner radius, segment
count, et cetera.
Scene Kit also supports 3D
text with the SCNText class.
And this supports a text
that use an extrusion,
multiple materials, a chamfer,
and new in Mavericks even the
curve you want for the chamfer
if you want to create
really fancy text.
And regarding the layout,
it supports everything
Core Text supports.
So all the fonts, kerning,
ligature, and things like that.
Then, new in Mavericks,
we introduce SCNShape.
A SCNShape lets you create a
3D object from a Bezier path.
So Scene Kit takes your
NSBezierPath and it extrudes it
to create a 3D object.
So to do this, instantiate
to SCNShape object
and give your Bezier path
and an extrusion depth.
Optionally, you can even provide
the curve you want for a chamfer
if you want a chamfer.
And that's it.
So for example, here is a Bezier
path that represents the map
of the second floor
of the Moscone.
I can use SCNShape to
create a 3D version of it.
And same thing for the
walls here, they are created
from another Bezier
path with SCNShape.
The last way to create things
programmatically is using
custom geometry.
So using the SCNGeometry class,
you can provide the vertex,
normals and texture
coordinates you want
to create your pure
custom geometry.
And so you have the full
control and you will need this,
for example, if you want
to represent some mathematical
functions or any kind
of data visualization
for example.
So that's for creating
scenes programmatically.
Now, the other way is to
load a scene from a file.
And loading a scene
from a file is essential
because complex scenes
are really hard
to create programmatically.
Complex geometries and complex
animations are usually created
using very specialized tools.
Scene Kit allows you to load
3D scenes from DAE documents.
A DAE document is an XML
file, XML-based format,
that is supported by all the
major 3D tools like 3ds Max,
Maya, Modo, Cinema
4D, et cetera.
A DAE document can describe a
lot of things in a 3D scene.
Obviously, you can describe
the geometry information
but also some animations,
reference to images,
all the light settings, the
different points of view
and even some more advanced
features like skinning
and morphing, and I will
talk about that later.
So DAE documents are
well supported on OS X.
You can open them in
Preview or with Quick Look
to get a preview of it.
We can directly see it
in Finder for example.
And you can do even
more with Xcode.
Indeed, Xcode has a
Scene Kit editor built-in
and this editor will let
you preview a 3D file,
play the animations, inspect
the scene graph, rename nodes,
duplicate nodes if you want.
Edit the materials,
configure the lighting,
change the point
of view, et cetera.
Once you are happy with your
scene, it's easy to load it
into your application.
Usually the first
step is to get the URL
to your document using NSBundle
and once you get the URL,
simply load that scene with
sceneWithURL:options:error:
and you will get
your scene created.
Once you have your scene,
it's easy also to render it.
Simply assign this scene to your
view using the scene property.
Same thing if you use a
SCNLayer or SCNRenderer.
And then, any modification
you do
on the scene graph automatically
reflects into the view.
There is no need to call some
update or setNeedsDisplay:
methods it's all automatic.
So let's see what kind of
modification you can do.
So the scene graph API
will let you do everything.
You can of course move, scale,
and rotate your objects,
add some animations, change the
colors and images dynamically,
change the lighting,
duplicate objects, et cetera.
And all of these are simply done
by modifying Objective-C
properties
of the objects of
the scene graph.
So the usual first step is
to retrieve the node you want
to manipulate with its
name and this is done
with
childNodeWithName:recursively:.
You can do it for
instance starting
from the root node
since it's recursive.
And once you get the node
you are interested in,
you can modify everything with
simple Objective-C properties.
For example, if you want
to move it to the origin,
set this position to
the vector (0,0,0).
And from the node you have
access to the attributes
like geometry, camera and light.
And from the geometry, you also
have access to the materials.
But you can do more than
simply modifying positions,
you can also animate
everything in your scene.
And for animations, Scene Kit
includes an animation engine
and regarding the API, it uses
the same programming model
as Core Animation with implicit
and explicit animations.
And actually, all the properties
of the scene graph are
animatable implicitly
and explicitly.
So implicit animations
are the animations
that are automatically generated
when you modify the
properties of the scene.
It works like Core Animation.
You start a transaction
and configure the animation
duration and timing function.
Note that here, you have
to use SCNTransaction
and not CATransaction.
And then inside the transaction,
you can modify whatever
property you like.
For example here, I
modify the opacity
and the rotation of my node.
And when you are done,
commit the transaction
and the animation
automatically--
is automatically triggered.
Then explicit animations,
this time we don't
introduce any new API.
We simply use the objects
from Core Animation.
So we support CABasicAnimation,
CAKeyframeAnimation,
and CAAnimationGroup.
For example, here
I create a simple--
a basic animation that targets
the rotation of my node.
Then I configure its
duration and destination value
and set it to repeat forever.
Finally, I add my animation
to my node with the same API
as Core Animation which
is addAnimation:forKey:.
And this makes my node to
animate forever like this.
OK. But you can do
more than just moving
and rotating around your nodes.
And the materials in particular
are something very powerful.
A material controls the
appearance of the surface.
It's represented by
the SCNMaterial class.
And the material is made
of material properties
that can contain a
color or an image.
So let me explain this.
A material is made of the
eight following properties.
And each of them has
a very specific role
in the final appearance
of your material.
The diffuse is the base
color of your material.
It's what the material reflects
when it is hit by some light.
It can be set to a color like
here, if I set to blue color
or it can be set to an image
like this earth texture.
Then the ambient property is
what the material reflects
when it is hit by
the ambient light.
For example here, it lets me
make the parts of the sphere
that are black because
they don't receive light
to show the earth
texture a little bit,
thanks to the ambient lighting.
Then the specular and shininess
control the specular highlight
and can be set to a color like
this or an image like here
if I want some part of
my materials to be shiny
and some other to be not shiny.
Then the normal property
lets me make--
set a normal map which
is a popular technique
to add some details to a surface
without adding more polygons.
For example here, I use one
to add some elevation to my--
to the mountains, to add
some bumps to the sphere.
Then the reflective is an image
or a cube map that is used
as a reflective environment.
For example here, I use a
simple image like this one
to add some sort of
glossy reflection.
This image is reflected
by the sphere and note
that it combines well with
the normal map as well.
Then the emission is a color
or an image that is emissive.
That means that it doesn't need
to receive any light
to be visible.
For example here, I set an image
that represents the lights
emitted by big cities.
So it's not very visible here
but if I switch off the lights,
you can see that the
other properties go away
and the emission
is still visible.
Now, let's switch
back the lights on.
Let's say, I want now
to add some clouds
over the earth model.
I can do it by adding a
sphere over the earth.
And then, use the transparent
property and set an image
that will control the
transparent areas of my surface.
You can use an image with colors
and gray scales if you want,
it's not just a binary image.
And last, the multiply
property is a color or an image
that is multiplied
to the material color
to produce the final fragment.
It is usually used
for shadow maps
and we'll talk about it later.
But you can also use it
to dim or tint an object.
For example, if I set a
yellow color, it is multiplied
with my material to
add a yellow tint.
And once your material
is configured,
it automatically adapts
depending on the light settings.
So if I switch off
the light again,
you can see that
the diffuse, ambient
and specular are
not here anymore
because there is no
light to reflect.
But the emission is still
emissive, this time,
it is tinted by the
multiply property.
And the clouds are still there
but this time they render black
because there is no
more light to reflect.
Regarding the API,
it's straightforward.
You can have-- you can access
the geometry from your node
with the geometry property.
To create a new material, simply
instantiate a SCNMaterial object
and set its diffuse, for
example here to a red color.
And finally, you can
assign your material
to your geometry to
make it look red.
As I said, every material
property can be set
to a color or an image.
But it can also actually
be set to a layer tree
which is very handy if you want
to have some animated content
mapped onto your 3D objects.
For example here, I
set a movie layer--
I use a movie layer to play a
movie mapped onto my 3D objects.
[laughter] And also, once
we have set your layer tree,
you can add child
layers and everything.
As soon as you modify any layer,
Scene Kit will automatically
redraw the scene.
You don't have to, again,
to call some setNeedsDisplay:
yourself.
So we can do already
a lot of things
with Scene Kit's
high level APIs.
But sometimes, it's--
if you want to do some
really specific task
or some more specific rendering,
it can still be useful
to have access to the lower
level which is OpenGL.
And Scene Kit provides the
necessary hooks for you
to plug your OpenGL
code to Scene Kit.
So Scene Kit allows you to plug
your code at several levels,
which are the scene level, the
node level, and material level.
And new in Mavericks,
we introduce the concept
of shader modifiers.
Let's start with the
first one, the scene.
So we can set a delegate
to the SCNView, SCNLayer,
and SCNRenderer, sorry, and your
delegate will be invoked before
and after the scene rendered.
And so, you can at
this-- in your delegate,
you can do whatever
OpenGL code, for example,
to do some procedural
background with OpenGL,
or any kind of overlay
with OpenGL.
And here, you are totally
free of constraints,
you can do whatever OpenGL code.
The context will
be already ready
and the viewport will
be already set for you.
Then at the node level,
this time you attach
a delegate to a node.
And Scene Kit will
invoke your code
when this node needs
to be rendered.
Scene Kit provides the necessary
information for you to render
at the correct location
in the scene.
For example, here we added a
node on top of the hole object
and set a delegate
that renders some kind
of custom particular
system with OpenGL.
And note that when you
set a delegate to a node,
it replaces Scene
Kit's rendering.
So the typical usage
is to set a delegate
to an empty node where-- that
is placed at the location
where you want your custom
effect to be rendered.
Another example of a particle
system, this time attached
to a child node of the
sword object and so,
you can see that
when the sword moves,
the emitter of the particule
system moves accordingly.
Next hook, at the
material level.
This time, you can provide
your custom GLSL program
to replace Scene Kit's shaders.
Scene Kit provides the
necessary geometry attributes--
sorry, the necessary transform
uniforms and geometry attributes
that you will plug to your
custom uniform and attributes
in your custom shader.
For example here, we
set a custom program
with a custom vertex shader
that does the morphing effect,
and a custom fragment shader
that does the smoke effect.
Note that in Mavericks, we
added some new APIs for you
to bind your custom uniforms
and custom attributes
in a more efficient
manner basically
by using blocks instead
of delegate methods.
So with a customer
material, you can--
we have a very fine
control on the rendering
because it's your
custom shaders.
However, the main
inconvenient is that you need
to reimplement everything
in your GLSL program including
projecting the vertex,
computing the lighting,
and managing the texture.
So that's for these reasons
that we introduce the concept
of shader modifiers
in Mavericks.
And the idea here is to
let you inject some snippet
of GLSL directly inside
Scene Kit's shaders.
And you do it at some very
specific stages and it combines
with Scene Kit's rendering.
So we call these
stages entry points
and the API looks like this.
Basically, you set a dictionary
to the shaderModifiers property
of your materials and the keys
of the dictionary
are the entry points
and the values are
your GLSL code.
Let's take a very
simple example.
At every entry points, you
have access to some data--
to some GLSL structures
that you can read or write
to modify the rendering.
For example here, you can
read the current output color
and modify it the way
you want with GLSL.
For example here, to do a
simple invert for example.
So Scene Kits provides four
entry points which are geometry,
surface, lighting, and fragment.
And the geometry entry point
lets you modify all the geometry
information in model space
so you can modify the vertex,
the normal and texture
coordinates in GLSL.
So for example here, I
can inject a little code
that just modifies the
Y position of my vertex
to do this wave affect.
And so, you don't have to
reimplement all the rest,
all the lighting and
all the textures.
You just focus on
the effect you want.
The surface entry point let
you modify all the surface
attributes which are
the diffuse, ambient,
specular, et cetera in GLSL.
For example here, we
did a car paint effect
by injecting a simple code
that modifies these properties.
So it generates some random
flakes by modifying the emission
and diffuse property
of the materials.
But all the rest, all the
geometry and all the lighting
and all that are still
done by Scene Kit.
Then the lighting entry point
lets you change the lighting
equation that is
applied for each light.
For example, here is a basic
rendering done by Scene Kit.
And here is a shader
modifier, so another equation
to do some sort of
cartoonish rendering.
And the last one is the
fragment entry point.
And this is the very last stage.
So at this stage, you have
access to all the information
from the previous stages like
all the surface information,
the lighting, et cetera.
You also have access to
the current fragment color,
and you can modify
it the way you want
to produce your custom
fragment effect.
So for example, here is the
default rendering in Scene Kit,
and here, a fragment modifier
that does an x-ray effect.
And this is done simply
by changing the opacity
of the fragment based on
the normal of the object.
And the color is just
simply set to a blue color.
Of course, you can combine
all of these effects
into a single dictionary.
For example here this virus
has a geometry modifier
to do the deformation, a
surface to do the noise effect.
The lighting is tweaked as well
to do some sort of
back lighting.
And the-- and with the fragment
modifier to do this kind
of hologram effect on top of it.
Regarding the API, you can set
a shader modifier dictionary
to the objects that implement
the SCNShadable protocol.
So basically, the
material, SCNGeometry
and all the geometry subclasses.
And one thing very useful
that I didn't talk about is
that you can even declare your
own uniform in your GLSL code.
And these uniforms are
automatically bound
to Objective-C.
That means that you can set the
values using Objective-C KVC
to your uniform and you can also
even animate your uniform using
implicit and explicit
animations with Core Animation.
Another thing that's
very handy is
that you can even declare
your custom texture sampler
in your shaders.
And these samplers are
also automatically bound
to your Objective-C code.
That means that you can still
use KVC to set your texture
by simply setting a
material property instance
to your sampler in
your GLSL code.
And since it is a
material property,
it works with images
and also with layers.
So the shader modifiers are
a very powerful new feature.
Now, I am calling Amaury to talk
about the other features
we added to OS X Mavericks.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> So hello.
My name is Amaury and
I'm a software engineer
in the Scene Kit team.
Thomas just showed you
the shader modifiers.
They are a fantastic tool
to bend Scene Kit
to your own needs.
And we added many more
new features in Mavericks
to help you build
better applications.
Today, I would like to talk
about six of these new features.
First is morphing.
Morphing is a popular
technique used
to animate objects
and deform them.
It works by interpolating
between a base geometry,
the geometry of your node,
and one or more morph targets.
So for instance, here I have a
geometry that represents a map.
I also happen to have
two other versions
of this geometry named
Target A and Target B.
I will use these
targets as morph targets.
So for instance, if I
increase influence of Target A,
the map is folded like this.
I can also use Target B
to fold the map like this.
And as you can see, this
is fully animatable.
You can smoothly transition
from one state to the other.
And of course, you can use
both targets at the same time
to combine their effects.
So, how does it work?
Scene Kit exposes the SCNMorpher
class to deal with morphing.
All the morphing information
and animations can be loaded
from a DAE file or
you can create
everything programmatically.
It's really up to you.
You can also use any kind of
geometry for your morph targets
as long as their
topology matches the one
of the base geometry, that is
to mean they have the exact
same number of vertices
and the same triangulation.
So that is morphing, and you
might want to use this feature
for say, animate a face with
different facial expressions
for your morph targets.
The second new feature
is skinning.
Skinning is a very
popular technique used
to animate objects
and characters.
It works by attaching
a skeleton made
of joints and bones to a node.
To better understand this,
let's show the skeleton used
to animate this character.
A skeleton is nothing more
than a node hierarchy.
The nodes being called joints
and the segment from a joint
to its parent, a bone.
You can simply animate the
character by moving the joints.
So, let's hide the skeleton
and play another animation.
How does it work?
3D authoring tools will
help you design the skeleton
and your animations, and this
information can be loaded
into Scene Kit via a DAE file.
You can also programmatically
set--
dynamically set the skeleton
of a node and move the joints.
[ Pause ]
Next, depth of field.
This is our third new feature.
We added a few properties
on SCNCamera
to provide a depth
of field effect.
The main two properties
are the focal distance
and the focal blur radius.
So, let's have a look.
The depth of field effect allows
you to blur areas in your scene.
The focal distance is a
distance from the camera
at which objects should be sharp
and the focal blur radius is the
amount of blur you want to use
for objects that
are out of focus.
So, for instance, if I increase
the focal distance the objects
in the background are
now sharp as the ones
in the foreground are blurred.
I can animate the focal distance
and look how the rook
stands out of the scene.
This is really beautiful.
And we worked really hard
to make this advance technique
both easy to use and efficient.
You can just-- right after
this session you can open your
projects and add a depth of
field effect and with no more
than two lines of
code and no effort
from your part you will make
any scene more beautiful.
So, our fourth new
feature is the support
of Core Image filters.
We added this support
in OS X Mavericks
and you might already
know how to use it
because it's the exact
same API as on CALayer.
You simply provide Scene
Kit with an array of filters
and they are automatically
applied.
So, let's take an example.
Here, I have a grid of objects
and let's say they are part
of a 3D application
with a 3D UI.
You want the user to be able to
make a selection and you want
to highlight this selection.
This can be done using a
CIFilter, a glow filter.
If I remove the filter
from one node and apply it
to another node, I can
move the selection.
And notice how the glow effect
exactly follows the shape
of the object even
when it's rotating.
This is because Core Image
filters work in screen space.
This kind of effect
would be really hard
to achieve in 3D space.
Also, Core Image filters apply
on the whole node hierarchy.
So for instance, if I group all
the objects in the background
under our common part and
set a filter on this parent,
they all get this old TV effect.
And of course, you can use
any of the built-in CI filters
or you can create your
own custom filter written
with your own kernel.
So, that is Core Image filters
and we think they will be
really useful for 3D UIs.
[ Applause ]
Next, our fourth feature-- our
fifth feature is constraints.
Scene Kit gives you
a lot of freedom.
You can manipulate your
nodes in any way you want
and you can even animate them
either explicitly or implicitly.
But sometimes, this
is not enough.
There are some kinds
of behaviors
that you cannot implement.
So that's why in
Mavericks, we add a new way
to manipulate your
nodes via constraints.
Constraints are applied
at render time
and at every frame
automatically.
The result of evaluating a
constraint is not destructive.
The result is used only
for presentation purposes
and do not modify
the model values.
So, Scene Kit exposes the
SCNTransformConstraint class
to allow you to freely
manipulate the transform
of a node.
You can create a constraint
by providing a block of code
that will automatically get
executed at render time.
And this-- and in this block of
code, you can provide Scene Kit
with any transform you want and
it's the one that will be used.
We also provide you with
the SCNLookAtConstraint.
As its name suggests, it is
really useful when you want
to make a node always look in
the direction of another node.
So let's take an example here.
I have a ball and
several arrows.
I will add a "look at"
constraint to each arrow
in the scene so that they look
at the ball in the middle.
And because constraints are
evaluated at render time
and for every frame,
if I animate the ball,
the arrows keep looking
towards it automatically.
And because constraints
apply on a node,
I can also apply this kind
of constraint on the node
that holds the camera so that
it looks towards the ball.
And you can also use it
to direct the spot light.
[ Applause ]
So the last new feature
I wanted to talk
about is animation events.
When dealing with
explicit animations,
it might be really useful
to trigger some actions
at some specific
moments in the animation.
An animation event is nothing
more than a block of code
that gets executed
automatically.
For instance, here I will have
an animation that plays a sound.
I will play it again.
Here, we set an event that will
be triggered when the middle
of the animation is reached.
OK. And because animation
events take every parameter
of the animation into account
such as the timing function,
the speed factor and the repeat
count, if I have one animation
with only one event but set
this animation to repeat,
the block of code will be
triggered several times.
And because you can provide
several animation events,
you can have one animation
with different events
that play different sounds.
So these were six
of the new features
that will help you build
new kinds of applications.
It will-- they will allow
you to make more dynamic
and more beautiful scenes.
But you also want to achieve
the best performance, right?
So in Mavericks,
we add a new tool
to help you debug
performance issues.
By setting the showsStatistics
property to YES on a scene view,
you will make an overlay appear.
This overlay provides you
with a lot of information
about what's going
on in the scene.
One of the most important
indicators is the FPS counter.
Your quest is to always
have this display 60 frames
per second.
So, if you click on the
little gear icon next
to the FPS counter, it
will show a debug panel.
In this debug panel
you can do things
such as showing the bounding
boxes, tweaking the parameters
of the depth of field effect,
dynamically change the point
of view and you can also
freeze the rendering,
and go through the steps--
go through the steps
of the rendering process
one step at a time.
So, using the slider, you can
see the rendering process draw
call by draw call.
In the overlay, you can also
check the number of vertices,
polygons and draw calls.
We want always this numbers
to be as low as possible
to achieve the best
performances.
So how can you do that?
Well, you might not be able to
reduce the number of vertices
without affecting the
quality of your scene.
But you might be able to reduce
the number of draw calls.
And this is what the
flattenedClone method is for.
It works by taking a node
hierarchy and making a copy
of it that will render exactly
the same but which is flat,
which has no child node.
So for instance, here I have a
parent node with four children.
These children have a total
of eleven geometry elements
but they use only
four materials.
The orange one, the blue one,
the purple one and the red one.
If I flatten this node, the
method will go through each node
and merge all the geometries
into one single geometry
that will have as many
geometry elements as materials.
So here instead of having eleven
draw calls, we have only four
which is a huge win
performance wise.
So what about geometries?
In Scene Kit, all the geometry--
all the node attributes
are shared by default.
The camera, the light,
the geometry,
the skinner, the morpher.
And this is a good
thing in general.
But say, you want to duplicate
a node and change its materials.
Because the geometry is shared,
if you change its materials,
it would reflect
everywhere in the scene.
So, to fix this issue you
have to unshare the geometry
by explicitly copying it.
But the good news is
that copying a geometry
is really cheap.
This is because all the vertices
and triangulation
information is immutable.
So Scene Kit doesn't
have to copy them.
So once you have
a copied geometry,
you can change its materials
without affecting the
other nodes in the scene.
So, that was about node
hierarchies and geometries.
Now, materials.
It's really important
to keep your shaders
as simple as possible.
This is not only true
for your custom programs
and shader modifiers,
it's also true
for Scene Kit's default
rendering.
The more lights in your scene,
the most expensive
the shader will be.
So, a good idea is to
keep the number of lights
in your scene as
low as possible.
But what if you can't?
What if you want a richer
lighting with many lights?
Well, a good idea would be
to pre-compute all the
lighting information
and bake them into textures.
And it's the same
idea for shadows.
Dynamic shadows are
really expensive.
Whereas pre-computed
shadows are fast
and they might even look better.
3D authoring tools will
help you bake this lighting
and shadow information into
textures and they can be loaded
from DAE files
or set programmatically
using the multiply property
of a material.
So let's take an example here.
Let's say I have a scene
that represents a dungeon.
It is lit by only one light, and
because there is only one light
in the scene, it's
very fast to render.
But it doesn't look
that great, right?
So, you might want a
richer lighting here.
So instead of adding one dynamic
light, let's say per candle,
we'll bake this into
textures using a 3D tool.
So, the first step is to
get rid of all the lights.
This is the same scene rendered
with no lighting at all.
Next, we will apply a light
map using the multiply property
to achieve this.
See, you have colored
lights, shadows
and the scene looks much nicer.
It's richer.
And in fact, this is
actually faster to render
than the first seen
with only one light.
So, light maps and shadow maps.
What about textures?
Well, one of obvious
thing is that you want
to avoid unnecessary
large images.
If a texture is never to be
rendered large on the screen,
then it shouldn't be
large in the first place.
Second, if you plan on using
the same image on ambient
and diffuse properties then
you should let Scene Kit know
so that it can optimize
its shaders.
And finally, you might
consider using mipmaps.
When activated, Scene Kit will
pre-compute several resolutions
of the image and select the
best resolution at render time.
This makes things more
efficient but it has a cost.
Pre-computing the mipmaps is a
bit expensive, so you might want
to use this feature if you
need faster rendering more
than faster setup.
The last thing I wanted to
talk about is levels of detail.
This is a feature that only
focuses on performance.
Here, you have two
objects that represent--
two geometries that
represent the same object.
As you can see, one is high res
and one is-- and one is low res.
And you can easy tell the
difference between the two.
But if I move these
objects very far
at some point it becomes
hard to tell which is which.
So, the idea behind
levels of detail is
to build several versions
of a single geometry
with different polygon counts.
This is actually a new
feature in OS X Mavericks
and Scene Kit exposes the
SCNLevelOfDetail class.
This class encapsulates
a geometry that is used
for a specific resolution as
well as a minimal distance
from the camera at which
this resolution can be used.
You then simply set a--
set an array of levels
of detail on a geometry.
So in this scene, I duplicate
this teapot many, many times.
If we hadn't activated levels
of detail, there would be more
than seven million
polygons in the scene
which would kill
the performance.
But thanks to levels of detail,
Scene Kit rarely uses
the best resolution.
And since the objects
in the background only have 256
polygons it makes rendering this
scene possible.
So that was about the new
features in OS X Mavericks
and now I hand over to Thomas
to-- for a quick recap.
>> Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> So yes to conclude,
so we presented some
of the new features we
added to this release.
We talked a little
bit about performance
and the new tools we have
to help you debug the
performance issues,
and also the new APIs that will
help you improve the performance
of your scene.
There are actually
many other new features
that we didn't have the time
to cover today, like exporting
to a DAE document for example.
We also support OpenGL's
Core Profile,
if you want to do
some really late--
use the latest features
of OpenGL.
And more. And I encourage
you to have a look
to these new features
in the seed.
And you probably guessed
that this presentation was
entirely written using Scene Kit
from the beginning
and we are very happy
to share this code
with you today.
[ Applause ]
So this code will be available
right after the session.
It is made as one single
file per slide so it's--
every time it's a simple file.
And this is kind of a collection
of fifty small sample codes
and every file is
independent of the other,
so I really think it's a
really good sample code
to get started with Scene Kit.
For more information,
please contact our
evangelist, Allan Schaffer.
We also have some documentation
online on the developer website.
And the developer forum is also
a good place to ask questions
and get answers and we
are very responsive on it.
So that's about it
and thanks for coming.
[ Applause ]