[ Silence ]
>> All right.
Hi, everyone and
welcome to this session,
Getting to Know Web Inspector.
It's the first of two sessions
today about Web Inspector.
The second session is
right after this one
and this session serves as an
introduction to Web Inspector.
So, if you haven't
used this tool before
or only occasionally, this is a
good talk to really get started
and get your hands on the tool.
So, my name is Antoine
[phonetic].
I'm an engineer in the
Safari and WebKit Team
and more specifically,
I work on Web Inspector
which hopefully makes me an--
a relevant speaker
for this session.
I really, really love
working on Web Inspector.
And the reason I love it so
much is that I've been involved
with Web Technologies my
entire professional career.
And some may not
remember that time,
but there was a time before
Web Inspector or tools
of that [inaudible], of
that kind, didn't exist.
And that time was a lot more
painful than it is today.
And so, let me tell
you how things used
to work before Web Inspector.
You'd be working on your
web content, your web app,
your website, whatever
it is that you're using
and that's being
powered by web content.
And you encounter an issue
and you try to fix it
and take your best guess as
to what the issues might be
in your HTML or your CSS or
your JavaScript, and so you'd be
in your Text Editor, scratch
your head a little bit
and then eventually you think,
"Okay, I think I got it.
If I change this
thing, type this in,
everything will look
much better."
And then what you would
have to do is you would have
to switch context, go back
to the browser, hit Command-R
to refresh the page after
the changes you've made
in the Text Editor.
And that's just not
an ideal scenario
because wouldn't it be
great if you could stay
in the same tool at all times?
And going back to about
a couple of years ago,
that workflow was
also appropriate
if you were developing an iOS
app and you're using UIWebView
to show-- to power some
of the user interface
of your application.
And you'd be using web
content and you'd be in Xcode,
changing that web content.
And this time, instead of
just switching to a browser
and refreshing, you'd have
to actually rebuild your app
to send it back down
to the device again,
and that would start kind
of a lengthy process.
Xcode will package the content,
compile any code
that's required,
send it down to the device,
and it's kind of lengthy.
And so all the time,
whether it's coming
from your Text Editor or from
Xcode waiting for your app
to be downloaded to the
device, you don't really know
if the changes you've made are
actually the correct changes.
And then once the
content finally loads,
you have to start a
little treasure hunt to get
to the point of your
app or web content
where you think the issue arose.
And so you keep going,
you cross your fingers,
you finally get there,
and unfortunately,
the bug is still
very much there.
So, every time that happens,
there's just a little bit
more added frustration
and it's just not
a good experience.
And so that whole scenario is
the reason why we're making
Web Inspector.
Web Inspector is the
Safari developer tool
to help you diagnose,
inspect, analyze,
and fix any issue you may
find in your web content.
And what's really cool about Web
Inspector is that it's a tool
that runs on your Mac and
you can target Safari on Mac,
but it applies just as
well to Safari on iOS
and your native app running
on iOS using UIWebView.
And even though in this talk,
we'll be using iOS mostly
as a target, always remember
that any feature you see
will apply just as well
to your native app on
iOS or Safari on a Mac.
And so, the way we can remotely
inspect pages on iOS devices is
that you can just run Safari
on your Mac, get your iPad
or any kind of iOS
device running Safari,
tether it up to your Mac and
then that's all you really need.
You're ready to go and you
can remotely inspect your
iOS content.
And you may have any number
of devices, or in fact,
you may be inspecting simulator
so that you're just
working on your workstation.
And this applies not just to iOS
Safari but also your native app
that you built yourself, send it
down to the device
using UIWebView.
Okay, once you've set up,
this is what you'll see.
This is Web Inspector.
And I think just like
any developer tool,
because these tools are
developed for power users
and developer will spend a
lot of time using those tools
to make their life better,
this might seem just
a little bit daunting.
We try to provide a lot
of great functionality,
and at first glance, maybe it's
a little bit tough to get into.
And so in this session,
we're going to drill
into this user interface and I'm
going to walk you through it,
give you a little
guidance to show you how
to use it the best way possible.
So, we'll start this
session with an overview
of the user interface and then
we'll take a really hands-on
approach so that you can learn
about some of the core features
of Web Inspector applied
to three core tasks.
The first one is something I
like to call Inspection Tweaking
where we'll be experimenting
with CSS in our DOM structure
to change the layout and
presentation of our page.
And then we'll start analyzing
the network performance
of our page trying to make the
load time of our page the best
as it can be or rather
analyze it
to figure out what's going on.
And finally, we'll get into
code debugging, trying to work
out some errors and some
JavaScript that we wrote.
So, I'd like to begin with an
overview of the user interface.
And to get started, I'd like
to jump straight to a demo
so we can just see it in action.
Okay, so Web Inspector is
not on by default in Safari.
It's a developer tool
and we want developer-specific
functionalities of Safari
to only be available
when they're needed.
So, let me show you
how to turn it on.
I'm going to switch to
Safari and I'm going to bring
up the preferences, and let
me zoom in just a little bit
so it's up more obvious.
We're going to switch to
the Advanced tab and right
at the bottom, right here,
there's a special menu item
called Show Develop Menu
and Menu Bar.
And as I zoom out and turn
it on and off, you'll notice
in the Menu bar that a
new menu item is going
to show up called Develop.
Okay, so we want to keep
it on, and at the moment,
that's all we need
to do in Safari.
Next, I'm going to switch
to the iOS Simulator.
Again, I'll be using Simulator
on stage but this will work just
as well with an actual
iOS device
or several iOS devices
connected to your workstation.
Okay, so in this case, what I
need to do is go into Settings,
then Safari, scroll down to
the bottom to the Advanced Menu
and turn on the Web
Inspector item right here.
What that means now
is that this device,
or rather the Simulator
can be a target
for Web Inspector running
in Safari on the Mac.
Okay, let's go back
to the home screen.
And now, what I should be
able to do is open Safari,
navigate to one of my favorite
websites on the internet,
switch to Safari on the Mac and
remotely inspect this web page.
So, how do I go about
doing this?
So, I'm going to go back to
my Develop Menu right here
and when I bring it up,
you'll notice the third item
which is named iPhone Simulator.
And for any iOS device
that's connected to your Mac
and has the Web Inspector
preference turned on,
these devices will appear in
this menu and you'll be able
to drill into this menu
to find specific WebViews
that you can inspect
on this device.
So, in our case, we only
have iPhone Simulator
and it has a single
application running, Safari,
and I can just hover over
the name of the web page
and it will show me, as
you can see in the back,
it will highlight the
WebView in question.
So, it might not
seem like a big deal
when you're targeting Safari
because the web page is
always going to occupy the--
almost the entire screen.
But imagine you're
working on an iOS app
when you have several
UIWebViews laid out on the page,
it might be hard to distinguish
which of this WebViews is
the one you want to inspect,
so this will make it really
easier to pinpoint what you want
to inspect specifically.
Okay, so let me zoom out.
I've picked this page and
this is Web Inspector.
Okay, so let's zoom in a little
bit on our Web Inspector and try
to work out exactly
what we can do here.
The first thing you'll
notice is that by default,
Web Inspector will
select the HTML
of the page you're inspecting
and show it's DOM tree
right in the center.
So, how do-- how can we go about
finding more about this page?
Well, there are three main
sections of Web Inspector.
The first one is Resources and
we've already got it selected,
and then we have
Timelines, we'll get back
to that one later,
and debugger, again,
we'll get back to that later.
Let's focus on Resources.
And the three icons
actually control the display
of the sidebar to the left,
which we call a Navigation
Sidebar.
This button also
acts as a toggle,
so when you don't need
the sidebar anymore,
you can just click on it,
removes it, click back on,
and will turn it back on so
that you can always control
what's exactly is on display
and customize your workspace.
Okay, so depending
on what I choose
in this Navigation Sidebar,
the content of the main view
here is going to change.
So for example, if I pick an
image, the content here changes.
If I pick a piece of JavaScript,
the content changes and so on.
This is because there's a
master-detail relationship
between those two things.
The sidebar is the master and
the content is the detail,
which is saying, "We want more
detail about this resource,"
and it appears right
away in the center.
So, one thing that's
really interesting
about the content here is
that it's divided
in three main areas.
So obviously in the center,
you got your source code
or your DOM tree or your image.
But at the top, we always have
what we call the Navigation Bar,
and what this lets
us do is browse
through the various resources
that we've gone through.
So, if I click Back,
I'll be back on my--
the image I was previously on,
and back again, I'll
be on the HTML.
And going back forward, I
can go back to my JavaScript.
So wherever you are in the
user interface and you want
to quickly go back
to where you were,
you can just use
the Navigation Bar,
which of course has a short--
keyboard shortcuts
available for it as well.
In the case of a DOM
tree, you also what we
like to call the Breadcrumb
Bar, and what it shows you is--
let me pick a deeper element.
What it shows you is the
hierarchy all the way
up to the HTML element for the
currently selected element.
So, I can go easily to the
header or parent div of the body
and this would be
the HTML element.
Okay, now let's focus at what
we can see at the bottom.
Here, we have what we call the
Quick Console and it's a piece
of user interface where you can
just type code wherever you are,
whenever.
And it's got two appearances.
The default appearance
is just a single prompt.
But if I type things in it,
I immediately get an additional
console log showing right up so
that I can see what
I've just evaluated
so I can type something
else, and you can see that.
And you can toggle this
Quick Console on and off
by just using the Escape key.
So, it's really easy to get more
information about your console
or just collapse it so that
you just focus on the prompt.
Okay, so that was
the Content Browser.
Now, what about those three--
those four icons to the right?
Well, the first thing
I'd like to show you is
that how these things would
change depending on what kind
of resource I'm inspecting.
So, if I go back to inspecting
an image, you'll notice
that I have a single
button here called Resource.
But if I go back to my HTML
page, I have more items.
The reason we have more items
is these control the display
of what we call the
Detail Sidebar.
It's a sidebar that
displays to the right.
In this case, I'm
going to select Styles,
and this will show
the Style Sidebar.
Again, there's a
master-detail relationship
which is going deeper down.
The master is the
Resources Sidebar,
we'll pick a resource which,
in this case, is an HTML file.
This is the detail
of the resource
and we can have even more
details about this HTML5,
HTML file by using one of
the Detail Sidebar icons
to the right, so I can drill
into styles information,
note information,
resource information,
and this is really only
contextual to whatever is
in the center which is itself
selected from the right.
So, there's this right to
left drilling of details.
Okay, again, these act as
toggles and it's really easy
to customize your workspace.
The last thing I'd like to
show you is this in the middle
which we like to call
the Activity Viewer.
Let me reload the page so
that the Activity Viewer fills
up with more interesting
information.
And I can reload the page
just by running Command-R,
I don't even have to switch
to my iOS Simulator or in fact
to iOS device, you can just do
it remotely from Web Inspector.
And in the center, we
have the load time.
Here, the page has some
difficulty running, actually,
sorry, it has-- I'm
really sorry about that.
Okay, this shows us the
load time, the time it took
until the load event
fired on the page.
And as you could
see, it kept running
until the page was fully loaded,
and that's a great metric
to keep an eye on as
you work on your page.
And these are always available,
so you always have a quick idea
of how many resources you're
dealing with, the complete sizes
of the page, and the amount of
time it took until it loaded.
And those three items to
the right are only relevant
when there are messages
in the console.
The first one will be for
console logs, the second one
for errors, and the
third one for warnings.
We'll get back to those later.
Here we are, we took a full
tour of the user interface
and I think this makes you
a little bit more familiar
with the Web Inspector.
So, let's recap what
we just saw.
This is the user interface
of Web Inspector and it split
into a series of subsections.
So, we have a little
coloring going on here
so you can see what
I'm talking about.
And so let's recap
what each of those are.
First, at the top we
have the Tool Bar.
We have the buttons to the left
that control the
Navigation Sidebars
and to the right,
the Detail Sidebar.
And to the center, we have
the Activity Viewer and always
on dashboard, it lets you
know how your page is doing,
how many resources it has,
how long it took to load.
And when we toggle the
buttons to the left
to control the Navigation
Sidebar,
we can see the sidebar
displayed to the left,
in this case, the
Resource Sidebar.
This controls what information
is displayed in the center
of the Content Browser, which
is split in three sections,
the Navigation Bar, the content
itself, and the Quick Console
at the bottom which
you can expand
and collapse by pressing Escape.
And finally to the right, we
have the Detail Sidebar toggled
by the buttons to the
right of the Tool Bar,
and this is our user interface.
So, let's start digging
into actual tasks
and see Web Inspector in action.
And I'd like to start by going
through inspection and tweaking.
And let me go back to demo
again so that we can look
at what we can do
with Web Inspector
to modernize a web page to make
it feel more at home on iOS 7.
Okay, so I'm going to open
Safari, get rid of the page
that we were previously on
and open a page I created
just for this demo.
Well, that page may
look familiar to you.
This looks like a page
of iTunes trailers.
And I took that page and
simplified it just a little bit
for a purpose of this demo.
And what I'd like to
do is, in this demo,
is to make it a little
bit better for iPhone.
I'd like it to fit the viewport
of iPhone so that you don't have
to zoom to like, to
look at the content.
And I'd also like to make
it feel a little bit more
like it were a web page trying
to mimic the aesthetics
of iOS 7.
Okay, the first thing I'm
going to do obviously is switch
to Safari, open Web
Inspector for this page and--
okay, let's get started.
The mission here is to always
remain in Web Inspector,
never switch context,
and make all the changes
in this one session of
usage of Web Inspector.
So, the first thing I'd like
to do is remove the background
of the page.
I just don't think this
picture here looks right.
It's landscape and I want a
portrait kind of experience.
So, what can I do
to make this better?
Well, I got the body element
selected here and I'm going
to open up the Style
Sidebar so I can control
that CSS properties
applied to this element.
And so this might
be familiar to you
if you used Web Inspector
before,
but the Style Sidebar
is just so much better
in Web Inspector in Safari 7.
Now, we can just simply click
here and edit as if we were
in our own Text Editor.
In this case, I'm selecting
all the background related
properties and by
hitting Delete,
I'm just going to
remove them all.
So, let me zoom out so you can
see what happens when I do that,
delete, the background
is gone instantly.
I didn't have to reload, I
didn't have to save anything,
I didn't have to go back to my
Text Editor and reload the page,
this is all happening live.
Okay, next, I think there's
an image on this page
that would work great
as a background image.
It's this little poster here and
it's got the right aspect ratio.
And so what I'd like to do
is make it the background,
and because eventually we'll
want to add a blur filter
to that image so that it
looks like an iOS 7 kind
of background, I will make
it-- I will keep it as an image
and try to move it to the
top of our DOM structure.
Okay, so let me do that, and the
easiest way I can find out where
that element is in my DOM tree
is I can use the Inspect button
in the Tool Bar and what
this lets me do is tap
on any element on the page.
And, again, remember this
could be in your iOS device.
You could be interacting
with it in real time.
And by just tapping on it,
it will reveal the note
right in Web Inspector.
So, here it is, we have an image
and the hierarchy above it.
Excellent.
So, let's take that image
and move it to the top.
So I suppose I could use a Quick
Console and write some DOM code
to remove it and
put it at the top.
But this is really not the most
intuitive way we could do it.
The most intuitive way on OS
X would be to just drag it
and drop it somewhere
else in the DOM tree.
So, let me do that again.
Just to show you, I'm going
to use Command-Z to undo
because we support
undo and redo,
and redo it so that you
see the changes I've made.
Excellent, the image is
now at the top of the page.
It's kind of small.
Oh, yeah, well, it's
got an explicit size,
and I probably want
to change that.
I just double-click
on the attribute
and I can just start
editing it right away.
So, let me type 100 percent,
again changes are instant.
Well, the Hide is set as well
and we're going to just get rid
of it such that it will match
the aspect ratio of the image.
Okay, well, there is
kind of a problem here
because the image is
really low resolution.
You can really see
it's all pixilated.
So, if I go back to where the
image was hosted, it was inside
of an anchor element
pointing to another image.
Oh, let's see what
that image is.
I'm just going to
click on the URL
and because it's not a
resource of the web page itself,
it's linked from the web
page, this will just download
to my desktop and open
in preview right away.
And I can see this image
as much higher resolution
and I think I just
like to use that.
So again, this is just
so easy in Web Inspector.
I can just double-click
on the attribute
and selects automatically
the text.
I'm going to use Command-C
to copy it, double-click
on the Image Source and paste.
And if you pay attention
to the left, the resolution
of the image is going to be
so much better right away.
There you go.
Excellent!
So, this is starting to
look a little bit better.
You know what?
I don't think I need
this Info panel anymore.
It's just too much information.
I'd like to really focus
just on the trailers.
So to find out where this
menu-- this info element is,
instead of inspecting--
using the Inspect button,
I'm going to just rollover to
various elements in the tree
and instantly, it will point
to where these are
painted on the page.
And until I find the right
element which is this one,
I'll just poke around,
select it, and delete it.
Again, I can undo
this by just doing--
pressing Command-Z and redo it.
So even destructive changes
like that is something you
can go back and correct
if it was not what you wanted.
Okay, things are coming together
because another thing I'd
like to do is to have the
page really match the viewport
of iPhone.
I should make sure that it has
the right viewport setting.
So let me click on the
head here, and I'm going
to use another great feature
of Web Inspector and just
like you can free form
CSSEdit, you can edit HTML
into free form way as well.
So I'm going to Control click
to bring up the Contextual menu
and press Edit as HTML.
And what this will bring up
is the small HTML editor right
within my page again and I can
just start typing name viewport
content equals width
equals device width,
and just to press
Tab to make it work
and there it goes,
it applied directly.
Awesome! So you notice there are
two things are just wrong now.
First of all, the menu
is completely gone.
I don't know where it went.
We'll get back to
that in a second.
It's also there's annoying
margins around the image.
That's just something I
need to touch on the body
and I can edit the style
of the body super simply,
I can just type here and
it's just ready to go.
So let me just type margin and
the CSS Editor auto-completes,
it knows all the
properties are--
that are available inside
of WebKit and in fact,
it all knows all the
properties that are available
to this specific
version of WebKit
because Web Inspector
talks to WebKit directly,
it's like your window
inside a WebKit.
So let me use Autocompletion
here and type 0--
let me just zoom out so you
can see, as I press 0, again,
instantly, changes are made.
I'm-- okay, so let's figure
out what happened to the menu.
So, if I select--
hover the menu here,
you'll notice there's nothing
highlighting on the page.
The menu is definitely gone.
So, I can just simply
inspect the CSS to find
out when we had-- what
may have happened.
And I'll notice here that
I have a left property set
up on the menu to be
something slightly convoluted
but let me explain to
you, what it does is
that it positions the
menu to the center
and then it will move it
480 pixels to the left.
That was great with the previous
version of the site that we had.
It's no longer accurate for
what we're trying to do now.
We've set up the viewport to be
the device width of the iPhone,
which means it's now 320 pixels,
so these values probably amount
to something that's
going to be negative
and our menu is just off page.
So to validate this theory,
I won't even have
to write any code.
What I'm just going to do is
click on the checkbox next
to the rule and that's going
to comment it out temporarily.
So let me just click on
it and here, directly,
you can see that without
that left property,
everything looks
like what I expect.
So, I'm just going to keep
that and I also I want
to change the top value to be 0.
And let me change the
width to be 100 percent,
and now my menu is starting
to look like what I want.
Okay, it'd be great if it was
just a slightly more revealing
of the background
and I think it's hard
to tell what the background
looks like at this stage.
So here again, I'm going to use
a DOM tree, use the arrow keys
to navigate until I find
the things I want to edit.
Here, I'd like to change
the title to just say
"Trailers," not view trailers.
Again, just double-click,
edit, return, you're done.
And let me [inaudible] as well.
Here, again, super simple.
Start typing text-align,
press Escape
and it automatically knows
all the values I can use
for this property.
So let's go with center.
Okay, much better.
Let me just make it a
little bit less opaque.
And so to do that, I'm going
to use another great
feature of Web Inspector.
And since I'm editing
a numeric value here,
I can use the Option
key and the Arrow keys
and I can just start
decrementing
and incrementing this value.
So I'm going to zoom out so
you can see it in real time,
option down, option up.
Okay, I got-- and again,
instantly, instant feedback
about the content on the page.
And let me change in
the similar fashion,
the gradient applied
to the menu content.
Okay, how does it look?
It's a lot more revealing.
We're getting there.
And the last thing I want
to do, like I told you,
is I want to get rid-- I want
to make the background blurred
so that it looks like
an iOS 7 backdrop.
So, I want to hide the
menu here so I can focus
in the background,
and it's really easy
to do in Web Inspector.
There's a key shortcut
you can use at anytime
when you select an element
in the tree and just press H
and it's going to
disappear temporarily,
we'll just apply some style
to make it not visible.
Okay, so let's select the
image and I'll add a new rule
to that image and automatically,
it creates the selector
that matches that element.
And let me type webkit-filter:
blur.
And so, let's play around
with that blur a little bit.
Let's start with five pixels.
And here, again, I'll adjust
it with the Option key
and the arrows until I get
the right amount of blur.
I think 10 pixels
just looks awesome.
Okay, I think we're done.
Let's go back to the Menu,
press H to turn it back on.
It's almost right but
there's something wrong.
The images are blurred
here as well.
And if you've paid attention,
you'll notice that the rule
that we added for the image
was a little bit too generic.
So let's change it.
Here, instead of having image,
we want to have a
more specific rule.
So let me just cut
this property,
add an ID to this element
so that we target just the
background specifically,
add a new rule again,
and this time,
it will create an even
more accurate selector
for this element because it
knows that it's specific image,
it's an image with
ID background.
So let me paste the new rule
and you'll notice as soon
as I paste the new rule,
the background will blur
and the content will
remain sharp.
Perfect! This is it.
This is what I wanted
and I could do it all
within Web Inspector.
I never had to switch
back to my Text Editor,
never had to reload, this all--
I could just experiment
to my heart's content
within Web Inspector.
Mission accomplished.
Okay, let's recap
what we just did,
inspection tweaking
experimentation.
Well, the first thing is as
soon as we open Web Inspector,
you were presented with the
DOM view of the web page.
And if you think back to
viewer source which has been
around forever ever since
browser existed, this is kind
of the same approach
except everything you can do
with this source is live.
You can edit it right away
and all the changes will show
up instantly on your web page.
It's just so cool.
And what's really great about
it is that you never had
to leave Web Inspector.
You can tweak and you never
have to reload or rebuild.
Again, think about
building an app using Xcode
that has web content, you
would have to usually rebuild.
Here, you don't have to.
You just use Web Inspector,
connect to your iOS device,
and you're good to go.
And it was really easy to find
the content that we wanted
to inspect by using two
different techniques.
The first one is we used the
Inspect button from the toolbar
and just tapped on the item
on the page that we wanted
to inspect and it revealed
immediately in Web Inspector.
And another way you can do it is
to do it the other way around.
You want to select
things in the DOM tree
and see what they
match on the web page.
And so you can just hover
DOM nodes in the DOM tree
and they'll highlight right away
on your page and your device.
That's really great.
And finally, anywhere you see
code, whether it's CSS or HTML,
we're just able to
click and start typing.
And in the case of CSS, it
knew all about the support of--
the support of CSS
properties on our page
and it let us have
autocompletion,
syntax highlighting.
It's just such a great
editing experience right
within Web Inspector.
And so, I really think
this idea of experimenting
with Web Inspector is something
that's just so much fun
and it's a great way to learn
about the capabilities of CSS
in the browser that
you're inspecting.
And just this morning at 9
a.m., you may have seen it.
If you've missed it, you
can catch it later on video.
It was a great session
and we went through a lot
of new CSS features made
available in Safari 7
and Safari on iOS and iOS 7.
The session was named "What's
new in Safari and WebKit
for web developers," and I
urge you to check it out.
It got some great CSS content
and some great things
you could experiment
with within Web Inspector.
And if you stay in this
room right after this talk,
we're going to go in
much greater details
about inspection tweaking
within Web Inspector.
We've only really
scratched the surface here.
There are so much more to see
so stay tuned and we'll get--
we'll show you a lot more.
So, that was inspection
tweaking.
Now, let's move to network
performance analysis.
And here again, I'd like to
tell you just a little bit
of a story here.
I think we're all here aware
that mobile devices are a
really important target.
It's how a lot of people--
it's, you know, I have my device
in my pocket, I hear
about something,
I want to check it
out right away.
I don't want to wait
until I'm at my desktop.
I just want to go and
look at it right away.
And so, a great experience
in mobile is an experience
where things load quick.
And a way to get things to
load quick on your web page
or your web content in your
iOS app is to have as little
and as few resources
as possible.
That's a great way
to get started.
So, obviously, you have to
have an HTML page, some CSS
and some JavaScript if you
want it to look really good,
and you also want it to
be a little interactive.
And you also want to
distinguish yourself
from other web pages
and, et cetera
and have a little themeing
so you have some images,
maybe one, maybe more than that.
And if you manage to keep
it down to this small number
of resources, you're
probably on the right path.
But I don't think this is
something that we can deal
with in the real world so much.
The expectations of devices
like iOS device is just so high
in terms of quality and
experience and the capabilities
of those devices are
just so astounding
and improved every year
that we want to do more.
So then, you'll probably start
using some JavaScript library
from the network and maybe some
other images that you're loading
from a third-party
service and then you're--
surely enough, you're starting
to have a lot more resources.
And on top of that,
those resources may not
be under your control.
Again, you may be using some
JavaScript library loaded
from a CDN or images
from Flickr.
And these are not
things that you control,
you don't know exactly what
size is going to be in advance
or the quality of the service
is going to serve them.
And this is just kind
of a complex situation.
And it would be really
cool if you could just find
out how things get loaded
and understand what could
be potentially a load issue
with your page that would impact
the initial user experience
for a user.
Well, this is when Web
Inspector comes in.
And using the Timeline's
panel, we're going to look
at how we can keep track of
resources using Web Inspector.
So for this demo,
I'm going to go back
to the developer.apple.com,
WWDC page.
So load it up in the
simulator, switch to Safari,
bring up Web Inspector,
and let's switch the
Timeline's panel.
This is what we're
interested in this section.
And the first thing you'll
notice as it loads is
that it's completely empty.
Well, the reason it is empty is
that for the Timeline's panel
to load with useful
content, WebKit needs
to run some special
instrumentation
on the page as it
loads and runs.
And we don't want you to be
running this code at all times.
We only want to run this code
in WebKit when it makes sense.
It might have some
performance issues.
It's only really useful
for instrumentation.
So, what we're going to
do here is we're going
to reload the page
with Web Inspector open
and the Timeline would populate
as soon as we start loading.
The other thing I'd
like to point out is
that not only can I do
Command-R to reload the page,
I can even do Command-shift-R
and what this will do is
that it will reload the page
while ignoring the cache.
This is very important
if we want
to diagnose network
related issues,
we want to test the full load
of the page and not just things
that haven't been cached yet.
So, Command-shift-R,
page starts reloading
and the Timeline is populating.
Okay, recording is done,
and this is what
we're presented with.
So, we're going to look
at this in more details.
The first thing I want to show
you is that these timelines here
at the top are split in
three different categories.
There's first, network request
in blue, layout and rendering
in purple, and JavaScript
events in orange.
For the purpose of this talk,
we're going to focus
on network request.
In the second session
right after this one,
we'll go in much greater
detail in the layout
and rendering section.
So if you want to find
out more, stay tuned.
So let's get rid of
this sidebar for now.
We want to focus on the content.
Hide this, and you'll
notice first
that we can see there is
some color coding in the list
of resources loaded right here.
Blue means an HTML page,
green means the CSS page,
orange means the
JavaScript piece of script,
and purple means images.
So, at a glance, you
can tell what's loading
without necessarily
having to look
at the name of the resource.
It's really handy.
Okay, so another thing that
I'd like to point out is
that I'm actually simulating
a 3G network on this computer,
so that it doesn't looks
as fast it would be
on a hardware network.
And when you're using
3G networks or worse
if you're using an EDGE network,
latency can be a big problem.
And for those who are
not aware with this term,
latency is the amount
of time that elapses
between the moment
WebKit asks for resource
and the moment the server
starts coming back to us
with the resource and
when it starts loading.
And latency might be
a lot more important
than the actual load time.
The 3G network is usually pretty
fast downloading content once
it's established the
connection with the server.
So, to illustrate that
a little bit better,
let me select the first item on
the page which is the HTML page,
let me select it, let me get rid
of the Resource sidebar
for a moment.
And you'll notice
here that the item
on the timeline split
in two sections.
First is a semitransparent
section
and a fully opaque section.
The transparent section
is latency, and it's just
so much more than the
actual download time
of 376 milliseconds out of
a total of 412 milliseconds.
That's just a lot
of time spent with--
just waiting on assets to
actually start downloading.
So this is a good indication
of how important it is to try
to reduce the amount of
resources you have on your page.
So, if you're using CSS in
multiple files or JavaScript
in multiple files, maybe you
should consider concatenating
them into a single asset so that
you have fewer assets to deal
with and this will improve
the load time significantly.
Okay, so let's keep looking at
the timeline and find out more.
You'll notice that there seems
to be a sequence of
things happening.
We have this first
resource loading upfront,
and then other resources
loading after that.
Why do they load
only after the HTML?
Well, that's pretty obvious.
The HTML will link
to CSS resources,
JavaScript files, and images.
And until we've loaded
and parsed the HTML page,
we don't what other
content we need to load.
So there's a sequence here
and a dependency established
on the HTML to load these
first two style sheets,
these few JavaScript
files, the CSS file,
and a couple more images.
And this is the core content
of the page, it's the content
that the page needs
to load upfront
to make sure it instantly has a
great experience to get going.
And so, that's a great approach.
You want to have your initial
content load right upfront
and any secondary
content load afterwards.
And in fact, this is
what this website does.
You will notice there is another
sequence of images load--
of images loading later on.
And these are queued by a style
sheet as only loaded afterwards,
so that we first get the
main part of the web page.
So these will be
the big WWDC image.
And more or less interesting
images will be loaded
right after.
So we can jump and see
for example here we have a
little Apple logo but it's not
as important as in the great
WWDC logo in the middle.
Okay, so that was a brief
overview of the timeline
for networking resources.
And what we saw here is how we
can visually see on the page
with a great graphical
representation how different
resources load on a timeline.
So we don't have to guess, we
don't have to look at a table
where it just lists start time,
end time, or anything like that,
we can just visualize
those things,
and that's really
makes us understand
at a glance how things get
organized on a page and load.
And the second thing is
that we make it really easy
to distinguish latency
and the download time.
Again, latency is not your
friend on the mobile network.
It's important that you try to
avoid having too many resources
and you can figure that
out really easily using
Web Inspector.
And thirdly, we could
really identify dependencies
and the sequence of how
things load on the page.
And this is really great
because, like I said,
you really want to make sure
your initial content loads
upfront and any second secondary
content only loads afterwards
so that your initial content
loads as fast as possible.
And to validate that technique,
you can use Web Inspector
and its timeline to
make sure things load
in the sequence you expect.
So again, stay tuned.
On the next session,
we'll have lot more
about the Timelines
panel, we'll be looking
at layout and rendering.
So, if you want to
find out more,
stay in this room
for the next session.
And on the topic of performance,
even though it's not directly
related to network performance
and more about layout
and rendering,
there's a great talk tomorrow
morning, we'll be discussing how
to optimize power and
performance for your web page,
9 a.m. in Russian
Hill, be there.
I will be.
Okay, let's jump to the
last section, debugging.
And here, again, we're going
to go straight into a demo
and see how we can
use Web Inspector
to debug issues with
our JavaScript.
So, for this specific demo,
I've prepared an update
on the initial demo
that we we're looking
at for Monsters University.
So let me jump straight
to that page.
And what I did here is that
is wanted to go further
in the iOS 7 experience
and provide a new header
with white background and
I wanted the user to have
to tap this back--
to tap this header
such that it would reveal
the list of trailers
with a neat little animation.
Okay, so, again, bring
up Web Inspector,
jump to Resources sidebar,
reveal our HTML page,
and what we did here is
that we added a little piece
of JavaScript whose role is
to toggle a specific CSS class
on the documents body, the class
is called Showing Trailers.
And let me just see
what that would look
like when it's applied.
And I can do that very easily.
I'll jump to the DOM tree
from the source code.
I'm going to select the body,
edit as HTML, and I'm going
to add the CSS class on it so
you can see what it will look
like when the CSS
class is applied.
I'm going to hit Tab and
you'll notice immediately
on the site how it
changes the rendering.
And so, we have an
animation going
as soon as we add this class.
Let me undo it, redo
it, and you'll notice
as we have this animation,
the background will blur
and the content will slide down.
So, this is kind of cool.
Let's see if this
actually works.
So, I'm going to reload the page
and the first thing
you'll notice is
that in the Activity Viewer, we
now see that we have an error.
Okay, let's bring
up the Quick Console
and we could have brought
that up by just clicking
on the Activity Viewer but here,
I've used the Escape command
so I don't have to get
rid of the source code
that I was looking at.
And you'll notice right there
they will tell me exactly what
went wrong, syntax error,
unexpected token,
closing parenthesis.
This in itself is
not that useful.
I'd have to hunt it down.
But of course, Web
Inspector makes
that easily-- easy as well.
It just tells me what file the
error happened and on what line.
And I can just click on that
and I'm going to zoom out
and I will jump straight
to the line
in question and highlight it.
So, it's red, letting me
know there's an error.
And what's really cool about
any kind of source we show
in Web Inspector is that we
always have syntax highlighting.
So here, if I bring my cursor
to this closing parenthesis
which just seems
to be the problem,
clicking on it will
highlight it in red.
And you'll notice
there's another piece
of code highlighted in red here
and it's the opening brace.
So it looks like this closing
parenthesis is expecting
to match something
else, and sure enough,
in my function declaration,
I forgot to close
using a closing brace.
So, let me type that, and right
away, it will show in blue,
meaning everything is cool.
All right, I probably
fixed my first error.
So, let me just reload
the page and it seems
like you have a second error.
So, let me jump again to the
Activity Viewer by just--
by the console-- sorry,
by clicking on it.
I'm going to bring up the Quick
Console and here, it says--
oh, I forgot to do
something, right.
There's something really great
that I forgot to mention is
that when we add our closing
brace, we actually need to save
that file for-- in order to
be able to reload the page
as script and it needs
to be reevaluated.
So, what I can do here
is, for the first time,
within Web Inspector, I
can just tap Command-S
and because I'm editing a
local file, I'm prompted
to override the existing
file, save it, replace it,
and this file will now be used
as a version that's
loaded by the web page.
So, this time let
me clear the console
by pressing Command-K
and reload.
This time, I will
not get that error,
instead I get a different error.
This time-- this is
the problematic line.
Let me bring up the Quick
Console again using Esc
and it says, "No,
it's not an object."
Okay, let's jump right
again to the error
in question, which
is further up.
Let me scroll up a
little bit, scroll here.
And, okay, so header
is null apparently.
Let me just set a breakpoint
so we can figure
out what's going on.
So, I'm going to bring
up the Debugger sidebar,
set our breakpoint here,
and make sure breakpoints
are enabled by clicking
on these icons right here
which will turn gray to blue,
which means my breakpoint
is set.
So, next time your page is going
to load, if there's an error
on this line, I will pause
automatically in the debugger,
so let me reload again.
And this time, I'm
pause executing
at this specific line, okay.
So, indeed, now I have a
different detail sidebar
which automatically came
up called Scope Chain
and this will let me take a look
at all the variables
available in the current scope.
In here, I can notice that
the header is indeed null
so there's no way I can
pull a function on it.
Okay, so what can I
do to work that out?
So, I'm going to bring up
the Quick Console again,
and what's really awesome
is that I'm just going
to be evaluating script right
where my script is paused
and understand what's happening.
So, for example, I can type
header and indeed it's null.
Okay, well, let's
try the document.
Surely, we'll have a
document object, right?
This is kind of-- if
you don't have that,
there's nothing you can redo.
We do have a document object.
Well, does it have any children?
So, let's look at
document.body, that too is null.
Let's go back to the code and
find out what may be going on.
I think I understand, the
problem is the script is in line
"the head element" and it
executes as soon as it's parsed.
But when it's parsed,
the rest of the page
that has not been parsed yet,
so even though I'm trying
to get a pointer to
my header in the DOM,
the DOM is not ready yet,
it hasn't been parsed.
That should be fairly
easy to fix.
Let me resume script by clicking
on the Play/Pause button
at the top and change
the source code.
And what I'd like to do is make
sure I only evaluate this line
of code when the DOM is ready.
And there's really helpful
DOM event that gets triggered
when that happens which is
called DOM content loaded
and let me just call that
function when that happens.
Again, I'm going to save,
turn off breakpoints.
I don't want to pause anymore
because I think I fixed the
problem, reload the page,
I clear the console
again with Command-K
to make sure there are no
errors as it gets loaded.
And this time, no
errors triggered.
Okay, looks like
I'm in business.
I'm just going to
click on the trailers
and the menu is just going
to magically appear for sure.
Well, I click and click
and nothing is happening.
Well, it's not quite right,
something is happening.
I get errors in my
JavaScript console yet again.
So, you know what I'm
going to do this time is--
I don't even want to know
where the error happened,
I'm going to turn
on the debugger
to stop all uncut exceptions.
That means that any time
there's an exception happening
in JavaScript that hasn't
been caught programmatically
in the code, the debugger
will automatically kick in.
So let me turn that on,
and without even having
to reload the page because I
can run this code again live,
I'm just going to
click on trailers,
and as soon as I click it,
again, I will break in the code.
So what's going on here?
Well, so I can use the
Scope Chain to take a look
at the various values
of my local variables
or the Quick Console to
just start evaluating code
but something new that we added
in Web Inspector in Safari 7,
which makes even easier,
is I can just mouse
over different tokens in the
code and I'll instantly see
where they evaluate to.
So the document is available,
it has a body this time
so what I did in the
previous stage worked.
I'm evaluating code
when the DOM is ready.
And-- oh, this doesn't work
anymore, classes is undefined.
Well, I guess there's no class'
member on documented body.
And so since I'm broken
into the debugger,
I'm going to start experimenting
and writing some code
to figure out what went wrong.
So let me clear the console
and type document.body.
I'm going to make
use of autocompletion
within the console to
figure out what it may--
what the property that I was
looking for might have been.
So, I'm sure it's
something related to class
but I can't remember the name.
So let me just start typing,
oops, "Class" and there you go.
There are two options,
class list and class name.
Class list is what I wanted.
Let me validate to
make sure it evaluates
to something that's not
undefined and it looks
like it is what I want.
Okay, excellent.
You know what?
I'm going to go back to my code,
change classes to class list,
resume script execution,
save the file, Command-S,
and I'm going to clear the
console again with Command-K,
I don't want to see
any [inaudible] errors,
reload the page, and finger
crossed, I'm going to click
on trailers and this
time, it just works.
Cool. Mission accomplished
again,
I got where I wanted
all with Web Inspector.
Okay, let's recap
what we just did.
Well, I'll start with
something that we didn't do.
You'll notice we
didn't use any technique
that I will call
somewhat ghetto.
We didn't use Alert to
find on what was going on,
we didn't even use
console log which is kind
of the modern version of Alert.
And what the debugger lets us
do is go beyond console log
and actually debug
the code in real time.
So we could use breakpoints
to pause JavaScript execution
and breakpoints are either
something you will target
directly yourself and say, "I
want to break on this line"
or it is something you can just
have generically happen whenever
an error is triggered,
so useful.
And using this Scope
Chain's detail sidebar,
you could always find out about
the context of your current code
or you can even just roll over
your content and use Popovers
to show what you understand
exactly what values
of the various members
of your code evaluate to.
This is so very useful.
And finally, my preferred
technique is to start coding.
I can bring up the Quick
Console, type whatever I want
in there, see what
it would evaluate
to in this current
context and figure
out what right code would
be for the JavaScript
that I was trying to fix.
And so, again, we'll go
in much greater details
about debugging in
the next session.
We've only scratched
the surface.
There is so much more you
can do with the debugger
in Web Inspector and Safari.
So stay tuned, stay in this room
and we'll find that a lot more.
And this wraps up our session.
We've looked an overview
of the user interface,
the master-detail
relationship going left to right
between the Navigation
sidebar, content browser
and Detail sidebar, and
the great Activity Viewer
within the Tool Bar so that you
can always see what errors maybe
triggered, your page load time
and the resources
you're dealing with.
And then we went
through three core tasks
that I think highlighted
different panels
within Web Inspector.
We started by inspection
tweaking where CSS
and HTML editing were
really front and center.
Then we looked at network
performance analysis
where the Timelines
panel made us--
made it really easy to just to
identify how things get loaded
in sequence and visualized
it with a great timeline.
And finally, we just debug the
JavaScript code in real time
within Web Inspector by just
using the great debugging tools
made available.
And so, if you like
what you just saw,
there are different
ways you can remain
and get involved
with Web Inspector.
And the first thing I'd like
to point out is that every day
as we make enhancements
to WebKit,
we build what we call
the "Nightly Build".
And this is like a
special version of Safari
that you can download
to your net--
to your desktop and have the
latest version of WebKit Code
from Open Source compiled in
and you can just
play around with it.
And you can go to
nightly.webkit.org
and you'll get it right away.
And if you find issues when
you're using Nightlys or even
if you find issues in the
currently shipping version
of Safari, you can just go the
bugs@webkit.org/newinspectorbug
and type any problem
you may have found.
You can also use that
that raise future request.
And we pay very close
attention to what goes
on in this bug tracker
and we try
to fix bugs as fast as we can.
And if you need to discuss
things a little bit more
interactively, you can
find us on IRC as well.
We hang out at irc.freenode.net,
the channel is
#WebKit-inspector.
And we actually spread all
around the world a little bit
so depending on what
time zone you are,
you should still find someone to
help you and answer questions.
There's something
even better that I'd
like to announce today is
that we're making Safari's
Web Inspector Open Source
contributed back to the
WebKit Open Source project.
And so, what it means is
that you can go ever further
than raising bugs and discussing
future request in IRC.
You can just completely
get involved with the code
and start fixing
things yourself.
In fact, one of the great
features that we show today
about how we can
save files locally
within the Web Inspector is
something that was contributed
by an external contributor.
So the sky is the limit.
You can just contribute as much
as you want to Web Inspector.
And so, for more information,
you can contact John Geleynse,
the Technology Evangelist.
We are greatly updated
documentation
for the Safari Web
Inspector guide
on developer.apple.com/mac.
WebKit.org is a lot
of information
about WebKit in general.
And the div forums let you
connect with one another
and we track those and
ask any questions you want
and we'll try to answer.
And so, I've already mentioned
some related sessions.
Here they are recapped.
Right here and--
right this morning--
sorry, there was a
session about CSS
and new features in the WebKit.
Right here and right now,
we'll have another more advanced
session about Web Inspector,
and tomorrow at 9
a.m., a great session
about power performance
for web content.
Okay, that's it.
[ Silence ]