[ Silence ]
>> Mark Hahnenberg:
Good morning everyone.
My name is Mark Hahnenberg
and I'm an engineer
on the JavaScriptCore team.
And today, I'm going to be
talking to you about how
to integrate JavaScript
into your Native Apps
on both iOS and Mac.
So, prior to today,
there has been a C API
to the JavaScriptCore
framework available on Mac.
And if you're interested
in that, there is a session
that was done on WWDC a number
of years ago about the C API.
But today, I'm going
to be talking to you
about the new Objective-C
API that we're releasing
to JavaScriptCore, and
it will be available
on both Mac and iOS.
So what were some of our goals
when developing this new API?
Well for one, we want
it to be automatic.
And what this means is that
there are certain things
that you want to do with a
framework like JavaScriptCore
and we tried to make that as
automatic and easy as possible.
The second thing is we
want the API to be safe.
So, we want you to be able
to recover from errors
if you happen to pass
something of the wrong type
across this border because
JavaScript is a dynamic language
as you know.
So you can pass various
objects around and we want it--
we want you to be able to not--
we want you to not crash
your application if you end
up doing something
a little squirrely,
so we want you to--
it to be recoverable.
And the final goal that we had
was this notion of fidelity
and what I mean by that is
whenever you're programming
in Objective-C and you're
interacting with JavaScriptCore,
we want you to feel like you're
programming in Objective-C
when you're writing Objective-C,
and we want you to feel
like you're writing JavaScript
when you're writing JavaScript.
So we don't want there to be,
you know, these crazy names
that lead with underscores
or maybe dollar signs
in there somewhere.
We want it to look like
JavaScript and look
like Objective-C in
their respective worlds.
So what are-- what exactly
will you learn today?
First, we'll talk about how to
get your Objective-C application
to talk to JavaScript,
so to call--
to evaluate JavaScript scripts,
to call JavaScript functions,
and to create JavaScript values.
Then we're going to talk about
how to get your JavaScript code
to be able to interact with
your Objective-C objects
and call Objective-C methods.
Then we'll talk a little
bit about memory management.
Objective-C uses ARC
and JavaScript is a
garbage collected language.
So, getting these to play
nicely together requires some
extra attention.
Then we'll talk about
threading and how
that interacts with the API.
And then we'll speak to-- a
little bit about interfacing
with the C API that
already exists today.
And finally, we'll talk a little
bit about using JavaScriptCore
in the context of a
WebKit WebView on Mac.
So, to start off, I'd like
to show you just a simple
application, a simple
demo using JavaScriptCore.
So I have a simple
Cocoa app here.
It has an NSTextView.
You can see there are
some words in there.
And what you're seeing is
that the words that correspond
to colors are being highlighted
with their corresponding color.
So for example, brown
is highlighted brown,
red is highlighted red.
And the logic that
implements this highlighting
that determines whether a
particular word corresponds
to a color is implemented
in JavaScript.
So I have a couple other things
that are implemented
in JavaScript here.
I have a button that's connected
to a JavaScript function
that shuffles the
colors and reassigns them
to drive yourself
a little crazy.
And if I don't want to wait
around for the random shuffle
to get back to the original
assignment, I can reset back
to the original assignment.
So I can-- as I type, it will
continue to highlight words
so you can type red,
orange, yellow,
but there's a couple bugs.
So for example, we have grey
but we don't have G-R-A-Y,
that doesn't work correctly.
And also typing capital
colors doesn't highlight
as we would expect.
And my favorite color cyan is
also not highlighted correctly.
So we can fix that
pretty easily actually.
I have the script that
implements this color mapping.
And what I'm going to do is
I'm going to edit the script
to give us a new
gray and cyan here.
You can see that this is a map
of normal JavaScript objects
that maps color names to their
corresponding red, green,
and blue value stored inside
the JavaScript objects.
And down here, here's
our callback
for determining what color
a word should be if any.
So, you can see that
if I uncomment this,
then we will take into account
words that have uppercase
in them that are still colors.
So I'm going to save this
file, go back to my application
and I have this Reload button
down in the bottom right
and it will reload the script
and now we correctly highlight
the colors, and I didn't have
to recompile which
is kind of neat.
So, that is a simple way to use
JavaScript in an application.
You just saw a simple
use of JavaScript
in an application,
a Cocoa application.
So let's look at how we might
implement something like this.
So, first we're going to talk
about how to get Objective-C
to talk to JavaScript.
So, here is a simple Hello
World program, Hello World.
We implement-- or we
import the framework header,
so JavaScriptCore.h. We create
something called a JSContext,
and we'll talk about
what that is in a second.
We use that context and call
evaluateScript, evaluating 2 + 2
and that will return
a result in a--
with a type of JSValue and
finally, we convert that JSValue
to an integer that we can
print out to the screen.
So let's talk about these
two core data types,
JSContext and JSValue.
First JSContext.
JSContext is a context for
evaluating JavaScript code.
It corresponds to a
single global object,
so in web parlance for you
guys coming from the web world,
it corresponds to
a window object.
But there is no thing
called a window
but there is a single global
object for global variables.
And the other type is JSValue.
JSValues live inside
of a JSContext.
They can be things like--
it's just a reference
to a JavaScript value
so they can be objects,
JavaScript arrays,
JavaScript functions,
Booleans, et cetera.
And they have a strong
reference to that value.
So it's kind of a strong handle
to that JavaScript value.
So keep it alive as long
as you're interacting
with that JSValue.
And they're tied to a particular
JSContext, each JSValue is tied
to a particular JSContext.
And why is that?
Well, any JSValue might
want to evaluate code
which we need a JSContext to do.
For example a function,
a JavaScript function
needs a JSContext
in order to evaluate code.
And that is also a
strong reference,
so JSValue keeps alive
all of those things
that it needs to do its job.
So there's a variety of
ways to create JSValues.
This is the-- you can create
things using the corresponding
Objective-C primitives like
Boolean's, doubles, et cetera.
You can create the JavaScript
values null or undefined.
You can create new JavaScript
objects, new JavaScript arrays,
regular expression and errors,
hopefully not too many of those.
And you can also
create new JSValues
and pass an arbitrary
Objective-C object.
So, this particular method,
this class method deserves
its own slide because a lot
of magic happens here.
So we will automatically
bridge your Objective-C object
to JavaScript so that
JavaScript can interact with it.
And we'll talk more
about exactly how
that works in a second.
Once you have a JSValue, if
you get it back from a call
or something, you
want to be able
to access the data that's inside
of it so we have various things
like converting to a
Boolean, to numbers,
to dates, strings, et cetera.
And when you call one
of these on a JSValue,
JavaScriptCore will do its best
effort to convert it to the type
that you asked for
using the semantics
of the JavaScript language.
You'll also notice at the
bottom, the two object method.
And this allows you to get-- if
you bridge an Objective-C object
to a JSValue, this
allows you to get
that Objective-C object
back out of the JSValue.
So now that we know
how to create values,
let's talk a little bit about
calling JavaScript functions.
So here's a simple factorial
function written in JavaScript,
and here's what it
looks like to call it.
So first, we load the script
from wherever it
resides on disk perhaps.
We evaluate the script using
the context like we saw earlier.
And since the script defines
a single global function,
we can use this new subscript
notation and pass the name
of the function from the
context to load that JSValue
from the global object,
from the global scope.
Once we have that
function, we can--
we simply use callWithArguments
and pass this--
and pass an NSArray
of arguments.
So this is this new
Objective-C notation
for creating array literals.
And you'll notice that
we passed an NSNumber 5
and this is significant because
JavaScript doesn't know how
to interact with NSNumber.
However, JavaScriptCore will
automatically bridge this
for you so that when
you call that function,
it gets the correct value, it
will get 5 as its argument.
And finally, we get the
result back and we print it.
It should be 120, right?
If the factorial
function is correct.
So, now that we know how
to interact with JavaScript
from Objective-C,
let's recap the demo
that I showed you
previously to show
where it uses some
of these things.
Here are the callbacks for
the Shuffle and Reset button.
And what we do is we look
at the plug-in object
that we create inside
of our JavaScript file,
and we use the subscript
notation
that I showed you earlier.
You can use this, not
only on the context,
but any JavaScript
value also works
with this subscript notation
to access fields of the object.
So we load the shuffleFunction
from the plug in,
and then we call the function
with an empty set of arguments.
So, if we look at the
corresponding JavaScript code,
here's the shuffleFunction,
it's a property
on the plug-in object
named Colors
and it does some
shuffling for us.
If you look up here, when
we're loading the plug-in,
we get the path from the bundle,
we load the script from the file
and then we use evaluateScript
to get the result of loading
that plug-in and we store it.
Now that you've seen how we
use interacting with JavaScript
from Objective-C in
that simple application,
let's move on to
getting JavaScript
to talk back to Objective-C.
There are two primary
ways to interact
with Objective-C
from JavaScript.
The first is to use
blocks, Objective-C blocks.
And these will be wrapped
inside of a JS function
that is callable
from JavaScript.
So-- And that's a
really easy way
to expose just a single function
to JavaScript that you want
to be able to call
back into Objective-C.
The other way is
to use something called
the JSExport protocol
and this protocol, by using this
technique, you allow JavaScript
to interact with your
Objective-C objects
as if they were JavaScript
objects.
It's a very powerful technique
for maintaining that fidelity
that I spoke about earlier.
So let's look how
these work exactly.
First is blocks.
So, like I said before,
it's an easy way
to expose Objective-C code
to JavaScript, very easy.
And we automatically wrap
the Objective-C block inside
of a callable JavaScript
function.
So what does that look like?
We can insert a block into the
context using this subscript
notation that I talked
about earlier.
And we pass a block as the value
that we're bridging
to JavaScript.
And you'll notice that the
block takes an NSDictionary
of RGB values as its argument.
And it returns a new
NSColor using those red,
green and blue values.
So, what this does is when
we pass this block in--
across this JavaScriptCore
barrier,
we create a makeNSColor
function,
JavaScript function
around the block.
Then, in our code,
we call makeNSColor
and we use these
JavaScript objects
that I showed you
earlier in the color map
and they're just normal
JavaScript objects.
And the cool thing about this
is that, you notice before
that the block accepts an
NSDictionary as its argument.
JavaScriptCore will
automatically bridge JavaScript
objects to NSDictionaries when
calling out to Objective-C code.
We call this makeNSColor,
and what happens?
colorForWord calls the function
and it forwards that call
to the Objective-C block.
It gets the resulting NSColor
and wraps it in turn inside
of a JavaScript object, and
then this colorForWord function
returns that NSColor.
So although blocks are very
easy to use, there are a couple
of caveats you have to be
careful about when using them.
So, the first is you should
avoid capturing JSValues inside
of your blocks.
And the reason for this is
that JSValues maintain a strong
reference to both their context
and their corresponding
JavaScript value.
And so if they're
captured by the block,
you'll leak that memory
because you won't be able
to release that JSValue.
You should-- instead you
should prefer to pass JSValues
as arguments to your blocks.
The second caveat is
along similar lines.
You should avoid capturing
JSContext inside of your blocks.
And it's for the same reason,
the JSContext maintains a strong
reference to the global object
and it will leak all of your
memory when it's captured.
Instead, you should
use the class method
on JSContext called
currentContext inside
of the block, and that will
return to you the context
of the caller, whoever
invoked that block.
This is an example
of what not to do.
You create a context, you
pass a block, and you use,
you capture that context inside
of the block, this is bad.
The right way to do it
is to create the context,
insert the block and then
use JSContext currentContext
where you were capturing
it before.
So now that we've
talked about blocks,
let's talk about JSExport
and how that works.
JSExport is, like I said
before, it's a really easy way
for JavaScript to interact
with Objective-C objects.
So, let's take a look at
what it would look like.
So imagine that I have a
MyPoint class represents a two
dimensional point, it has an X
and a Y property, description,
instance method,
and a factory method
to create new MyPoints,
so a class method.
And what would we like this
to look like when interacting
with this-- an object of
this class in JavaScript?
Well, we'd want the
properties to look
like JavaScript properties.
So, you could get their value,
you could set their value.
We want the instance methods
to look like functions
on those objects, so dot
description in this case.
And we want class methods
to look like functions
on these global class objects,
in this case, capital MyPoint.
So, the way to get this to
work with JSExport is simply
to change its interface
into a protocol
that inherits from JSExport.
So now, we have a
MyPointExports.
And this, by inheriting
from JSExport,
you signal to JavaScriptCore
that this is the list of methods
and properties that I want
JavaScript to be able to access
when I pass an object
that implements this
MyPointExports protocol.
So, you'll also notice that
when you had your interface
for MyPoint now, you don't have
to re-list all of those methods
because it's a protocol so
that's how protocols work.
And that's nice because
you don't get a lot
of duplication of information.
But you can also, if you
don't list a particular method
in your JSExport protocol,
it will not be exported
to JavaScript.
So if you only want to-- it's
a purely opt-in protocol.
And then your implementation of
MyPoint will look just exactly
like Objective-C code.
This speaks to that
kind of fidelity
that we were talking
about earlier.
You don't have to register
all sorts of functions,
you don't have to do
a lot of extra stuff
like you just write your-- you
write your Objective-C class,
you write your JavaScript
code and you're done.
So like I said before, when
you inherit from JSExport,
you enumerate the methods
and properties that you want
to export to JavaScript.
Properties become
JavaScript getters and setters
on the objects as you're
interacting with them
in JavaScript so it will-- the
getter and setter will call
into Objective-C code.
Instance methods become
JavaScript functions
on those objects.
And class methods become
JavaScript functions
on the global class object,
the capital MyPoint
that we saw earlier.
So let's look at how
we would use this.
So we allocate our
context like before.
We evaluate some geometry script
which I'll show you in a second.
Then we create two of our points
just like we normally would,
alloc init with XY, and we load
the function from the context
like we saw earlier,
in this case,
it's euclideanDistance
between two points.
And then, we callWithArguments
and pass the two points
and they're automatically
bridged to JavaScript.
Similarly, if we want to
expose the global class object,
capital MyPoint, we can pass
the class to the context as well
and it will automatically
be bridged
so that JavaScript
can interact with it.
Then we can load, for example,
a function named midpoint
which might want to create a
new point given two other points
and we can call it the same
way that we did before.
We get a result back in the form
of a JSValue and we use toObject
to get the new point back out.
So this is the geometry script
that I referenced earlier.
It has two functions,
euclideanDistance and midpoint.
They accept two arguments
each, point1 and point2.
And I'd like to call
your attention
to how this script
uses those properties
that were defined on point.
It looks exactly like a
normal JavaScript property.
It looks like you're
programing in JavaScript here.
It's completely transparent
that these are actually
Objective-C objects
under the hood.
[ Pause ]
So, now that we've talked
about bridging the gap
between JavaScript and
Objective-C and vice versa,
let's talk about some
more advanced API topics.
First of all, memory management.
So as you all are
probably aware,
Objective-C uses ARC, yes.
And JavaScriptCore uses
garbage collection.
So what does this mean?
Well, first of all, it means
that all the references
in JavaScript are strong.
It doesn't matter if you
create reference cycles
because the garbage collector
can handle reference cycles.
So for this particular
JavaScript, the Objective-C API,
the memory management
is mostly automatic,
JSValue keeps things
alive for you as long
as you're using the JSValue
so you don't really have
to worry about that.
However, there are
two situations
that require a little
bit of extra attention:
First is storing JavaScript
values in Objective-C objects
as instance variables.
You can't just store a
JSValue inside of your object,
you will very easily create a
reference cycle and we'll talk
about how to deal
with that in a second.
The second is adding JavaScript
fields to Objective-C objects,
and what I mean by that is if
you have an Objective-C object
that you bridge to JavaScript,
if you add a field to it
that is not one of the
properties that you listed
in your JSExport
protocol, we will--
we allow that but we'll create
a new extra JavaScript-only side
field, so you have to be careful
in that case too and what--
the mechanism to
manage this correctly--
manage these two
situations correctly,
I'll talk about it in a second.
So, here's an example of how you
can create a retain cycle doing
the wrong thing.
So we have a JavaScript
constructor, ClickHandler,
looks like a function
but it's a constructor,
and it accepts a
button and a callback,
so the button is an
Objective-C object
and the callback is the
JavaScript function you want
to call whenever this
button is clicked.
So the ClickHandler makes
a reference to the button
and it also sets the buttons
onClickHandler to itself
and then it stores the
callback for use later,
pretty, pretty pedestrian.
However, you get into a little
bit of trouble if you try
to implement the
setOnClickHandler setter
like this.
The onClickHandler, if you just
assign the JSValue directly
into the instance
variable of MyButton,
then you'll create a retain
cycle as you can see here.
So MyButton has a strong
reference to its onClickHandler
through its JSValue to
the ClickHandler object.
And the ClickHandler has
a strong reference back
to the button through
this.button.
And it wouldn't really work
to make this a weak
reference either
because then ClickHandler
would disappear
and we wouldn't get our
callbacks as we expected.
So we need a different
type of edge,
a different type of reference.
And the name of that
reference is JSManagedValue.
So, this is the correct
setOnClickHandler.
We take the JSValue
that's passed to us
and we create what's called
a JSManagedValue using
managedValueWithValue passing
the handler there, and we assign
that to our onClickHandler
field.
Then we ask the JavaScript
virtual machine,
which has access
through the context,
to add a managed reference
between ourselves, the button,
and the onClickHandler
that we're now referencing.
Now, what exactly is this
addManagedReference deal?
So you can think of
addManagedReference
as creating a garbage
collected reference,
it's not a strong reference,
it's not a weak reference,
it's a new type of reference,
it's a garbage collected
reference
as represented here
by the dashed line.
So now we have this
garbage collected reference
that tells JavaScript-- it tells
the JavaScript garbage collector
about this edge, it lets it
know that this edge exist
and that it may need to
do some special things
to keep that memory alive.
So we resolved our
reference cycle here.
So, JSManagedValue by
itself is a weak reference
to a JavaScript value.
So this is how you
create weak references.
JSValue is a strong
reference, JSManagedValue
by itself is a weak reference
to a JavaScript value.
addManagedReference:withOwner
which is the--
notifying the virtual
machine of the presence
of this JSManagedValue,
turns the JSManagedValue
into a garbage collected
reference.
And what this means is that, if
JavaScript can find the owner
where you saw the owner
parameter at the end, withOwner,
if JavaScript can find
that during its garbage
collection cycle,
it keeps the reference alive.
Otherwise, the reference
is released.
So now that we talked
about memory management,
let's talk a little
bit about threading.
But first to talk about
threading, we have to talk
about virtual machines.
In this case, JSVirtualMachine
which we used
in the previous slide
when we were
calling addManagedReference.
So, a JSVirtualMachine
is a container
that can contain
multiple JSContexts
and you can have
multiple JSVirtualMachines
in a single process that
have different contexts
and some JSValues live
inside of these contexts,
and you can pass JSValues
between JSContexts
in the same virtual machine.
That's good.
But, you can't pass them
between JSVirtualMachines.
And the reasons for this
are a little bit technical,
but shortly,
each JSVirtualMachine
has its own heap
and its own garbage collector.
So if you pass-- if you
were to pass a JSValue
from one JSVirtualMachine
to another,
that particular garbage
collector doesn't know how
to deal with things
from a different heap.
So that's the reason that
you're not allowed to do that.
So how does JSVirtualMachine
affect threading?
Well, so the API itself,
JavaScriptCore, is
a thread safe API.
You can call into various
JSContexts and evaluate code
and create values and that sort
of thing on different threads
and everything will work fine.
However, the locking
granularity is at the level
of a JSVirtualMachine.
So, this means that you
can call into JavaScript
on different threads in the
same virtual machine, however,
whenever one thread is
executing JavaScript,
no other thread can be
executing JavaScript
in that virtual machine.
So, if you want to add
concurrency or parallelism
to your JavaScript program
in your native application,
you should use separate
JSVirtualMachines
which can execute concurrently
on separate threads,
in that way you can
take advantage
of the parallelism there.
We're going to talk
about interfacing
with the JavaScriptCore C API.
The C API has its inherent
warts, but it's very easy
to start to convert over
to the new Objective-C API.
There's a one to one
correspondence between JSValues
and JSValueRefs and JSContexts
and JSGlobalContextRefs.
And we make it very easy to get
one where you wanted the other
or get the other
where you have one.
So, for example, if you
have a JSGlobalContextRef,
you can call
contextWithJSGlobalContextRef
and pass that JSGlobalContextRef
and we'll give you
the appropriate--
the corresponding JSContext.
The same goes for the other way.
You can call JSGlobalContextRef
on the context that you have
and we'll give you
the C API equivalent.
Same for JSValue.
Now that we looked at all
of these advanced features
of the API such as memory
management, let's take a look
at sort of the tip
of the iceberg
of what is possible using
the new Objective-C API
in an application.
So I'm going to show you an
application called ColorMyCode.
And to give you an idea of what
this application is before I
start opening things, it's a
simple text editor similar--
along the same lines
as ColorMyWords,
but it's kind of
turned up to 11.
So it's a text editor that
can highlight code as many
of you probably use
something like that.
And it uses JavaScript
to implement a sort
of plug-in system, so that it's
very easy to add new languages
that it can syntax highlight.
It also uses JavaScript
to allow the definition
of new color schemes
and uses JavaScript
to load a configuration
file that, you know,
sets all of these
different things up.
All right.
So, I'm going to open
the project here.
Build it. We open a new window.
Now, I'm going to type
some JavaScript code.
[ Pause ]
OK and let's save it.
And now that we have a file
extension, the editor detects
that this is JavaScript so
it highlights it accordingly.
So, we can also--
this particular--
I implemented two languages.
One is JavaScript of course
and the other is Scheme.
OK, I want to do some Scheme.
Let's just save that for now.
Probably you don't want
to watch me code Scheme.
So, I'm going to save
it as a Scheme file.
And now, the editor
is configured
to use a different
color scheme for Scheme.
And you can see that it
highlights different keywords.
So, if I were to type function
in here, it doesn't really work
because that's not a keyword.
It does things like comments
so I can type a comment,
"Hello, this is my comment."
It does strings, so string.
Sure, strong, why not.
[laughter] You can do
numbers, et cetera,
same goes for JavaScript.
We have comments, we
have block comments,
we have strings again,
and numbers as well.
So that is that, and if
you look at the code here,
I'll just show you very
briefly, don't be afraid.
It's split up into separate
plug-ins on this for--
different ones for highlighting.
In this particular case, we pass
a token and based on the type,
if it's a keyword,
we do one color;
if it's an identifier
we do another color.
Here's the configuration
file that says,
"For a particular file, type
JavaScript, use this plug-in,
this highlighting, this
color scheme, et cetera."
So that's just a brief example
of what's possible using
the new Objective-C API
to JavaScriptCore.
And I don't want to
scare you away with kind
of the relative complexity
of that demo.
It only took about a weekend
to throw that together
and it's actually not
very much coded at all.
So, it's definitely possible
and it's very, very easy.
So, now that you've
seen that, now we talked
about native applications
outside of web content.
Let's talk a little bit about
how to use JavaScriptCore
in the context of a
WebKit WebView on Mac.
So first of all, why would
you want to use this?
Well, for example, you could
implement your own custom
console for your application
that displays web pages.
And you could log in
a very specific way
like you could log back
to the web server or,
you know, a variety of things.
You can pass your own
objects that you defined,
your own native objects and use
them inside of your web content.
So, the way to do this is to
use the WebFrameLoadDelegate,
and this is a delegate that
you set on the WebKit WebView.
And you want to-- it's
an informal protocol,
so you'll want to
override the -webView:
didCreateJavaScriptContext:
forFrame delegate callback.
And so you can install your
custom objects using the context
argument passed as
the second argument,
so it
didCreateJavaScriptContext.
And you can build your whole
native API using that context
like I showed you earlier
with the subscript notation,
you can insert things
into the global object
and all of that good stuff.
You can evaluate new
scripts, et cetera.
And if you used some of
the old callbacks before
like the WebScriptObject
interface
in the WebFrameLoadDelegate,
it replaces those old
callbacks gracefully,
meaning that if it's
running on--
if your application
is running on a client
that doesn't have the
new API available to it,
it will fallback gracefully
to use your old implementation
of your callbacks.
And a good example of
this is the iTunes store
on Mac uses a WebView
for its content.
The iTune store uses HTML, CSS,
JavaScript web technologies
but it uses its own custom
native objects to do things
like when you click
the Buy button, it--
the rest of iTunes already
has a lot of code set up to
like process your credit card
and all of that good stuff.
So, they just call
into that code
that they've already written
and they can take advantage
of that directly in
their web content.
So here's a simple example
using the console example
that I described earlier.
So I define my
MyFrameLoadDelegete
and I override the callback.
You can see the second argument
is the context, that's the one
that I really care about.
And I create a new
console using alloc init.
Imagine it's like a kind of
a normal console that has
like a log that you can call.
And I insert it directly
into the global object
using the context.
And so here's the HTML that
could take advantage of this.
So you'll see I have a
normal HTML web page.
In the body there's a button
and when you click the button,
it calls this handler guy
which will then call the
myConsole.log function instance
method on that Objective-C
object that you inserted.
So in summary, we've covered
getting Objective-C to talk
to JavaScript and in
turn, getting JavaScript
to talk back to Objective-C.
We talked about interfacing
with the JavaScriptCore C API.
We talked about how to
get reference counting
and garbage collection to
play nicely together using
JSManagedValue and
addManagedReference.
We talked about threading and
how to use threads effectively
at the granularity
of JSVirtualMachine.
And we talked about using custom
objects in WebKit WebViews
and using that
WebFrameLoadDelegate callback
to insert your own native
objects into your web content.
So I have a Call to Action.
For all of you who views the
C API, I would challenge you
to convert one bit of your-- one
small segment of your old code
to use the new Objective-C API.
You'll see that it's
much more concise
where something might have
taken five lines before,
it might take only one now.
It's much less verbose
and it eliminates a lot
of the retain release bugs
that you might have experienced
using the old JavaScriptCore
C API.
And if you're new to this
whole JavaScriptCore framework,
I would challenge you
to add a small snippet
of JavaScript somewhere
in your app,
maybe to load a configuration
file
or something on those lines.
And you'll see that it's really,
really easy to do what
you were trying to do
and it's very concise.
But you-- at the same time,
you feel like you're
still programming
in either Objective-C
or JavaScript depending
on what you're currently
writing.
For more information, I--
contact John Geleynse.
He's the technology evangelist.
The documentation is not
current but it's coming.
This is the-- this
documentation on the slide is
for the current JavaScriptCore
C API
but it will be updated
in the future.
And of course you can go
the Apple Developer Forums.
So related sessions, this
is for the people online.
These are all the kind
of web content related
because JavaScript
is a web technology.
So if you want to know more
about web technologies,
I'd recommend you to
check out these sessions.
Most of them have
already passed.
But, yeah, thank you very much.
[ Applause ]