[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Hello. Good morning,
everyone.
Welcome to Part 1 of
iMessage Apps and Stickers.
My name is Bhaskar
and I'm an engineer
on the Messages Team at Apple.
Today we are introducing
iMessage apps.
And what that means is that
you will be able to write apps
that run within the context
of the Messages application.
iMessage apps can provide
three main types of content.
Number one, they can
provide interactive messages.
Interactive messages
are a type of message
that your application generates
and when your user taps
on this message, it will
launch your application.
For example, in the
screenshot shown here,
I'm using the DoorDash app
to send a menu to my friends
for the party that we
are having later tonight.
On their phones they will
be able to see that message
and if they have the application
installed, they will be able
to tap on it and tapping
will launch DoorDash.
At that point they will be
able to modify the menu,
add stuff to it, and
send a reply back to me.
iMessage apps can
also provide Stickers.
Stickers are images
generated by your application
and we believe it
helps create a very fun
and interactive experience
between iMessage users.
And lastly, iMessage apps
can provide every other type
of content that Messages has
always supported, like photos,
videos, text, links, et cetera.
Also in iOS 10 we will
have a Messages App Store.
What that means is that
the apps that you write
and create will be
shown and displayed
in this Messages App Store.
Users will be able to get to
this App Store via Messages
and they will be able to
download your applications.
Applications that your users
have downloaded will be
displayed within
Messages in the UI
which we call the
Messages App Drawer.
We also have this great
feature that allows your users
to discover your
applications very easily
and we call it inline
app attribution.
Let's try to understand what
that means with an example.
In the screenshot shown here
I have received a Sticker
from my friend but I do not
have that application installed
from which he sent the Sticker.
In that case, as you can
see the zoomed in area,
beneath the Sticker we will
have the name of the application
from which the Sticker was sent.
And tapping on the piece of text
will launch the Messages App
Store and present me
with the application
from which the Sticker was sent.
And then I can download
the application and use it
like any other iMessage app.
In this example shown here, I
used the Sticker as an example
to illustrate inline
app attribution.
However, it applies to
every other type of content
that your iMessage
app can generate.
Also creating an iMessage
app is very similar
to creating any other
iOS application
that you have already created.
You will be able to use the
same set of technologies
and framework that you
already use currently.
For example, some of the
things that you can use are:
You can do in-app purchase
within your application;
you will have access
to Apple Pay;
and your iMessage app will
also be able to use the camera.
And we believe these
technologies
and features will allow you
to create great apps
for your users.
Now let's talk about
supportive platforms.
iMessage apps will
only run on iOS 10.
However, the content that your
application generates will be
sent to, and can be viewed
on watchOS and macOS devices.
In watchOS 3.0, within
the Messages application,
we also have a new page
called the Recents Page.
The Recents Page, amongst other
things, will display Stickers
that your users had recently
sent from their phone.
And you users will
not only be able
to see these recent Stickers,
they will also be able
to send these Stickers
from their watch just
like they are able to
send it from their phones.
So that was about the
Messages App Store
and the Messages platform.
Now let's get into details
of creating iMessage apps.
This is what we're
going to cover
in the rest of the
session today.
First we are going to talk
about the Messages framework.
Messages framework is the
framework that you guys need
to familiarize yourself with
to create iMessage apps.
Then we're going to talk
about creating a
Sticker Pack application.
Next we are going to go into
details of Sticker file formats
and other constraints
around Stickers.
And lastly we're going to talk
about creating a custom
Sticker experience using the
Messages framework.
What we will not cover
in today's talk is how
to create an application that
provides interactive messages.
We will cover such an
application in Part 2
of our talk and I
do request you guys
to please come back for that.
That will be here on Thursday
at 1:40 p.m. Messages framework,
Messages framework
is the new framework
that we are introducing
in iOS 10.
Messages framework
acts as an interface
between your iMessages app
and the Messages application.
When your user taps on your app
icon to launch your application,
it is through this framework
that we discover your app,
launch it, and provide
your application with data
and other context
your application needs
to lay out its UI.
Once your application has
presented its UI your users are
ready to interact with it.
And at the end of that
interaction your application
will hopefully generate some
content that your user wants
to share by Messages and your
app hands this content back
to Messages by this framework.
And at that point your
users are ready to share
that thing via Messages
with whomever they're
talking to at that point.
I would like to mention
that the Messages framework
and iMessage apps
are built on top
of existing app extension
technology.
And in that sense your
iMessage app is an app extension
and in this scenario the
Messages app is acting
as the host application
for your iMessage app.
For those of you
who are not familiar
or who have not made extensions
before, I do recommend
that you please go back and
take a look at this WWDC talk
from 2014 that introduces
extensions in iOS and OS X.
So as I just mentioned, iMessage
apps are extensions, however,
there's one key difference
as compared
to other extension
points on iOS.
Unlike other extension
points you do not have
to provide a containing
application
for your iMessage app.
You can only ship your
iMessage app if you want to.
But if you already have
a containing application
that you created or that
you're already shipping
to the App Store, you can
always include an iMessage app
within your containing
application because,
as I mentioned, these
are extensions.
So if you provide a
containing application,
then your application will
show up in the main Home screen
of your users' phones and
the Messages App Drawer
within Messages.
It will also show up
in the main App Store
and in the Messages App Store.
But if you do not provide a
containing application, then,
as you can see, your
application will not show
up in the main Home screen
and the main App Store.
It will only show up in
the Messages App Drawer
and the Messages App Store.
I would like to mention that if
you do not provide a containing
application, you still
have to provide an icon
for your containing application.
This is the icon that will
be used in other parts
of the system like the Settings
application to show information
about your application,
for example,
the amount of storage
it is using.
So now let's talk
about Stickers.
Stickers are a fun way and
a new way to communicate
with other iMessage users.
Your users can send
Stickers inline just
like any other iMessage
your users already send.
Or your users, not
your Stickers,
or your users can drag Stickers
out of their applications
and attach them to
other Message bubbles.
And we believe this lends
itself to a very expressive
and engaging messaging
experience.
But what do Stickers
mean to you?
Stickers are basically images
that your application provides.
These images can be animated
or they can be static.
And we believe Stickers
are a great way to share
or promote any content
that you may have.
And we generally think
Sticker applications are going
to be very, very popular
amongst iMessage users.
So now let's talk about
creating Sticker apps.
There are two ways to
create a Sticker app.
First, you can create a Sticker
Pack application using Xcode.
If you go down this
route, you do not have
to provide any code
for your application.
You only have to
provide the assets
for your Stickers
and the app icons.
But if you want to
customize your application,
you can do so by providing code.
And your code in this case
will provide Stickers via the
Messages framework.
At this point let me
show you a demo of how
to create a Sticker Pack
application using Xcode.
So I have my machine here and
I'm going to launch Xcode.
And here I'm going
to say I'm going
to create a new Xcode project.
And under the Title of
Application I'm going
to select Sticker
Pack Application.
And then I'm going to hit Next.
And I'm going to name my project
"SFStickers" as the assets
that I'm going to use are going
to be assets depicting various
landmarks in San Francisco.
So I click Next here.
And for now just let me
create it on my desktop.
I'm done. Let me quickly
make Xcode bigger.
Great. So, as you can see here
in the template that you get
in a Sticker Pack application,
there are no source code files.
That is a very deliberate
design of this template
and so let me reiterate this,
if you create a Sticker
Pack Application,
you cannot provide any code.
You only provide the Sticker
and the app icon assets.
So let's see how to do that.
I go into the Stickers --
that's the Catalog which
has two catalogs within it.
One is the Sticker Pack and the
other is the iMessage App Icon.
I click on Sticker Pack.
And, as you can see it says I do
not have any Stickers and I need
to drag and drop the
images to add new Stickers.
So let me do that.
So go to Finder and
I go to Desktop.
And I have some assets
here that I want to use.
So I'm going to click on
the first one and I'm going
to drag and drop it here.
So that's Golden Gate Bridge.
I'm going to drag
the second one.
That's Chinatown.
And just to be quick
I'm just going
to select everything
else and drag it here.
Great. So I have all my assets.
So these assets are a PNG type.
Xcode also allows you
to create an [inaudible]
in your Sticker using the
individual frames of the PNG.
Let me show you how to do that.
So I'm going to click, or
rather right-click here
and I'm going to
go to Add Assets.
And I'm going to say
New Sticker Sequence.
So when you create a new Sticker
sequence Xcode expects you
to provide the individual
frames of the Sticker
that you're about to create.
So I'm going to go
back to my desktop.
I'm going to click here where
I have the individual frames.
I'm going to drag
the first one in.
the second one in.
Third one.
And finally the fourth one.
Now let's go back to Xcode
and see what it does.
So as you can see, I
have an enlarged version
of the Sticker here and click
in its center will actually
show it to me animating.
Looks good.
Now let me just throw
in the app icons.
I go to the App Icon Catalog.
I go in here and I select
these things, drag it here.
Looks like I may
have missed one.
Let me quickly do
that one again.
All right.
So I provided the app icons.
At this point I'm ready.
My app is done.
So let me try and see
how it looks like.
I'm going to go here
and test my application
against the simulator.
I'm going to select iPhone 6s
as the device I want
to test against.
And I'm going to go to Product
and I'm going to hit Run.
I'm just going to wait
for this thing to show up.
Great. So Messages has shown up
and since I'm creating
an iMessage app,
I'm testing it against Messages.
And I'm going to run it.
And the simulator is launching.
Great. So here you can see I
have two simulated conversations
in Messages in the simulator.
By simulated conversation what
I mean is if you go into one
of them and send a
message, it will show
up as an incoming message
in the other conversation.
And just to clarify, you will
not be able to send messages
out of the simulator
to real devices.
So going into the first one
and I type in something.
And at this point I'm
just talking to myself so.
As you can see, this
is my message here.
Great. Now let me see
what my app looks like.
So I go in the App
Drawer, and there you go.
My application is ready
here to be launched.
I click on it.
There you go.
The assets have shown
up right there.
These are the same assets that I
just added and I can scroll down
and look how they look like.
And, as you can see the
animated PNG is also here.
And I can click on one
of them, peel them,
drag them out of
the application,
and attach to a message
bubble right here.
Great. And as you can
see, I can go back out,
go into the other conversation.
I see the Sticker here.
So this is how you create
a Sticker Pack application.
However, there's one more thing
that I want to show you here
and that is how to
customize certain aspects
of this application.
So going back to asset Stickers,
I will show you now how
to change the sizes of the cells
in which your Stickers are being
displayed in this grid here.
So to do that, let
me go back to Xcode.
And I'm going to click
Go To The Top right here.
And as you can see,
there's a drop-down menu
by the name Sticker Size.
I click on that.
There are three options,
Small, Medium, and Large.
And I'm going to click
Large and see how
that changes my application.
I run it again.
And Messages is launched.
Let me go back to
my application.
And there you go.
As you can see, the Stickers
are now presented two-in-a-row
and they're presented
in larger cells.
And there's more
space between them.
I'm going to go into more
details of the implications
of changing the Sticker cell
size later in this session.
In that demo I showed you how
to create a Sticker Pack
application using Xcode
and in this technique,
like I showed you,
you do not have to
provide any code.
You only provide the
assets for the Stickers
and for your app icons.
I also showed you how to use
the tool built into Xcode
to create an APNG Sticker
using the individual frames
of the APNG.
And lastly, we also
talked about how
to change the Sticker
cell sizes.
Now let's talk about supported
file formats for Stickers.
We support four formats.
These are PNG, APNG,
JPEG, and GIFs.
And out of these four formats,
if you want to provide
animated Stickers,
we support APNG and GIFs.
We are also making certain
optimization under the hood
to make sending Stickers
faster as compared
to other iMessage attachments
and also to reduce the
on disk storage space
for Stickers.
And to help us make these
optimizations we have
to limit the file sizes for
Stickers to 500 kilobytes.
So as I just mentioned, we
support four file formats,
however, we do recommend that
you use PNG and APNG for most,
if not for all of your Stickers.
Let's try to understand why
we have that recommendation
by taking a look at
these screenshots.
So here I have two conversations
which look nearly identical
but there's a subtle
difference between them.
And so let me zoom in
to show what that is.
As you can see, the conversation
to the left has Sticker placed
on the photo and it
is in PNG format.
And the conversation to the
right has the same photo
and the same Sticker but that
Sticker is now in a GIF format.
If you observe carefully
and in the zoomed in areas,
the one on the left,
that is the PNG,
does not display any
artifacts around it's edges.
But the one on the
right, that is the GIF,
is displaying certain artifacts
around the edges
of the Stickers.
Now this is happening
because PNGs
and APNGs handle
transparency very well
but GIFs do not handle
transparency that well.
And if you were to compare
the transparency properties
of JPEGs, JPEGs in fact do not
handle transparency at all.
And hence keep in mind your
Stickers can be dragged
out of your applications and
attached to Message bubbles
and therefore transparency
is a very important factor
to consider while
designing your Stickers.
We also request you to
please try out your Stickers
on various colored
backgrounds like black, white,
and even multi-colored
backgrounds because, again,
your Stickers can
be placed on photos.
In the demo I just showed
you how to change the sizes
of the cells in which your
Stickers are being displayed.
There are three supported
cell sizes
and they are small,
regular, and large.
And for each of these sizes
we have a recommended maximum
dimensions of the
Stickers that it supports.
For small it is 100 by 100
points at 3x the scale.
For regular it is 136 by
136 points at 3x the scale.
For large the maximum
supported dimension is 206
by 206 points at 3x the scale.
If you provide Stickers that
are larger than the dimensions
that are supported by the cell
size that you have selected,
then your Stickers will be
shrunken down and displayed
by Messages framework and in
that case they may not look
like exactly the way you
intended them to look like.
But if your Stickers
are within these bounds,
then they will be
displayed as is.
I would also like to clarify
that we always request you
to provide us Stickers at
3x the scale regardless
of the resolution of the device
in which your application
is running.
Messages will take care of
scaling down your Stickers
if needed according
to the device
in which your Stickers are
being currently displayed.
So that is all I had to talk
about the Messages framework
and creating Sticker
applications.
At this point I would like
to hand it over to Lily
who is going to talk
about creating a custom
Sticker experience.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Bhaskar.
My name is Lily and I'm an
engineer on the Messages Team.
I'm going to talk to you
about creating a custom
Sticker application.
First, why would you want
to create a custom
Sticker application?
The first major benefit
is you will be able
to customize how you display
Stickers in your application.
In our previous example
we saw Stickers displayed
in a nice grid layout.
However, if you wanted
to position your Stickers
in any other format or even
change the background color,
you would need to create a
custom Sticker application.
A custom Sticker
application will allow you
to dynamically create stickers.
In our previous example
we bundled assets
into our application
and in order
to update those assets
we would have
to push an update
to the App Store.
If you want to pull your
assets from your servers,
or allow you users to
dynamically create them
on device, they could do so and
then you wouldn't have to update
through the App Store.
Messages extensions will
also provide camera access,
allowing your users to create
fun Stickers using the camera.
And finally your application
can utilize In-app purchases,
allowing your users
to unlock Stickers.
We can create a custom
Sticker application using
Messages framework.
Messages framework
provides the building blocks
for creating a Sticker
application.
In our example of Sticker
Pack applications built
through Xcode, they use the
same classes in this framework
so you could ideally create
the same application using
Messages framework.
In the screenshot we have
onscreen we have an application
that's displaying Stickers.
Well, you'll notice that the
background color is pink.
So I'm going to show
you how we can customize
and create an application
like this.
So let's go into a demo.
So I'm going to open
up Xcode and I'm going
to create a new project.
Bhaskar created a
Sticker Pack application
but this time we're going to
create a Messages application.
So I'm going to go
ahead and choose that.
And I'm going to call my
project "Nature Stickies"
as we're going to
use nature assets.
And we'll go ahead and
create this project
and we'll put it on our desktop.
Great. So you'll see here
that we have two folders:
Nature Stickies and
Messages Extension.
Nature Stickies does
not have source code
as this is the containing
bundle application.
You'll provide an app icon
here for your System Settings.
However, we're interested in
the folder, Messages Extension.
So we're going to go ahead and
click on MessagesViewController.
And we'll see that
MessagesViewController is going
to be our principal class.
It is a subclass of the
MSMessagesAppViewController.
The MSMessagesAppViewController
is going to be the controller
that handles callbacks from
the Messages application.
We'll be talking more
about these callbacks
and how your application
can handle them
in Part 2 of our talk.
So we can go ahead and get
rid of these functions here.
I'm going to select them
and then press Delete.
Great. So let's take a
look at Messages framework.
If we click here we have an
MSStickerBrowserViewController.
The
MSStickerBrowseViewController
will allow us to
display stickers.
It has two properties.
It has an MSStickerBrowserView
which is the view
that our Stickers
will be displayed in.
And it also has an MSStickerSize
which decide the cell sizes
of our grid for the
MSStickerBrowserView.
We'll also see that the
MSStickerBrowserViewController
conforms
to the MSStickerBrowserView
DataSource protocol.
This protocol, when implemented,
will return the number
of Stickers your
application will be displaying
and the Sticker at a given index
for the MSStickerBrowserView.
So if we want to
display our Stickers,
we'll need to create an
MSStickerBrowserViewController.
And to implement the data
source we'll go ahead
and subclass this.
So I'm going to go ahead
and create a new file.
And I'm going to choose
Swift and click Next.
And I'm going to call
this NatureStickerBrowser
ViewController.
Great. So I'm going to go
ahead and import UIKit.
And then I'll go ahead
and import Messages.
Great. So now let's
create our class.
I'm going to go ahead and
create our NatureStickerBrowser
ViewController class
as a subclass
of the
MSStickerBrowserViewController.
As I mentioned,
the
MSStickerBrowserViewController
has two data source methods
that we'll need to implement.
So I'll go ahead
and fill those in.
So now we'll need a way
to create our Stickers
and store them.
I'm going to go ahead and create
an array to hold our Stickers
and we'll see that our
Stickers are at MSSticker.
And MSSticker is an
object that has a file URL
that points to an asset on disk.
It will also have a
localized description
which will be used
for accessibility.
So let's go ahead
and create a Sticker.
I'm going to go ahead and
add assets to our bundle.
I'm going to click Add Files
and then go to my desktop
and choose these assets here.
And I've added them
to my application.
In this example we're just
adding assets to our application
but you can imagine how your
applications can either pull
these assets from your
servers or allow your users
to create them on device.
So now we'll need
to create a Sticker.
So we'll write a
function to do that.
Great. So here we
take our bundle.
We create a file URL
pointing to our asset on disk,
and then we initialize
our MSSticker
with a localized description,
and then add it to our array.
So now let's go ahead
and write a function
that will load all
of the Stickers.
Cool. So now we can go back
to our MessagesViewController
and create an instance.
And we'll create a
NatureStickerBrowser
ViewController, and we'll
instantiate it, and viewDidLoad.
Great. So now we instantiated
our browserViewController
with a Sticker size.
This will allow your application
to display your Stickers
in the grid layouts that
we showed you earlier.
So this application will
create a Sticker application
like we did through
Xcode without code.
So let's go ahead
and customize this.
I'm going to write a
function that will allow me
to change the background color
of our MSStickerBrowserView.
So we'll write that
function here.
And we're just changing
the background color
of the MSStickerBrowserView.
And I'm going to go back
to the MessagesViewController
and call that.
So now we can change
the background.
And let's go ahead and
run our application.
So I'm going to choose
the iPhone 6s
and I'm going to hit Run.
Oops. Oh, I forgot something.
We forgot to actually
implement our data source.
So let's go ahead and do that.
So I'm going to return the
Stickers count and I'm going
to return a Sticker
out of given index.
And now we're ready to run.
So I'll choose Messages as the
application I want to run in.
Great. And now we can
open up the App Drawer
and then you'll see that
we don't have an icon
because we forgot to add that.
And we'll see that we have our
app named Messages Extension.
In order to change what our
display name is we would have
to go into our project, click on
the Messages Extension Target,
and then we could
change it here.
But for now let's just see what
our application looks like.
So you'll see we now have an
application that has Stickers
with a pink background.
So this is one small example
of how you can customize
your Sticker applications.
So let's go back to the slides.
So to recap what
we just went over,
we introduced the
MSStickerBrowserView Controller.
This ViewController
will display Stickers
in your application using
the MSStickerBrowserView.
This controller also conforms
to the MSStickerBrowserView
DataSource protocol.
This protocol will
return the number
of Stickers your
application will be displaying
and the given Sticker.
We also introduced the MS
MessagesAppViewController.
This ViewController is what your
principal class will subclass.
This MSMessagesAppViewController
handles callbacks
from the Messages application.
Again, we'll talk more
about this in Part 2
and how your application
can handle these callbacks.
So that was a small example
of how we could customize
a Sticker application
by just changing the
background color.
But what if we want to do more?
Your application can add Sticker
support using just two classes,
the MSStickerView
and an MSSticker.
So if we wanted to
create an application
that displays Stickers
in a different way
than the
MSStickerBrowserViewController
does, we can do so by
using these two classes.
On the example I have behind
me we have an application.
This application
is actually using a
UICollectionViewController
to display Stickers.
And each cell
of the UICollectionView
has an MSStickerView.
The MSStickerView is the class
that will be providing the drag
and drop functionality
of Stickers
into the Messages transcript.
So we also see that
there's a Plus icon
which doesn't have
the MSStickerView.
Tapping it will expand
our application,
allow us to choose a Sticker,
and add it to our collection.
Also note that we were able
to transition how our
Stickers were displayed.
Your application
can go from being
in a compact mode
to an expanded mode.
Your users can also
toggle this so by clicking
on the chevron in the bottom.
So your application will have
to be able to handle being
in a compact and
an expanded mode.
So I'm going to show you how
you can handle these callbacks
and create an application
like this.
So let's go into another demo.
So I'm going to open up an
application I already have.
And it's called Sticker Picker.
And let's go ahead
and make this bigger.
Great. So we're back in
our MessagesViewController
which is our principal
class, again,
subclassing the
MSMessagesAppViewController.
We had two views
that we displayed,
our UICollectionView
holding MSStickerViews,
and we also had a view
that would allow us
to add Stickers to
our application.
These two views are
going to be represented
in a StickerPickerCollection
ViewController
and in an
AddStickersViewController.
Let's take a look
at the StickerPickerCollection
ViewController.
The StickerPickerCollection
ViewController,
subclass is a
UICollectionViewController.
The items that we'll have
are a CollectionViewItem.
So it can either be
the AddSticker item
or it could be a Sticker.
So let's go ahead and
look at the Sticker cell.
The Sticker cell has
an MSStickerView.
The MSStickerView will
have a Sticker and,
in order to handle animations
of your animated Stickers,
we would have to call
startAnimating and stopAnimating
when we are displaying
our MSStickerView.
So let's go back
to the StickerPickerCollection
ViewController.
Great. So when we create this
ViewController we're going
to go ahead and create
all of our items.
We'll create an AddStickerItem
and then we'll load our
Stickers the same way we did
in our previous example.
We'll return the number of
items in our collectionView
and we'll create Sticker
cells or the Add Sticker cell
for an item at a
given index path.
When creating the Sticker
cell we're going to want
to assign the Sticker
value of our stickerView.
So let's go ahead and do that.
So we have now put a
Sticker on our stickerView.
And, as I mentioned, our
Stickers can be animated.
And we'll need to be calling
start and stopAnimating
to control these animations.
When we're going to display
our Sticker we're going to want
to call startAnimating and when
we stop displaying our Sticker
we're going to want
to call stopAnimating.
So we can write a
function to check
if the Sticker is
animatable or not
by loading the image file URL,
and using a CG image source,
and counting the frames.
If we have more than one frame,
we know that we have
an animated Sticker.
So we'll go ahead
and implement this.
So we'll check to see
if our Sticker cell
Sticker can animate.
And if it can, then we'll
call startAnimating.
And then when we're done
displaying our cell we'll go
ahead and check if our Sticker
is animating, and if it is,
we'll call stopAnimating.
Great. So let's go back to
the MessagesViewController.
And we'll go ahead
and instantiate the
StickerPickerViewController
as that's going to be
the view we want loaded
when we first launch
our application.
So we'll do that in viewDidLoad
and then we'll present it.
When the user taps the
Add icon we'll want
to create the
AddStickersViewController.
And then we're going
to want to transition
into an expanded mode.
We can do so by calling
requestPresentationStyle.
This will tell the
Messages application
that your application
wants to be expanded.
You'll then get a call back
from the Messages
application once you've done
this transition.
So
in didTransitiontopresentation
Style we'll get a call back
and we'll first check to see
if we have an
AddStickersViewController.
And if we do and our
presentation style is expanded,
we'll go ahead and
present that view.
Or else we'll present the other
view we want to show in compact.
After we choose a Sticker
we're going to want
to go back to compact.
So we'll then again call
requestPresentationStyle
.compact.
So if we run our
application we'll be able
to see all of this in play.
So I'm going to go ahead
and choose Messages
as the application
I want to run.
And we're going to launch.
I'm going to go ahead and
click on the App Drawer.
And we're going to
click on Sticker Picker
and wait for it to load.
Great. So now we can go
ahead and add a Sticker.
And I'm going to choose
this cute panda right here.
And we'll see it
also animating here.
And then we can send
our Stickers.
So to recap what we just
went over, we introduced,
we showed you how to create
a Sticker application using a
UICollectionView and
in each of the cells
of the UICollectionView
we had an MSStickerView.
The MSStickerView allowed
us to drag and drop Stickers
into the transcript and
it also had an MSSticker.
We also showed you how you
can transition from a compact
to an expanded presentation
style.
And we also showed you how
you can handle such callbacks
from the Messages application.
Remember that your users
can toggle between the two
by tapping on the chevron icon
so please keep that in mind
on designing your application.
Bhaskar talked about the Sticker
File Formats that we used
when creating a Sticker
Pack Application.
These same file formats apply
to creating a custom
Sticker application.
So to summarize what
we went over today,
we introduced iMessage apps as a
platform to you as a developer.
There's a new way to
interact with Messages
and it's really fun
and exciting.
We also introduced
Messages framework
and how you could create
Sticker Pack Applications using
Messages framework.
We showed you how to create a
Sticker Pack Application using
Xcode with no code.
And we also showed you how
to programmatically create a
custom Sticker application.
In Part 2 of our talk
we're going to show you how
to create an application that
will allow your application
to send interactive messages.
For more information
please visit the website
and we'll have a related session
back here in the Presidio
at 1:40 p.m. on Thursday.
Thank you so much.
We can't wait to see
what you guys create
and please come to our labs.
Have a great rest
of the conference.
[ Applause ]