[ Music ]
>> Good afternoon.
[ Applause ]
>> Welcome.
My name is Olivier Gutknecht
and I manage the UIKit team
and today we're going to talk
about what's new in UIKit
and other system
frameworks in iOS 10.
But first, I'd like
to talk about,
what is not new, in Cocoa Touch.
Why, since last WWDC,
we introduced a number
of very important products.
The iPhone 6S with 3D Touch.
The iPad Pro 12.9
inch and 9.7 inch.
The Apple Pencil, and
the Smart Keyboard.
And, with these products
there is a number
of key technologies
you can adopt
to make your applications
really shine.
The first thing that I want
to talk about is adaptivity.
When we introduced adaptivity
2 years ago one thing
that we introduced was the
concept of a size class.
The iPhone was a
compact size class.
The iPad is regular.
And now we have the
12.9 inch iPad Pro,
do we need gigantic size class?
We don't. Because now
we have all the tools
in the framework
to express that.
We have the trait system
which is how your application
will understand the context
and environment of
your application.
Size classes, that's one very
important trait but then,
you have everything
you need to be able
to build a size based
layout on these devices.
We added new support
for size classes
in Interface Builder and,
in the framework itself,
from auto layout to asset
catalogs with dynamic type,
with layout guide, and
even UI appearance,
everything is ready
and fully integrated.
We're going to have also,
two sessions this week
making app adaptive.
The first one's going to focus
fundamentals and the tools.
And the second one,
will be about the API
and the techniques you can use
to make your application
adaptive.
And this morning there was
an amazing, session focused
on design, you should watch.
The second thing that I'd like
to talk about is touch input.
Last year, with the iPad
Air 2 and the iPad Pro now,
we have 120 Hz touch scanning.
We are scanning faster than
the screen refresh rate.
And now, with Apple Pencil
we have additional properties
on touches so you can get
orientation precise location,
force.
With iPhone 6S, you have
the same force information
with 3D Touch and we shift
in our iOS 9, in our iOS 9.1.
The APIs you need to build
amazing UIs with these devices.
And Dominique Wagner is going
to present how you can
leverage touch input on iOS.
The last thing that I'd like to
mention is the Smart Keyboard.
We have an API for you, so you
can express keyboard shortcuts
in your apps, I think you have
more users than ever interacting
with your application
with a keyboard.
So you can have dynamic
in context shortcuts.
The API for that is reasonable.
It's actually, an API
that is new in our iOS 7.
And it's important now
because since iOS 9,
we can display these
beautiful automatic shortcuts
when you hold the command key.
Now, let's talk about what
is new in Cocoa Touch.
I'd like to cover
four things today.
One, the core technologies
you probably already use
in your applications.
And, we're going to discuss
how, with UIKit and other API,
you can build better UIs
for your applications.
We're going to show how
the new system features
in iOS 10 can make your
application better.
And, we're going
to conclude with,
how your application
itself can extend the system
with all new extension points.
So let's talk about
these core technologies.
Swift 3 is probably
the first thing here.
Because with Swift 3, every
single API we have is new again.
Because we change the rules,
we change how we translate
from Objective-C to Swift.
And we are doing that,
to make your code better
so it can feel native really,
when writing that in Swift.
So for instance, something
like preferred font,
we are now using
the first argument
to make the intent clear.
We also try to not repeat
ourselves, UI Color,
black color now is
just white or black.
One thing that I really like
with Swift 3 is how APIs
and core graphics
now really feel great
when writing UIKit application.
And, even something like,
grand central dispatch,
is now a full object API.
Let's talk about grand
central dispatch.
There is a feature that I really
like, something very common
with the dispatch is the
create your own private queue.
And when queue work item to be
executed as synchronously and,
a new thing in iOS 10, is you
can actually set the queue
to automatically wrap every work
item in an autorelease pool.
It's real easy to do, you
just create a dispatch queue,
and you pass the
autorelease work item.
We have a full session on GCD,
and conquering programming.
Foundation, foundation
also adapted a lot
of Swift enhancement, we dropped
the MS prefix from many classes
and we have a major new feature,
we are adding value types
to the foundation API.
It's not just that.
We also have full
support for units
and measurements in foundation.
Another thing is a new date
formatter for the AP 601 format.
If you know what AP 601 is,
you're probably very
happy about that.
[ Applause ]
And another nice feature is how
we're making date computation
better with new NS
date interval.
We have two sessions
on foundation,
What's New in Foundation
and Swift,
and Measurements and Units.
Yesterday, we announced
support for universal keyboard,
copy on your Mac and
paste on your iOS device.
So how do you use that
in your application?
You just use the existing UI
Pasteboard API, that's it.
There is one thing
you need to know.
You might have to fetch a very
large asset on your device,
if I do a copy of
a very big image,
it might take a second or two.
So you might see this UI.
So to avoid, problem when
retrieving remote data,
you should check first, if
you need that data or not.
So you can avoid this UI.
We added four new methods
to UI Pasteboard for that
so you can easily check for
screen, URLs, images and colors.
Another thing in
UI Pasteboard is
that you can now control what
you publish on the pasteboard.
So now you can restrict your
data, on the local device
or set an expiration date.
[ Applause ]
Now I'd like to talk
about color.
It's not a software feature,
it's really a hardware feature
that we have now in the new iMac
5K, and the iPad Pro 9.7 inch.
It's a technology shift, you can
now represent colors on screen
that was not physically
possible before.
And, we are changing how we
are going to represent colors.
The iOS devices were using
the sRGB color space.
Now with this device,
you're going to work
in that extended
sRGB color space.
So what does that mean for you?
So first, iOS is actually
already color managed.
iOS and [inaudible] and in iOS
10, we are exposing the API
to work with a wide color range.
The first way is to
just use UI Image View.
UI Image View is actually
already color managed
since iOS 9.3, so
you're ready there.
What about UI Color?
We made that very simple.
We have one existing
initializer, in it with RGB.
Second one, and new one,
in it with display P3 RGB.
The first one is how you can
represent an arbitrary color
in the extended sRGB space.
So now you can express a
color that goes beyond the 0
to 1 range, if you want
to go beyond classic sRGB.
The second one displayP3,
displayP3 is actually
a color display
that is quite common
on the creation side.
So if you receive a spec with
a wide color, it's very likely
that you're going
to use displayP3
which is why we made that,
initializer available.
And that's it.
We don't have a color
space class.
You can just use these two
initiliazers and you're done.
Now, I'd like to talk
about image rendering.
Image rendering is something
that you're probably
already using today
with the UI graphics
begin image context,
add image from text APIs.
Kind of thing that you do in
direct on when you want to,
render an image off screen.
So there is one problem
with this API.
It's actually 32 bits sRGB only,
that's a built in assumption.
Also, that's not our best API,
it was there before the blocks
and it's not really extensible.
So, something that you're
writing with, the graphics,
begin image context, API,
would look like that.
And I don't know how many of
you already made the mistake
of trying to get the image
after the begin image context.
I'm definitely one.
But now, we have a new class,
the new UI graphics
render class.
And what this is giving you is,
first, it's fully color managed.
It's going to do the
right thing by default.
If you're on a 9.7
inch iPad, you're going
to get a wide color context.
If you're not, you will
get the classic context.
The other thing, it's
block based, easier to use.
And, it's an object
based API so we have
to increase our classes
for images and PDFs.
Also, and that's
quite important,
that class will manage the
lifetime of your context.
Which means that we can do
some memory optimization
under the hood.
Let me give you an example.
For that the equivalent
of the one before,
you just create your renderer.
You try to generate an
image, it's just a matter
of passing the block, and
having your drawing code here.
And the thing that's
really cool about that is,
if you call again, the
image method here are going
to just be used the
context again.
A new feature related to
images is asset catalogs.
With asset catalogs, we have
support for wide color assets,
right to left and left to
right assets, and compression.
And of course they're
fully integrated
with the trait system in UIKit.
So, let's see the first one.
What color asset?
So what do we want to do here?
If you're embedding,
a wide color asset,
in your application, you
want to be able to deploy
on a non-wide color device.
So what we are going to do is,
we're going to do a generation
of sRGB variant automatically
for you.
And that's going to be fully
compatible with App Thinning,
so we're going to deploy
only what is needed
on the right device.
The other new feature in
asset catalog is compression.
We added support for a
lossy compression scheme.
And, it's going to automatically
pick, if you choose so,
it's going to automatically
generate the right variants
for a given device.
So you will a great balance
between footprint and quality.
And again, that's completely
compatible with App Thinning
so we only deploy what is
needed on a given device.
The last feature I
want to describe here
for asset catalog
is the direction
or image asset support.
It means that now, directly
at the asset catalog level,
you can specify that an
image should be an RTL asset
or a left to right asset.
Or something that should
be automatically flipped,
directly in the asset
management system.
We also have a full session on
international user interfaces,
where you can learn more about
the improvements in iOS 10.
Now, I'd like to switch
to how you can build
better user interfaces
and interactions in iOS 10.
And the first thing is,
you need to make sure
that everybody can interact
with your application.
We have the new accessibility
inspector
and one thing you can do with
that is, it's really great,
you can connect to an
app and automatically,
immediately know the
accessibility properties
of a given UI element.
There is another
really nice feature.
You can also run an audit
on the application running
in the simulator or your device.
Just so you can have a
first hint about the kind
of problems you might want to
fix, probably you really want
to fix, with your application.
One thing though, it's just like
Xcode if you have 0 warnings
that doesn't mean that
your application is
absolutely perfect.
But, that's a great first step.
We also have a new
way to interact
with your applications
in iOS 10.
We added a new gesture,
speech recognizer,
[ Foreign Language ]
And not just for English.
And it's a very simple API.
The SFSpeech recognizer,
is something
that can do continuous
speech recognition.
And, you can connect
it to an audio file
or a live audio stream.
So you can do real time,
speech recognition.
You can configure it to have a
recognition that is optimized
for dictation, or for
very simple strings.
Just want to give you
an example of this API.
You create a recognizer, you
configure it with a request,
you start a task,
and we're going
to call you back with results.
Really easy to use.
We have a video in line in
the WWDC app about this API.
Another great improvement
in iOS 10 is text input.
One thing you can do now is to
add information about the kind
of content you have
in your text field.
So, with that we can provide
intelligent suggestions
in quick type.
So for instance if my text
field is about location,
I'm going to see an
address in quick type.
We have many predefined
content types, for people,
you can specify first name, last
name, full name, or locations,
and in that case
that was configured
as a full street address.
Or even things like email,
telephone, credit card numbers.
Another thing about text input
and text is how you
can render text in iOS.
In iOS 7 we added support for
dynamic type and in iOS 10,
we are making the
content size category
for dynamic type, a trait.
So what does that mean?
Before iOS 10 the content size
category was just a property
on UI application.
And, you actually sent
the notifications.
If the user was changing,
the content size,
you had to react this
notification and update your UI.
Now, because it's integrated
as a trait, it's available
on view controllers which mean
that you can use dynamic
type in all UI extensions.
And we actually also added
support for dynamic type
in existing elements
in new UIKit.
So if you build your UI with
text field, text view, labels,
and you want to react,
to the size change,
now in iOS 10 you can
use new adjust font
for content size category
and your label and text view,
text field going to
just react to that.
And your application, if you're
using audio app for instance,
will update automatically.
So I think that's a really
great feature for dynamic type,
full automatic support, for
labels, and text fields.
[ Applause ]
We also wanted to add new
customization in UIKit.
A good example is
the tab bar items,
now you can customize the batch
colors and the text attributes
in tab bar items, and you can
also customize the unselected
theme color.
So let's say that I
have a standard tab bar
that is going to look like that.
If I add this code, to my
application, that's going
to be my new tab bar UI.
Which is probably also
why I'm not a designer.
[ Applause ]
Another great customization,
in web views.
When we ship Peek and
Pop for 3D Touch iPhones,
we had a very simple API in
UIKit for view controllers.
And we had built in
support, WK web view.
And now in iOS 10, you
have fine control of Peek
and Pop behaviors
in the web view,
which means that you can
use custom view controllers
when doing a Peek.
And you can have preview
actions, and a great consequence
of that is, when you Pop in
a web view, you can decide
to stay inside your application.
It's available as new delegate
methods on the web view class.
But, the thing that I'm really
excited about for Peek and Pop,
is the new UI preview
interaction class.
So, Peek and Pop in UIKit,
is really two things.
There is a look, this blur
effect, this nice animation
when you want to
preview something.
And there is a feel, how
do we react, to pressure,
how do we detect the intent
of the user, is that attack,
a scroll, the beginning
of a Peek?
With UI preview interaction,
what you can do is
to use a UIKit provided
implementation for the feel,
but have your own
animation for Peek and Pop.
And, that's just a new delegate
on that class, so you can know
when you move from Peek
to Pop, and we are going
to give you the progress,
the progression progress
so you can plug your own
interaction, your own animation.
You can do completely
custom Peek
and Pop UI we think
that's a really big deal.
[ Applause ]
If you want to learn everything
about Peek and Pop and 3D Touch,
we have a full session
here on Thursday at 4 p.m.
Another new thing is
something that we added
in scroll views that
you asked for.
And it's actually full support
for the UI refresh control.
[ Applause ]
It's available on
UI scroll view,
and scroll view of classes.
So we already had support for
table view and refresh control,
so it mean that now you
can use refresh control
in correction views.
Let's talk about
collection view.
That's a great feature in UIKit.
And last year we added support
for automatic self-sizing
cells in flow layout.
What you had to do before is,
you had to compute
that estimated size.
And sometimes it's not easy but,
at the UIKit level we know
what cells are going on screen.
So we have a new
mode in flow layout,
so you can pass automatic
and we're going to do
that estimation for you,
you don't need to try to do
that estimation anymore.
[ Applause ]
Do you know that we
have reordering support
in UI correction view?
We do. And we are improving
that by adding paging
support in collection view.
That's something that is exposed
at the scroll view level,
and correction view will now
do the right thing for you.
But, one feature this year,
that I'm really excited
about for collection view
is, smooth scrolling.
It's a real simple,
and smart idea.
So, if I have a grid,
in a collection view,
and I'm going to
scroll that grid.
At some point, I'm going to
need to bring three cells
on screen at the same time.
And if your cells are a
little bit complex to layout,
it might take some time
and you might rob a frame.
That's not great.
So what we are doing
now, is something
that we call cell prefetching.
The idea here is before we
actually need a cell on screen,
we're going to ask you for
that cell, and we are not going
to ask for a cell as a block
of cell like an entire row.
We're going to ask for one
cell, then another and another.
So we're going to, amortize
the cost for the cell set
up in your application.
A great thing about
that it's automatic.
If you rebuild your
application for iOS 10,
you get that behavior
completely for free.
[ Applause ]
But there is more.
We have a new protocol, we
call that data prefetching.
Because sometimes, it's not just
about doing the layout
for your cell.
Sometimes you need
to fetch data.
You need to read from the disc.
You need to fetch data from the
network so it would be great
if we could tell you hey, we are
going to need that index fast.
So you can prepare, in advance.
That's exactly what
this new protocol does.
You implement a few delegate
methods, we're going to tell you
when we, are about
to ask for a cell
so you can have the data ready.
So that's going to improve,
again, the performance
of your collection
view based application.
And, we made also that
available on table views.
[ Applause ]
We have an entire session
about new UI collection view,
cell prefetching,
data prefetching,
reordering, don't miss this one.
But I think the major new
feature in UIKit this year,
is something that we call the
UI View Property Animator,
It's a new animation API.
It's a new animation
API that's going
to let you build
interruptible animation.
Animation you can scrub,
animation you can reverse.
We are exposing a new
set of timing curves.
And it's fully dynamic.
You can add animation
on the fly.
And the way, I describe
that new API is,
just like a timeline in a movie.
Something that you can
scrub, post, play, reverse.
The model is really simple,
it's really easy to use.
You just have to
create a new animator.
You set the timing
parameters and the duration,
you add your animation.
And you start the animation,
and because you have an object
that represent that animation,
that's how you can post that
or change its progress.
It's also fully integrated
in the view controller
operation system and we're going
to explain everything
about that,
in Advances in UI Animation
and Techniques this Wednesday.
But I'd like to show you,
what you can build with that.
So, this is a very simple
photo app, that's something
that you could do before,
have customization transition
in a navigation controller.
But with this animation API,
I can start the transition,
catch that mid flight
with a gesture, move it,
release it, and catch
that again.
I'm going to reverse
my transition,
and let the animation finish.
And what's amazing about that,
is that it's just
one transition.
So we are moving the same
context from non-interactive
to interactive gesture driven
to non-interactive again,
to gesture driven to
interactive to non-interactive.
You can fully blend
gestured based interactions
and animation.
We think that's a great
feature, we cannot wait
to see what you're going
to build with that.
[ Applause ]
Now, I'd like to talk about some
new features we have in iOS 10.
And the key thing here
is, there's nothing
that you absolutely
need to adopt.
No, it's quite the opposite,
what can we do to help you.
We have new feature
that we think are going
to make your application better.
Features are going to
simplify your architecture.
Things that are going to measure
application more integrated.
A good example of that
is something very simple.
Is how we changed, openURL.
So first, we made
that asynchronous
with a completion handler but we
also added for universal links.
So you know universal link
is when you open a URL,
to a social network
for instance,
if you have a native app it's
going to open the native app.
But now, with this new
API, you can actually check
if there was an application
on the system install.
So if there was not, you can
stay in your application,
you can still keep
the experience instead
of opening [inaudible]
for instance.
So that's going to really
improve how you can integrate
content and deal with those
application in the system.
Another great feature, is the
changes we made to Core Data.
The first one is something
that we call, query generation.
The idea here is, it's quite
common to have a context
for your menu I and
that you're doing work
on background queues,
in separate context.
And what you can do is
query generation is,
you can actually pin,
your model on your menu i,
you can control exactly when you
want to move from one version,
to another version
of your model.
So it mean that you don't have
to deal with force anymore,
because something changed
in the background queue
because you can decide exactly
when the menu i should move
to a new version of your data.
That's a really great way
to simplify your core data
code in your applications.
The other feature is,
about connection pooling.
Now in a store we
have full support
for a multiple reader,
one writer mode.
That's going to give you
great performance enhancement.
We also have, new features on
the tool side, but for that,
I suggest you go
to the What's New
in Core Data session on Friday.
Another way to model data
in your application
is to use CloudKit.
So CloudKit, we already had
to hold for public databases,
and private per user databases.
And what we are adding in
iOS 10 is record sharing.
So you can have multiple users,
accessing the same record.
So that's going to open
a completely new class
of application with CloudKit.
So that's great.
But something that is
sometimes, difficult to do
with collaboration based app,
is how to deal with the UI flow.
How do you invite person to
collaborate on a document?
How do you do that in a way
that is going to be secure?
So we added the new UI
cloud sharing controller.
Which is a view controller
expose by UIKit
and it's really easy to use
just pass the new share object
that is going to control
record sharing in CloudKit.
And we're going to generate
automatically for you that UI
to manage the invitation
flow, and the invitee list.
That's really easy to build
a collaboration based app
in CloudKit.
We have an entire
session on CloudKit,
What's New with CloudKit,
that's going to be
in Presidio on Thursday.
Now, I'd like to talk
about NS user activity.
NS user activity is
a class that we use
to capture the state,
of your application.
And, we are using that already,
for things like Handoff
and Spotlight.
What we are doing now, in iOS
10, is we are adding support
for locations in user activity.
So if I'm in an application
that deals with addresses,
I can express that, the
current activity for the user,
is about this address.
So you just pass a map kit item
you attach that to the activity
and now you understand how
I build that suggestion
in the text field
a few minutes ago.
The system will notice
that, oh maybe this app,
is dealing with these addresses.
So that's probably a
very good suggestion
for a text filed
about an address.
That's going to open completely
automatically for you,
if you had options
under activity.
We have many new ways you
can use to increase usage
of your application with what
we call proactive suggestion
which is this intelligence
based, activity based,
features in iOS 10,
on your applications.
Another place, where we use
NS user activity is in search.
So in iOS 9, we added support
for indexed activities.
It was real easy to use,
we just create an activity
and pass text field information
and that would just
show in Spotlight.
But now what you can do is,
we have a new button
here, search in app.
And, your user can now go
back, directly to your app,
and you can continue
search automatically
in your own application.
It's real easy to adopt.
Step one, you need to add,
a new key to your info plist
to tell us that you support
Spotlight continuation.
The second step is to
implement a new UI application
delegate method.
It's real easy to implement.
We are giving you the user
activity, you can build the UI
and display the search,
continued in your application.
The recent thing new also
with search, last year,
we added support for
indexing your content
with Core Spotlight.
But now you can actually search
for your data in Spotlight.
We are opening the
Spotlight index.
And that's great
because we have,
a fully optimized implementation
of that index for power
and performance and we have
very powerful quarry model.
So it's real easy to use.
You just build a search
query, you pass a request
and you can search the
Spotlight index for your data.
So you can integrate
system indexed data and data
from [inaudible] coming from a
network for your application.
We have a new session, this year
about search APIs that's going
to cover continuation,
Core Spotlight search,
and other features.
We shipped Replay
Kit, that was a way
to record your screen
in your application.
In iOS 10, you can use
Replay Kit as a live stream.
So you can have live
broadcasting,
of your application and because
we are also providing extension
point, it mean that third-party
services can give you
that live broadcast ability.
And we are using that for
instance, in playgrounds.
Another great framework
is SceneKit.
SceneKit is really powerful
3D engine you can use
to integrate 3D interactive
component in your application.
The major new feature of
this year is a completely new
rendering engine,
physically based rendering.
I could say that it now
supports high dynamic range
or is internally using
a linear cross space.
But I think that's
better to show you.
This is your fire
truck on iOS 9.
truck on iOS 10.
That's really amazing.
[ Applause ]
And it's now available
on the Watch OS 2.
We have a full session of
SceneKit Rendering in Presidio.
Then I'd like to
talk about Apple Pay.
Two things about Apple Pay.
First, we are extending
how Apple Pay is going
to be available to your users.
Today, Apple Pay is on
iOS and on the Watch,
and as you learned
yesterday, we are expanding
that Apple Pay on the web.
We have support for
Apple Pay on the Mac.
So for users, Apple
Pay is everywhere.
But what's great
is, as a developer,
we already have support
for Apple Pay
in your UIKit based application.
But now, you can use
Apple Pay in Safari
with the new Javascript
framework.
But it could also mean
that, you can use Apple Pay
in your [inaudible]
Safari view controllers.
The other place where you
can use Apple Pay now,
is in non-UI code.
We have a new API,
for non-UI extensions.
And using Apple Pay in
extension, is, really amazing,
that's a great feature for
instant for your iMessage apps.
This is the kind of flow
you can now build directly
in messages with an extension.
I would like to point you to
the two session on Apple Pay.
The first one that
is unfortunately
at the same time
Apple Pay on the Web.
And just after that,
there is What's New
in Wallet in Apple Pay.
I would like to, finish with
how you can make iOS better.
How you can integrate with iOS.
We have major new
extension points in iOS 10,
messages, Siri, CallKit.
We also improved
existing extension,
for instance something
like keyboards,
now you can use the same
globe key, keyboard peeker
from your keyboard extension.
We can also give you
hints about the language,
the user is interacting with.
So you can build
multi-language support
in your third-party extension.
Another thing that we
improved in iOS 10,
is the new display
modes for widgets.
So, before, you were just,
you just had to pass us
with you preferred size.
Now we have a user
controlled size.
The compact mode, which is fixed
height and the expanded mode
which is variable height.
It's really easy to adopt.
You don't have to do
anything, but we have new API
so you can know when the
widgets are going to move
from compact to extended.
You can give us a maximum size,
you can know the display mode.
You can customize the
information you want to display.
There is one thing that,
I'd like to point out about,
widget though is, this is going
to appear on the lock screen.
So, be careful about the kind
of data you're presenting here.
One thing to keep in mind is,
be consistent with the kind
of data you're presenting
in your widget.
If I configure, if
I add your widget
to my home screen,
the lock screen.
I expect that I'm always going
to see the same kind of data
at the same level of privacy
and that I'm not going
to be surprised by thing
that I don't want to see
on my lock screen when
my iPhone is locked.
A completely new framework in
iOS 10 is user notifications.
So user notification, that's
something that we used to have
at the UI application level.
We have a new framework but, we
are exposing the same features.
We are adding a few
enhancement there.
First, we are unifying local
and remote notification.
So much easier to deal with.
[ Applause ]
You have better control on
how you're going to deliver,
how we are going to deliver
notification to the user.
Another great thing is,
we're going to tell you,
before displaying
the notification.
So in-app, you have
better control
on the notification itself.
And, that's also a unified model
across all different platforms.
In addition to these
API enhancements,
we also have two extensions.
The first one is the
service extension.
The service extension is
something that you can insert,
on the device when we are
receiving the notification
and before, it's
actually displayed.
So you can process the payload
before it appears on the screen.
And, two great use cases, the
thing you can build with that.
You can have media attachment,
the payload is pretty small.
But if you know what you want
to display for a given, payload,
you can, when receiving
that notification,
fetch that and display.
And the other great feature
is end to end encryption,
because now you're in
charge, on both sides.
On the server and
of the local device.
So you can receive something,
and decrypt that
in your own code.
We think that's a
great new feature
and great new possibility
for extensions.
[ Applause ]
This is the other
extension we have
for the user notification
framework.
You can have embedded UI
views in your notification.
There is one restriction though,
you cannot directly interact,
with the view, but you have
the notification actions.
We have two session on user
notifications, Introduction
to Notification and
Advanced Notification
in Pacific Heights on Wednesday.
Another new framework in
iOS 10 is CallKit and again,
we are offering a new
extension point here.
The directory extension,
we let you configure how we
should block incoming calls.
You have full control on that.
The second feature is, how
we identify a phone number
and display our label.
So when we receive a call,
we first going to check
in the address book and then
if we cannot find a match,
we can add your extension.
It's real easy to use API.
It's non-UI extension point.
It's really two methods.
But the real great new feature
in CallKit is the
call provider API.
With the call provider API,
we have a real first
party experience
for your voice over
IP application.
Which mean that now,
you can have something
like full screen
incoming call UI
when you receive a
call in your app.
But it's not just that,
we are fully integrating
your application
with a core management on iOS.
And things like,
favorites and recents,
we are automatically get, the
calls from your application.
You can support Siri,
you can support CarPlay,
you will be integrated with
do not disturb and Bluetooth.
That's a major new
feature for a mobile hone.
[ Applause ]
We can learn all about
that in the Enhancing Voice
Over IP apps with CallKit.
I'd like to talk about Siri.
So, you might not
know about that.
But Siri is actually
something that is different,
depending on the context.
So if you're using Siri,
from the home screen
with the home button, or if
you're using Siri with hey Siri,
or if you're using
Siri with CarPlay,
or as an accessibility feature.
Siri is going to tune
itself to that context
so you can have the best
possible interaction with Siri.
It's a quite complex task.
Because it's involved
the recognition phase,
understanding the domain,
understanding the environment,
and that's something that we
are going to do for you for free
when you build a
SiriKit extension.
What we're going to give you,
is an intent representing
the request,
and that's how your extension
will interact with that.
And, you can also help Siri
by giving your own vocabulary,
which might be specific to your
app, or specific to the user,
so we can again,
tune the recognition
of the interaction with Siri.
So how did that work?
The idea behind intents
extension is,
it's a non-UI extension that
will represent that interaction
between Siri and
your application.
So it's based on the
concept of intents,
coming from Siri and responses.
And the main idea here is,
intents are a domain
specific thing.
So you have the messaging
domain,
the payment domain, etcetera.
And for messaging, you
have a list of intents
that Siri can recognize
and interact and send
to your application for
[inaudible] Siri interaction.
So the main goal here, for
Siri intents, extension is
to make sure that, you and
Siri are on the same page
when Siri understood a request.
That valid request, that we need
to have a confirmation on that,
let's execute the request,
that's basically the flow.
And when you use Siri
to say something like,
"tell Miko on WWDC chat
that we need to meet
after this session," what
Siri is going to encode
in the intent is the fact that,
it's in the messaging domain.
It's the same messaging intent,
there is a receipt in here,
that's about your app and
we have content from you.
We have a second
extension for Siri Kit
that the intents UI extension.
It's actually an
optional extension.
But with that you can embed
your own UI into Siri transcript
so you can have a confirmation
that is tune to your content.
That's really great.
And, another great thing
about the intent system is,
it's not just about Siri.
It's a way to describe the
request, of course we use
that in Siri to communicate
with your app.
But, that's also how we
integrate with CallKit,
that's how we do the right
sharing extension in maps.
And the reason the
feature that is,
really great is that's how
you can donate information
to the system about what
you're user is doing.
For instance, in
your message app.
And it's combined with and
it's user activity of course,
and with that, let's say
that I am sending a message
using my WWDC chat application,
then in the contacts UI, we're
going to show the information
about this contacts
automatically.
And when we have,
a list of actions,
we can show you directly your
application there, if you expose
that information
through an intent.
And at some point,
your application will be
just default application
in the standard contact card.
That's really amazing in term
of adding visibility
to your application.
I'd like to conclude
with the iMessage apps.
So, messages is really
becoming a platform,
and we have two features
here, one is the sticker packs
and the other one is
the messages extension.
So sticker packs, no code
required, you just have
to package your images,
static or animated.
You use Xcode for that and
you can just distribute
that on the messages store.
The other thing you can do,
with iMessage apps is use
a new messages extension.
With that you can write, a
fully UIKit based extension
and you can do things like,
dynamically generating
stickers content.
You can even use a
camera in that extension
which is completely new.
And, you can tune your
UI to have this compact
or expanded mode and that's
going to live-in messages,
that's a great feature
but you can do even more.
You can custom the
bubble itself,
it mean that your extension,
using the messages
framework can actually have,
a concept of a conversation in
messages integrate with that,
connect with what the
other user changed.
We have full support
for messages extension
in [inaudible] and iOS 10.
That's real easy to use and
that's great feature for you
to integrate in messages.
The other thing that you can
have with that is of course,
completely custom content
in your interactive bubble.
We have two session for iMessage
applications, messages, apps,
and sticker, that was this
morning, and the second one,
focusing on the extension part
that's going to be on Thursday
at 1:40 p.m. Thank you
very much, enjoy WWDC.
[ Applause ]