[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Good afternoon and
welcome to a peek at 3D Touch,
I'm Tyler Fox and
later I'll be joined
by my colleague Peter Hajas.
We're both engineers
on the UIKit Team
and we're really excited
to tell you all today,
how you can adopt 3D Touch
to take your app's user
experience to the next level.
We'd like to start
today by reviewing some
of the fundamentals of 3D Touch
and showing you how it
shows up across the system.
From there, we'll talk about
Home Screen Quick Actions.
Home Screen Quick Actions
are one of the easiest ways
that you can add 3D
Touch to your apps today.
They let users jump straight
from the Home screen,
right to those key
activities in your application.
From there, we'll talk
about Peek and Pop.
Peek and Pop are a seamless
way for users to preview
and navigate content
in your applications.
We think that most apps will
benefit greatly from adding,
for adding support with Peek
and Pop to your content.
Finally, we're excited
to tell you all
about UIPreviewInteraction,
this is brand new API in iOS 10
that allows you to make 3D
Touch unique to your apps.
It's for those of you
that want advanced control
of the 3D Touch interaction
and it lets you use the
same force processing
that we've honed for Peek
and Pop, but bringing
in your own custom
user interface.
It's really great and we can't
wait to tell you all about it.
So with that, let's get started,
by talking about 3D Touch.
Devices that support 3D Touch
have a force sensitive display
that precisely measures
the pressure
of touches on the screen.
Now iOS has always let users
directly manipulate the content
on the user interface.
This has been a hallmark
since the original
iPhone was introduced
with its multi-touch display.
But 3D Touch extends this
even further, allowing users
to connect even more closely
to their content on the screen.
Let's take a look at some of
the ways that 3D Touch shows
up across the operating system,
starting with the Home screen.
When you press on an app icon,
we reveal the Home
Screen Quick Actions.
As you can see here with Camera,
these let you jump straight
into some of the key
activities in each app
that you come to perform.
For example, taking a
selfie in the camera app,
using the front facing camera,
or taking a regular photo
with the rear facing camera,
recording video or
a Slow-mo video.
Now, new in iOS 10, if your app
provides a widget it will also
show right alongside the
Home Screen Quick Actions
when the user 3D
touches on your app icon.
And something else to note
is that while you're pressing
on each of this app icons,
the device is playing haptic
feedback to let you know
when you've reached
the threshold
where the quick actions
will spring open.
Now let's move into
messages, to take a look
at an example of Peek and Pop.
Here in messages, you can
see I've received a photo
in a conversation with a friend.
If I start to lightly apply
pressure to that photo,
I can peek into it to
reveal a nice large preview
of that content.
Then if I continue to apply
pressure, I'll pop straight
to that photo, which takes it
full screen and lets me interact
with it, just like
I had tapped on it.
Peek and Pop is really
nice because it allows you
to preview content and
perhaps change your mind
and release your touch
without actually having
to go tap the back
button and navigate back.
Now, one thing to
note here is that,
as we're crossing these two
different thresholds for Peek
and Pop, the device, again,
is playing haptic feedback,
to let you know when you've
reached these two thresholds.
That's Peek and Pop.
Let's take a look now at Mail,
at some of the interesting
pieces of the same interaction.
I want you to notice
how fully interactive
and interruptible 3D Touch is.
As I modulate the
pressure of the touch
on the screen, as
you'll see here.
We're using blur and scale
effects to let you know
that you can continue to
interact with this content.
And note how fluid
and responsive the
entire interaction is.
This is one of the
hallmark features
that differentiates 3D
Touch from traditional touch
and gesture based interactions.
So you might be wondering,
why should I support 3D
Touch in my application?
Well one of the best
uses for 3D Touch is
that it can quickly accelerate
access to existing features
that your app already provides.
You saw a great example of this
with Home Screen Quick Actions,
letting users go straight
into those screens
within your app just like deep
links and let them get straight
into the action that
they're trying to perform.
But another really great
thing about 3D Touch is
that it makes possible, brand
new immersive interactions
that were never before possible.
We're going to show you a
great example of this later on,
when we go through this new
UIPreviewInteraction API.
Finally, we've adopted 3D Touch
throughout the system in iOS 10.
And so users expect all of your
apps to support it as well.
Let's go ahead and talk
about how you can start
adopting 3D Touch today
with Home Screen Quick Actions.
And to do this, I'd like to
introduce you to AppChat.
AppChat is a sample app
that we've been working
on to highlight some
of the great features
of 3D Touch in our application.
Here you can see that 3D Touch,
sorry AppChat is an [inaudible]
messaging application.
You can take a photo and send
it to your friends as a chat
and here you can see
I've received a list
of different chats
from my friends.
I can tap on anyone of them, and
view those chats full screen.
Just like that.
AppChat is a very
familiar UIKit application.
And we'll show you the different
ways that we've added support
for 3D Touch to it, starting
with Home Screen Quick Actions.
So when you press on
the AppChat app icon,
we'll reveal some Home Screen
Quick Actions for AppChat.
You'll note, I can choose
to create a new chat
that will open the Camera
so I can take a photo
and then choose one of
my friends to send it to.
But alternatively,
I can choose one
of these bottom 3 quick
actions which are quick actions
that will let me send
a chat directly to one
of my top three friends.
The friends that I communicate
with most in AppChat.
So there are actually
two different types
of Home Screen Quick Actions.
Let's talk about them now.
The first type is Static Quick
Cctions, these are specified
by your app at build time.
And they're great
for fixed actions
that are always available
in your app.
For example with AppChat, we
have the New Chat Quick Action.
I can always create a new chat
and then send it to
one of my friends.
On the other hand, we have
Dynamic Quick Actions.
Dynamic Quick Actions are also
great because they allow you
to customize and
tailor the quick actions
that are shown to the user.
But let's take a quick look
at Static Quick Actions first.
Static Quick Actions are defined
in your apps info.plist file.
As such they're available
as soon
as your app has been
installed on a user's device.
Now let's take a
look at an example
of how we add a Static
Quick Action to AppChat.
Here's our info.plist file, you
can see with just a few lines
of code, that we
are able to create
and add this New
Chat Quick Action.
I'd like to call out
a few things here.
You'll notice we're specifying
a type, this is a string
that your application
defines which you'll use later
on when the user selects
one of these quick actions
to know how to handle it.
We also provide a title,
New Chat in this situation.
And, also an icon type which
is a constant from a list
of system provided icons
that you can display.
So in this case that's how
we get that nice chat bubble.
One thing to keep in
mind is that you'll want
to localize any user
facing strings
in your info plist.strings
file as a best practice.
That's Static Quick
Actions, let's go take a look
at Dynamic Quick Actions
which I eluded to earlier.
So these are defined by your
app at runtime and provided,
from your app to the
system at that point.
As a result though, they're
only available once the user has
launched your app for
the very first time.
Now, Dynamic Quick
Actions are shown
after any Static Quick
Actions, space permitting.
You'll only get to
display a total
of four quick actions
on the home screen.
So you'll want to
make sure to save room
for any Dynamic Quick Actions
if you intend to provide them.
You can also include an
optional system icon,
a custom icon using a template
image from your application.
Or you can even create an icon
using an address book contact
from the user's address book.
This is what AppChat
is doing to pull
in those nice profile
photos, right next to each
of those three Dynamic
Quick Actions
for the top three friends.
Let's walk through
some of the code
to see how we can
implement this.
Well for this example we'll
start by looking for a contact
that matches our
friend Lexi Torres.
The first thing we want to make
sure to do is request permission
from the user to
access their contacts.
Assuming we have that
permission, we can go forward,
and actually query their
contacts for a contact
that matches this friend's
name that we're interested in.
If we get at least one match,
we can then pass that contact
to our UIApplicationShortcutIcon
initializer.
That will go ahead and create
the icon that we'll use
with this quick action.
But of course we may not
have received access,
permission to access
the user's contacts,
or we may not have found
a match for this friend.
So we'll want to
have a fall-back,
in this case we'll use
the system's message style
to display as the icon.
Now that we have
the icon, we can go
and create our actual
quick action.
In this case we'll need to
specify a type, very similar
to how you saw with the
static quick action.
As well as a subtitle,
we'll use send a chat here,
and then we'll pass all of these
over to our [inaudible]
ApplicationshortcutItem
initializer to create our
first Dynamic Quick Action.
From here, we can continue to do
this as many times as we want,
to create any additional
quick actions.
And when we're done,
we'll package them all up,
in a nice array,
and hand that over
to UIApplicationsShortcutItems
property.
This has the effect
of registering these Dynamic
Quick Actions with the system,
so that they can display
on the Home screen.
One thing to keep in mind is
that this shortcutItems property
only displays your apps,
only contains your app's
dynamic shortcut items
or Dynamic Quick Actions.
The Static Quick Actions
are only specified
in your info.plist and won't
be contained in that array.
Let's take a look at how all
of this comes together
back on the home screen.
Fantastic, with just those few
lines of code, we were able
to create one Static
Quick Action, New Chat,
as well as three different
Dynamic Quick Actions.
One for each of our
top three friends.
There's now one more thing
that we need to do though,
that's of course to
handle these quick actions
when the user selects one.
There are two different
scenarios to keep in mind here.
The first one is if your
app is already running
and is being activated,
meaning your app is
in the inactive or
suspended state.
In this case we'll
use the callback
on UIApplicationDelegate,
application
performActionForShortcutItem,
completionHandler.
In here, we'll use the
shortcutItem that's passed
in to actually handle
the quick action.
Now this could mean many
things depending on your app
and which quick action you have,
but generally you're
probably moving the user
to a particular screen
within your application.
If you handle the quick
action, you should make sure
to call the completion
handler, passing a Bool
that indicates whether or
not you actually handled it.
Great, that's the
first scenario.
The second scenario
for us to consider is
if the app was actually launched
as a result of a quick action.
So in this case our
app was not running.
Here we'll use the
familiar application
didFinishLaunchingWithOptions
callback,
on UIApplicationDelegate.
Inside, we'll access
the shortcutItem key
of the launchOptions dictionary
that's passed in to see
if our app was launched
via a quick action.
If it was, we'll go ahead
and handle the quick action,
just as we would
have done before.
And then we'll make sure to
return false from this method,
that tells the system we did
actually handle a quick action
here, and it will prevent
it from calling the method
on the previous slide.
That's pretty much all there is
to it in terms of both creating
and handling both dynamic
and static shortcutItems.
But let's review some of the
best practices to keep in mind.
First, every app should
provide quick actions,
as you see here they're
really easy to create
and they provide great
value, showing up right
on the Home screen,
letting users go straight
to those key activities
that your app provides.
As such, you'll want to focus
on providing quick access
to the highest value tasks
that your app offers.
Remember you only
have 4 different slots
to display quick actions.
So decide wisely
which ones you choose.
To help you with
that, you might want
to use Dynamic Quick
Actions, but it's important
to keep your quick
actions predictable.
Users are going to be quickly
opening your Home Screen Quick
Actions and choosing one.
And if you're doing things
like changing up the order,
that'll probably
confuse your users
and they'll find a
frustrating experience.
One interesting thing to
remember here is that,
you should be prepared to
handle Dynamic Quick Actions
from a previous version
of your application.
The reason is, if you remember,
Dynamic Quick Actions don't
take effect until your app runs
and has the ability to
provide them to the system.
So if your app was
just recently updated,
it will still be showing
the Dynamic Quick Actions
from the previous version.
As a result, if the semantics of
your quick actions have changed,
it's a good idea to keep
this in mind when handling it
and to do this you might want
to consider including
your app's version number
in the info plist, I'm sorry,
in the user info dictionary
that you can include with
the Dynamic Quick Actions.
Finally, try not
to add functionality that's only
accessible using quick actions.
And remember, not all of
our devices support 3D Touch
and even on ones that
do, users have the option
to disable 3D Touch
in the accessibility
settings of the system.
With that, I'd like to invite
Peter on stage to tell you all
about Peek and Pop, Peter.
[ Applause ]
Go for it.
>> Thank you, Tyler.
I'm really excited to talk to
you today about Peek and Pop.
As Tyler showed you earlier,
Peek and Pop allows people
to quickly preview and navigate
to content inside your app.
And I can speak from
my personal experience,
that it changes the
way you use the phone.
We're going to talk through
Peek and Pop with the sample app
that Tyler showed
you earlier, AppChat.
As Tyler showed you,
in the last section,
AppChat is a standard UIKit app.
So tapping on one of the
messages, in the table,
brings me to the message so I
can check it out full screen.
A general rule of thumb
for adding Peek and Pop
to your app is that if user
accessible content can be tapped
to navigate to it, it should
also support Peek and Pop.
So let's apply that
rule to AppChat.
That means that when I apply
pressure to one of the cells
in this table, we
should get a quick Peek.
In our API, we refer
to this as preview,
because we're getting a
preview of the View Controller
that we could navigate to.
Now if we continue
to apply pressure,
that'll Pop full screen,
ready for us to interact with.
In our API, we refer to this as
commit, because we've committed
to navigating to
this View Controller.
Cool, so let's go
through the components
of a Peek and Pop interaction.
First and foremost, we have
our registered View Controller,
this is the View Controller
that contains the user
interface elements
that we'd like to preview.
In our case, these are
our message table cells.
Each registered View Controller
has a whole series of sources,
these are individual
interface elements
that each have their own
preview View Controller.
In AppChat, this is a natural
fit for our chat table cells.
Finally, we have the
previewed View Controller,
this is the View Controller that
will show inside of the preview
which represents the element
that we tapped in the table.
Usually this is the same
element that we'd show
after tapping on that content.
So tapping on it, and previewing
on it, by applying pressure,
shows us the same content.
So with that, I'd like to
go step by step with what,
how we adding Peek
and Pop to AppChat
which will closely
mirror how you'll add Peek
and Pop to your app.
So we're going to start off in
our registered View Controller.
Remember this is that
table View Controller
which contains our
presentation's source view.
We're going to conform
to the
UIViewControllerPreviewing
Delegate protocol.
This delegate will
be called back
at various stages during
the Peek and Pop interaction
to provide information
to the system.
It's really easy to implement.
Next, we'll want to make sure
we registerForPreviewing.
A great time to do
this is in viewDidLoad.
We're going to
registerForPreviewing
with ourself as the delegate,
passing our tableView
as the sourceView.
Because the tableView
is the common ancestor
for all the interfaced elements
that we'd like to preview.
Now let's go ahead and implement
the two required delegate
methods in the previewing
delegate protocol.
The first is for providing
a preview ViewController.
This will provide
a ViewController
for a particular location
inside the sourceView.
The method is called
previewingContext
ViewControllerForLocation,
and it's easy to implement.
First, we're going to find the
indexPath representing the point
that we were passed in
by the delegate method.
We can do this by hit
testing the tableView.
Next, we're going to
create a ViewController
with the model object
represented by the indexPath,
this is logic that you
probably already have
and did select row at indexPath.
Next, and this is
really important,
we're going to set
the sourceRect
of the previewingContext.
Remember, the sourceView
is the entire tableView,
and we want to make sure to
lift off just the cell off the
screen, in that beautiful
blur and scale effect
that Tyler showed you.
By setting the sourceRect the
system will appropriately cut
out that element and
lift it off the screen,
it looks really great.
Finally, we'll return
the ViewController back
to the system.
Now there are two
really important parts
about this delegate method that
I'd like to highlight for you.
The first is that this method
will be called every time we
think we're going to
initiate a preview.
As Tyler said before, we want
to keep the interaction fast
and fluid, so we're going
to call it opportunistically
to make sure everything's ready.
As a result, you need to make
sure to not take too much time
when returning a
ViewController from this method.
If there's asynchronous
work that you can do
in the background, before
preparing this ViewController,
do that there, and don't
block the main queue.
This will keep things feeling
fast, fluid, and responsive
as we apply pressure
to interface elements
inside your app.
The second important piece
of advice I have for you
about this method,
is its return type.
UIViewControllerOptional, that
means we could return nil.
If you return nil
from this method,
we won't lift any
cells off the screen,
we won't do any blurring, we
won't play any haptic feedback,
we won't do a preview.
But you should make
sure to only return nil
if there truly is nothing
to preview at that location.
You should make sure that
similar looking content
in your app is previewable
in a similar way,
this way people won't be
squeezing their phones trying
to get a preview, because
similar looking stuff will be
previewable similarly.
Great, so with that,
we've implemented the preview
part of this interaction.
But we're not done yet.
We need to implement the
second required method
on this protocol, which is
for providing the commit.
This one's even easier
to implement,
it's called previewingContext
commitViewController.
This will be called by the
system when it's time to commit,
we've crossed that
force threshold,
we're going to place
some haptic feedback,
so let's get the
ViewController on screen.
Here, we're going to do whatever
it is we need to do to get
that ViewController on screen.
AppChat is a simple UIKit app
that uses navigation controller,
so we're just going
to call show.
This will have the
default effect
of pushing the ViewController
onto the nav stack.
But there's something really
cool about this method.
UIKit has made it so that
you can perform any type
of ViewController transition in
this callback, push something
onto the navigation stack,
do a custom presentation,
even move the ViewController
into a custom container.
Do whatever it is you need
to do inside your app to get
that ViewController on screen,
and UIKit will handle the
animation on your behalf.
So great, we've implemented
commit ViewController,
and now we've got that awesome
commit, which will allow us
to navigate full screen
and begin interacting
with that content.
Now we've added Peek
and Pop to our app,
but we can do a little
bit extra work
to take the experience,
to the next level.
Another aspect of Peek and Pop
that's really cool is preview
quick actions.
And by adding these to your
app, you can allow users
to access the most
common actions
with the content shown
inside the preview.
This is really powerful
and allows people
to use your apps even
faster than before.
If we go back to our
familiar architecture diagram,
we'll see that these preview
quick actions are owned
by the previewed ViewController.
This is the ViewController
that's capable of responding
to these actions because these
take action on the content shown
in that ViewController.
These are easy to add.
All we have to do is override
the preview action items
function, in UIViewController.
This returns an array
of UIPreviewActionItems.
We can create UIPreviewActions
using API you're already
probably familiar with.
It resembles UIAlertAction
and UITableViewRowAction.
You just pass a title, a style
and a closure, and we'll call
that closure when the action
is selected by the user.
Next, we'll just
return that array
of actions back to the system.
Now we've got one action here
for applying with a heart,
but AppChat lets you reply
with a whole bunch of emoji.
So what we really want to
do is group those emoji
into one group action.
We've got API for that too,
through UIPreviewActionGroup.
All you have to do is create
an array of preview actions;
here we have them for all of
the emoji you can respond with.
And then create an action
group with a title, style,
and the array of those actions.
This is a great way for you
to group related actions inside
your preview quick actions.
There are two other
important parts
for the preview action
API that are also handy.
And this is through
the style enumeration
on preview action item.
The first is the selected style
which will show a little
check mark next to that item,
to let the user know that
they may have already selected
that option previously.
Now before we came
out with beta 1
that check mark was
feeling a little shy,
so you'll be noticing that it's
missing from the first seed
but rest assured that
that bug will be fixed.
The other style that's
really handy
to use is the destructive style,
which we can use to indicate
that an action may
perform a destructive act.
You'll see that here behind
me with the block action.
So by adding Peek and Pop,
and preview quick actions,
we've taken the experience
inside your app
to the next level and
sped up the interaction
that your users can have.
Let's review some best practices
for adding Peek and
Pop to your app.
First and foremost,
remember the rule of thumb,
content that can be tapped
should also support Peek
and Pop.
You can look to Apple's
system apps
for a great hint
at how to do this.
Next, make sure to return
a preview view controller
consistently from the
delegate call back.
Similar looking content in
your app should be previewable
in a similar way.
In that same previewing
context callback make sure not
to take too long.
Remember, we don't want
to block the main queue
because we want this interaction
to remain fluid and responsive.
Make sure to set the sourceRect
of the previewing context,
to lift the appropriate user
interface element on screen.
So, that's it for Peek and Pop.
Now I'd like to turn
our attention
to some super cool
new API in iOS 10.
UIPreviewInteraction.
UIPreviewInteraction lets you
take the Peek and Pop feel,
which is force processing
and haptic feedback,
but bring your own
user interface.
And as we'll see in a moment,
this a really powerful concept.
Let's look at an example.
In AppChat, in our
chat detail view,
we've got this handy Reply
button at the bottom.
On a non-3D Touch
enabled device,
we can tap on that Reply
button to get a whole list
of the emoji we can reply with.
And then we can tap
on one of these emoji,
to send it back to our friend.
But on a 3D Touch
capable device,
we can make this
interaction a lot more fluid
and a lot more fun.
With just a few lines of code
using UIPreviewInteraction,
we added something really neat.
We can apply pressure
to the Reply button
and interactively
present that sheet,
notice how the blur
was fading in and out.
Then while keeping my
finger down on the screen,
I can slide around to pick
an emoji to reply with.
Hopefully we don't
pick the devil.
And then we'll send
it back to our friend.
This type of one touch
interaction is something
that 3D Touch is perfect for.
Another thing that
3D Touch can help us
with is accelerating actions
that can live closer
to the user's finger.
In iOS 7, we added
the slide back gesture
as an alternative
for the Back button.
And this is more convenient
because it's right next
to where your finger is, you can
just move it over to the edge
of the screen and slide back.
And by using 3D Touch, we
can add that convenience
to your app's interactions.
So we can actually 3D Touch
anywhere in this photo
to interactively bring
up that reply sheet
and then we can actually
commit that reply sheet open,
by applying some more force,
and then pick an
emoji to reply with.
This type of rich interaction
that can make things feel a lot
more fluid, and a lot more fast,
is exactly the type of thing
that we hope you'll build
with UIPreviewInteraction.
UIPreviewInteraction
takes the same Peek
and Pop force processing
that we've honed
for the system provided
Peek and Pop UI,
and the automatic haptic
feedback as we move
through the stages of the
interaction, but allows your app
to bring the user interface.
And what's really
exciting about this is
that people can now build
muscle memory for Peek and Pop,
and apply that same
muscle memory
in the system standard
previewing appearance,
but also in the custom
interactions that you'll build
with UIPreviewInteraction.
And that muscle memory will
be universally applicable,
this is really cool.
So let's walk through step
by step how you might add
preview interaction to your app.
We're going to start
off by conforming
to the
UIPreviewInteractionDelegate
protocol.
This delegate will be informed
at various stages during
the preview interaction
to let you know what's going on.
Next, we'll want to make sure to
create our preview interaction.
Again, viewDidLoad is a
great time to do this.
Here, we'll create our preview
interaction with a sourceView
and set ourselves
as the delegate.
Now, preview interaction is
all about state transitions,
so let's talk through how
these state transitions work.
When the interaction starts,
if your delegate implements the
optional preview interaction
should begin callback, we'll
call that, or if you don't,
we'll begin the interaction.
Now, as the force moves
from the beginning
of the interaction
towards the preview state,
we'll message back your delegate
with previewInteraction,
didUpdatePreviewTransition
:ended.
Check it out.
These force progress
updates are given
as a normalized value
from zero to one.
And what's really important
to highlight is this is not just
a direct translation of force.
Because it's using the
algorithms that we developed,
for Peek and Pop, we're actually
detecting the user's intent.
So this is not just some
simple force translation.
As we move between these two
force states, we'll be notified
at every step along the way
with our current progress
through the interaction.
And once we reach the
target state of preview,
we'll hear about it because
the progress will move to one,
and will passed true
for the ended parameter.
And, the device will
automatically play
haptic feedback.
Let's go through a sample
implementation of this method.
Again the method is
previewInteraction,
didUpdatePreviewTransition
:ended.
And here we're just
going to update ourselves
for the current progress
through the transition.
Now notice, this is actually
plug and play with a number
of UIKit technologies.
We can use it to drive a
UIViewPropertyAnimator,
a percent driven
interactive transition,
or even a UIKit dynamic system.
These instantaneous updates
for the state transitions work
with all these technologies.
And if the interaction ends,
we'll want to show our
completed preview appearance.
This is the first
required delegate method
on UIPreviewInteraction.
The second is for
responding to cancellation,
it's called
previewInteractionDidCancel.
This will be called whenever
the user lifts their finger
or if the interaction should
cancel for any other reason.
For example we got a phone call,
here we'll set our progress back
to zero, and reset ourselves
to our initial appearance.
But notice that we're doing this
inside an animation closure,
we'll want to animate
ourselves back to rest
to avoid things flashing
around when we lift our finger.
So that's how we can respond to
the preview state transition.
But remember in AppChat,
we also want to respond
to the commit state transition
for sticking our
content on screen.
We can implement the
optional delegate method,
previewInteraction
didUpdateCommitTransition
:ended, to respond to our
progress through commit.
So, when we're between the
beginning of the interaction
and the preview state,
we'll call back
didUpdatePreviewTransition.
And once we reach the
target state of preview,
we'll pass a progress value of
one and an ended value of true.
And we'll also play
some haptic feedback,
then we'll begin
sending messages
to didUpdateCommitTransition
:ended, with the progress
from preview to commit.
This is the same sort
of progress update normalized
values from zero to one.
And, once we reach the
target state of commit,
we'll pass a progress
value of one ended as true,
and we'll play another different
piece of haptic feedback.
Let's go through a way in which
you might implement this method.
So in our implementation
of previewInteraction
didUpdateCommitTransition
:ended, here we're going to
update our progress for commit.
Again, this works
with the whole suite
of UIKit animation
and dynamics API.
And once the interaction ends,
we'll just show our
completed commit appearance.
So that's it for
UIPreviewInteraction.
Now if you're building
a game or a drawing app,
there's some low level
force API that you can use.
This API provides
normalized access
to the force values coming
in with each UITouchObject,
through two properties
on UITouch,
force and maximumPossibleForce.
These values will be
populated on all devices
that support 3D Touch,
along with touches coming
from an Apple Pencil that
support Apple Pencil.
And we won't get into them
in more detail here, instead,
I encourage you to
check out the video
for the leveraging
touch input on iOS Talk.
It's a really great talk and
goes into these APIs in depth.
So let's review.
As Tyler showed you earlier,
Home Screen Quick Actions allow
your users to jump straight
into action with many
of the common activities
inside your app.
And most applications
will really benefit
from adding Home
Screen Quick Actions.
Next, I showed you how Peek
and Pop allow seamless fluid
and quick interaction like never
before and lets people interact
with your app in
a whole new way.
And we think that many
apps will really benefit
from adding Peek and Pop.
Finally, we looked at
UIPreviewInteraction,
which allows you to explore
new depths in the ocean
that is 3D Touch, and
really take a great look
into the next dimension
of multi-touch.
Finally, it's important to note
that users will expect all apps
on their device to
support 3D touch
so we would highly encourage
you to adopt these features.
For more information and to
download the AppChat sample app
that we showed you
throughout this talk,
which uses all these
technologies,
check out the address behind me.
There are a few related
sessions,
one on the new
UIKitPropertyAnimator API,
which works great with
UIPreviewInteraction.
And another for leveraging the
lower level touch input on iOS.
And that's it, thank you so
much, and have a great rest
of your conference, thank you.
[ Applause ]