[ Music ]
>> Good morning everyone,
welcome.
[ Applause ]
Thank you for attending this
session, my name is Sara Raid,
I'm an internationalization
software engineer,
and today with my
colleague, Joaquim Lobo Silva,
we're going to talk about
international user interfaces.
So let's get started.
At Apple we support over 40
localizations in our software
and every language has its
own challenges, but today,
in particular, we are going to
talk about two specific right
to left languages
that we support
which are Arabic and Hebrew.
So this language has
presented a unique challenge
in building your apps and
that's because of the nature
of the writing direction.
So why are we talking about
these languages specifically?
With over 400 million
people in the Middle East,
this really is a growing market.
So just last year, we
opened two Apple Stores
in the UAE these are images
from the opening in Abu Dhabi,
Dubai and just few weeks ago,
we launched Apple.com in the UAE
in Arabic for the first time.
This is really, really exciting,
but what does it mean to you?
As a developer, you have growth
opportunities in this market
and designing word ready apps
for your customers
is really important.
So in this session we're mainly
going to talk about right
to left languages, but if you
are interested in learning more
about designing word ready
apps, check out these two talks:
Inclusive App Design,
which focuses more
on the human interface
aspect of it
and Internationalization Best
Practices if you'd like to learn
about internationalization.
Last year, on iOS 9 we extended
internationalization support
to fully support languages
written from right to left.
And just after that, we
included native Hebrew
and Arabic localizations
into watchOS 2.1.
This year I'm happy to say
that we have been working
on redesigning macOS
for this market.
So now, I would like to
walk you through some,
the agenda to see what we
going to cover in this session.
So first, Joaquim is going
to start with a quick recap
of the APIs we introduced last
year, then he's going to talk
about what's new in iOS
X with image handling,
and how you can evaluate
layout direction.
He will finish up with
watchOS support, then,
I am going to talk about what's
new in macOS, and what's new
in text support and how can you
handle displaying mixed text
correctly in your applications.
And with that, I'm going
to hand it over to Joaquim,
to talk about iOS, Joaquim.
[ Applause ]
>> Alright, thank you
Sara, good morning.
Thank you all for coming.
So, my name is Joaquim,
and I'll get things started
by talking about iOS.
So as Sara mentioned, last year
at WWDC we announced full right
to left UISupport on iOS 9
across the entire platform.
When your users run their apps
in these languages they
expect your UI to adapt
to the nature of
these languages.
UIKit does a lot of the work
for you, all of its controls
and views do the correct
thing when running
in a right to left context.
Managing the layout between
these views can be done using
auto layout.
And this can either
mean high level elements
such as UIStack view new in iOS
9, also announced last year,
which lets you easily model
and maintain your UI in terms
of easy to use horizontal
and vertical groups
that can be nested.
And the nice thing
about stack view is
that it manages auto
layout constraints for you.
And in particular, for right
to left languages it manages
leading and trailing constraints
and what these are, are
left and right properties
that change automatically to
right and left when running
in a right to left context.
Having said that, it's
important to note that just
because these languages are
written and read from right
to left, this doesn't mean
that every single control
in an aspect of your app should
strictly follow the writing
direction of these languages.
There are nuances and some
exceptions even to keep in mind
when designing for
these languages.
So one example up above is
playback UI, anything related
to playback such as rewind and
fast forward, video and audio,
timeline scrubbers, these
should all stay the same
across layout direction.
Another example is
something we call spatial UI,
this can either refer
to clusters of controls
that don't have a specific
directionality associated
to them, things like left
and right text alignment
which should obviously stay
in the same position
across all languages.
And also the example above
which is the compass,
so things that have a physical
or geographical correspondence
should also stay the same,
north, east and west don't
change in right to left.
On iOS we have semantic content
attribute that helps you manage
and in turn, determine and
fine-tune the layout flow
of individual views
and their sub views.
This exposes an enum it's
a property on UIView,
like I said before, and
it's got all the cases
that I just mentioned,
so one for playback,
one for spatial UI, we have
self-explanatory force direction
cases as well, in
addition to unspecified
which is the default value.
And this is probably where most
of your views will fall into.
So, if you want to look
at these in more detail
and if you're also new to right
to left UI design in general,
I highly recommend you check
out this talk from last year,
New UIKit Ssupport
for International UI.
It goes into all of these
concepts into great detail
and also talks about some of
the new API, or not new anymore,
some of the API we added in
iOS 9 for right to left UI.
So that's a recap of what
we have right now in iOS
for layout, and with that I'd
like to move on over to images.
So images for right to left are
interesting because they tend
to fall into one of
three categories.
The first one is universal
images, so these are probably
where most of your images will
fall into, they're just artwork
or icons, and they don't need
any special consideration
for any language or
writing direction.
So they just stay the same, this
is of course familiar to you
as regular UIImage or
setting a name on a image view
and Interface Builder.
The second category is images
that do have the direction
associated to them.
So whether this is
a representation
of navigation arrows such as the
Back button in navigation bars,
or the detail disclosure
or disclosure indicator
on UITableView cells,
or in this case,
a simplified representation
of text,
these should be mirrored
in right to left.
And simply flipping the image
will produce the correct result
for right to left, so in this
case I just flip the image,
and now bullets are
in the correct place.
On iOS you can do this
using imageFlippedForRightTo
LeftLlayoutDirection, we
call this method on a UIImage
and the object returned
by it, when displayed
in the UIImage view, does the
correct thing automatically
if it's running in a
right to left context.
Lastly, the third
category is images
that do have the direction
associated to them but,
they are relatively complex
such that simply flipping
them would actually produce an
incorrect result
for right to left.
So in this case I have
that same bulleted list,
but instead of bullets
I have checkmarks
and when I flip the image
the checkmarks are now
in the correct place,
but they're also flipped
and they should actually
stay the same
in this example for
right to left.
So really what I need here is
two separate images entirely,
one for each layout direction.
So I can fine-tune my
image for right to left
and now it's displaying
correctly,
but now I have two
different images.
And up until now the way
you would do this on iOS
to display the correct one
at runtime is really
with a runtime check.
You would use our semantic
content attribute API to check
for your layout direction and
then load the correct image
from your bundle at runtime.
On iOS X we're changing
things up a little bit,
and we're starting with the
deprecation of image flip
for right to left
layout direction.
And with it we're
introducing a new concept
that will let you do all three
of these things using
just regular UIImages
or image names in
Interface Builder.
Introducing, brand new,
directional image assets
in Xcode 8 for your
asset catalogs.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
So, what does this mean?
So your image assets, in Xcode,
you will now have a new concept
and a new property that you
can set, it's called direction
and the values that you
can set echo the concepts
that I mentioned in
the previous slide.
So an image can either
have a fixed direction,
you can specify also
that an image is designed
for one layout direction
and that it should mirror
for the other, either from
left to right to right
to left or vice versa.
Or you can simply specify
two different images right
in your asset catalogs,
one for each direction.
Now these are image assets and
you might already be familiar
with the technology for other
kinds of image specialization
such as different
pixel densities or for
across different platforms.
So really this is the same
concept and all you have
to do is either set an
image in Interface Builder
or load it using
UIImage, image named.
And with that, I'd love
to show you a demo.
Alright so, so I have
here a very simple app
and let me just run it once
to show you how it looks like.
It's called Flags and in
true international fashion,
of course it's a
flag quiz game, yay.
So, this is pretty
straightforward,
it's a lot of fun in groups,
and what you can see
here is very simple UI.
So I've got here the
flag that I should guess
and I have a Reveal
button down at the top,
does anybody know what
this one is by any chance?
I know it's Friday,
early, 9 a.m. yeah?
Yeah, alright, I heard,
I'm hearing France a
lot, that's good, cool.
Okay, so thank you.
We also have two arrows,
so one to go forward
for the next question
and one to go back.
And this is all done using
auto layout constraints
and this is a vertical
stack view as well.
Anybody know what this one is?
Oh, wow, okay, awesome,
listen to that, okay.
Sweet, yeah, that's my
home country, Portugal, so,
you get the idea, right?
So, I'm thinking of adding right
to left support to this app.
Now I don't speak a word of
any language that happens
to be written and read in
right to left, but if I want
to see how my app would
look like, I don't have to.
Xcode allows me to
simulate a right
to left environment
right from itself.
So all I have to do is go to
edit my scheme, so up here
and edit the scheme
right at the top.
So this drops down
and with run selected,
I have Options tab
here at the top.
And over here I have an
application language override.
So this lists my
supported localizations
which are just English
at the moment
but I could also pick a right
to left pseudo language.
What this is going to do
is it's going to run my app
in my development language which
is English, but it's also going
to make the UI think
that it's running
in a right to left environment.
So I can just do that,
close, and rerun the app.
Yep. So let me start
the game again.
So already we're seeing
a few things right,
the navigation bar is
doing the correct thing,
it's showing the Back
button in the right place.
And my UI largely
looks the same,
except you might
have already noticed
that the arrows are now pointing
at each other which,
looks kind of wrong.
They're actually in the
correct place, so forward is now
on the left, which is
correct for right to left.
But the images themselves
have not adapted,
so I need to do that.
Now all I have to do in Xcode
8 is go to my image assets,
so I'm going to go ahead
and select them here.
And you'll notice that I
have two different images,
one for the back arrow,
and one for the forward.
And I'm going to go
here in the inspector
and select this new
direction property and instead
of it being a fixed image,
it's a left to right image
that mirrors for the
opposite layout direction.
I'm going to go do the same
for the forward arrow, whoops,
just so you can see that,
left to right mirrors
instead of it being fixed.
And now let me just
run my app again,
and see how it looks like.
Cool, let's start the game.
Alright, that's all I had to do
to now completely
support right to left.
This is without an
extra single line
of code dedicated
to right to left UI.
Auto layout, stack views and
now image assets do the heavy
lifting for you at runtime.
And by the way, I forgot to
mention this is also backed
by a page controller that
also, manages the gestures
for going forward and
backwards, so I don't even have
to worry about that either.
So that's the demo on image
assets, let's go back to slides.
Cool. So that's a brief
look at image assets
in the new direction support.
Now you can also do all of this
if your images are not
directly stored in your bundle
and say you're fetching
remote content
that you know has a
particular directionality
and you want display on your UI.
So this is for images
not stored locally,
you can associate these
images using trait collections
in UIKit.
We also have the
convenience method on UIImage
that lets you specify that
one image is a counterpart
of another and that
it should be mirrored
for adding to an image asset.
It's called imageWith
HorizontallyFlippedOrientation
and it's probably simpler if
I just show it to you in code.
So here it is and all I have
to do is create an image asset,
in this particular example I'm
getting a left to right image
from the remote source,
like a server.
And my right to left image
is just that same object
but horizontally flipped and
I'm using this new method
on UIImage.
Then just register each image,
one for each layout direction
using a trait collection
for left to right
and right to left.
And then really you might
already be using or writing code
that is similar to this, you
just get the image compatible
with a trait collection
for say an image view.
And this probably doesn't
even have to change
because once again, it's the
same concept we just have a new
directionality property
on top of it.
So that's directional
images, new in Xcode 8, iOS X,
and also watchOS and macOS.
We have a new trait which
is, layout direction
as you saw before, this is a
new UITrait collection in UIKit
and because this is a new trait,
there are some things to keep
in mind when it comes to
evaluating layout direction
on iOS with this new concept.
So let's say just as a very
simple example I have a UIView
subclass and I'm doing
some very custom layout
on layout sub views,
and it's represented
by this very simple blue box.
This is informed by semantic
content attribute whether it
should be left to
right or right to left,
and you can use our
API for this.
Now if this is unspecified,
semantic content attribute can
defer to your app environment
and this can either be
part of a trait environment
which has a trait collection,
or the app's general user
interface layout direction.
Now really, your UIView should
probably really only care
about whether or not it should
be left to right or right
to left, that's it, right.
And this can get pretty
complicated real fast.
So I'm happy to say that
on iOS X, you can do just
that by using this new
property on UIView,
it's a computed property
called effectiveUserInterface
LayoutDirection and it takes all
of these concepts into account
and tells you immediately
whether you should be laying
yourself out in left to
right or right to left.
If you're not using UIKit or
UIView In particular at all
for your drawing, say you have
a game using a SceneKit view
or a SpriteKit view, but
you still want to make use
of these view controller
concepts.
You can with this new
class method on UIView
that gives you the same, that
same layout evaluation relative
to a semantic content attribute.
And that's a brief look
at what's new in iOS,
so we saw brand new directional
image assets ready for use
with Interface Builder
and regular UI images
with no extra lines
of code needed
for right to left support.
You can do the same
thing with images
that are not directly
stored in your bundle,
and as a result we
are deprecating
imageFlippedForRightToLeft
LayoutDirection in iOS X.
We also just took a look at
the new convenience property
on UIView for determining layout
direction in custom layouts,
in addition to a class method
that lets you achieve the
same thing in other contexts.
So that's iOS, and now I'd
like to move swiftly
on over to watchOS.
So watchOS 2.1 added
Arabic and Hebrew
as selectable system languages.
And what this means
for your apps is
that watchKit is now
right to left aware.
So all watchKit elements
now do the right thing
when running in Arabic
or Hebrew.
We have an API that's
similar to iOS
that lets you fine-tune
individual group
or interface object instances.
And it's important to note
also that, having said that,
it's natural that it
should follow that,
a lot of the design
concepts that we saw
in iOS do apply on the watch.
So, the idea of pushing and
popping interface controllers
in their direction, these
should adapt for right to left
and you should keep this
in mind if you have any UI
that reflects this as well.
Any horizontal layout that
prioritizes certain things first
or has an ordering like showing
an image on a table view cell,
and then a label, you
should also adapt.
And, something very particular
to the watch, of course,
is the idea and concept of time
and in particular
clockwise and anti-clockwise.
And this is going back to
those nuances and exceptions,
if you have any radial
or clockwise
and anti-clockwise UI
this should stay the same
across layout directions, just
one of those things to keep
in mind in addition to the
concepts that we talked about.
So how do you do
this using the API?
So like I said before,
all interface objects now do
the right thing when running
in right to left,
these are your buttons,
your sliders and your switches.
In addition to that,
the concept of direction
and alignment also
change automatically.
So this means that the direction
of horizontal interface groups
and their alignment and also
alignment for any object
in watchKit relative to
its parent also changes.
So in the example, above
I have a very simple app
with a horizontal
group up at the top
with left alignment
and direction.
And a vertical group at the
bottom with left alignment.
When I run this app in Hebrew,
all of these change to right,
so note the ordering
of the elements
at the horizontal
interface group as well.
We have semantic content
attribute just like on iOS
with the same cases
that I talked
about to help manage
individual interface,
interface objects or groups.
And seeing this in action
is really just as simple
as any other property that you
would set on a watchKit object.
If you're not using
watchKit to draw your UI,
say you're using
SceneKit or SpriteKit,
they're new in watchOS 3,
you could still evaluate
a layout direction
if you have a semantic
content attribute in mind.
So here I just got the
direction using a class method
on interface device and once
I have that I just check
if it's left to right
or right to left.
And that's a brief look at
what we added in watchOS 2.1.
So once again it's the same
ideas and principles as iOS.
All watchKit elements do the
correct thing out of the box
with no extra work needed
and any custom UI or elements
that you have should
also reflect this.
Keeping in mind of course,
the nuances and exceptions
that I mentioned and you can
use semantic content attribute
to help determine the
layout direction at runtime.
And with that, I'd like to
hand it over back to Sara,
to talk to you about macOS and
handling bidirectional text,
thank you very much, I hope you
have a great Friday, thanks.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you.
So let's talk about macOS.
Just like the other
platforms, iOS and watchOS,
the concepts are exactly
the same for macOS.
So if you are using
standard AppKit controls,
you will get the
behavior out of the box
when you're running your app
in a right to left environment.
So now I would like to walk
you through some examples
from our own system to show
you how active controls behave.
So let's start with what we
call system level controls.
So we call these
system level controls
because the layout follow the
system language is running
in instead of your
app layout direction.
But this will make more sense
with some visual examples,
so let's take a look,
at the menu bar here.
So I'm running my system in
a right to left environment
and as you can see here,
the upper menu starts
from the right edge
of the window.
Also, the elements inside the
menu expand from right to left.
And this concept also
applies to NSWindow.
So by design we decided to
keep window controls always
consistent across
all apps regardless
if your app is localized or not.
So if you are doing
your own logic
and you're doing your own custom
controls you will need to take
that into consideration
and update that logic even
if you don't support Arabic
or Hebrew localizations.
Next, app level controls.
So app level controls here,
we follow the app language,
your layout direction
in your app.
So for example, NSTableView,
so this is a screenshot
from the activity monitor app,
we're using a stack table view
and as you can see the table
view [inaudible] reverse order
automatically when I'm running
my app in Arabic for example.
Another example,
NSCollectionView
and from the finder app
where the collection view flow
layout flows from right to left.
I will give you one
more example.
NSScrollView and the
same concept here,
so we also switch the position
of the scroll bar
inside the scroll view.
And this also will
avoid overlapping
with the content of
your application.
And keep in mind if you are
using web views in your apps,
so scroll in there works
a little bit differently.
So WebKit will look at the
content of your webpage
and evaluate its HTML
attributes and based
on that value it will
position the scroll bar.
So for example here, I'm running
Safari in English and I am
in Apple.com in English.
So looking at the content of
my webpage, so I will get,
the dir attribute here
is set to left to right
so we position the scroll
bar on the right side.
If I take the exact
same configuration,
but this time I am in
Apple.com in Arabic,
so looking at the content.
So here my content is in Arabic,
looking at the dir attributes
here again, it's set to right
to left, so we switch the
position of the scroll bar.
So these are just examples
from WebKit controls
and AppKit controls,
and now I would
like to talk to you about API.
So we just saw in
the last example
that WebKit's controls work
a little bit differently
from AppKit.
So with that we are
providing a new API
in WebKit called
userInterfaceDirectionPolicy.
As I mentioned, the default
value is set to the content
of your webpage, but you can
override this value if you want
for example your scrollers
to follow the system
language instead
of the content of your webpage.
So you can override it to use
system instead of content.
Next, let's talk
about AppKit API.
As a quick recap, if you use
standard AppKit controls you
don't have to do anything,
everything will just
work for free.
Now you might have a specific
design in mind and you want
to layout your views
by yourself.
So in that case we
highly recommend
that you use StackViews
and GridViews.
So grid views are new to macOS,
and both these tools are really
powerful because they will set
up auto layouts constraints
for you under the hood.
And they also use leading
and trailing constraints
which will flip your
views automatically
when you're running in a
right to left environment.
If you are not using StackViews
or GridViews, use auto layout.
If you're not familiar with
it, there are great sessions
from previous years and there is
a session this afternoon called
What's New in Auto
Layout, check it out.
Finally, if you're
using storyboards
in base approach
we also take care
of flipping the text
alignment for you.
In addition to that, we
have an API in NSView
that will let you get and
set the layout direction
of your views.
So for example here,
I have a banner slider
that has two values,
left and right.
So I want my slider
to be consistent
across all my localizations,
because it makes sense
left should always stay
on the left side and
right should always stay
on the right side.
So here it will make total sense
if I force the layout direction
of my slider to be
always left to right.
So as I mentioned, we
have an API in NSView
that will let you do that.
The default value is set
to NSApp.userInterfaceLayout
Direction,
but you can override it
to left or right based
on what you want to
do in your views.
Now let's talk about images.
As we just saw in
Joaquim's demo,
we introduced directional
image assets, in asset catalog.
So assets catalogs
also exist in macOS
and they work exactly the same
way as iOS, so I'm not going
to go through details here.
But again, sometimes you
don't have your images
in your application bundle
but you still want to get them
from a remote location,
let's say a server.
So we also have an API in
NSImageRep that will let you do
that and register
your images in code.
So let's go through an
example together here,
just see how it works.
So as I mentioned, sometimes you
have images in another location
and you want to register them.
So first what you need to
do is to create your left
to right image by
using NSImage API.
And once you have that you need
to set this layout
direction to be left to right.
So same thing for your
right to left image,
but this time you will
need to use NSImageRep API.
So once you have both images, so
you need to register your right
to left image representation
with the left to right image
and that by using
other presentation API.
So with that, once you have both
images registered we will load
the right image for
you at runtime,
either if you're running
your app in a left
to right localization or a
right to left localization.
Finally, we have new
convenience initializers
for common AppKit controls.
For an accessory for example, it
will set the alignment attribute
and auto layout attributes
correctly for you.
And for NSButton, it
will flip the image,
the checkbox position, and the
Radio button positions also
for free.
So with that, I would
like to show you a demo
to summarize what we
just saw in the section.
Alright. Cool, so I got
inspired by Joaquim's demo
and I created a scoreboard
app so we can track our scores
when we are playing
the game together.
So here I have a simple,
app where you can see it
in my view controller, I
just have a table view,
and I already setup my
auto layout constraints.
And inside my table view cell
I have an image, a text field,
and a [inaudible]
so pretty simple.
So here I'm using
StackViews to lay
out the elements inside my table
view cell, so I didn't even need
to worry about setting
up auto layout constraint
because text view just
took care of that for me.
And here at the bottom,
I have a label
where I update my highest
score and my best play.
So pretty simple.
So what I'm going to do now,
I'm going to simulate a right
to left environment
directly on my app
and see how it looks like.
Great. So I'm going to
go to my scheme editor,
to my application language
and choose my right
to left pseudo language
instead of my system language.
I'm going to build
and run my app again.
And it's building, great.
So as you can see here without
writing one line of code,
just by using storyboard,
StackViews,
auto layouts, it just works.
So that's it, so now that my app
looks great in right to left,
what I'm going to do, I want
to go back to my code and,
I'm going to run
my app, this time,
in my system language instead
of right to left pseudo language
So this will just run
the app in English
because my system
now is in English.
Now I'm going to
run my app again.
So why I'm doing this, so I just
want to show you another aspect
of international
user interfaces.
So here, so my app looks
great in English as well,
and now I want to join the game.
So I'm going to add
a new player.
I'm going to click here, add
a new player and here just
for fun, I want to write my
name in my native language.
So I'm going to go ahead
and change my keyword
to use Arabic instead
of English.
Alright, so I type my
name in Arabic, great.
And I'm also really good at
guessing flags, so I'm going
to win this game, so I'm
not going to waste time.
So I'm just going to
update my score anyway.
So, alright, see
what happened here?
So just by updating my name, so
my label is completely broken
because it jumps
to the right side
and now my label just reads "!
has the highest score 12, Sara."
That doesn't make any sense.
So in the next section I
would like to show you how
to solve this kind of
problem and how can you render
by directional text correctly.
So let's go back to slides.
So we just saw in the demo
app, just by entering my name
in Arabic, it broke the
rendering of my text.
So now let's see how we can
fix these kind of problems.
So rendering text in
your applications is
really important.
It doesn't matter if
you support localization
of that specific language,
even if you are supporting
only English,
your users can still
read and write content
in any other language.
And when it comes to text, it's
really important to remember
that text alignment and
text directionality are two
different concepts.
So for example here, I have
a paragraph in English,
it's right aligned, it's
fine, it looks great,
because you might need
to do that by design,
so it won't break
the text rendering.
But if I take the same example
but this time it's left aligned,
but I'm forcing the writing
direction of it to be right
to left, that will break
the rendering of your text.
As you can see here the
exclamation marks are not
in the correct position.
So let's talk a little
bit for that.
Lateral alignment is
default in all our platforms,
so if you don't override
that value,
so we'll get the right
behavior, in most cases.
So let's talk about
text directionality
because it's a little
bit more complex.
So here I'm just going to give
you a really simplified overview
of the text engine by algorithm.
But if you want to
learn more about Unicode
by the algorithm please check
out the full specification
in Unicode.org.
But let's start with the basics.
So there are three types
of Unicode characters.
So they can be either
strong left to right,
for example scripts
that we are familiar
with Latin, Chinese or Japanese.
They can be strong right to left
characters for example scripts
like Arabic, Hebrew, Farsi or
Urdu and there are characters
that they don't have a
directionality at all,
and we call these neutral
or weak characters.
For example spaces.
So how the text engine decides
about the directionality
of a specific paragraph?
So the text engine just look
at the first strong Unicode
characters, that's it.
And if it's a strong
right to left,
my paragraph would
be right to left.
If it's strong left to right,
my paragraph will have a left
to right directionality.
So let's walk through an example
together to see how it works.
So if I take my label
from the demo app,
%@ has the highest color.
So I have no idea at runtime
what my %@ will be replaced by,
because my user can write
or input anything,
use any keyboard.
So let's take the
simple case here,
where my %@ will be
replaced with a Latin name.
So here the first character
is an A, it belongs to Latin,
so it's a strong left to right.
So the directionality of my
paragraph here is left to right
so it renders correctly.
Now if my variable is
replaced with an Arabic name.
So the first strong character
here is an Arabic character
which give the directionality
of my whole paragraph
to be right to left.
So that's why the, my
text rendering was broken,
so this is wrong.
So the right behavior here will
be something, so I will expect
to see something like that,
even my name is in Arabic.
I want it to be on the
left side and the rest
of my paragraph will be rendered
correctly from left to right.
So wouldn't it be great
if I had something
that will take my
variable, will isolate it
and give it its own
writing direction
without affecting the
rest of my paragraph?
And that's possible
with Isolates supports.
So Isolates are the latest
Unicode [inaudible] characters
that were introduced
in Unicode 6.3
and that our text engine
supports in all our platforms.
So as I mentioned, Isolates will
allow some text to be isolated
and have the directionality
of its first strong character
and that's without affecting
the surrounding text.
And I'm happy to
say, you don't need
to insert these characters
yourself, like in case-by-case
because if you use
localizedStringWithFormat,
we do that for you
automatically.
So localizedStringWithFormat
will isolate %@ automatically
and it will do the
right thing at runtime.
So now, I would like to
go back to the demo app
and fix the issue we introduce
earlier just by one line
of code, so let's do that.
Alright, so cool.
So now I'm going to go back
to, my view controller here
and this is where
I update my label.
So just to save some time
I already wrote the code
to use localized standard string
with format instead
of a regular string.
So I'm going to go ahead here
and comment this regular string
and uncomment the line that is
using localizedStringWithFormat.
I'm going to run my app again,
and see if my issue's fixed.
Right, so as you can see
here, so my problem is fixed.
So my name now is on the
left side of my sentence,
I can read it correctly.
So let's see if it works
with English names as well.
So see here if I update
with, Rana, see if it works.
And with Arabic names as well,
and that's Isolates
support in our platforms.
So let's go back to slides.
[ Applause ]
Alright so let's summarize.
So in this session we introduced
directional image assets.
So it's easier now for you
to support different images
for both your left to right and
right to left localizations.
We have new APIs for you
on iOS, watchOS and macOS.
And auto layout is your best
friend if you want to lay
out your views and support
other localizations.
And we also improved
our text engine
by supporting Isolates
Unicode characters.
So with all these improvements,
it's really easy for you,
as a developer, to go ahead
and reach new markets.
For more information, please
visit developer.apple.com
to find our session there and
thank you so much for coming.
And those are related sessions
if you didn't watch
them already,
please check them
out, they are good.
And have a wonderful
day, enjoy the rest
of WWDC, thank you so much.