[ Music ]
>> So hi, everybody.
[ Applause ]
I'm Melissa, I'm one of
the core data engineers
and this literally the first
year that no one has told me
to break a leg before I go out
on stage, because frankly I did
that a month ago and
this my first day
without a cast [laughter].
So if I'm limping around
you'll know what happened.
[ Applause ]
So one of the best
parts of working
on core data is actually
being able to get
up on stage here every year
and tell you guys like what new
and interesting stuff
we've been doing and boy,
this year we have a lot of it,
and it's really useful and we,
we hope you're going to love it.
So I'm going to talk about a
new feature, query generations,
some changes in the core
data concurrency world.
I'm going to talk about some
new stuff we've done in the area
of core data stack configuration
and some new APIs we've added.
And we're going to talk a
bit about what we've done
to integrate more neatly and
cleanly with Swift and some
of the improvements we've made
in the area of Xcode
integration.
And that's a lot so, on with
the first, query generations.
Query generations is a
new feature we've added
but before I sort
of get into talking
about query generations
I need to talk
about faults a little bit.
Core data uses faults a lot,
as some of you may know.
Manage objects can be faults,
their relationships
can be faults,
and if you're using
batch fetching,
then the array you get back
from NSManagedObjectContext
execute fetch request,
is going to be a very
specialized fault.
So that being said,
what is a fault?
Well, up here on the
screen I've got a picture
of an object graph, I've got
a country, the United States.
State, California,
couple of counties,
Santa Clara and San Francisco.
And some cities in Santa
Clara, San Jose and Cupertino.
And some of this is a piece
of like a tourist guide a
guidebook, something you can go
in and navigate through
to find points of interest
in a city you're planning
on going and visiting.
But just based on what we
know about the United States,
this isn't a full object
graph, this is actually a piece
of an object graph, sub graph.
Because we know that the
United States has other states,
and those states
have other counties,
and those counties
have other cities.
And you know, beyond
that we know
that the United States is
only one of many countries.
And even in a guidebook I'm only
interested in sort of looking
at one set of data at a time.
If I'm planning a trip to
San Jose, I don't really care
about Oregon or Washington,
or anything like that.
I don't even really care
about San Francisco.
I need to be able to
get to those object,
to those destinations
if I'm interested
and change my mind later about
what I'm interested in browsing.
But for the immediate short
term, while I'm looking
and planning my trip to Santa
Clara County, I don't care.
And that not caring
is represented by,
in memory a fault, it's an
object that knows how to go off
and retrieve data
later, at some point
if I decide I want to use it.
So say I find out my
friend is getting married
and her wedding's in
Seattle and I want to go,
you know plan a trip to Seattle.
So at this point I'm going to
navigate back up to the U.S.
and come down, I want
to look at Washington
and core data will automatically
retrieve the information
for Washington even
though it wasn't in memory
when I first loaded
the sub graph.
And you know, I can navigate
down from that and so on.
And that's what a fault is,
it's that future or promise,
or lazy loading, these
are all different names
for the same kind of
thing, that core data does
to help minimize the
amount of data you have
in memory at any given point.
Why do we use faults?
Well performance, performance,
performance, and
also performance.
The best most performing
application is one
that doesn't do any
work you don't need.
You don't load objects over
the iobus, that you don't need.
You don't spend any
time [inaudible]
on objects that you don't need.
You don't want to have those
objects sitting around pushing
up your heaps high water mark
if your user's never
going to look at them.
But there is kind of
one issue with faults,
and it's sort of this.
Here we have that object
graph again, and in this case,
we've got a lot of faults.
And I'm navigating down my
tree and I go to Santa Clara
and I want to fire
the Cupertino fault.
But in the meantime, an external
process has been importing data
from the web and for whatever
reason it's deleted Cupertino.
Well, what happens?
I have a fault that's
supposed to go off
and retrieve information
about Cupertino
but there's no information
there anymore.
I said, I talked a lot about
not loading data you don't need,
but in this case, you
find yourself wondering,
well did I actually need
that data after all?
Oops.
In core data right
now, you handle this
by using the
shouldDeleteInaccessibleFaults
property on
NSManagedObjectContext.
If you set that then
when the context notices
that you're trying to fire a
fault for a deleted object,
it will mark the fault as
being deleted and populate all
of its properties with nils.
This is mostly what
you're going to want
but sometimes it
can be inconvenient
because your UI doesn't
know how to deal
with you know, a nil identifier.
The other alternative is
to prefetch everything,
use relationship keypads
for prefetching to load all
of the objects you think
your user might want.
That moves you into
an escalating battle
with your user trying
to figure out exactly,
predict what they're going
to want, that can be tricky,
users are unpredictable,
we all know that.
The other alternative,
there is a third one,
there's always a third
one, write lots of code,
starting with using
existing object with ID
on the manage object context
to make sure that the object is
in the database before
you try the fault.
Write lots of try catch,
exceptional handlers
around all your fault firing
and frankly that's not
really fun code to write,
you'd really rather be
writing interesting features
for your users to use,
because that's why they come
to your application,
because it does neat stuff.
But let's step back
for a second and think
about your user interacting
with your application.
The user view and the
UI often doesn't care
about seeing the
absolute latest,
freshest, snappiest data.
How do we know this?
Let's think about gas
pumps for a second.
Most of you are familiar
with them, you've put gas
in a car at some point.
Gas pumps have a display that
tells you how many gallons
or how many liters you've
actually put in your car.
And that display has
a thousandths field,
and I'd like a show of hands
for everybody who's capable
of reading that field,
in real time,
as they put gas in their car.
That's about what I expected,
none of you can process it,
the human brain wants data
sort of batched up neatly
in intervals that
it can understand.
So the user doesn't really
need latest, freshest data,
they just need it
to be, you know,
reasonably, quickly updated.
And a user who's saving
data, also doesn't care,
this is why core data
has merge policies,
they want to make a bunch
of edits and they want
to have those edits saved
and mingled with whatever's
in the database and have
the right thing happen.
You pick the merge
policy you want
because you know your
users better than we do.
So what if we could take
this insight and build on it?
What if we could provide a way
to give your UI a stable view
of data in the database?
What if we could give you
a way to handle changes,
update changes
deterministically?
And what if we could
do all of this
so that you would
never see this again?
[ Applause ]
And now I can talk
about query generations.
Query generations are a way
of giving your manage object
context a basically a read
transaction on data
in the database.
All reads into that manage
object context are going
to see the same view of data
until you choose to advance it,
and you'll never see could
not fulfill a fault again.
And the important part is
we do this efficiently,
that's always been
the tricky bit.
How do they work?
Well, I've got a
database, it has an object
in it, id 1, name fred.
And because these are
slides, I'm going to cut those
down because I need all the real
estate I can get for this built.
In a traditional database
that's what you've got,
you have one file, it has one
view of data in the world.
Using query generations though,
that becomes the
first generation
of data in your database.
And processes come along,
this can be your application,
it can be an importer, it can
be an extension on a watch,
something modifies the database.
A new generation is created.
And, more data is
created, new objects.
And at this point, the user
launches your application,
creates manage object
context and you load data.
And that context now
knows what generation
in the database it
loaded data from.
So as other processes or
contexts or whatever come along
and modify the database
some more,
more generations are created,
that context still
knows its generation.
Second context comes up, loads
some data, makes some edits,
and saves and in saving it
creates a new generation
and tracks that it's now
representing generation,
in this case 6, in the database.
And at this point if we
fire a fault, in context 1,
even though the object
underlining
that fault may have been
deleted in generation 6,
it's still visible to the
context because it's still
in the database under
the label generation 3.
And at this point the user can
go make some edits in context 1,
delete some objects, change some
objects, insert new objects.
And when they save that context
core data will use the merge
policy to merge all of those
changes with whatever's
in the database and
create a new generation 7.
In the same way that context 1.
[ Applause ]
In the same way that context 1
had visibility onto generation 3
when it was pinned
to generation 3.
Context 2 can do whatever it
would like with its objects,
turn them back into
faults, refire those faults,
and it will still see
the data as it existed
in generation 6 in the database.
So basically it's full
read transactionality
at the manage object
context level.
We've talked a lot
about how context have,
are essentially right
transactions
and now we've made them
read transactions as well.
So allows you to immediately
isolate your work on a context
by context level,
and minimize stuff
like preventive prefetching
which means,
you know, everybody wins.
Basics. An individual context
can choose what behavior it
wants, it can decide that it
wants the current behavior
that you're used to
in iOS 9 and macOS 11.
We call unpinned, see top
of tree when you load data.
You can also specify
that a context should pin
to whatever generation is
current in the database
when data is first
loaded into that context.
Or you can specify
that you want it to pin
to a specific generation
if you have another context
pinned to that generation.
Nested contacts are going
to inherit their
parents' generation,
they're implicitly unpinned
but they'll see data as viewed
through the, the
generation of their parent,
plus whatever pending changes
their parent has sitting
around unsaved.
Updates are kind of important,
we've all acknowledged that,
the user doesn't
want to see updates,
eventually they don't want to
see, you know 10 year-old data.
Generations are updated when
you explicitly tell a context
to update by setting a
new generation token.
They're updated on
save, they're updated
if you call mergeChanges,
will update to top of tree
at that point since you've
told the context that,
you know it should be looking
at a new set of changes
in the database,
and it's updated
as a result of calling reset.
Thing to note though is that,
registered objects
aren't refreshed
when you update the generation,
you may not want that,
and it's easy for us to let
you do it, it's a lot harder
to let you undo it if we
choose to do it for you.
If you want to refresh the data
you'll have to call a fetch
or refreshAllObjects, but it
gives you control over when
that data actually gets updated.
If you want to use query
generations you'll need
to be using and SQL store and
it needs to be in wall mode.
Although if you try and
use query generations
and you haven't met those
two requirements it will sort
of fail gracefully and just
revert to the unpinned behavior.
How did we do it?
Well, there's an now opaque
token that you can use
to track a query generation.
This will tell the
context, you know when
and what store it
loaded data from.
The query generation token
has a method current,
you can use to retrieve
a token to indicate
that a context should
pin when it loads data.
ManagedObjectContext, we
have a few new methods,
there's a property,
query generation token
that will tell you what query
generation a context is using.
It'll be nil if the
context is unpinned.
And you can set a query
generation from a token,
either the current token
from class property or,
the result of calling
queryGenerationToken
on another manage
object context.
A generation won't include
stores that were added
to the store coordinator after
the generation was created.
If you load data into a
manage object context,
add a store to the
coordinator and then do a fetch,
you will not see results
from that new store.
But it does not prevent
you from removing stores
from the coordinator, although
you're going to see an error
if you try and load data into a
context when you've removed all
of the stores that it was
trying to load data from.
And now I'm going to talk
about concurrency because,
well we always talk
about concurrency.
This is the current state
of affairs in core data,
and it's manage object
context is an actor.
You use perform and
performAndWait to interact
with it, do schedule
blocks for execution
on the managed object
context queue.
There is a third model,
which, or another model,
which is to use the
confinementConcurrencyType
which allows you to
message the context directly
but that's deprecated
because it turns
out that that's really
hard to get right
in any threading situation.
The persistent store
coordinator is also an actor
and has the same API
perform and performAndWait.
And the coordinator will
serialize request coming
in from individual managed
object context along
with whatever request you've
directly scheduled using the
perform and performAndWait
APIs on the coordinate.
And at this point I'd like to
make an important announcement,
we have added, for those of
you who are programming in ObjC
and using manual retain
release, and auto release pool
around perform, block and wait.
This means that you're now
going to be responsible
for extending the lifespan
of any objects created
in the blocks you've
scheduled if you want
to use those objects
outside the block.
It's easy to remember to
do that for the results of,
for example an execute fetch.
It's a little bit less
immediately obvious
that you also need to
do this for any NSErrors
that may be being returned.
This doesn't only affect people
using manual retain release
and we have a link time check
so you won't see this behavior
until you recompile
for iOS X or macOS 12.
But let's talk about concurrency
as it exists in the world today.
Or, as it exists in the
world until yesterday.
Context 1 tries to do
something that requires going
to the persistent store, so
it messages the coordinator.
Which, because its sterilizing
requests, takes a lock.
And at this point context 2,
which may be your UIContext
wants to do something and tries
to message the coordinator.
But because the coordinator is
locked, context 2 has to wait,
as the request from context 1 is
passed down to persistent store
and whatever work is necessary
to evaluate, evaluates.
And it's only when that
work finishes and the thread
of execution returns that
context 2 can take a lock
on the coordinator and
have its work dispatched
down to the store.
And this means that context 2
is basically going to be blocked
on whatever work it is
that context 1 is doing.
And eventually it will return
but in the meantime
your IU might have,
you know been a little bit slow.
New stuff, the SQL store now has
a connection pool and is capable
of handling multiple
concurrent requests.
Specifically it can now
handle multiple readers
and a single writer, size of
the connection pool varies
from platform to platform.
We've adopted it and
we'll show you how
to change it in a couple slides.
So how does this work now?
Well context 1 dispatches
to the coordinator,
and well no lock is taken.
Context 2, which may still be
your UIContext also dispatches
the coordinator and both
of those messages are sent
down to the persistent
store at the same time.
Persistent store then does
whatever work it needs to figure
out what messages
it needs to SQLite
and those are sent
down to SQLite.
And it's only at that
point that a lock is taken,
and this is the standard
SQLite file block.
SQLite does whatever it needs
to do, begin opens transaction,
right it's a bunch of SQL,
closes the transaction,
ends at that point returns.
So you can see at this point
that we've really, really,
really decreased the scope of
the critical section there.
And why do you care?
This is going to make your
UI a lot more responsive,
you can fault and
fetch in, for example,
a main UI while background
work is happening
on a separate context.
And the immediate fallout
from this is it really
simplifies application
architecture, a fairly
standard pattern,
has been that people will have
an importer context that's
loading data for
example, from the web.
And another, a main UIContext
is vending data to the main UI.
And they end up having
these on separate stacks
because the UI needs
to be responsive
and they need the
critical section locking
to be as small as possible.
And the only way to get
that before when you had
to lock the entire stack, was
to have two separate stacks.
And that introduced an issue
with doing hand offs between,
okay there's a manage object
context did save notification
but it's coming from an entirely
separate persistent store
coordinator and I need
to migrate that over.
That's no longer an issue there,
you can now attach both context
to the same persistent store
coordinator, they'll execute
in parallel and you can
just do standard merging,
and as a huge bonus this means
they're sharing the row cache
which is really going to
decrease your memory footprint.
It's going to divide
it by 2, since well,
we've only got one
row cache nowadays.
It's on by default, it's for SQL
stores only, and it only works
if all coordinated stores
on a persistent store
coordinator are SQL stores.
You can configure the size
of the connection pool
using the NSPersistentStore
ConnectionPoolMax
SizeKey, that allows you
to specify the maximum
size the connection pool.
If you want serial
request handling,
the old behavior,
you can set it to 1.
We do reserve the right
to say you tried to set it
to one million and that's
kind of silly so we're going
to use a more reasonable number.
It should be transparent to
most of you right off the bat,
your UIs will possibly get
a little more responsive.
The big thing we noticed
internally once we turned this
on, was a whole bunch of
people said, hey, wow I can rip
out a couple hundred, couple
thousand lines of code.
And you should do it because man
is that satisfying [laughter].
A few of you.
[ Applause ]
A few of you may notice,
some minor timing issues.
If you had a context, context
1 that had a perform block
and wait and context 2 that also
had a perform block and wait,
originally context 2 would
not start executing its block
until context 1's block had
returned, that's no longer true.
So for the like .1% of you
who are in that situation,
your timing's going to
change and you may need
to decrease the bandwidth
connection pool,
the rearchitect.
The rest of you, you'll
just get to build new
and interesting and
simpler code.
And at this point I'm
going to drag my co-worker,
Scott up on stage and
he's going to talk
about a bunch of other stuff.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks Melissa.
Good morning, let's talk
about setting up core data,
starting with adding
a persistent store.
To add a persistent
store to a coordinator,
you need four pieces
of data and,
to do most operations
you need at least two.
New this year, core data has
introduced a new type called
NSPersistentStoreDescription
that encapsulates all
of the data needed
to describe a store
and also includes convenience
API for common options
like whether the store
should be opened read only,
the timeout that the coordinator
should use, automatic migration
and mapping options which are
both enabled by default now.
And a new option, for adding
stores asynchronously,
this new type works
with a new method
on the persistent
store coordinator
that takes a trail
enclosure with parameters
for the store description and an
optional NSError that is non-nil
if the operation failed.
If you're adding a store
asynchronously you can extend
the conditional in a
call back for things
like posting a notification or
pushing your application's UI
after the store has
been successfully added.
This way your app's model setup
can happen off the main thread
which is especially useful
when your application launches
since a migration
may cause a delay.
Remember, if iOS notices that
your app hasn't been responsive
for a while after launch,
then it will kill the app.
This can prevent a migration
from ever finishing but,
it's not a problem anymore
if you're adding a
store asynchronously.
So that's persistent
store descriptions but,
there's a lot more involved
in setting up core data stack.
To represent a core data stack
you need at least three objects,
plus the boiler plate to
associate them with each other.
New this year, core data
has yet another type
that encapsulates
those objects and most
of the boiler plate called
NSPersistentContainer,
not only does it [laughter].
[ Applause ]
I realized a lot of you have
written this type yourselves
maybe but [laughter] this one
not only encapsulates modeling
configuration it
also has a name,
a list of store descriptions,
and a method
to load store descriptions
from that list
that haven't already been
added to the coordinator.
This means that the
project boiler plated needed
to setup core data goes
from an entire page of code
to just a couple of lines.
[ Applause ]
So there's a lot of
code missing here now,
let's take a look
at how it all works.
The container guarantees that
its properties are always valid
so the getters for things like
the coordinator and the model,
will always return new
objects that are safe to use.
The container's initializer
finds a model based on the name
that you pass into
the initializer,
there's also another initializer
that takes an explicit
model argument.
By default, new containers
have a single store description
in the list, it's an
SQLite with default options
and a file name based on
the name of the container.
And it's stored in a directory
that's defined by a class method
on the container, and
a persistent container,
by default will return
you a directory based
on the platform that you're on.
So it will use the application
support directory on macOS,
your container document
structure on iOS and launchOS,
and your containers
caches directory on tvOS.
If you want to set your own
directory then you can subclass
in this persistent container
and override the direct,
sorry the defaulted
directory URL class method.
We think container's really
helpful for setting up core data
but they also provide
convenience
for common operations.
Containers have a main queue
context property called view
context that you can
use to drive your UI.
There's also a factory method
that vends background contexts
that are ready to use
but most of the time,
you'll probably want to
use the container's method
for performing background tasks
which is called
performBackgroundTask.
So instead of having to setup a
new background context and wire
up and then a queue a
block just to do something
in the background you can just
pass a block to the container.
Using performBackgroundTask
can have a benefit to the
on code concision using it
gives core data the ability
to reduce the number of
contexts that are created
to do your work, and also can
work with connection pooling
to ensure that your
app stays responsive,
even under heavy load.
Speaking of common
context work flows,
the NSManagedObjectContext has
a new property this year called
automatically merges
changes from parent.
It's a Boolean and
when you set it
to true the context will
automatically merge,
save the change the
data of its parent.
This works for [laughter].
[ Applause ]
This is really handy, it
works for child context
when the parent saves its
changes, and it also works
for top level context when a
sibling saves up to the store.
It works especially well
with generation tokens
which Melissa talked
about earlier.
So your UIs can be maintenance
free if you pin your UI context
to the latest generation and
then enable automatic merging,
your faults will be safe
and your object bindings
and fetch results controllers
will keep themselves
up to date [laughter].
Alright. Let's talk
about generics.
Core data has adopted generics
this year and they work great
in both ObjC and Swift.
There is a new protocol
called NSFetchRequestResult,
and it is adopted by all of the
types that you'd ever expect
to see back from the fetch
request like NSManagedObject
or all the entity subclasses.
Object IDs, NSDictionary
and NSNumber.
NSFetchRequest is now
parameterized based on the type
of the results which
is restricted
by protocol conformance and
in Swift, the fetch method
on NSManagedObjectContext
plums the type
of fetch request all the
way out to your results.
[Background noise] Finally,
a fetch results controller
who adopt the parameterization
of the fetch request
used to create it.
Speaking of
NSFetchResultsController,
if you're using UICollection
view, sorry there we go,
UICollection view,
it's really easy
to adopt the new data
source prefetching feature
if you're using core data.
All you need is an
asynchronous fetch request,
to get the request off the main
thread and you want to make sure
that you're not returning
objects as faults.
For more information about
data source prefetching,
check out Steve and
Peter's talk from yesterday,
what's new in UICollection view.
If you're a Mac developer I
also have good news for you.
The fetch results controller
is now available on macOS.
[ Applause ]
Okay, so let's talk about some
common operations in core data,
starting with getting
an entity description.
Oops this, there we go.
For this you need the
entity's name as a string
and a managed object context.
Creating a fetch request also
requires a string constant
as well as a type
cast if you want
to take advantage
of the new generics.
And finally, there is
creating a new managed object
which has all three
things, a string constant,
a context parameter,
and a type cast.
These operations are all
getting easier this year
through improvements we've made
to manage object subclasses.
The entity description is now
a class method on the subclass.
[ Applause ]
Don't worry this gets
better [laughter].
The class also has
a factory method
for creating new fetch
requests that are fully typed.
[ Applause ]
And finally, you can
create a new manage object,
object using just the
subclass's initializer directly.
[ Applause ]
There's one more thing
that's worth talking
about which is performing
a fetch request.
I mentioned earlier that
the context fetch method is
parameterized in Swift but ObjC
doesn't support method level
generics, so we've
also added actor
like semantics to
fetch requests.
So you can just call
its execute method
from inside a block
submitted to a context
and it will return
properly typed results.
[ Applause ]
All this new API for model
subclasses should make a lot
of things much easier
but I'm guessing
that you're not really looking
forward to regenerating all
of your subclasses, but
don't worry because,
this should be the last year you
have to do anything with them.
Because Xcode 8 can now generate
that code for you automatically.
[ Applause ]
You can configure code
generation per entity
and Xcode will write
the generated code
to your project's derived data
so it doesn't pollute
your source tree
with code you didn't write.
You don't want to
edit these files
since the code is
automatically regenerated
when you change your model
but if you want to do things
like add your own instance
variables or something
to the subclass, then
you can also tell Xcode
to only generate a
category or extension
and then you can own
the class itself.
In Swift all you need to do
to use this feature
is import the module
that your entities belong to
which is often the same module
as your code, but
in ObjC you'll need
to know a bit more
about how this works.
The most important file in,
to know about in ObjC is the
core data model header file.
Each model has its own header
file and you need to import it
to get access to all of that
model's generated classes.
If we zoom in for a look at
the other generated files
for entities configured
to generate classes,
Xcode creates two headers that
you probably already recognize
from generating classes
yourself.
One declares the class interface
and the other declares
the managed properties.
This is mostly important
to know for ObjC
because if you're
generating a category,
then Xcode will not
generate a class interface,
and the model's header will
import the category directly.
Categories can't be declared
without a class interface
so the generated code
expects to find a header
in your project that's
named after the class.
This is a file that you
own, and if it doesn't exist
in your project then your
target will fail to build.
So let's take a quick break
from slides and have a look
at what all this new
stuff means for you.
I have Xcode 8 open
here and we're going
to create a new Xcode project.
And use iOSes master
detail application.
We've updated the templates
this year to use the new UI.
So if we, save this somewhere
and go to the app delegate,
then we can see that,
we're using a persistent
container here and we're wiring
up the master view controller
with the container's
view context.
If we go to the master
view controller,
we can see where it
creates a new object
that we're already using
subclass initializers
that are generated by core data.
And we're not using KVC anymore
we can set properties directly
on the manage object and if
we command click we get taken
to the generated file.
If we come back and we look
at how the fetch results
controller is set up,
there we are.
We can see that raising the
fetch request factory method
on the event subclass
and there's no extra
explicit typing here
when we create the fetch
results controller but its type,
which is really tiny,
but if we zoom in here,
is passed through from
the fetch request.
This means that elsewhere,
in the sub,
prepare for segue, there we go.
When we get an object from the
fetch results controller it
comes back with the right type.
So that's all great we
have no type cast anymore.
And, but I don't want this
app to show timestamps
in the master view controller
like it does by default.
So let's add a title attribute
to our event entity here.
And we want it to
be a string type.
Alright so we've
rebuilt, saved our model,
and if we go back here
and go to configure cell,
and we can delete
this code here.
And take advantage of
Xcode's auto completion
to get a new property that
we just set up in our model.
[ Applause ]
And again if we command
click on it,
all of the code has
been updated.
[ Applause ]
One of the best hidden
benefits of this is
if you're using manually
generated subclasses
or even KVC, if you change
the name of an attribute,
you can wind up with
some really weird bugs
because your project
compiles but when it comes
to actually making the calls
you get a run time error,
because the key path
doesn't exist anymore.
Automatically subclass
generation takes care
of all of this.
So let's automatic
subclass generation as well
as some working examples
of core data's new API.
Last, let's talk about
what's new in SQLite.
The SQLite library that comes
with the operating
system has some new tricks
that you won't find
anywhere else.
The first of which is
multi-threading assertions.
SQLite on Apple platforms does
not have thread safe connections
and multi-threading bugs
can be hard to diagnose,
sometimes because they usually
manifest as a crash report
with a single thread
deep inside SQLite.
To make these issues
easier to identify
and reproduce the system
SQLite supports new environment
variable that enables
multi-threading assertions
when they fire you'll see
two threads in SQLite,
and they're both using
the same connection.
SQLite has always supported
user defined logging functions
through a configuration that
you can set using SQLite3 config
but that function needs
to be called before the
library is initialized
which may have already happened.
SQLite configurability is great
but we're running
a modeling system
that has built-in
logging facilities
so there's now another
environment variable
that chimes SQLite
logging to the system log.
Finally, I want to talk
about file operations.
All databases are represented
by a combination of files
and file operations
cannot be atomic
when they're in multiple files.
The result of this is that
all file operations are
inherently unsafe.
Unix file APIs to
NSFileManager, everything.
This is really important
and I want to share a couple
of concrete examples of
how things can go wrong.
Let's say I notice two database
files in the directory and,
my code wants to do some clean
up so it deletes them but in
between deleting the database
and the journal something
connects to the database file.
That database doesn't have
access to the journal,
so it can't make
sense of the database,
so it starts reporting
errors immediately
which affects your app.
Unless you can guarantee
that nothing is currently
or it will ever try to
connect to a database,
it's not safe to
delete its files.
Let's say I have a
database in wall mode
and something is using it,
and the database finally gets
moved aside for some reason.
When it gets open
in its new location
that connection creates a
new journal and lock file,
now you have two connections
that are using different
journals and locks,
it's not long before they wind
up corrupting the database.
These examples may seem
contrived or rare, but there are
over a billion devices out there
with potential for problems
with every possible operation
on every possible file,
something will happen to
someone using your app
and they'll be very upset when
they wind up losing their data.
Hard links are especially bad,
don't use hard links
with database files.
So, new this year the
SQLite library that comes
with the operating system takes
advantage of dispatch sources
and database connections
will report errors
after an illegal operation
affects their files.
On its own the system solve
data corruption problems
in most cases the damages
has already been done.
So to help you identify
and debug these issues we've
added another environment
variable that causes
connections to assert as soon
as they detect an illegal
operation has affected
their files.
If you're curious for more ways
that your database
can get corrupted,
SQLite has an instructional
manual
on their website called how
to corrupt a SQLite
database file [laughter].
Luckily these problems
are avoidable.
If you're using SQLite
directly, you want to make sure
that there's only one piece of
code that owns that database
and that code needs to go
into the exclusive file access
so files can't be
changed when they're open.
If you're using core
data, and you should,
there's API in the
persistent store coordinator
that is always safe to
use with SQLite databases,
whether they're open or not.
There's replacePersistentStore
which replaces one database
with the contents of another.
And there's also
destroyPersistentStore
which safely deletes
everything in the database
and leaves an empty
database behind.
Alright, that's it for what's
new in core data this year.
To recap, we have a new
feature called query generations
which gives you a stable view of
your data at a snapshot in time.
We use support connection
pooling
and a persistent
store coordinator now
which allows multiple
readers at the same time
as a single writer, allowing
you to keep snappy interfaces
at the same time that you're
doing a lot of data work.
Setting up core data
is a lot easier
and then using it is also
a lot easier with new API,
that works especially
well in Swift.
This is all supported by great
new integration with Xcode
and we also have new
features in SQLite
that should make debugging
common problems much easier.
For more information,
please check
out the developer website,
this was session 242.
If you want to know more,
there's what's new in Swift
as well as what's new in Cocoa.
Thanks for coming.
[ Applause ]