[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Hello, I'm Anna.
Welcome to the Thread Sanitizer
and Static Analysis talk.
Since our team works on
bug-finding tools, we are going
to tell you about new
ways of catching bugs.
I'm going to start with
giving a brief overview
of Address Sanitizer and
then dive much deeper
into Thread Sanitizer which is
a new feature we introducing
this year.
Later, Devin is going
to come up and tell you
about the new checks we've added
to the Clang Static Analyzer.
But let's start.
Sanitizers, [inaudible]
LEM tools
that combine compile
time instrumentation
and runtime monitoring
to find bugs at runtime.
They're similar to Valgrind.
However, their main advantage is
that they have low
runtime overhead.
They work with Swift
and Objective-C,
and they have tight
integration into the Xcode UI.
So last year we've
introduced Address Sanitizer
to macOS and iOS.
This tool finds memory
corruptions such as stack
and heap buffer overflows use
up the freeze, double freeze.
It's extremely effective
at finding memory issues.
So if you're not using
it already, I highly,
highly, highly recommend it.
This year we've extended
the tool
to provide full support
for Swift.
Which will be especially
exciting to those of you
who love to live
dangerously in Swift.
So what does it mean if you
are using unsafe pointer types?
Run your test with Address
Sanitizer turned on,
it will find some bugs for you.
Now, while Address
Sanitizer mainly focuses
on memory corruption issues,
there is another large source
of bugs that are
threading issues.
These are even harder
to reproduce and debug.
They're sensitive to timing.
They might occur only in
some certain circumstances
which means that
the appellations
that contain them will have
unpredictable behaviors.
So this year we introduce
support to another tool,
Thread Sanitizer which
will help you to both find
and better understand
your threading bugs.
TSan reports mainly
different kinds of bugs,
so let's take a look
at some of them.
It will tell you about use
of uninitialized mutexes.
This might not seem
like a big deal.
However, if you are
using a mutex
that is not appropriately
initialized that will lead
to very subtle bugs
in your applications
because you're not actually
getting any mutual exclusion
when you use such a mutex.
Another example are
thread leaks.
If your application
has a lot of threads
and if those threads
are leaked, you will,
and if there's memory leaks.
Another one unsafe
call in signal handlers
and unlocks from a wrong thread.
However, data races are by
far the most common problem
because they're so
easy to introduce.
They happen when multiple
threads access the same memory
location without using
proper synchronization.
So let's see how this tool works
by going into an Xcode demo.
So here I'm going to demo
this Thread Sanitizer
on an alpha version of
last year's WWDC app.
So here as you would expect,
it brings up a schedule
for the week.
However, notice this
interesting visual bug.
Even though all the session's
data has been downloaded,
the network activity
indicator keeps spinning.
Now, I know I use a global
variable to decide when to show
and hide this indicator so there
might be a threading problem.
Let's see if Thread
Sanitizer can help us find it.
In order to turn on Thread
Sanitizer, we go to edit scheme.
Choose diagnostics tab.
And click here on
enable Thread Sanitizer.
Now, here you can choose
to pause in the debugger
on every single issue and
debug that issue right there.
Or you could choose
to keep running,
collect all the threading issues
that Thread Sanitizer report,
and explore them later on.
The second workflow is new in
Xcode 8, and it's only supported
by Thread Sanitizer, so let's
take a look how that works.
When your launch application
under Thread Sanitizer,
Xcode is going to
rebuild your project
with extra compiler
instrumentation, and it's going
to launch it in a
special mode that tries
to find threading issues.
So here is our application
is up.
And Xcode tells us that Thread
Sanitizer detected two issues
by displaying this
purple indicator
in the activity viewer.
Clicking on this purple
indicator will take us
to the issue navigator.
And while previously
we only used it
to display build time issues
such as compiler warnings,
compiler errors,
Static Analyzer issues.
This year has been extended
to provide support
to runtime issues.
And this is where Thread
Sanitizer's issue found
its home.
So Thread Sanitizer
reported two problems.
Let's take a look at each one.
The first one is use
of uninitialized mutex.
Now, this problem occurred
as you were running
that application
sometime in the past.
Thread Sanitizer is going to
tell us about that exact moment
by providing a historical
stack trace.
Even though this is
not a live stack trace,
you can walk its frames as
if it was a live stack trace.
So let's take a look.
At some point we
called acquire lock.
That called pthread mutex lock,
and passed an invalid
mutex reference.
That was called from
reset feed status
which was called
from the initializer.
Now, as you can see here
we do initialize the mutex,
but we initialize
it after we use it.
It's a simple ordering bug.
So just reordering those
to statement should
take care of that.
Okay, let's go on to the second
problem which is a data race.
Also, here Thread Sanitizer
tells that there is a data race
on the variable called
activity count.
Now, that's the same global
variable that they use to decide
when to show and
hide that indicator.
Since this is a data race,
Thread Sanitizer will
tell us about two events.
The two race accesses.
A read and a write here.
So the read happened
on thread 11,
and the write happened
on thread 13.
Notice that neither of
those are a main thread,
and the stack traces
are the same which means
that they are probably
executing the same cord
from multiple threads
without using synchronization.
So let's take a look.
Okay, here we are updating
this activity account variable.
Now, I could have fixed
this race by adding a lock.
But notice that this
is just a symptom.
The next line here
updates the UI.
And we know that the UI
updates should happen
on the main thread.
So the proper fix here is
to dispatch both the counter
increment and the UI update
onto the main cue with
Grand Central Dispatch.
This will both take care
of the logical problem
in our application and
also take care of the race
because all the threads
will access
that count variable
from the same thread.
Now, I'm sure I sound
very convincing
and you all believe me
that I fixed the bugs.
However, the best way
of checking yourself is
to run the tool again
on your project.
So we should rerun
the application again
with Thread Sanitizer turned on.
And again it's going
to rebuild your project
with this extra checking and
launch it in the special mode.
Now, the application is up.
We see that the strange
visual UI bug is gone,
and Thread Sanitizer
doesn't report any issues.
So all is well.
Let's go back to slides.
[ Applause ]
So just to recap the demo, you
can enable Thread Sanitizer
in the Scheme Editor when you
go to the diagnostics tab just
like you did with
Address Sanitizer.
In addition to ASan's workflow
of stopping in the debugger
on the very first issue,
Thread Sanitizer it
supports an additional mode.
Where you could keep routing
as the issues that detected,
and then you could explore
them in the issue navigator.
They will stay there until you
launch an application again.
So let's now talk about what
Xcode does behind the scenes
to make this all work.
In order to use Thread
Sanitizer,
Xcode passes a special flag to
both Clang and Swift compilers
that instruct them to produce
an instrumented binary.
This binary links to a TSan
runtime library that is used
by the instrumentation to
both monitor the execution
of the program and detect
those threading issues.
So if you're building and
running Cocoa command line,
you can pass an option to
either of the compilers.
And Xcode will also
support Thread Sanitizer
by providing
enableThreadSanitizer option.
Now by default, TSan
will keep running
as the errors are detected.
But you can instruct it to
abort on the very first issue
by setting this TSan options
environment variables to halt
on error equals 1 when
you launch your process.
That will allow you to have the
same workflow as what you have
with Address Sanitizer.
So where can you use this tool?
Thread Sanitizer is
supported on macOS
and in the 64-bit simulators.
It is not supported
on the device.
So now you know how
to use this tool,
how to launch it,
how to find issues.
Let's talk about what, how you
can fix the bugs it reports.
And we'll focus mainly
on data races
because this is the biggest
category of bugs it reports.
So what is a data race?
Data race happens when multiple
threads access the same memory
location without using proper
synchronization and when
at least one of those
accesses is a write.
And the problem here that
you might not only end
up with stale data, but the
behavior here is unpredictable.
You might even end up
with a memory corruption.
So what are the reasons
for data races?
Well, it often indicates that
you have a logical problem
in the structure
of your program.
And only you will
know how to fix it.
On the other hand, it also means
that we are missing
some synchronization.
So let's talk about
that second scenario.
Here is an example of
a data race in Swift.
We have a global variable data.
We have a producer
that sets it for 42
and a consumer that prints it.
If those two pieces
of code are executed
by two different threads,
there will be a data race.
So how about this code?
We introduce another variable
called is data available.
And we set that flag after we
update the data in the producer,
and in the consumer we are going
to wait until the flag is set
and then if once it's
set, we print the data.
Well, this looks very logical.
It seems like it should work.
The problem here is what you see
is not what will get executed.
The instructions here can be
reordered by either the compiler
or the CPU, so you cannot
assume that the flag is set
after the data is updated.
The order of the instruction
is not guaranteed neither
in the producer nor
the consumer.
So what is the point
here of this slide?
I just want to demonstrate
that trying
to roll your own synchronization
methods is often not a
good idea.
What should we do instead?
We should use something
that's available already.
For example, Grand Central
Dispatch is a very good option.
You can dispatch
the recent accesses
onto the same serial
queue that will make sure
that they execute it
on the same thread,
and there will be no data race.
So now as you might recall
Thread Sanitizer works
for both Objective-C and Swift.
So let's use Objective-C
for our next example.
Here is lazy initialization
code.
And we are implementing
method called getSingleton.
That makes sure that we return
the same shared instance
to all of its callers.
Now, if this code is
executed by multiple threads
without proper synchronization,
there will be a data race
when both threads try to update
the shared instance variable.
Okay, so what about this code?
We tried to fix the
problem by allocating
and initializing
a local variable,
and then we are using atomic
compare and set operation
to make sure that
threads atomically update
that global variable.
So there will be no
data race on the right.
This might look like a step
in the right direction,
but this code still
has problems.
So let's take a look at them.
First, it's very difficult to
reason about memory management
when you are using atomics.
So, for example, here you
will have use-after-free
if you are using ARC.
And if you are using MRR, this
object will be leaked only
in case there is a race.
So that's not good.
That's not the only problem.
Another problem here is
that since the read
is unsynchronized,
there could still be a race
where one thread is trying
to read that shared variable
and another one is trying
to atomically set it.
So this is undefined
behavior, and that's not good.
What should you do instead?
I mean, if you know
the solution already,
use Grand Central Dispatch.
Dispatch wants performed
laziness socialization for you.
It's even simpler in Swift.
Both global variables and
class constants have dispatch
one semantics.
So you can choose either
of those two solutions,
whatever works best
for your code.
Okay, so just to summarize,
you should use the highest
level API that's suitable
to your needs.
And most people should be
using Grand Central Dispatch.
If that's not suitable, you
can use pthread APIs or NSLock,
for example, now, we do have a
new OS unfair lock that's new
on our platform this year,
and it replaces OSSpinLock.
And they also have
C++ and C11 Atomics.
They are supported
by Thread Sanitizer.
But as you've seen in
the previous example,
they're very difficult
to use correctly.
And besides the performance,
being here is either not
measurable or negligible.
So don't choose to use those
APIs if you did not measure
that they actually have
something on your application.
So for more information
about all of those APIs,
please attend Concurrent
Programming talk on Friday.
So now let's talk
about benign races.
What are those?
Some developers argue that
on some architectures,
for example x86, you do not
need to insert synchronization
between a read and a write
because the architecture
itself guarantees automaticity
of those operations
on pointer size data.
Now, it's important to
remember that any race,
even at a benign
race, is considered
to be undefined behavior
from C or C++ standard.
So not only will you be
surprised if that code
with benign races write, runs
on an architecture you have
not tested well on before.
But the compiler is free to
reorder those instructions
as if no other thread saw that.
So the bottom line
is that you might end
up with very subtle bugs.
So as our engineering lead
for Thread Sanitizer
[inaudible] "Fix all the bugs."
[ Applause ]
Now, to the most
exciting part of our talk.
As we all know, data races are
hard to reproduce since they're
so sensitive to timing.
So the most interesting thing
about Thread Sanitizer is
that it can detect races that
did not even manifest during
that particular program run.
Let's see how it does that.
When you compile your
program with Thread Sanitizer,
it instruments every memory
access, and it prefixes it
with a check, with a code.
But first, records the
information about that access.
And second checks if that
access participates in a race.
So let's take a closer look.
For every aligned 8 bytes
of application memory,
Thread Sanitizer
shared those state,
keeps track up to four accesses.
So suppose we have four threads.
Thread one writes to
that memory location.
Thread sanitizer updates
that, stores that information
to shadow thread to
reset memory location.
Again, we record that, and
we keep going on and on.
So now what happens if you
have more than four accesses?
Thread Sanitizer uses
an educated guess
onto what cell to evict next.
So here it evicts access
to that same thread
which lets it not
lose precision.
However, if we had access
from a fifth thread,
it would evict a random cell.
So bounding the number of
accesses like this means
that we might not catch
all races and all cases.
Okay. Now, let's talk about
how it detects data races.
Thread sanitizer uses
a well known technique
of vector clocks
for race detection.
So how does that work?
Thread local storage for
each thread keeps track
of threads own counter
and the counters
of all the other threads.
This counter is initialized
to zero,
and every time a
thread accesses memory,
its counter is incremented.
So, for example, here
suppose thread one access two
memory locations.
Thread two accessed
22 memory locations.
Thread three accesses
55 memory locations.
Now, this timestamps
are not comparable.
Each thread uses those
timestamps or counters
to order the accesses to
memory that it performs.
Okay. So let's go back and
bring back our memory location
and its shadow and see
how its threads interact
and how they update
the counters here.
We'll also add the
lock that threads used
to synchronize access
to that memory location.
Okay, thread one writes.
It's a well behaved thread.
It's going to acquire a lock.
It's going to update
its counter.
It's going to write to
that memory location.
Now, Thread Sanitizer sees that.
It's going to update the shadow.
Before updating the shadow,
it sees that there is nothing
in the shadow, stored in
the shadow which means
that that memory location
has not been accessed before.
So it just safe to go
ahead and write that down.
Now before releasing the lock,
thread one is going to update it
with its own timestamp,
and it releases the lock.
Now, it's time for
thread two to write.
Again, thread two is a
very well behaved thread.
It's going to acquire the lock.
Now, acquiring a lock like
this lets thread two see
that thread one has
implemented its counter.
Now, thread two implements
its own counter,
it writes to that
memory location.
Thread Sanitizer sees that it's
trying to update the shadow.
Now, here it sees that there
is something there it shadowed
before, so that means
that memory location has
been accessed already,
so it's going to
check for races.
By comparing the timestamps,
Thread Sanitizer sees
that thread two has synchronized
after thread one has
accessed the memory.
So there is no data race.
And we can just proceed
with the update.
Before releasing the lock,
thread two is going to update
with its own timestamp.
And it releases the lock.
Okay, now it's time for
thread three to write.
Thread three has been
waiting for a long time.
It's so excited to write
to that memory location.
Guess what, it forgets the lock.
It implements the counter,
writes to the memory location,
Thread Sanitizer is
there, it's watching.
It's trying to update the
shadow and check for races.
So here the Thread Sanitizer
sees that the old view
of thread three is too old.
The reads and writes stored
in the shadow happened
after thread three
last synchronized.
This allows Thread
Sanitizer to catch the bug.
[ Applause ]
So what's important to know
about this algorithm is
that the sensitivity of
timing that we associate
with data races does
not apply here.
TSan can detect races even if
they did not manifest during
that particular run
but could occur
if you run your application
again
or your users run
your application.
And this makes using Thread
Sanitizer much more effective
than debugging and trying to
reproduce those data races
in the [inaudible] without
the use of the tool.
Now, another thing
to remember here is
that Thread Sanitizer is a
runtime bug finding tool,
so it will only catch races
if you provided sufficient
coverage.
So please run all your tests
with Thread Sanitizer turned on.
And that was Thread
Sanitizer new in Xcode 8.
Use it. It will find bugs,
it will make your
applications better.
[ Applause ]
Now, off to Devin who will tell
you about the checks we've added
to the Clang Static Analyzer.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Anna.
Unlike the sanitizers, the
Static Analyzer can find bugs
without even running your code.
It does this by systematically
exploring all paths
through the program.
This makes it great
at catching hard
to reproduce edge-case bugs.
It's supported for
all of the languages
that Clang compiles to, so
C, Objective-C, and C++.
This year, we've added three now
checks to the Static Analyzer.
A check for missing
localizability,
a check for improper
instance cleanup
in your manual retained
release code,
and a check for nullability
violations.
Let me tell you about them.
A common bug in localized
apps is to forget
to localize a UI element.
This can be very
startling for your users.
They'll be using your app
in their own native language
when all of a sudden,
out of the blue a string
in your language
shows up in their UI.
This is not a good
user experience.
So let me give you a demo
of how the Static Analyzer
can catch this kind of bug.
Okay. So I'll demo
the Static Analyzer
on the same app that Anna used.
To run the analyzer, you can go
to Xcode's product menu
and choose analyze.
This will explore a large number
of paths through your program
and try to find a
bug along each one.
Just like Thread
Sanitizer, if address,
if the Static Analyzer
finds an issue,
it will display this
blue Static Analyzer icon
in Xcode's activity bar.
If you click on it it will
show you the issue navigator,
so it looks like we have
a localizability issue.
A nonlocalized string is flowing
to a user-facing property.
So we should localize it.
But looking at this method,
I don't see anything
immediately wrong.
So I'm going to click
on the diagnostic.
This shows me more information
about how this nonlocalized
string ended up flowing
to the user-facing property.
I can explore this path
with the path explorer bar
at the top of Xcode's editor.
Working my way backwards, I can
see that this method is called
from a TableView
data source method,
and then an intern it's passing
in this nonlocalized
constant string.
So let's localize it.
To do so, I'll use the NS
localized string macro.
This will load a
translated version
of the string at runtime.
Now, it's really important
when using this macro
to also include a comment
for your translator
to help them correctly
translate that string.
So I will say "This
is the button
that resets the session filter."
Okay. Let's run the
analyzer again
to make sure we fixed the issue.
Looks great.
So I'll switch back to slides.
[ Applause ]
To recap, you can run the
analyzer from the product menu,
and it will display any of
the issues that it finds
in the issue navigator.
As we saw, it's super
useful to click
on that diagnostic
to show the path.
This makes it easy to
understand the issue
and ultimately how to fix it.
So the analyzer can now
find missing localizability
as we saw.
But it will also warn us if
we've forgotten to provide
that comment to our translators.
Here I've provided a comment of
nil which is not helpful at all.
And so the analyzer will warn
about it you can
turn these checks on
and other Static Analyzer checks
in the Static Analyzer section
of your project's
build settings.
The check for missing
localizability will be turned
on automatically by Xcode if
your project has localizations
in more than one language.
The check for missing
comments is off by default,
but you should make
sure to turn it
on if you don't communicate
these comments
to your translator
in some other way.
For example, you might
already be doing this directly
in your strings file.
This year we've also
improved checking of dealloc
in your manual retained
release code.
It's really important under
manual retained release
to not release instance
variables that are synthesized
for assigned properties
in your dealloc.
If you do so, this can cause
an over-release when the owner
of that value also releases
it and can crash your program.
So the analyzer now
warns about this.
On the other hand, you must
release instance variables
that are synthesized for
retain or copy properties.
Because if you don't,
they will leak.
The analyzer warns
about this as well.
Yeah!
[ Applause ]
So this is an awesome check.
It found a bug in every single
manual retained release project
that we ran it on.
So try it out.
Of course, the best way to get
rid of retained release issue is
to update your project to
automated reference counting.
[ Applause ]
Fortunately, Xcode can help
you do this automatically.
If you go to the edit menu
and choose convert
to Objective-C ARC.
This will have the compiler
handle all of the messiness
of retained release for you.
Finally this year,
we've added a check
for nullability violations.
This builds on work from last
year where we annotated our STKs
to indicate whether methods or
properties take or return nil.
For example, Core Location's
timestamp property is non-null.
This is because every
measurement
of a location also has a
corresponding date and time.
In contrast, its floor
property is nullable.
That's because this
property will return nil
when the location is in
a venue that's not indoor
location enabled.
You should annotate your
own headers with nullability
because it enables a
new program and model
where you communicate
your expectations
about nullability
directly to your clients.
This is important
because violations
of those expectations can cause
crashes or unexpected behavior.
In fact, we thought it was
so important that we built it
into Swift where the optional
type requires you to check
for nil before using a value.
Now, it's important in
Objective-C as well,
and so we've added a check
for nullability violations
to the Static Analyzer.
And this check is
particularly useful for projects
that mix Swift and
Objective-C code.
And it finds two
kinds of issues.
There might be logical
problems in your code.
Maybe you're returning
nil when you shouldn't.
Or you might have an
incorrect annotation.
So let's take a look
at how to fix each
of these two kinds of issues.
A common mistake is to
initialize a local variable
with nil and then later
fill it in with a series
of non-exhaustive branches.
This method, for example,
returns a short description
of a location.
Either the name of a
city or the country
that contains that location.
But we fail to consider
an important case.
What if the location is
in international waters?
Then there will neither
be a city nor a country.
And so this method will
unexpectedly return nil.
And the analyzer will
tell us about it.
Fortunately.
This is awesome, too.
[ Applause ]
Fortunately, the
fix here is simple.
All you need to do is
initialize your local variable
with a nonnil default.
In this case, we'll use the
constant string Earth and,
of course, we'll make
sure to localize it.
On the other hand, it
could be that your code
in the implementation
is perfectly fine,
and it's the annotation
that's incorrect.
And we found that one way
that this commonly arises is
when you use the convenient
NS assume nonnull begin
and end macros.
These macros wrap a portion of
your header and say that inside
of the reins that they wrap,
that types will be
implicitly nonnull.
This can save you
a lot of typing,
but it also makes it
really easy to forget
to mark a property as nullable.
In this example, the
pressure property returns nil
when the device doesn't
have a barometer.
But the property is
implicitly nonnull.
Fortunately, the fix
here is simple as well.
We can simply explicitly
mark that property
as nullable inside
of that region.
And this will tell clients
that they shouldn't
expect pressure data
to always be available.
Now, you do need to
be careful about this.
That's because the nullability
of your API is a contract.
And so you shouldn't change it
just to make the analyzer happy.
Instead, you should carefully
consider the API that you want
to expose and use that.
If you do decide to change
your API, you'll also need
to carefully think about
backwards compatibility.
This is particularly
important in Swift
where nullability changes
how a type is imported.
You might also find
yourself in a situation
where you can change
neither the implementation
of your method nor
its annotation.
And in these cases, you can
suppress the analyzer diagnostic
with a cast.
One way that this commonly
arises is in methods
that defensively return nil
when a precondition is violated.
In this example, the
method returns nil
when an index is out of bounds.
If there's existing code
that relies on this behavior,
then you can't remove that check
and you can't replace
it within a cert.
Instead, the right thing
to do is tell the analyzer
that that's what you meant
by casting the return
value to nonnull.
So that's what's new in the
Static Analyzer and Xcode 8.
[ Applause ]
So let's wrap up.
Today we told you about
three great tools.
These tools find real bugs.
Address Sanitizer and Thread
Sanitizer find memory corruption
in threading issues at runtime.
And the Static Analyzer
can find bugs
without even running your code.
So please use these tools
on your own projects.
They will help you find your
bugs before your users find them
for you.
If you're interested
in more information,
you can go to your
session website.
And there's also
several related sessions
that we think you
might find helpful.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]