[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Welcome.
My name's Philippe Hausler, and
I work at Apple on Foundation,
and today we're going to
talk about Swift On Servers.
We'll go over why Server-Side
Swift is compelling,
how all the pieces fit together,
what you get out of box,
what you don't, some real-world
examples of Swift running
on the server, and, most
importantly, what you can do
to contribute to making
Swift On Servers awesome.
Modern application
development isn't just building
for one platform.
It's an ecosystem.
You'd be hard pressed
to find an application
that doesn't have some sort
of server-side component,
be it from analytics,
real-time communications,
or shared state being
stored in the Cloud,
servers are an integral
component
in making rich and
compelling apps.
Now building the
next great thing,
often there are contact
switches that have to be made.
You end up humming along,
writing your application,
and the next thing you
know you're writing
in a different language.
This can cause downtime and
repeated implementations,
and we all know how much we
dislike repeating ourselves
in code.
But Swift running on the
server has the potential not
to just provide a seamless
development experience
but also a richer and more
compelling user experience, too.
By sharing the right
parts of your code base,
time can be saved not
just for writing it
but also testing and QA.
But it's not just the language.
It's the API's.
It's often hard to disambiguate
the architecture of the API's
from the construction of
the language with constructs
like strings, arrays,
dictionaries, concurrency.
They often become a core set
of libraries expressing
that language.
And with that, it brings us
to the architecture of Swift,
not just on the server,
but how Swift fits together
on all platforms.
As in early design
consideration,
Swift wouldn't just be
a Darwin-only language.
It can by its very nature
run on many platforms,
and with the community's help,
that goal has just been started
to be realized with
platforms, support to platforms
like [inaudible] SD,
targets like Raspberry Pi,
and even things like
Windows and Android.
Some pretty exciting stuff.
On all of these, Swift relies
on the system libraries.
Building on top of that, you
have the standard library.
It provides some of those
fundamental basic building
blocks and data structures.
On Darwin, we have an
addendum called the overlay
that aids system frameworks
to interface better in Swift,
but since there is no foundation
or dispatch shipped with Linux,
a portable interface
was established to fill
in those fundamental pieces.
We started off with an outline
of what needed to be there
and a few initial
implementations,
and with the community, we have
added many of those basic items
that are needed for
any modern development.
So when you application
comes into the mix,
you can see that all
of the pieces just fit together
the same way on both platforms.
With Swift built in this
manner, as a developer,
you can pick the right pieces
out of your application to build
for the server and use
familiar constructs
that you're used to using.
Swift.org is the central place
for getting the most
recent version of Swift.
Signing up for the
mailing list, getting links
for the GitHub repositories or
continuous integration builds,
or a great place to
read the documentation
on the most recent
developments in Swift.
It is the place for
the Swift tool chain.
So what comes in this toolbox?
Out of the box, you get
support for building
on both Linux and Mac.
So you can develop on your Mac
and deploy to the Linux servers.
There are continuous
integration servers to ensure
that the changes that are made
to the language and API's happen
and continuously integrate
so that everything
works as expected.
You have the standard library.
That gives you those basic
building blocks, protocols,
structures, and types
that you would use
in building any Swift
application,
but you also get Foundation,
Dispatch, and XCTest as projects
within the, the Swift
tool chain.
These give you a cross
section of portable API's
that can keep your code
nearly the same as you build
across multiple platforms.
But you also get a suite of
tools for compiling, packaging,
and debugging Swift apps as well
as the Swift Rebel to complete,
try out some of those new
features, and you get all
of these things on
both platforms.
Now there are a few things
that are not included.
There was a design, a design
decision that was made
that some things just
didn't make sense
in a cross platform nature,
or that they were better,
better served to let developers
build their own solutions
since they're highly
specialized.
New platforms are not just code.
They are continuous
integration and verification,
and the champions reporting
to new platforms usually know
the best to implement those.
User interface is a very
platform-specific thing.
On iOS, you have UIKit.
On Mac, you have
AppKit, and even though
that they share a
lot of similarities,
there have to be
two different things
because they're solving
different problems.
For that matter, UI
can be web templates,
and sometimes the user in user
interface isn't a person, and,
instead, it's another
service connection
that is routing a
service protocol.
These are all clearly something
that are very, very specialized.
Now deploying your
applications to the server in
and of itself is a
specialized task.
This way you can pick
the right service
that fits your requirements,
your budget, your scale, and,
of course, your application.
This shouldn't have to be tied
to a specific track in Swift.
Running on the server, you
can have multiple applications
running with multiple
versions of Swift.
It's amazing to see the
enthusiasm to create an open
and sharing community,
and these are just a few
of the great things,
great opportunities
to enrich the Swift ecosystem.
There have already been some
great efforts put forth in all
of these areas and more,
and our fellow contributors
over at IBM have been making
some really pretty neat things.
We've gone over some
abstract overviews.
So let's dive a little
bit deeper.
So here to present some
real-world examples
of how they're, they are
getting involved in Swift
at IBM is John Ponzo
and Patrick Bohrer.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Philippe.
Hi. My name is John Ponzo.
I'm the Technical Leader for
Mobile Cloud Development at IBM,
and I'm thrilled to
be part of WWDC today.
We at IBM are very excited about
Swift community and being part
of the open source, and
we see great potential
for the language.
For those unfamiliar, let me
tell you a little bit about IBM
and our involvement with Swift.
Apple and IBM announced
our partnership focusing
on enterprise apps
and solutions in 2014.
And, subsequently, IBM became
one of the first, early adopters
of Swift when it was announced
here at WWDC just two years ago.
Since that time, we've created
over 100 enterprise
applications,
building those apps and
solutions entirely in Swift,
and we also have one of
the highest concentrations
of Swift developers at IBM
building these apps today.
Our experience building
these enterprise apps
and solutions consistently
points to the importance
of the backend, enabling
a great experience.
As developers, we know
how important it is
to have a backend, to enable
a great mobile experience.
We also know it's
important for us to quickly
and safely deploy the right
code to the right place,
and that's why we're so excited
to help bring Swift
to the server.
We appreciate the
wealth of activity
around Swift.org community,
ranging from the mailing list
to code contributions and
new open source projects
that are forming.
I'd like to highlight some of
the things that we're doing
at IBM to help the open
source community bring Swift
to the server.
First, I'll tell you about
community enablements
and tell you about
our Swift Sandbox
and Swift package catalog
services that we created
to help developers to
easily learn, discover,
and share Swift assets.
Next, we are motivated by
consistent developer experience
that links the client and
server, and towards that end,
we created the Kitura web
framework that's helping
to motivate and prioritize
our contributions
into the core libraries of
libdispatch and foundation.
And next, Cloud enablement
is an important part
of the development
process, and we are driven
to make it even easier and fun
to deploy Swift to the Cloud.
Through early support in the
IBM Cloud for Swift runtime
and the introduction of
Xcode companion applications
to help deploy that
code to the Cloud.
When Swift.org was
released in December,
one of the first things
that we wanted to do was
to help grow the
developer ecosystem.
We saw the value of the
language, and we wanted
to quickly introduce
it to other developers.
We created the Sandbox that
allowed, it allows developers
to easily run and
test code on Linux.
The Sandbox runs in a
browser, and with it,
you can easily start writing
your Swift code, save that code,
and see the execution
on the server.
Since we released the
Sandbox, we've added a number
of enhancements based on
community feedback and requests.
The Sandbox currently supports
a mobile UI, multiple UI themes,
autosaving of code,
and the ability
to select multiple
Swift runtimes.
Also, to help developers to
share questions and solutions
around Swift, we added code
snapshot support that's backed
by a persistent URL.
You could use this to share
code across mailing lists
and developer forums
like stackoverflow.com.
Thank you, and we've seen
over 1.5 million executions
in the Sandbox since we
launched in December,
and this is over
200 percent increase
since just this February.
And the Sandbox is
unlocking access
to Swift from other platforms.
In fact, we're seeing
steady growth and interest
in executions and
sessions coming
from other operating systems.
We're very pleased to see this,
and we'd like to see
Swift grow even more.
We're also seeing usage
from around the globe.
Developers using the Sandbox
to learn Swift and collaborate.
Our intent is to continue
to support the Sandbox
to help grow the community.
A vibrant package ecosystem
is critical to any language.
While the Swift Package Manager
specification is an early
technology, everything
that we're doing
on the server is based on
the creation and composition
of Swift-based packages.
Because of this, we found
the need to both discover
and to publish our own packages.
So we created the Swift package
catalog to help with this goal.
We continue to update
the package catalog
as the Swift Package Manager
specification evolves.
And today we have over 1,500
Swift Package Manager compliant
packages on the catalog,
and this is up 400
percent since February.
Next, when we start
thinking about servers,
a foundational requirement
for any server language
is the ability
to stand up web interfaces.
While web frameworks are
responsible for listening
on ports and routing code
to the appropriate logic,
we thought it was very
important for that logic to be
as consistent as possible
with the client-side
programming model.
And towards that end, we
created the Kitura framework.
We open source Kitura
in February.
It's a modular package
based web framework.
It leverages libdispatch and
Foundation for concurrency
and utility library support.
It's also driving IBM's
contributions to Swift.org.
We're using Kitura to build
our service-side applications,
and we're working with the
community and have a number
of committers outside of IBM
working on Kitura actively.
It's an important part
of what we're doing
to server enable Swift.
We're also optimizing our Cloud
for Swift-based workloads.
And I'm pleased to
announce our latest updates
to our Cloud foundry-based
build packs for Bluemix
that includes everything
that you need
to rapidly deploy your
Kitura-based applications
to the IBM Cloud.
These build packs include the
very latest Swift runtimes,
core libraries, and
dependent C libraries.
They're needed to deploy
Kitura to the Cloud.
But in addition, development
is, is key, and we're pleased
to announce IBM Cloud
tools for Swift,
a Mac companion application
to allow you
to easily build end-to-end
applications in Swift.
The tool helps you to quickly
and easily connect
your client-side apps
with service-side Swift
that runs in the IBM Cloud.
Just continue developing
your projects, your client
and service-side projects
in Xcode, and use this tool
to link those projects and
deploy your code to the server.
Now with that introduction, I'd
like to welcome my colleague,
Patrick Bohrer, up to the stage
who will show you
service-side Swift in action.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, John.
I'm Pat Bohrer.
I'm the Technical Lead for a lot
of the fun stuff we're
doing at IBM around Swift.
So we're thrilled to be
here at WWDC, and I'm going
to be leading what
I call the fun
and exciting part
of the session.
It's fun because I'm going to be
doing some live coding of Swift
on the server, and it's
exciting because both
of my demos are dependent on a
working network to the Cloud.
So wish me luck.
So as we talk about server-side
Swift, it can mean a lot
of things to a lot of
people, but for this audience
and for this session,
we're really talking
about web services.
So what are web services?
In a very simple
level, they're programs
that are off running
in a machine.
They're listening.
They're listening for
incoming requests.
They're responsible for
routing those requests
to some server-side logic,
and return and response.
And now as far as what's out
there, it could be a browser,
it could be another application.
Who knows?
It could be another service,
but as simple level,
that's what it is.
So to get started, that
sounds simple enough.
Let's go ahead and jump in,
and do a live demo of that.
OK. So as I mentioned,
oftentimes these web
services are running on Linux,
and we've heard about
Swift running on Linux.
So let's go ahead
and do our work
for this first demo
on Linus itself.
Let's go ahead and do that.
So here we have Linux
and running.
Make sure I'm not lying.
So let's go ahead and
create a directory
to do some, to play around.
So we'll very creatively
create a play directory.
You can see we have
nothing in here.
And now we'll use the
Swift Package Manager.
So every, as John mentioned,
everything we're doing
on server-side is
based on packages.
And so we're going to
use, this is a version
of the Swift Package Manager
that, for those watching later,
this syntax changes, but for the
version that we're using today,
it has an initialization step.
And so if we issue this command,
we can see that it's
created a few files.
So based on the structure
and the Package.Swift file,
the Swift Package Manager knows
how to build your application.
And so as you can see here,
we have a Package.Swift,
and it's created a Sources.main,
and that's all we really need
to build a Swift, a
simple Swift package.
So with that said, let's
go ahead and build this.
So we can issue Swift build,
and that was easy enough.
And so it's created a
.build/debug play executable.
So let's run that.
Ah. Hello world.
But we're building web services.
So let's get real.
OK. So here, this is what
our Swift Package Manager has
created for us.
So, again, it's best that
we have a package based
on our directory called Plays.
It's named our executed play,
and so that's why
that got named.
And we want to add one piece
here, and that's a dependency
on Kitura, and that's
all we need to specify.
So now we will go
to our main file.
Let's delete our
old hello world,
and let's add a bit
of code here.
So what this code does
is, again, old faithful.
We're pulling in Foundation.
We're also importing
Kitura and a couple
of Kitura support packages.
Here, we're specifying a
router, as I mentioned,
for incoming requests.
We have to route these
requests somewhere.
And we're going to
specify one route,
right here, that is /hello.
So if any, if any requests
come in, we'll run this code.
Simple enough.
We'll specify some
response headers,
and we'll send back a
string saying hello world.
Now down here we specify
what port we'll listen to,
and it's the 8095, and we
start listening on this port,
and we specify our
router as a delegate,
and then we start the server.
So it's pretty simple.
Let's go ahead and save that.
Now we're going to build
Kitura for the first time,
and so we've added
some pieces here.
As John mentioned,
we're leveraging
libdispatch and Foundation.
And so what it's doing
is it's pulling down,
the Swift Package Manager's
pulling down everything we need.
So we wrote the code
we care about,
and the Swift Package Manager
is pulling down Kitura,
it's pulling down our
networking, it's pulling
down some system support,
a logger, all the things
that you'd need in a, in a web
service, as well as the ability
to listen on sockets
and everything else.
And so each of these are
discrete packages that are
out on GitHub that
you can pull in.
And it's compiled and built.
So now let's go ahead and
run this executable again.
So we can see that it's now,
it just says it's
listing on port 8095.
So let's go ahead and
take a look at that.
We'll bring up local host 8095
because it's running locally
on our, on our Mac and Linux,
and you can see we
see a Kitura page.
So this basically, if we haven't
defined the default route,
it'll bring up this page
and specify other
ways to get started.
You can always override this,
but for us all we've
specified is hello.
[ Applause ]
And so, of course, the
first thing you have
to do is say hello world, right.
So the first step, but,
really, when you, when you think
about it, let's go back,
we'll do a bit more here.
Let's go back and
edit our main file.
We have a lot of
that we can use here.
So we have Foundation,
and we also have the
ability to generate JSON.
So add a little helper code here
to help us create a JSON string.
We'll also add a new
route called today.
So now, again, here's a new
route that if anything comes in,
saying /today, it'll do,
it'll leverage Foundation
to go get the current date.
We'll go ahead and create
an NSDateFormatter just
like we would on the client.
We'll use that DateFormatter
to create a date string,
a time string, and now we'll get
into the meat of our response,
and so here we'll create a
payload which, is a dictionary,
and now because in the Internet,
you know, it's all JSON.
So we specify message is hello
world, our date is our date,
our time is our time,
and, again,
we convert that into a string,
and that's what we
send back this time.
So let's take, see
what that works.
Let's go ahead and rebuild.
Much faster.
All the packages are here.
So that's good.
So, again, we'll run this again.
You can see we're
listing on 8095.
We'll reload and see we're still
responding hello world on hello,
and now let's look at today.
And there we go.
We have our JSON payload.
And now, again, every time
someone comes in here, it's,
it's executing that code,
and it's return and response.
So that's at a very simple
level how to get started.
OK. My wife said to take
off the glasses [inaudible].
So that was pretty fun, but now
let's make this a little bit
more interesting.
So as we go through, first
I'd like to introduce you
to a really interesting sample
that we've made available
to this community, and
it's called BluePic.
So BluePic is a sample
photosharing application
that's social.
It has a rich client interface,
a very beautiful interface
that we've built and provided
as part of this overall sample.
It also has a really
interesting backend.
That is, a Swift server backend,
pure Swift using Kitura,
running the IBM Cloud, and it's
also leveraging some interesting
services that I'll mentioned
like Watson or ObjectStore,
[inaudible] SQL databases,
all that good stuff.
And if you're, if you're
ready to dive deeper,
it even has some use of
IBM's brand-new event driven
programming model
called OpenWhisk
that also supports Swift.
So, again, this package
has a lot going on,
and it's available now
on GitHub for those
who want to get started.
So before we dive
into demo mode here,
I want to spend a little
bit of time talking
about the design pattern here.
So unlike before where we had a
web browser as the client-side,
we, of course, have
an iOS application.
It has our model
view controllers,
and you can see it also
has a networking interface
with requests and responses.
And it's talking to
our Swift middle tier,
which is similar to
what we just did.
It's just a little bit more
interesting, but, again,
accepting an incoming
route request,
routing those to some logic.
And then, finally, we
also have another piece
where we have some interesting
services, which we'll get
into in a bit, for holding all
of this data of our application.
So, again, just to dig
a little bit deeper.
So we have the client-side.
It's responsible.
It's very user specific view
driven for rendering some nice,
you know, interactions
with the, with the user
of the application, and
then we have the midtier.
The midtier is responding
to all of the clients
with the things they have,
but it's also doing some
really interesting things.
So as photos get submitted
into the midtier, it can,
it'll accept those photos.
It'll save them into
ObjectStore.
It'll create some
metadata around them,
but it'll do a few other things
that are pretty interesting.
So it will take those
photos, and submit it
over to Watson's Vision Insights
and extract just tags
about the photos.
Is it mountains and lakes and
all that good stuff, right.
So it's kind of adding
the special sauce
to our application
from the midtier.
It will also notice
where the photo is taken
and call Watson's
Weather Insights,
and pull down information.
What was the weather
like at that location?
So we're adding all of that.
So, again, instead of
making all these round trips
from the client-side, we're
making it from the server-side,
which is always on, always
available to go ahead
and do our service
composition there.
And the fact that this is
end-to-end Swift lets us deploy
the right code to
the right place.
So now here is BluePic
off running in the wild.
It's running on a device.
It's connecting into
the, you know, the Cloud.
The application server,
which is then talking
to all the different services
I mentioned, and that's great.
Now if something comes
up, and we have to debug
or develop this application
further, what do we do?
Right. Well, as iOS developers,
we know exactly what to do.
We pull down the source for
that application onto our Mac,
we load it all up into Xcode,
and we're good to go, right.
We can debug this.
We can debug the application.
You can even be calling
out into the Cloud
and making other requests.
So this is something we
know how to do today,
but now that this midtier
is also running Swift,
what do we do?
Right. You probably don't want
to be using VI like
I was on Linux.
But, again, we can
do the same thing.
We can pull down the source code
for our server-side code, again,
onto our Mac, load
it up in Xcode,
and now we can also just
do normal development
and debug locally on our Mac.
So we're debugging
and developing.
It's exciting.
So now our development world
got a whole lot bigger, right.
So we actually control
everything from end to end,
from the client to the midtier,
even to the services
that we touch.
So we, we really are
excited about this
because we think it brings
down that development cycle of,
you know, as you're doing things
on the client, and you want
to add some capabilities
on the backend,
it's all in the world
that you understand.
Towards that end, as
developers ourselves,
we thought we can go
a little bit further.
So just like we've done
with the package catalog
and the Swift Sandbox,
we created this application
called IBM Cloud Tools for Swift
as a Mac application to
help us manage this bigger
development world.
So we're really excited
about it.
This application actually
makes it possible for us
to manage this entire stack
end-to-end, and we, you know,
there's a lot of things
that we could do by hand,
but why not have some tools
to help you with this, right.
So we're excited to hear
your feedback on this just
like we have the
Sandbox and the catalog.
And we'll keep, you know,
we're just getting started
with this application, and,
again, as developers ourselves,
we know what we want it to do.
We'll keep adding things, and
we'll listen to this community
as well, but we're
really excited
about the possibilities here.
So our goal is really to
empower this community
to keep creating great
applications, and now powered
by Swift on the server.
So now with all of that
background, let's actually jump
in and do some demos again.
Going to show you just
how bright this future is
with Swift.
OK. So first off, this is the
IBM Cloud Tools for Swift.
If you want to get
started, it presents you
with an interface that's
a nice rich interface,
and for those wanting to
get started with BluePic,
it even has an ability to
create a BluePic project
to create just a Kitura project
or to create an empty project.
Now the part that's interesting
about this is not only is it
doing a clone of these projects
in bringing them down, it's also
under the covers provisioning
resources in the IBM Cloud
to deploy that project when
you're ready, and it will,
in fact, when you create these,
it will go ahead and deploy it
because it knows it's
a working example.
So, again, to get up
and running quickly,
it's a great way to start.
For us, we've already created
a BluePic application here,
and you can see we
have a demo BluePic.
Very cleverly named.
And here you can see we
have a client application,
a binding between a client
application and a Cloud runtime.
Both of these are in Swift.
Additionally, if we drill in,
here to the server-side code,
you can see it has a reference
to where the code is locally
on our, on my machine as well
as a binding to where it goes
into the Cloud as well as all of
the services that is provisioned
on behalf of this application.
So, again, I can manage all
of this locally on my Mac.
As well as I can go ahead and
launch with one click into Xcode
to look at my client-side.
So here's the BluePic
client-side application.
It is also created, let me zoom
in here a little bit, this file.
It's a Bluemix.plist.
Knowing this development
cycle, being able to run
against your Cloud
services locally
versus remotely it's very
easy to control this.
It'll either listen locally to
8090 or remotely out in Bluemix
and pass in the,
the credentials.
So, again, the thought here
is to make this really simple.
So here we'll go ahead and
run this, and so let's imagine
that somebody's filed a bug
report about the application.
So here's our application.
Again, it's got a
nice pretty interface.
We can scroll through.
We can see some pictures.
If we click on these pictures,
we can see there's
more information.
So the name is nature
of this one.
We can see who took it.
We can see, supposedly,
this was in Austin, Texas,
which we don't have mountains.
So. We can also see what
the weather was like,
and then thanks to
Watson Insight,
we see that there's
a few tags here.
So this is interesting.
If I click on tags, I
can see, OK, here's the,
we have one photo
that has a lake.
If I go back, let's
click on mountain,
and we can see there's a few
photos that have mountains, and,
again, all of this was done
by integration on the backend.
We didn't have users
having to tag this.
This was just auto extracted.
But we heard that
there's some complaint
about when I click cloudy skies.
So let's look at that.
So we click cloudy sky,
and we don't see anything.
So we know what's going on here,
and somehow the server's not
returning the right results.
So now let's switch.
We want to go ahead and figure
out, get to the bottom of this.
And so we'll go over
here, and we'll click
on our server-side code.
It will launch us and
show us the directory
where the server-side code is.
And if I go ahead and
load that into a terminal,
you can see a lot of the
same files as I mentioned,
we're doing Swift
3.0 on the server.
We have our Package.Swift.
We have our sources.
But, additionally,
I went through
and created an Xcode project
of the server-side code.
So let's go ahead and open that.
So here's the code, and, again,
here's a get handler for images.
So we know that when we
want images, our image feed,
we'll call this get
on/images on our server.
So if we look at this, we want
to go through and say, OK, well,
somehow when we pass in a tag,
we're not returning
the right results.
So let's set a break point
here, and we'll run our server.
And now we can see our server is
listening locally on port 8090.
Now let's switch back.
So here we're going to have our
client application say local is
yes so that it will actually
connect to our local server,
and let's rerun the simulator.
By the way, I'm getting
far too lucky
with all this network
connectivity.
So keep up whatever
you're doing.
OK. So let's just scroll down
to the file we had a little
problems with.
Let's click on here.
Let's click on cloudy skies.
Ah, great.
Here, we hit a break
point in the server.
[ Applause ]
So if we want to get a feel
for what's happening here,
and say we want to print tag.
And we can see, kind
of hard to see that.
We can see that the
string is coming
in as cloudy percent 20 sky.
That's no good.
We don't want that.
So let's take a look at that.
We also know that we
have Foundation here.
So what if we go ahead
and use Foundation
to clean this up a bit.
We'll remove the
percent in coding.
Oh, this is now a variable
instead of a [inaudible].
Let's go ahead and build this.
We'll run it again.
Rerun the server.
Let's go back to
our application.
Oh. There we go.
Timed out waiting for us.
Let's go back.
Let's click cloudy sky again,
and see if we fixed our problem.
Print to tag.
Ah, much better.
That's what we want.
So let's go ahead and turn off
this break point and continue.
And we see we got our result.
[ Applause ]
So now additionally, since
we've fixed this problem,
I can go back into
Cloud Tools for Swift,
and I can do a redeploy of
this state out to the server.
So it will start redeploying
that code right away.
So, again, it's that simple
to work with your client-side
and your server-side and
redeploy to the Cloud.
[ Applause ]
So I hope you really like these
demos, and I got to tell you,
I feel a tremendous amount of
relief that everything worked.
So on behalf of IBM,
John and I would just
like to thank everyone
for their time.
This is a really exciting
time to be a Swift developer,
and we invite you to join us and
the broader community to join in
and bring, to bring the
power of Swift to the server.
And for more information about
anything you've heard here,
about what we're,
what's cooking at IBM,
we have our
developer.IBM.com/Swift Dev
Center that you can go to.
And with that, thanks again.
I'll hand it back to Philippe.
[ Applause ]
>> So as you can see, IBM has
been doing some really awesome
things with Swift.
They've not just been
contributing some great code,
but they've also been
enriching the community
with their vast experience
building services
and streamlining
development flows.
Some of their work
has been integral
in making server-side
Swift possible.
But you, too, can help make
server-side Swift a reality,
and there are a number of things
that definitely you
can contribute with.
Portions of Swift
are not yet finished.
There's a lot of work to be
done, and there are a few things
that are not yet
to be implemented,
and unimplemented just means
an opportunity to contribute.
There are number of easy ways
that you can help pitch in.
The bug tracker even has a
category for issues tagged
as starter bugs, but code
isn't just implementations.
Designing new API's and
guidelines that will work well
in Swift are something
that are being worked
on on a daily basis
in the e-mail list.
Many of the discussions are
working on the language itself,
and coming from contributors
like you.
And, of course, your packages,
your applications are what going
to make Swift on
the server awesome.
And if you have any questions
as for resources or links
to what we've actually talked
here today, we've got a,
this session, we have
everything culminated together,
and there are number of other
really awesome related sessions
that I would highly
suggest watching.
The API design guidelines
can, goes over some
of our thoughts behind actually
the new naming within Swift 3,
and I would highly suggest
that you take a look
at the What's New in
Foundation for Swift.
All of the new value
types and features
that are being added are
going to be available
on the server as well.
Of course, performance is
not just necessarily your
local application.
We all, we need to
be able to make sure
that our servers are going
to be responsive and quick.
So performance, all across the
board, both on Linux and Mac is,
by far, something to look into,
and I would highly suggest
to take a look at the
new, new things in GCD
that are being released
with Swift 3.
And with that, thank
you very much.