[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Good morning.
How many of you have apps
in the App Store or working
on apps that play video?
That's quite a few of you.
Good. Whether for sports, news,
entertainment or education.
What's the most important
part of your video playback?
Is it the Play/Pause control?
The scrubbing?
Maybe the audio and
subtitle settings?
No. Of course not.
It's the video presentation.
So it's important when users
are using your application
and watching your video
that they focus entirely
on your video presentation.
And they aren't distracted
by trying to figure
out your user interface.
That's why it's important
that video playback be easy,
consistent and predictable
for viewers as they move
between apps on their Apple TV.
Video playback on Apple
TV appears simple,
but it's no easy task.
There are many different
tools for user interaction,
including the buttons and touch
surface of the Siri remote,
Siri voice commands, older Apple
TV remotes, the iOS remote app,
Bluetooth keyboards, game
controllers, and of course,
infrared universal remotes.
Wouldn't it be great if you
didn't have to deal with this?
I'm Dan Wright and
today I'll be talking
about how you can accomplish
all this easily with AVKit.
AVKit provides modern playback
with a consistent
user interface.
Let's take a quick look at some
of the features AVKit provides.
Here is AVKit playing a video
with a transport bar visible
showing the elapsed time,
the position in the video
and the time remaining.
Touching the surface of
the remote reveals hints.
And clicking on the edges
will skip forward or back.
Or by holding down
the touch surface,
viewers can fast
forward or rewind.
And when paused,
swiping side to side
on the remote will scrub quickly
through the entire video.
Swiping down reveals info panel,
which includes information
about the video and navigation
markers as well as access
to settings related to
audio and subtitles.
Finally, AVKit supports Siri
voice commands automatically.
And as I go back
to the beginning,
or "What did she say?"
to skip back 30 seconds
and replay
with captions turned
on temporarily.
AVKit uses the modern
media stack,
the same as on iOS and macOS.
AVKit provides the
user experience.
AVFoundation and CoreMedia
provide the core playback tools.
And UIKit or on macOS AppKit
provides interface elements.
Today we're going to
talk about three things.
First, we'll show you how easy
it is to get started with AVKit.
Second, we'll look at several
of the ways you can extend
the playback experience
with features unique to tvOS.
And third, we'll talk
about some best practices.
All right, let's get started.
Let's talk about
AVPlayerViewController.
AVPlayerViewController uses
an AVPlayer, AVPlayerItem
and AVAsset provided
by your application.
The AVAsset represents
the audio visual media.
AVPlayerItem represents the
presentation state of an asset.
The AVPlayer controls playback.
And AVPlayerViewController
sits on top, providing the UI.
Let's look at how you'll
provide your media to AVKit.
There are four steps.
First, create an
asset from the URL.
Second, create a
playerItem of the asset.
Third, create a player
with the playerItem.
And fourth, associate the player
with the playerViewController.
Now, you can simplify
all that to one line just
to create the player directly
from the URL and assign it
to the player property of
the playerViewController.
All right.
Next, let's see how you can
embed an inline player view.
First, you'll set up your
playerViewController.
Next you're going to set the
frame to the inline view.
We're setting the
frame directly here,
but you should use
constraints, of course.
And third, add the view from
the playerViewController
to your view.
And add the playerViewController
itself
as a child view controller
of your view controller.
Now, once you're ready
for interactive full-screen
presentation,
you can just present
the view controller
and it will automatically
animate
from the inline playback
to the full screen.
All right.
Let's talk about extending
the playback experience.
AVKit for tvOS was introduced
in tvOS 9, last fall,
with several enhancements.
Namely, the ability to add
non-interactive overlays.
Restrict playback interaction.
Provide informational metadata.
Navigation markers.
And identify interstitial
content.
With tvOS 10, we will introduce
a couple new enhancements:
The ability to modify
skipping behavior
and presents content proposals.
And now let's talk
about each of these.
Overlays are for logos and
other overlaid graphics.
The playback overlay view
lies above the video,
but below the controls.
Views may be static or animated.
But views will not
receive focus or events.
Let's move on to
restricting playback.
The requiresLinearPlayback
property
of the player view controller
limits user interaction
when set to Play and Pause.
Things like fast forward,
scrubbing, skipping,
chapter navigation and so on are
all forbidden when this is set.
Typically you'll set it to true
when you want to enforce viewing
of a particular section
of video,
for example ads or
a legal notice.
The external metadata
property supplements
or replaces information
embedded in your asset.
Things like title, description,
genre, media content and rating,
PG-13 or R, that sort of
thing, or poster artwork.
Let's go back to our screenshot
that showed the info
panel we saw earlier.
And I want to direct
your attention
to this top section right here.
This is where the informational
metadata is displayed on tvOS.
Now, in addition, it'll also be
displayed in the iOS remote app.
Here we see the artwork,
which in this case looks
like a still from the video.
We have the title.
We have the duration, which
comes directly from the asset,
a media content rating
and a description.
Now, let's look at
how we're going
to create external
metadata items.
And we will create a
couple of helper functions
to make it a little easier.
The first one called
metadataItem takes an identifier
and a value.
And it's going to
return an AVMetadataItem.
And so metadataItem has a
whole bunch of properties.
You really need to set three,
these three: The value,
the identifier, and
often overlooked,
the extended language tag.
Now, you see here I've set it
to the string und which is short
for undefined and it
acts like a wildcard.
So if you do not have a more
specific language translation
available, this is the version
that AVKit will display.
If you don't have any
translations, if everything,
for example, is in English
or everything's in French,
then just use und so that users,
regardless of their
language, will see something.
Now, artwork is a
little bit different.
The value of the artwork
metadataItem is an
image representation.
So it's raw data.
You can use PNG or JPEG.
You also need to set the data
type field to identify what kind
of data you're providing.
And once again, you
set the identifier
and the extended language tag.
Now we're going to
bring it all together.
We're going to create several
external metadata items.
We create an array.
Then we're going to use our
helper function to add a title,
a description and the poster
image to that array --
oh, and sorry, also the genre.
And then finally we're
going to assign that array
to the external metadata
property of the playerItem.
All right.
Back to our info panel.
Now we're going to look down
here at the bottom part.
This is the navigation section.
And this is displaying a
navigation marker group.
Navigation markers most
often are used for chapters.
But they allow for easy access
to different parts
of your video.
Navigation marker groups
are for chapters or events.
Examples of events would be
in a sports video you might have
game highlights, for example.
A navigation marker group
is defined by an object
of class
AVNavigationMarkersGroup.
And it contains an array
of navigation markers,
in this case chapters.
Every marker has a title.
And in most cases
an image as well,
usually a thumbnail
from the video.
But that's optional.
An event group itself also has a
title, a chapter group does not.
All right.
Another little helper function,
the create navigation marker.
This takes a title, a
description and a time range.
Now, the time range is the
time range of the thing
that you're navigating to.
However, the duration
is optional.
If you don't really care to set
it, you can just leave it zero.
Here again, we're
creating metadata items.
In this case, for a
title, description.
And then finally we're going to
create the timed metadata group
with our metadata
and the time range.
All right.
Now let's talk about
interstitials.
Here we see a video with several
interstitials as indicated
by the dots on the
transport bar.
The user is watching
an interstitial here.
And the time above the
transport bar is counting
down the time remaining.
The time below is the
elapsed time into the video.
Interstitial content is content
that is unrelated
to the main video.
So for example, advertisements,
legal notices,
other things like that.
An interstitial time range
identifies the portion
of an asset that contains
interstitial content.
And interstitial
time ranges collapse.
The dots on the transfer bar
are [inaudible] holes as we saw
in the previous slide.
And finally, during scrubbing,
interstitial content is hidden.
So the user just is navigating
through the entire main video
and they're not getting
distracted
by ads popping ups
as they're scrubbing.
Now here we have a diagram
comparing the timelines
of your asset on the top
and the transfer bar as seen
by the user on the bottom.
We have a nine minute asset
with a couple of interstitials,
both of which are going
to be collapsed into dots.
And you'll notice
that the duration
on the transfer bar has
been reduced by the length,
or rather the duration
of those interstitials.
Now let's look at creating and
declaring interstitial content.
First, on your server you should
stitch the interstitial content
directly into your HLS asset.
Then, in your client app,
you will declare the
interstitial time ranges.
And implement a few
delegate methods
to enforce playback policy.
Here's a short snippet
showing how
to declare the interstitial
time ranges.
For each interstitial create
an AVInterstititalTimeRange.
Then set the
interstitialTimeRanges property
of your player item
to this array.
In this case we're just
creating a single interstitial
time range.
Next, the delegate methods.
There are three important
ones I'm going to talk about.
The first is willPresent.
willPresent is called when one
of your interstitials
begins to play.
Typically, this is
where you're going
to change requiresLinearPlayback
to restrict navigation.
So for example, if this
is an advertisement,
you probably need, for
contractual reasons,
to require the user to watch
the entire interstitial once
they start.
You set it to true.
Then they can't skip out.
They could still pause,
head to the kitchen
or something and come back.
But they can't navigate,
they can't skip
over it once they're inside.
didPresent is called at the
end of your interstitial.
And usually you set
requiresLinearPlayback back
to False so that the users
can once again navigate.
And finally,
timeToSeekAfterUserNavigatedFrom
time to some target time.
So this is called when the
user navigates or indicates
that they want to navigate to
a different part of your video.
For example, they
skipped forward or back.
They scrub and hit Play again.
Or they use the navigation
markers to jump
to another part in your video.
The oldTime is the time
that they were playing
at just before they skipped.
The targetTime is the time
that they want to watch next.
The time returned
by this delegate is
where you want playback
to resume.
So by default, if you didn't
implement this method,
it would resume at
the target time.
AVKit would seek to the target
time and start playback there.
If you provide the start time
of an interstitial instead,
AVKit will automatically
redirect to that interstitial.
Now, if you do redirect
to an interstitial,
unlike in our very simple sample
here, you're going to want
to save the target time.
And when your interstitial
is complete,
seek back to the target time
so that the user can once
again resume at the time
that they wanted to watch.
Now let's turn to
skipping behavior.
Here we see the skipping
indicator.
And this is a new skipping
indicator in tvOS 10,
the skip by item indicator which
can replace the older indicator,
which is the skip forward
or back 10 seconds.
In tvOS 10 you can choose
between these two
skipping behaviors.
If your app is displaying
something like a movie
or a TV show, it's probably
most useful for users to be able
to navigate skip 10 seconds
back and forward at a time
to more easily find the scene
that they're looking for.
If you have a series
of short videos,
for example exercise videos,
it probably makes more sense
to let users easily skip to the
next video, the next exercise,
or the previous video,
previous exercise, then to move
around a little bit
within an exercise.
So, to accommodate that, you can
change the skipping behavior.
There are two skipping
behaviors defined today.
The default, which
is to skip plus
or minus 10 seconds,
and skip item.
And there are three properties
in the PlayerViewController
related to this:
The skipping behavior
and properties to enable
and disable the skip forward and
skip backward hint indicators.
So let's look at
skipping by item instead
of skipping a few seconds.
First thing we're going
to do is we're going
to set the three properties.
Select the new skipping
behavior.
In this case we're just going
to always enable skip
forward and skip back.
I'm being a little lazy.
And then we're going to
implement two delegate methods.
Skip to next item,
all we're going
to do is replace the current
item with the new video.
And skip to previous item.
Same thing, but going backwards.
Okay. Now for a demo
of all these features,
I'd like to welcome
Jonathan Long to the stage.
Jonathan.
[ Applause ]
>> Good morning.
My name is Jonathan Long.
I work with Dan on
AVKit for tvOS.
And today, we are going
to be demoing an app
called AVKit Player.
I have the project
open here in Xcode.
And this is the main
view controller.
It is the subclass
of UIViewController.
And we have a reference to
an AVPlayerViewController.
We obtain this reference in
the prepare for segue callback.
In addition, we also create
an AVAsset, an AVPlayerItem
and an AVPlayer, which we assign
to the PlayerViewController's
player property.
I'll go ahead and
build and run this
so we can see what
it looks like.
[ Music ]
So here's our
playerViewController
in full screen with all of the
standard user interactions.
If I swipe down to
reveal the info panel,
you can see that
there's not a whole lot
of interesting information here.
Most notably we are
missing the info tab.
So the first thing we're
going to do is we are going
to add some external metadata
and some navigation markers
so that info tab shows up.
Jumping back into Xcode, the
first thing that we're going
to do is we are going to
add some external metadata.
To do this we need to
create some AVMetadataItems,
add them to an array
and assign this array
to the
playerItemExternalMetadata
property.
I'll go ahead and add some
helper functions here.
These probably look
very familiar,
as they are the same ones
that Dan showed you
in slides earlier.
The first creates and
AVMetadataItem for artwork,
setting the data
type to be JPEG.
The second creates
an AVMetadataItem
for all other value types,
setting the extendedLanguageTag
to be undefined.
Now, I have one more
helper function here
that takes a dictionary
as its argument.
And it simply maps the key
value pairs of this dictionary
to create AVMetadataItems
and returns an array
of AVMetadataItems.
So now with these
helper functions,
we can set the
playerItem.externalMetadata
property to be our array
of AVMetadataItems.
Cool. So we created
AVMetadataItems,
added them to an array,
assigned that array
to the
playerItem.externalMetadata
property.
So now let's move on and
add some navigation markers.
I have some helper
functions here for that.
The first creates an
AVTimedMetadataGroup
with a title, a description
and a time range.
The second creates an
AVNavigationMarkersGroup
with a name and four
time metadata groups
that represent different
time ranges in our content.
So now with these functions,
I can set the
navigationMarkerGroups property
on the playerItem to be an array
of AVNavigationMarkerGroups.
We'll name this one
Additional Group.
Cool. So we created an
AVNavigationMarkersGroup
with some time metadata
groups with a name.
We added that to an array.
And then we assigned the array
to the navigationMarkerGroups
property on the playerItem.
So, let's build and run
and see what happened.
So here is our Player
View Controller again.
And I can swipe down
to see the Info tab.
And now we see in the
metadata space all the metadata
that we've specified as well
as the artwork for this title.
And if I select down
at the bottom,
one of the navigation
markers that we've added,
we can skip to that
point in the content.
So with just a little
bit of code it's easy
to add external metadata
and navigation markers
to provide a rich user
experience in your info panel.
Now I'll hand it back
over to Dan to talk
about new APIs in
AVKit for tvOS.
Dan.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Jonathan.
All right.
Content proposals.
Content proposals are about
suggesting what to watch next.
You may have seen Up
Next suggestions in some
of your favorite apps such
as Netflix, Hulu, HBO.
When you reach the end
of each episode of, say,
"The West Wing" you'll
see a suggestion pop
up to watch the next
episode and so on and so
on until it's 3:00
in the morning.
Many apps implemented their
own version of this for tvOS 9.
And then it was kind of tricky.
No more. With tvOS 10 AVKit
provides a standard way
to present your own
customized Up Next experience.
We call these Content Proposals.
Here is one example
[ Applause ]
Thank you.
Now, you have the entire
screen to work with.
So you're not limited
to anything here.
This is just an example.
In the lower right
we have some metadata
and some big buttons
that you can press.
Up here we have the
currently playing video.
And here is the thumbnail
representing the proposed video.
Now, a content proposal is
represented by an object
of class AVContentProposal.
This is basically
a model object.
Now, there are several
properties on here.
I'm not going to spend a
lot of time on all of them.
But I want to highlight
a few important ones.
The first is
contentTimeForTransition.
This is the time within
the currently playing video
that you want your proposal
to be presented to the user.
So, if you specify the
duration of your video or zero
as a shortcut, that means
that you want it to appear
at the very end of the video.
However, if you're presenting a
TV show or a movie or something
like that, you probably
have a bunch of end credits
that the user may not
want to sit through.
And you may want to present
your proposal at the beginning
of those end credits, in
which case you can set this
property accordingly.
Next automaticAcceptanceInterval
allows you to specify a timeout
for your presentation.
You can say, for
example, 30 seconds.
Which means that if the user
does absolutely nothing,
they take no action
for 30 seconds,
then the proposal will
be automatically accepted
and advanced.
If you don't set this, then your
proposal will just stay onscreen
until the user takes
some sort of action.
Title and preview image
would be the bare minimum bit
of information that you
should provide to a user.
You can, of course, provide
as much additional information
as you like: Description,
maybe a little widget
to set a user rating,
maybe additional suggestions
for alternate videos.
And finally, the way you
specify your content proposal is
to set the next contentProposal
property
on the current playerItem.
So let's look at creating
the content proposal.
Well, this is pretty easy.
We just create an instance
of AVContentProposal.
We're going to specify
a time of zero
for our
contentTimeForTransition.
This means we want it to
show up at the very end.
This is a nice shortcut if you
don't have the duration yet.
For example, if your
playerItem hasn't loaded.
And we're going to set the
title and a preview image.
In this case, our proposal
is for Episode 2 of Season 9
of a fictional TV show
called "Happy Hijinks."
In this case we're going set
one of the optional properties
of the content proposal, a URL.
And we're going to set it
to the URL for this episode,
for our own use later.
Now we assign the
proposal to the playerItem,
which should show the proposal.
Naturally, this is
the playerItem
for Season 9, Episode 1.
And, once again, we've got three
interesting delegate methods.
shouldPresent is called
immediately before your proposal
is to be presented to the user.
Now, you could take this
opportunity to return False
and prevent the proposal
from being presented.
But you can also use it as a
last minute opportunity to set
up to prepare for
your presentation.
And we'll show an example
of that in just a minute.
didAccept is called when the
user accepts your proposal.
That means they want to watch
the video that you've suggested.
It will also be called
if the timeout occurs.
And didReject is called
if the user has indicated
that they want out
of your proposal.
They want out of the video.
They want to get
back to your menu.
Now finally, you will
implement your presentation
by creating a custom subclass of
AVContentProposalViewController.
There are a few interesting
things in the subclass.
Let's look at two,
preferredPlayerViewFrame
is the frame onscreen
where you want the video to
appear during your presentation.
Now, the base class
simply returns the frame
of the entire screen, in which
case the video will continue
to fill the screen.
And your presentation controls
will be overlaid on top.
However, you can specify
a smaller rectangle,
maybe off to the side in
a corner or something,
to give yourself lots of space,
the rest of the screen to work
with for your controls.
And dismissContentProposal
is how content proposals
are dismissed.
You can specify one
of three actions:
Accept, Reject and Defer.
Defer means the user simply
wants to hide your presentation,
get back to watching the
end credits so they can,
I don't know, maybe they
want to spot their name
in the end credits if
they worked on the video.
And then as the name implies,
Defer, it will reappear
at the end of the video.
Now let's look at responding to
those delegate notifications.
shouldPresent.
In this case, we're going
to create an instance
of our custom
contentProposalViewController
subclass and assign it
to the
contentProposalViewController
property
of the playerViewController
and return true.
This lets us set that up
at the very last minute
when we know we're going
to actually need it
and not allocate
a bunch of memory
that the user may never get to.
didAccept.
Here all we're going
to do is we're going
to replace the current
playerItem
with a proposed content
playerItem.
Pretty straightforward.
We've seen this code
a few times already.
You'll notice here I'm making
use of the URL property
of the proposal that I set when
I created the contentProposal.
Now, if this is literally
all you're going to do here,
you don't need to
implement this.
Because AVKit, if you provide
a URL on your proposal,
AVKit will automatically do this
if you don't implement
the delegate method.
All right, and now for a
demo with content proposals.
Jonathan.
[ Applause ]
>> Hello, again.
All right.
So, let's continue with
AVKitPlayer and add an
Up Next experience
by subclassing
AVContentProposalViewController.
So the first thing we
need to do is we need
to create a custom subclass of
AVContentProposalViewController.
I have one right here
that I will go ahead
and add to our project.
So, this is our
UpNextContentViewController.
It is a subclass of
AVContentProposalViewController.
And we have some
UI properties here
such as a UIImageView,
a UILabel and others.
We override the
preferredPlayerViewFrame
to return the CGRect that we
want our playerViewController's
view to animate to when the
contentProposal is presented.
Now, the rest
of the viewController
simply handles the layout
of its view and subviews.
So we'll jump back into
our main viewController.
So there's two more
things that we need to do.
First, we need to create an
instance of AVContentProposal
and assign it
to the playerItem's next
content proposal property.
So, here we are creating an
instance of AVContentProposal.
We have a transition time,
a title and a preview image.
We're also setting the
automaticAcceptanceInterval
to be 15 seconds.
In addition, we set the
URL and the metadata
on this content proposal that
corresponds to the next item
that will be played if the user
chooses to accept this proposal.
Finally, we set the
contentProposal we just created
as the next contentProposal
property on our AVPlayerItem.
So the next thing we need to
do, and the last thing we need
to do, is implement two
playerVIewController
delegate methods.
You can see here that we set the
playerViewController delegate
to Self.
And the two methods that we need
to implement are
shouldPresentProposal
and didAccept.
So in shouldPresentProposal
we create an instance
of our custom subclass of
AVContentProposalViewController
and we assign that as the
playerViewController's
contentProposalViewController.
In addition we return
true to indicate
that the contentProposal
should be presented.
And finally, in didAccept,
we need to handle
transitioning our player
to the next playerItem.
So, to do this, we get the
URL from the contentProposal.
We create an AVPlayerItem
from that URL.
And then we simply replace the
current item on our playerItem.
And we're done.
So let's build and run
and see what happens.
So I'll go ahead and skip closer
to the end of the content.
[ Music ]
And here is our contentProposal.
As you can see, the metadata
that we specified is here.
The preview image as
well as the title.
And if I select Play
Next, we would transition
to our next playerItem.
So I think if you
have implemented this
on tvOS 9 you'll be very happy
with this API and you will find
that it's much easier to use.
I'd like to invite
Dan back up to talk
about some best practices
of the AVKit.
[ Applause ]
>> Okay. Best practices.
I'm going to talk
about a few things.
Things to do and
things to avoid doing.
First, some things that
we recommend that you do.
Once again, present or present
view controler will handle
zooming automatically
from an inline view.
So there's no reason to
implement your own animation.
Second, remember Playback
is only interactive
when full screen.
Third, use the new
content proposal API.
Some of you wrote it
the hard way before.
And we encourage you to switch
over to doing it the new way.
I think you'll find your
code is a lot simpler.
It's easy to understand
the flow.
And you may avoid some
bugs and other things
that you may have
had trying to get it
to work just perfectly before.
And observe the error property
of the player in playerItem.
This is how you find
out about errors
that occur during playback.
And I'm going to talk about one
particular error in a minute
that you should handle.
But you should watch for
any errors that occur
and respond appropriately
to the user.
All right.
Now a few things to avoid.
Avoid toggling
showsPlaybackControls.
This property is not
for temporarily showing
or hiding the controls.
This is for indicating
your permanent intent.
So when you set this to false,
you're saying we don't want
the playback controls at all.
So if you toggle
this back and forth,
what you're doing is
you're telling AVKit
to destroy all the
controls and recreate them.
Destroy them.
Recreate them.
And it's not very
efficient, as you can imagine.
Second, some people hate this,
but avoid adding supplemental
gestures to playback
because it's going
to confuse users.
People will not discover them.
And by the same token, do not
overload the Select button
or touch service gestures.
Not only will that
confuse users,
but you'll likely
break in the future.
Now, some more general tips.
Replace your asset if
you see this error:
AVErrorMediaServicesWereReset.
If you don't respond to this
and the media services
are reset during playback,
video playback will fail.
And the user won't be able
to do anything except,
hopefully, get out.
So what they'll have
to do is get out,
go back to your menu
and go back in.
If you catch this error
and automatically replace
your asset, your player item
and your player, basically
your AV foundation objects,
then you can more
seamlessly handle this case.
And the user will barely even
know that anything happened.
Now, some other sessions
with best practices
for playback include this year,
Advances in AVFoundation
Playback.
It was earlier this week.
You can catch the
video in the WWDC app.
And two years ago we had
an excellent session,
Mastering Modern Media
Playback, which includes tips
for both AVKit and
AVFoundation and getting them
to work well together.
So in summary, AVKit provides
standard playback controls
and behaviors, support for
remotes, game controllers
and Siri, full access to the
media stack, powerful new APIs
and it's easy to get started.
Be sure to check out the sample
code for more in-depth examples.
And we're excited
to see your app.
So, for more information,
go to the URL on the screen.
We'll have links to the sample
code and other resources.
And check out some of
the related sessions.
We also have on here the HTTP
Live Streaming session also
earlier this week.
And a pair of sessions
on using TVMLKit,
which is an alternative approach
to using AVKit directly.
So, thank you.
[ Applause ]