[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Welcome.
This is Part 2 of our
What's New in Metal session.
My name is Charles Brissart,
and I'm a GPU Software Engineer,
and together with my colleague,
Dan Omachi and Ana Tikhonova,
I will be telling you about
some of our new features.
But first, let's take a look
at the other Metal
session at the WWDC.
The first two sessions I call
Adopting Metal uncovered some
of the basic concepts
of Metal as well
as some more advanced
considerations.
The What's New in Metal session
covered our new features.
Finally, the Advanced Shadow
Optimization session will tell
you how to get the best
performance out of your shaders.
So this morning you were
told about tessellation,
resource heaps, memoryless
render targets as well
as some improvement
for GPU tools.
This afternoon we'll tell you
about function specialization,
function resource read-writes,
wide color, texture assets,
as well as some addition to
the Metal Performance Shaders.
So let's get started with
function specialization.
It is a common pattern
in a rendering engine
to define a few complex
master functions
and then use those master
functions to generator minimum
of specialized simple functions.
The idea is that the
master function allow you
to avoid duplicating card while
the specialized function are
simpler on those as a result
of better performance.
So let's take an example.
If we are trying to write a
material function you could
write a master function
that implements every aspect
of any material that
you might need.
But then, if you are trying
to implement a shiny --
a simple shiny material,
you would probably
not need reflection,
but you will need a
specular highlight.
If you implement a
reflected material
on the other hand you will
need to add reflection
on also the specular highlights.
Our transition material will
need subsurface scattering,
but probably no reflection
or may be no specular
highlights either, and so on.
You get the idea.
So this is typically implemented
using preprocessor macros.
The master function is
compiled with a set of values
for the macro to create
a specialized function.
This can be done at runtime,
but this is expensive.
You can also try to
precompile every single variant
of the precompiled function, but
-- and then store them in Metal,
but this requires
a lot of storage
because you can have
many, many variants,
or maybe you don't know
which one you will need.
Another approach is to
use runtime constants.
Runtime constants avoid the need
to recompile your functions.
However, you need to
evaluate the values
of the constant at runtime.
That will impact the
performance of your shaders.
So we are proposing a new way
to create specialized
functions using what we call
function constants.
So function constants
are constants
that are defined directly in
the Metal shading language
and can be compiled into IR
and stored in the Metal lib.
Then at runtime you can provide
the value of the constant
to create a specialized
function.
The advantage of
this approach is
that you can compile the
master function offline
and store it in the Metal lib.
The storage requirement is small
because you only store
the master functions.
And since we run a
quick optimization pass
when we create the
specialized function,
you still get the
best performance.
So let's look at an example.
This is what a master
function could look
like using a preprocessor macro.
Of course, this is
a simple example.
A real one would be
much more complex.
As you can see, different parts
of the code surrounded by what
if statements so that
you can eliminate
that section of the code.
Here is what it would look
like with function constant.
As you can see at the top,
we are defining a number
of constants, and then
we use them in the code.
To define the constants, you use
the constant keyword followed
by the type, in this case
Boolean, and finally the name
of the constant and the
function constant attribute.
The function constant attribute
specifies that the value
of the constant is not going
to be provided at compile time
but will be provided at runtime
when we create the
specialized function.
You should also note that
we are passing an index.
That index can be used
in addition to the name
to identify the constant when we
create the specialized function
at runtime.
You can then use the
constant anywhere in your code
like your normal constant.
Here we have a simple if
statement that is used
to conditionalize
part of the code.
So once you've created your
master function and compiled it
and stored it in a Metal lib,
you need to at runtime
create specialized functions.
So you need to provide the
values of the constant.
To do that, we use an MTL
function constant values object
that will solve the values
of multiple constants.
Once we created the object,
we can then set the values
of a constant either by
name, by index, or by name.
Once we have created an object,
we can then create the
specialized function
by simply coding the
new function with names
and constant values on the
library, providing the name
of the master function as well
as the values we just filled.
This will return a regular MTL
function that can then be used
to create compute pipeline
or render pipeline depending
on the type of the function.
So to better understand
how this works,
let's look at the
compilation pipeline.
So at build time, you use the
source of your master function
and compile it and
store into a Metal lib.
At runtime you load
the Metal lib
and create a new function using
the MTL function constant values
to specialize the function.
At this point, we
run some optimization
to eliminate any code
that's not used anymore,
and then we have an interior
function that we can use
to create a render pipeline
or a compute pipeline.
You can declare constants
of any scalar or vector type
that is [inaudible]
in Metal , so float,
half, int, uint, and so on.
Here we are defining
half4 color.
You can also create intermediate
constants using the value
of function constants.
Here we're defining
a Boolean constant
that has the opposite value
of a function constant a.
Here we are calculating a
value based on the value
of the value function constant.
We can also have
optional constants.
Optional constants are constants
for which you don't need
to always provide the value when
you specialize the function.
This is exactly the same
thing as using a what ifdef
in your code when using
preprocessor macros.
To do this, you use the if
function constant defined built
in that will return true if
the value has been provided
and false if otherwise.
You can also use
function constant to add
or eliminate arguments
from function.
This is useful to avoid, to
making sure you don't have
to bind a buffer or texture
if you know it's not
going to be used.
It's also useful to replace
the type of an argument,
and we'll talk about --
we'll talk more about this
in the next couple of slides.
So here we have an example.
This is a vertex function that
can implement skinning depending
of the value of the
doSkinning constant.
The first argument of the
function is the matrices buffer
that will exist depending
on whether the doSkinning
constant is true or false.
We use the function
constant attribute to qualify
that argument as being optional.
In the code, you still need to
use the same function constant
to protect the code
that's using that argument.
So here we use doSkinning
in the if statement,
and then we can use the
matrices safely in our code.
You can as well use function
constant to eliminate arguments
from the stage in struct.
Here, we have two
color arguments.
The first color argument
as type float4 on these use
for attributes, that
is attribute 1.
The second lowp color is a
lower precision color half4
but is overriding the
same attribute index.
So you can have either
one or the other.
These are used to
specifically change the type
of the color attributes
in your code.
There are some limitations with
function constants, namely,
you cannot really change the
layout of a struct in memory,
and that can be a problem
because you might want
to have different constants for
different shaders and so on.
But you can work around that
but adding multiple arguments
with different types.
So in this example, we
have two buffer arguments
that are using buffer index 1.
They are controlled
by function constants,
use ConstantA and ConstantB.
So these are used to
select one or the other.
Note that we have -- we use
an intermediate constant
that is the opposite
of the first constant
to make sure only one
of the arguments will
exist at a given time.
So in summary, you can
use function constant
to create specialized
function at runtime.
It avoids front end compilation,
and because we only use --
and it only uses fast
optimization phase
to eliminate unused code.
The storage is compact
because you only need
to store the master
function in your library.
You don't have to
ship your source.
It can only ship the IR.
And finally, the unused
code is eliminated,
which gives you the
best performance.
So let's now talk about
function resource read-writes.
So we're introducing
two new features,
function buffered read-writes
and function texture
read-writes.
Function buffered read-writes
is the ability to read and write
to a buffer from any function
type and also the ability
to use atomic operations
on those buffers
from any function type.
As you guessed, function texture
read-writes is the ability
to read and write to texture
from any function type.
Function buffer read-writes
is available on iOS
with a 9 processor and macOS.
Function texture read-writes
is available on macOS.
So let's talk about function
buffered read-writes.
So what's new here?
What's new is the
ability to write to buffer
from fragment function as well
as using an atomic operation
in the text and fragment
function.
These can be used to
implement such things
as order-independent
transparency, building lists
of lights that affect
the given tile,
or simply to debug your shaders.
So let's look at
the simple example.
Let's say we want to
write the position
of the visible fragments
we are rendering.
It could look like this.
So we have a fragment function
to which we pass
an output buffer.
The output buffer is
where we are going
to store the position
of the fragments.
Then we have a counter, so
another buffer that we start
after [inaudible] that we
use to find the position
into the buffer,
the first buffer,
to which we want to write.
We can then use an atomic
preparation to count the number
of fragments with that
has been already written
to get an index in the buffer.
And then we can write into
the buffer the position
of the fragments.
So this looks pretty good,
but there is a small problem.
The depth and stencil
test when you're writing
to buffer is actually
always exhibited
after the fragment shader.
So this is a problem
because we are going
to still perform the
rights to the buffer,
which is not what we want.
We only want the
visible fragments.
It's also something to be aware
of because it will
impact your performance.
That means we don't have any
early Z optimization here,
so we are going to
exhibit fragment shader
when we probably
wouldn't want to.
Fortunately we have a new
function qualifier early
fragment test that can be
used to force the depth
and stencil test to appear
before the fragment shader.
As a result, if the depth test
fail, we will skip the execution
of the fragment shader and
thus not write to the buffer.
So this is what we need here,
to reach the final function
with the early fragment test
attribute which otherwise
to only execute the function
when the fragments are visible.
Now let's talk about
function texture read-writes.
So what's new is the ability to
write to texture from the vertex
and fragment functions as well
as the ability to read and write
to a texture from
a single function.
This can be used, for
instance, to save memory
when implementing post
processing effects
by using the same texture
on both input and output.
So writing to texture
is fairly simple.
You just define your texture
with the access qualifier write,
and then you can
write to your texture.
Read-write texture, a texture
to which you can both --
that you can both read
and write in your shader.
Only a limited number of formats
is reported for those textures.
To use the read-write texture
you will use the access
qualifier of read-write, and
then you can read to the texture
and write to it in your shader.
However, you have to be careful
when you write to the texture
if you want to read the results,
if you want to read the same
pixel again in your shader.
In this case, you need
to use a texture fence.
The texture fence will ensure
that the writes have
been committed to memory
so that you can read
the proper value.
Here, we write to a given pixel,
and then we use a texture fence
to make sure we can
read that value again
and then we can finally
read the value.
We should also be
careful with texture fence
because they only apply
on a single SIMD thread,
which means that if you have
two threads that are writing
to a texture and the
second thread is trying
to read the value that was
written by the first thread,
even after a texture
fence, this will not work.
What will work is if each thread
is reading the pixel values
that it was writing
to but not the ones
that are written
by other threads.
So one note about reading,
we talked a lot about writing
to buffers and textures.
With vertex and fragment
functions,
you have to be careful.
In this example, fragment
function is trying to write --
is writing to a buffer
and a vertex function is
trying to read the results.
However, this is
not going to work
because of having the
same RenderCommandEncoder.
To fix this, we need to use
two RenderCommandEncoder.
The fragment function
writes to the buffer
in the first
RenderCommandEncoder while the
texture -- the vertex function
in the second
RenderCommandEncoder can finally
read the result and
get proper results.
You should note that
with compute shader,
this is not necessary.
It can be done the same
compute CommandEncoder.
So in summary, we
introduced two new features,
function buffer read-writes and
function texture read-writes.
You can use early fragment
tests to make sure the depth
and stencil test is done
because the execution
of the fragment shader.
You should use a texture fence
if you are trying to read data
from a read-write texture
that you have been writing to.
And finally, when using vertex
and fragment shader to write
to buffers, you need
to make sure
to use a different
RenderCommandEncoder
when you want to
read the results.
So with this, I will hand the
stage to Dan Omachi to talk
to you about wide color.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Charles.
Thank you.
As Charles mentioned,
my name is Dan Omachi.
I work as an engineer in Apple's
GPU Software Frameworks Team
and I'd like to start
off talking to you
about color management,
which isn't a topic
that all developers are
actually familiar with.
So if you are an
artist at either the --
either a texture artist
creating assets for a game
or a photographer editing
photos for distribution,
you would have a particular
color scheme in mind,
and you'd choose
colors pretty carefully.
And you'd want consistency
regardless of the display
on which your content is viewed.
Now it's our responsibility
as developers
and software engineers to
guarantee that consistency.
If you're using a high level
framework like SceneKit,
SpriteKit, or Core Graphics,
much of this work is done
for you, and you
as app developers don't
need to think about it.
Metal, however, is a
much lower level API.
This offers increased
performance and some flexibility
but also places some of this
responsibility in your hands.
So why now?
You've been able to
use different displays
with different color spaces
with Apple devices
for many years now.
Well, late last year, Apple
introduced a couple of iMacs
with a display capable
of rendering colors
in the P3 color space.
And in April, we introduced
the 9.7-inch iPad Pro,
which also has a P3 display.
So what is the P3 color space?
Well, this is a chromaticity
diagram,
and conceptually this
represents all of the colors
in the visual spectrum, in
other words, all the colors
that the normal human
eye can see.
Of that, within this
triangle are colors
that a standard sRGB
display can represent.
The P3 display is able
to represent colors
of a much broader variety.
So here's how it works on macOS.
We want you to be able to
render in any color space
and as I mentioned, high level
frameworks take care of this,
this job of color
management for you
by performing an operation
called color matching
where your color and one
color space is matched to that
of the display color space
so that the same intensity
on the display regardless
of the color space
that you're working
in is displayed.
Now, Metal views by default
are not color managed.
This color match
operation is skipped,
and this generally offers
increased performance.
So by default, you're
ignoring the color profile
of the display, and therefore,
the display will interpret
colors in its own color space.
Now, this means that sRGB
colors will be interpreted
as P3 colors, and rendering will
be inconsistent between the two.
So if this is your application
with an sRGB drawable
and this is the display, well,
when you call present drawable,
these colors become
much saturated.
So why does this happen?
Well, let's go back to
our chromaticity diagram.
This is the most green
color that you can represent
in the sRGB color space,
and in a fragment shader,
you'd represent this as
0.0 in the red channel,
1.0 in the green channel
and 0.0 in the blue channel.
Well, the P3 Display
just takes that raw value
and interprets it,
and it basically thinks
that it's a P3 color.
So you're getting the most
green color of a P3 Display,
which happens to be a
different green color.
Now, for content creation
apps, it's pretty critical
that you get this right because
artists have used careful
consideration to
render their colors.
For games, the effect is more
subtle, but if your designers
and artists are looking for this
dark and gritty theme, well,
they're going to be disappointed
when it looks much more cheerful
and happy when you
plug in a P3 Display.
Also, this problem can get worse
as the industry moves towards
even wider gamut displays.
So, the solution is
really quite simple.
You enable color management
on the NSWindow or CAMetal
by setting the color space
to your working color space,
probably the sRGB color space.
This causes the OS to
perform a color match as part
of its window server's
normal compositing pass.
So if here's your
display, or excuse me,
here's your application
with sRGB drawable
and here's the display,
the window server takes your
drawable when you call present
and performs the color match
before slapping it on the glass.
Now, all right, so now
you've got that consistency.
What if you want to
adopt wide color?
You want to purposefully render
those more intense colors a wide
gamut display is only
capable of rendering.
Well, first of all, you
need to create some content.
You need your artist to
create wider content,
and for that we recommend
using the extended range sRGB
color space.
This allows existing assets that
aren't offered for wide color
to continue working
as they have,
and your shader pipelines don't
need to do anything different.
However, your artists can
create new wider color assets
that will provide much
more intense colors.
So what exactly is the
extended range sRGB?
Well here's the sRGB
triangle and here's P3.
Extended range sRGB
just goes out infinitely
in all directions, meaning
values outside of 0 to 1
in your shader represent
values that can only be viewed
on a wider than sRGB
color display.
So I mentioned values
outside of 0 to 1.
This means that you will need to
use floating point pixel formats
to express such values, and for
source textures we recommend a
couple of formats.
You can use the BC6H
floating point format.
It's a compressed format
offering high performance
as well as the pack float
and shared exponent formats.
For your render targets, you
can use this pack float format
or the RGBA half-float
format, allowing you
to specify these
more intense colors.
Color management on
iOS is a bit simpler.
You always render in
the sRGB color space,
even when targeting
a P3 Display.
Colors are automatically matched
with no performance penalty.
And if you want to use wide
colors, you can make use
of some new pixel formats
that are natively
readable by the display.
There's no compositing
operation that needs to happen.
They can be gamma encoded,
offering better blacks
and allowing you to do linear
blending in your shaders,
and they're efficient for
use as source textures.
All right.
Here are the bit layouts
of these new formats.
So, there are -- there
is a 32-bit RGB format
with 10 bits per channel
and also an RGBA format
spread across 64 bits.
Now, this, the values
of this 10 bits are --
can express values
outside of 0 to 1.
Values from 0 to 384 represent
negative values, 384 to 894,
the next 510 values, represent
values between 0 and 1
and those greater than
894 represent these more
intense values.
Now, note here that the RGBA
pixel format is twice as large
and therefore uses twice
as much memory and twice
as much bandwidth
as this RGB format.
So, in general, we recommend
that you use this only
in the CAMetal Layer if
you need destination alpha.
All right, so you've made
the decision that you want
to create some wide
gamut content.
How can you do this?
Well, you have an artist --
author using image
editor on macOS,
which supports the P3 color
space, such as Adobe Photoshop.
You can save that image as
a 16-bit per channel PNG
or JPEG using the
display P3 color profile.
Now, once you've got this image,
how do you create
textures from it?
Well, you've got
two solutions here.
The first is you can create your
own asset conditioning tool,
and from that 16-bit per channel
Display P3 image you can convert
using the extended sRGB floating
point color space using either
the ImageIO or vImage
frameworks.
And then from that on
macOS, you'd convert to one
of those floating point pixel
formats I mentioned earlier,
and on iOS you'd convert to one
of those extended range pixel
formats I just mentioned.
All right, so that's option one
if you really want
explicit control
of how your textures are built.
The next option is
to use Xcode support
for textures in asset
catalogues.
With that, will automatically
create extended range sRGB
textures for devices
with a P3 Display,
and I'll talk a little bit more
about asset catalogues
right now.
So for a while now you've been
able to put icons and images
into an asset catalogue
within your Xcode project.
Last year, we introduced app
thinning whereby you can create
a specialized version
for various devices based
upon device capability
such as the amount of memory,
the graphics features set,
or the type of device, whether
it be an iPad, Mac or TV
or watch or even
phone, of course.
And when your app was
downloaded, you download
and install only the single
version of that assess made
for that device with the
capabilities you specified.
The asset was compressed over
the wire and on the device,
saving a lot of storage
on the user's device,
and there were numerous APIs,
which offer efficient
access to those assets.
So now we've added texture
sets to these asset catalogues.
So what does this offer?
Well, storage for mipmap levels.
Textures are more
than just 2D images.
You can perform offline mipmap
generation within Xcode,
will automatically color
match this texture.
So if it's a wide gamut texture
in some different color space,
will perform a color
matching operation to the sRGB
or extended range
sRGB color space.
And I think the most important
feature of this ability here is
that we can choose the
most optimal pixel format
for every device on
which your app can run.
So on newer devices that support
ASTC texture compression,
we can use that format.
On older devices which
don't support that,
we can choose either
a noncompressed format
or some other compressed format.
Additionally, we can
choose a wide color format
for devices with a P3 Display.
So here's the basic workflow.
You create texture
sets within Xcode.
You assign a name to the
set, a unique identifier.
You'll add an image and
indicate basically how
that texture will be used,
whether it's a color texture
or some other type of data like
a normal map or a height map.
Then, you'll -- can
create this texture.
Xcode will build this texture
and deliver it to
your application.
Now, you can create these
texture sets via the Xcode UI
or programmatically.
Once your texture is on the
device, you can supply the name
to MetalKit, and MetalKit
will build a texture,
a Metal texture,
from that asset.
So I'd like to walk you
through the Xcode workflow
to introduce some of
these concepts to you.
So, you'll first select
the asset catalogue
in your projects
navigator sidebar
and then hit this plus button
here, which brings up this menu.
Now, here's where you can create
the various types of sets.
There are image sets, icon
sets, generic data sets,
as well as texture and
cube map texture sets.
So once you've created
your texture set,
you need to name it.
Now, your naming
hierarchy need not be flat.
If you have a number of textures
that are called base texture,
one for each object, you can
create a folder for each object
and stuff your base texture
for that object in that folder,
and your hierarchy can be
as complex as you'd like.
You add your image, and then
you set the interpretation.
Now there are three
options here.
Color, in color NonPremultiplied
perform this color
match operation.
The NonPremultiplied option
will multiply the alpha channel
by your R, B, and G --
RGB channels before
building the texture.
The data option here will
-- is used for normal maps,
height maps, roughness maps,
textures of noncolor type.
Now, this is all you need to do.
Xcode will go off and
build various versions
of this texture, and it
will pick the most optimal
pixel format.
You can, however, have
more explicit control.
You can select any number
of these traits here,
which will open up
a number of buckets
that you can select
to customize.
You can add different
images for each version.
You probably wouldn't
use a different image,
but may be a different
size of an image.
So on a device with
lots of memory,
you can use a bigger
texture, and a device
with a smaller memory, you would
use a much smaller texture.
And then you can specify how
or whether you want mipmaps.
The all option will
generate mipmaps all the way
down to the 1 by 1 level and the
fixed option here will give you
some more explicit control,
such as whether you want
to use a max level and
also whether you want
to have different
images for each level.
And finally, you can override
our automatic selection
of pixel formats.
Now I mentioned that you can
programmatically create these
texture sets.
You don't really want to
go through the Xcode UI
if you've got thousands
of assets.
So there's a pretty
simple directory structure,
and within that directory
structure are a number
of JSON files.
Now these files and directory
structure is fully documented
on the asset catalogue
reference.
So you can create your own
asset conditioning tool
to set up your texture set.
So once you've got this
asset on the device,
how do you make use of it?
Well, you create a MetalKit
texture loader supplying your
Metal device, and then
you supply the name along
with its hierarchy
to the texture loader
and MetalKit will go off
and build that texture.
You can supply a couple
of other options here
such as scale factor if
you have different versions
of the texture for different
scale factors or the bundle
if the asset catalogue is
in something other
than the main bundle.
There are also a couple
of options here that
you can specify.
So I'd really like you to
pay attention to color space
and set your apps apart
by creating content
with wide color.
Asset catalogues can help
you achieve that goal.
As well, they provide a
number of other features
which you can make use of,
such as optimal pixel
format selection.
I'd like to have my colleague
Anna Tikhonova up here to talk
about some exciting improvements
to the Metal Performance
Shaders framework.
[ Applause ]
>> Hi. Good afternoon.
Thank you, Dan, for
the introduction.
As Dan said, my name is Anna.
I'm an engineer on
the GPU Software Team.
So let's talk about
some new additions
to the Metal Performance
Shaders.
We introduced the Metal
Performance Shaders framework
last year in the What's
New in Metal Part 2 talk.
If you haven't seen
that session,
you should definitely
check out the video.
But just to give
you a quick recap,
the Metal Performance Shaders
framework is the framework
of optimized high performance
data parallel algorithms
for the GPU in Metal .
The algorithms are
optimized for iOS,
and they have been available
for you since iOS 9, for the A8
and now the A9 processors.
The framework is designed
to integrate easily
into your Metal applications
and be very simple to use.
It should be as simple as
calling a library function.
So last year, we talked
about following a list
of supported image operations,
and you should watch the video
for lots of details
and examples.
But this year, we've added
some more cool stuff for you.
We've added wide color
conversion, which you can use
to convert your Metal textures
between different color spaces.
You can convert between
RGB, sRGB, grayscale, CMYK,
C3 and any color
space you define.
We've also added Gaussian
pyramids, which you can use
to create multiscaler
presentations of image data
on the GPU to enable
multiscale algorithms.
They can also be used for
common optical flow algorithms,
image blending, and
high-quality mipmap generation.
And finally, we've added
convolutional neural networks,
or CNNs, which are used
to accelerate deep
learning algorithms.
This is going to be the
main topic of this talk.
So let's just dive right in.
First of all, what
is deep learning?
Deep learning is a field of
machine learning which goal is
to answer this question.
Can a machine do the same
task that a human can do?
Well, what types of
tasks am I talking about?
Each one of you has an
iPhone in your pocket.
You probably took a
few pictures today,
and all of us are constantly
exposed to images and videos
on the Web every day, on
news sites, on social media.
When you see an image, you
know instantly what is depicted
on it.
You can detect faces.
If you know these
people, you can tag them.
You can annotate this image.
And this works well
for a single image,
but what if you have more
images and even more images?
Think about all of the images
uploaded to the Web every day.
No human can hand
annotate this many images.
So deep learning is a technique
for solving these
kinds of problems.
It can be used for sifting
through large amounts of data
and for answering questions
such as, "Who's in this image?"
And "Where was it taken?"
But I'm using image-based
examples in this talk
because they are visual.
So they are a great fit for
this type of a presentation,
but I just want to mention
that deep learning
algorithms can be used
for other types of data.
For example, other types
of signal like audio
to do speech recognition
and haptics
to create the sense of touch.
Deep learning algorithms
have two phases.
The first one is
the training phase.
So let's talk about it,
give a specific example.
So image that you
want train your system
to categorize images
into classes.
This is an image of a cat.
This is an image of a dog.
This is the image of a rabbit.
This is a labor intensive task
that requires a large number
of images, hand-labeled
annotated images
for each one of these
categories.
So for example, if you
want to train your system
to recognize cats, you need to
feed it a large number of images
of cats all labeled, and
same for your rabbits
and all the other animals
that you want your system
to be able to recognize.
This is a one-time
computationally expensive step.
It's usually done offline,
and there are plenty
of training packages
available out there.
The result of the training
phase is trained parameters.
So I will not talk
about them right now,
but we will get back
to them later.
The trained parameters are
required for the next phase,
which is the inference phase.
This is the phase where
your system is presented
with a new image that has
never seen before, and it needs
to classify in real-time.
So in this example, the system
correctly classified this image
as an image of a cat.
We provide GPU acceleration
for the inference phase.
Specifically, we give
you the building blocks
to build your inference
networks for the GPU.
So let's now talk about what
are the convolutional neural
networks and what are these
building blocks we provide?
The convolutional
neural networks, or CNNs,
are biologically
inspired and designed
to resemble the visual cortex.
When our brain processes visual
input, the first hierarchy
of neurons that receive
information
in the visual cortex are
sensitive to specific edges
or blobs of color, while
the brain regions further
down the visual pipeline respond
to more complex structures
like faces or kinds of animals.
So in a very similar way,
the convolutional neural
networks are organized
into layers of neurons
which are trained
to recognize increasingly
complex features.
So the first layers are trained
to recognize low level features
like edges and blobs of color,
while the subsequent
layers are trained
to recognize higher
level features.
So for example, if we
are doing face detection,
then will have layers that will
recognize features like noses,
eyes, cheeks, and then
combination of these features,
and then finally faces.
And then the final few layers
combine all the generated
information to produce the
final output for the network,
such as the probability that
there is a face in the image.
And I keep mentioning features.
Think of a feature as a
filter that filters the input
for that feature,
such as a nose,
and if that information is
found, it's passed along.
If that feature is found, this
information is passed along
to the subsequent layers.
And, of course, we need to
look for many such features.
So if we're doing face
detection, then looking
for just noses is
simply not enough.
We also need to look for other
facial features like cheeks,
eyes, and then combinations
of such features.
So we need many of
these feature filters.
So now that I've covered
convolutional neural networks,
let's talk about the
building blocks we'll provide.
The first building
block is your data.
We want you to use MPS images
and MPS temporary images,
which we added specifically to
support convolutional networks.
They provide and optimize layout
for your data, for your input
and intermediate results.
Think of MPS temporary images
as light-weight MPS images,
which we want you to
use for image data
with a transient lifetime.
MPS temporary images are built
using the Metal resource heaps,
which were described in the
Part 1 of these sessions.
They address some of
the reused cache memory,
and they avoid expensive
allocation
and deallocation of
texture resources.
So the goal is to save
you lots of memory
and to help you manage
intermediate resources.
We also provide a collection
of layers, which you can use
to create your inference
networks.
But you may be thinking
right now, "How do I know
which building blocks
I actually need
to build my own inference
network?"
So the answer is
trained parameters.
The trained parameters, I
mentioned them previously
when we talked about
the training phase.
The trained parameters give
you a complete recipe for how
to build your inference
networks.
They tell you how many
layers you will have,
what kind they will be, in
which order they will appear,
and you also get all those
feature filters for every layer.
So we take care of everything
under the hood to make sure
that the networks you build
using these building blocks have
the best possible
performance on all iOS GPUs.
All you have to do
is to mine your data
into this optimized
layout that we provide
and to call library
functions to create the layers
that make up your network.
So now let's discuss all these
building blocks in more detail,
but let's do it in a context
of a specific example.
So in this demo, I have a system
that has been trained
to detect smiles.
And what we'll have is
in real-time the system will
detect whether I am smiling
or not.
So I will first smile,
and then I will frown,
and you will see the
system report just that.
[ Laughter ]
All right.
So that [inaudible] my demo.
[ Applause ]
Okay. So now let's take a
look at the building blocks
that I needed to build
this kind of a network.
So the first building
block we're going to talk
about is the convolution layer.
It's the core building block of
convolutional neural networks,
and its goal is to
recognize features and input.
And it's called a
convolutional layer
because it performs a
convolution on the input.
So let's recall how
regular convolution works.
You have your input and your
output and in this case a 5
by 5 pixel filter
with some weight.
And in order to compute
the value of this pixel
in your output, you need
to convolve the filter
with the input.
Pretty easy.
The convolution layer
is a generalization
of regular convolution.
It allows you to have
multiple filters.
The different filters are
applied to the input separately,
resulting in different
output channels.
So if you have 16 filters.
That means you have
16 output channels.
So in order to get the value of
this pixel in the first channel
of the output, you need
to take the first filter
and convolve it with the input.
And in order to get the value of
this pixel in the second channel
of the output, you need
to take the second filter
and convolve it with your input.
Of course, in our examples,
mild detection we are
dealing with color images.
So that means that your input
actually has three separate
channels, and just because
of how convolutional neural
networks work, you need
three sets of 16 filters
where you have one set
for each input channel.
And then you apply
the different filters
to separate input channels
and combine the results
to get a single output value.
So this is how you
would create one
of these convolution
layers in our framework.
You first create a descriptor
and specify such parameters
as the width and height of the
filters you're going to use
and then the number of
input and output channels.
And then you create
a convolution layer
from this descriptor and
provide the actual data
for the feature filters,
which you get
from the trained parameters.
The next layer we are going to
talk about is the pooling layer.
The function of the
pooling layer is
to progressively reduce the
spatial size of the network,
which reduces the
amount of competition
for the subsequent layers.
And it's common to
insert a pooling of the
in between successive
convolution layers.
Another function of the
pooling layer is to summarize
or condense information
in a region of the input,
and it would provide two pooling
operations, maximum and average.
So in this example, we take a 2
by 2 pixel region of the input.
We take the maximum value
and store it as our output.
And this is the API
you need to use
in the Metal Performance
Shaders framework to create one
of these pooling layers.
It's common to use
the max operation
with a filter size of 2 by 2.
The fully connected layer is
a layer where every neuron
in the input is connected to
every neuron in the output.
But think about it as a special
type of a convolution layer
where the filter size is
the same as your input size.
So in this example, we have
a filter of the same size
as the input, and
we convolve them
to get a single output value.
So in this architecture,
the convolution
and pooling layers operate
on regions of input,
while the fully connected
layer can be used
to aggregate information
from across the entire input.
It's usually one of the
last layers in your network,
and this is where your final
decision-making is taking place
and you create -- you generate
the output for the network,
such as the probability that
there's a smile in the image.
And this is how you
would create one
of these fully connected layers
in the Metal Performance
Shaders framework.
You create a convolution
descriptor
because this is a special
type of a convolution layer,
and then you create a
fully connected layer
from this descriptor.
We'll also provide
some additional layers,
which I'm not going to cover
in detail in this presentation
but they are described
in our documentation.
We provide the neural
layer, which is usually used
in conjunction with
the convolution layer,
and we also provide the soft
max and normalization layers.
So now that we've
covered all of the layers,
let's talk about your data.
I mentioned that you
should be using MPS images.
So what are they really?
Most of you are already
familiar with Metal textures.
So this is a 2D Metal
texture with multiple channels
where every channel corresponds
to a color channel and alpha.
And I mentioned in my
previous examples that we need
to create images with
multiple channels,
for example, 32 channels.
If we have 32 feature filters,
we need to create
an output channel --
an output image that
has 32 channels.
So how do we do this?
So an MPS image is really
a Metal 2D array texture
with multiple slices.
And when you're creating
an MPS image,
all you really should
care about is
that you are creating an image
with 32 -- with 32 channels.
But sometimes you may need to
reach the MPS image data back
to the CPU, or you may want
to use an existing Metal 2D
array texture as your MPS image.
So for those cases,
you need to know
that we use a special
packed layout for your data.
So every pixel in a slice
of the structure contains
the data for four channels.
So a 32-channel image would
really just have eight slices.
And this is the API you
need to use to create one
of the MPS images
in our framework.
You first create a descriptor
and specify such parameters
as the channel for data format
with the height of the image
and the number of channels.
And then you create an MPS image
from this descriptor,
pretty simple.
Of course, if you have
small input images,
then you should batch them
to better utilize the GPU,
and we provide a simple
mechanism for you to do this.
So in this example, we create
an array of 100 MPS images.
Okay, so now that we've
covered all the layers,
we've covered data, and
now let's take a look
at the actual network you need
to build to do smile detection.
So we start with our
inputs, and now we're going
to use the trained parameters
that I keep mentioning
to help us build this network.
So the trained parameters
tell us that the first layer
in this network is going
to be a convolution layer,
which takes a three-channel
images input
and outputs a 16-channel image.
The trained parameters also give
us the three sets of 16 filters
for this layer, and these
colorful blue images show you
the visualization of
the output channels
after the filters have
been applied to the input.
The next layer is
a pooling layer,
which reduces the spatial
resolution of the output
of the convolution layer by a
factor of two in each dimension.
The trained parameters tell us
that the next layer is
another convolution layer,
which takes a 16-channel
images input
and outputs a 16-channel image,
which is further down reduced
in size by the next
pooling layer,
and so on until we
get to our output.
As you can see, this
network has a series
of convolution layers
followed by the pooling layers,
and the last two layers are
the fully connected layers,
which generate the final
output for your network.
So now that we know what this
network should look like,
and this is very common for a
convolutional neural network
for inference, so now
let's write the code
to create it in our framework.
So the first step is
to create the layers.
Once again, the trained
parameters tell us that we need
to have four convolution layers
in our network and I'm showing
that the code had to create
one of them for simplicity
but as you can see, I'm
using exactly the same API
that I've showed you before.
Then we need to create
our pooling layer.
We just need one because
we're always going
to be using the max operation
with a filter size of 2 by 2.
And we also need to create
two fully connected layers,
and once again I'm only
showing you the code
for one for simplicity.
And now, we need to take
care of our input and output.
In this particular
example, I'm assuming
that we have an existing Metal
app and you have some textures
that you would like to use
for your input and output,
and this is the API that you
need to use to create MPS images
from existing Metal textures.
And so the last step is
to encode all your layers
into an existing command
buffer in the order prescribed
by the trained parameters.
So we have our input and our
outputs, and now we notice
that we need one more
thing to take care of.
We need to store the output
of the first layer somewhere.
So let's use MPS
temporary images for that.
This is how you would create
an MPS temporary image.
As you can see, this
is very similar
to the way you would
create a regular MPS image.
And now we immediately use it
when we encode the first layer.
And the temporary image
will go away as soon
as the command buffer
is submitted.
And then we continue.
We create another temporary
image to store the output
of the second layer, and so
on until we get to our output.
That's it.
And just to tie it
all back together,
the order in which you encode
the layers matches the network
diagram that I showed
you earlier exactly,
so starting from the input
and all the way to the output.
So now we worked through
a pretty simple example.
Let's look at a more
complex one.
We've ported the
inception inference network
from tensor flow to run
using the Metal Performance
Shaders framework.
This is a very commonly
used inference network
for object detection, and
this is the full diagram
for this network.
As you can see, this
network is a lot more complex
that the previous
one I showed you.
It has over 100 layers.
But just to remind you,
all you have to do is
to call some library functions
to create these layers.
And now first, let's take a
look at this network in action.
So here I have a collection of
images of different objects,
and as soon as I
tap on this image,
we will run the inference
network in real-time
and it will report
the top five guesses
for what it thinks
this object is.
So the top guess is
that it's a zebra.
Then this is a pickup
truck, and this a volcano.
So that looks pretty good
to me, but of course,
let's do a real live demo
right here on this stage.
And we'll take a picture
of this water bottle,
and let's use this
image, water bottle.
[ Applause ]
So what I wanted to show
you with this live demo is
that even a large network
with over 100 layers can run
in real-time using the Metal
Performance Shaders framework,
but this is not all.
I also want to talk about
the memory savings we got
from using MPS temporary
images in this demo.
So in the first version of
this demo, we used MPS images
to store intermediate
results, and we ended
up needing 74 MPS
images totaling in size
over 80 megabytes for
the entire network.
And of course, you don't
have to use 74 images.
You can come up with your
own clever scheme for how
to reuse these images, but
this means more stuff to manage
in your code, and we want to
make sure that our framework is
as easy for you to
use as possible.
So in the second
version of the demo,
we replaced all the MPS images
with MPS temporary images,
and this gave us
several advantages.
The first one is reduced
CPU cost in terms of time
and energy, but also creating
74 temporary images resulted
in just 5 underlying memory
allocations, totaling just
over 20 megabytes and this
is 76% of memory savings.
That's pretty huge.
So what I showed you with
these two live demos is
that the Metal Performance
Shaders framework provides
complete support for building
convolutional neural networks
for inference, and it's
optimized iOS GPU use.
So please, use the
convolutional neural networks
to build some cool apps.
So this is the end of
What's New in Metal talks,
and if you haven't seen the
first session, please check
out the video so you can learn
about such cool new features
as tessellation, resource heaps,
and memoryless render targets
and improvements to our tools.
In this session, we talked
about function specialization
and function resource
read-writes, white color
and texture assets,
and new additions
to the Metal performance
tools, concentrating
on convolutional
neural networks.
For more information about this
session, please go to this URL.
You can catch the
video and get links
to related documentation
and sample code.
And here's some information
on the related sessions.
You could always
check out the videos
of the past Metal
sessions online,
but you can also catch
an advanced Metal shader
optimization talk later today,
and just note the location
of this talk has
changed to Knob Hill.
Tomorrow, you have an
opportunity to catch the Working
with White Color talk
and the Neural Networks
and Accelerate talk
where you can learn how
to create neural networks
for the CPU using the
Accelerate framework.
So thank you very
much for coming,
and I hope you have
a great WWDC.
[ Applause ]