[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, hello
everybody and welcome
to Controlling Game
Input for Apple TV.
I'm JJ Cwik, Game
Technology Software Engineer.
Now when we introduce Apple
TV back in September we talked
about the 10 foot experience.
We talked about it being a
shared communal experience,
one that's ideally suited
to longer gameplay sessions.
And the fact of the matter is
that people just love playing
games in their living room
and Apple TV is great for that.
It gives you the tools you need
to create really
compelling game experiences.
And I'm really happy to talk to
you today about the Siri Remote,
MFi game controllers and how
to best integrate
them into your game.
Now before I start
spoiler alert,
here's what's new in tvOS 10.
As you heard on Monday, games
with advanced game mechanics
that cannot be supported
by the Siri Remote can
optionally include the
requirement that they
require game controllers.
Now we've also included
support for up
to four MFi game controllers.
This is going to be great
for multiplayer gaming.
And as you also heard on Monday,
we have an Apple TV Remote app
that can be used to control
your Apple TV and can be used
as a game input device.
Now I'll talk about all
these throughout the course
of the talk, so let's
get started.
Now apps on tvOS
typically take their input
from the focus engine or
they also take the inputs
from touches and gestures.
But there's also a third
option available and that's
to read inputs directly
off of the Siri Remote
and game controllers with the
Game Controller framework.
Now let me give you
a quick overview
of the Game Controller
framework for those of you
who may not be familiar with it.
The Game Controller framework
was initially created
to expose third-party game
controllers to your games.
These compatible game
controllers are what we call
MFi controllers.
Now the framework has
since been updated
to also include support
for the Siri Remote.
The Game Controller framework
is a standardized simple API
that allows you to
access all controllers
and use the same
API calls regardless
of the controller vendors.
It standardizes detection
of controllers.
It seamlessly handles
controllers that connect
and disconnect while
your game is running.
And it allows you to
control input or rather
to read inputs off of the
controllers using polling
or an event-driven model.
And it's also available
on tvOS, iOS and macOS.
And so even though this talk
is geared towards tvOS a lot
of the code and concepts
still apply on iOS and macOS.
So now that you have
an understanding
of the framework I'd like to
talk about some specifics.
There is a core class
in the Game Controller
framework called GCController.
This represents physical
controllers
and it's the same class
for the Siri Remote
and MFi game controllers.
Now the first thing you're
probably going to want to do
in your app is to get a list
of all the currently
connected controllers.
And to do this you use the
controller's class method
on GCController.
This returns you a list of the
currently connected controllers
as an array of GCController
instances
or an empty array if none exist.
It's also common for controllers
to connect and disconnect
as your app is running and to be
notified of this add observers
for the GCCcontrollerDidConnect
Notification
and GCControllerDidDisconnect
Notification.
A great place to do this is
in your application Did
Finish Launching with Options.
So now we know which controllers
are connected and I'd
like to shift focus and
talk about the Siri Remote.
Now the Siri Remote is
surface to your game
as a game controller using
the GCController class
that I just mentioned.
And in the Game Controller
framework, there's this concept
of profiles and profiles grouped
together common functionality
and the Siri Remote
supports two profiles.
The first is called
GCMicroGamepad.
This is what you use to
access the touch surface
and the buttons on
the Siri Remote.
The second profile that the
Siri Remote supports is called
GCMotion and this is what you
use to access the gyroscope
and accelerometer
on the Siri Remote.
Now note that this is different
than what you might be used
to on iOS where motion comes
through the CoreMotion
framework.
On tvOS motion comes through
the Game Controller framework.
So let's look at each of
these profiles in turn.
First, the GCMicroGamepad.
Now the touch surface on
the Siri Remote is surface
to your game as a
virtual DPAD of sorts.
And you can query its value
using an analog representation
as an XY coordinate pair or
as a digital input basically
as four buttons up,
down, left and right.
The GCMicroGamepad profile
also has an A button
and this corresponds
to clicking the remote.
This is ideally suited for the
primary action in your games,
especially when the
remote is being held
in portrait orientation.
And the profile also has
an X button, this is useful
as a secondary action
in your games
and it becomes really natural
when the remote is tilted
on its side and held in
landscape orientation
to have a thumb on
the touch surface
and another thumb
on the X button.
Now note that there's also a
Menu button on this remote,
I'll be talking about
that momentarily.
And the remainder of the buttons
on the remote are
reserved for system use.
Here's a code example
to show how simple it is
to read inputs off
of the buttons.
Here we see we have a controller
that's already been connected
and from that we can read
the MicroGamepad profile.
That stores the button A
and button X properties
and from there we just
check the isPressed property
to determine whether or not
those buttons are pressed.
Now we also support
an event-driven model.
So if you want to be notified
when the buttons are
pressed instead of having
to poll you can do that.
These are called the
pressedChangeHandler
and this block of code that
you supply is run whenever the
button changes state.
Notice of this is called twice
for traditional button
press once on button down
and another time on button up.
So those are the buttons.
Let's look at the DPAD now.
The DPAD as I mentioned
can be read
as four buttons up,
down, left and right.
And interestingly, has
a second representation
as two axes, xAxis and yAxis.
So let's look at those.
Here you can see there's a DPAD
property on the MicroGamepad
and it has xAxis and
yAxis properties.
From there we read
the value property
which returns a float normalized
between zero or sorry,
normalized between
negative 1 and positive 1.
Now as you'd expect, we also
have an event callback for that.
And note in this case our
value change handler is used
or we're supplying a
value change handler
on the DPAD itself not
on the xAxis and yAxis.
This is because we want to
be notified whenever either
of those two axes changes.
Now there's some interesting
aspects of the DPAD remote
that I'd like to talk
to you about now.
And the first one is
called DPAD windowing.
Now what this is is it really
defines where the origin
of your x and yAxis
is for the DPAD.
Now you might be wondering
shouldn't this always be
at the center and the answer is
a lot of times, no not really.
A lot of times a player doesn't
concern themselves so much
with the precise location
that they're touching
on the touch surface,
but rather they just want
to put their thumb
down and move relative
to where they initially
touch down.
And that's what DPAD
windowing allows you to do
as a game developer is to tap
into this relative motion.
So initial touch downs
on the touch surface
establish an origin
and then further movement from
there has DPAD values reported
to your game relative
to that origin.
Let me explain with an example.
So here's our touch surface
and I place my thumb
down right here.
Notice it's not at the
midpoint of the touch surface,
but with DPAD windowing
enabled this is where our origin
for our x and yAxis
is established.
Also note there's an imaginary
DPAD window placed outside
of that centered
about the origin.
Now watch what happens
as I move my thumb
across the touch surface.
The values reported to your
game are relative to this origin
and in proportion to
the size of the window.
Now as I continue
dragging my thumb
across the touch surface
it drags the window
and the axis along with it.
Now we have established a new
origin and any further movement
across the touch surface
has the DPAD values reported
to your game relative
to this new origin.
So that's DPAD windowing.
If you want to receive absolute
DPAD values all the time you can
opt into this with the
reportsAbsoluteDpadValues
property, set this to true
and we always have the origin
at the physical midpoint
of the touch surface.
Then as I place my
thumb down and move it
across the touch surface all
the values reported are relative
to the physical midpoint
of the touch surface.
So that's DPAD windowing.
Next up rotation.
So the DPAD values
surface to your game are
in portrait orientation
and this means X is going
to the right and Y is going up.
However, this might cause a
problem if the player wants
to play in landscape
orientation.
In this case, your game would
need to transpose those values
so that it's proper
to be played in game.
But then what happens if
the user tilts the remote
in the other direction,
you would need
to transpose those values
in the opposite direction.
And how would you even do
this, you'd either have
to force the player to play
in a particular orientation
all the time or you'd have
to start reading
accelerometer data
and track the orientation
changes yourself.
And this isn't something
you want to be doing.
So we've provided a property
for this called allowsRotation.
Now by default this
property is set to false.
But if you set it to true,
then the DPAD values reported
to your game will
be with respect
to whatever orientation the
remote is being held in.
So when this is true
and when the remote's
in portrait orientation
X is going
to the right and Y is going up.
And in landscape left X is going
And in landscape right
you've guessed it X is going
to the right and Y is going up.
So if your game wants
to allow players to play
in landscape orientation
set allows rotation to true
so you don't have to worry
about orientation changes
or rotating DPAD
values yourself.
So that's rotation.
Next up motion.
As I mentioned earlier,
the second profile
that the Siri Remote
supports is called GCMotion.
Now as the user moves the
remote around the gravity
in user acceleration
vectors supplied
by the GCMotion profile
are updated.
Note that these values are
already filtered before they get
to your game.
So if you have a tvOS game
and you're doing motion
filtering we suggest you remove
that so that you don't
introduce any unnecessary lag
into your game.
Also, this is fused motion data
and what we mean by that is
that the accelerometer and the
gyroscope help to reinforce
and correct each other.
So just like on your
iPhone the gravity vector
from the accelerometer
helps to correct the drift
in the gyroscope and
the gyroscope data helps
to smooth the values coming
from the accelerometer.
They reinforce each other.
But really, vigorous
motion can overwhelm that,
so for this reason we recommend
you avoid creating scenarios
in your game that
require the user
to vigorously shake the remote.
Because this causes data
that's difficult correct
until the sensors have
had a chance to stabilize.
Next up I want to talk
about the Menu button.
Now all controllers
supported by tvOS
in the Game Controller
framework have a Menu button.
It's the same Menu button
with the same behavior
on the Siri Remote and
MFi game controllers.
Now in an app on tvOS when
the Menu button is pressed the
recommended behavior changes
depending on the context.
Sometimes pressing the Menu
button will minimize your app
and return you back to
the Apple TV Home Screen.
That's typically done in
your game's main menu.
At other times pressing the Menu
button will go back one level
in your apps menu hierarchy
and this is typically
done in submenus.
Lastly, pressing the Menu
button sometimes pauses
or resumes your active gameplay.
Now nongame apps
written entirely
in UIKit get the first two
behaviors largely for free
without any additional
work, but most games due
to their custom UI have to do
a little bit of extra work here
to indicate to the
system their intent.
Let me explain.
So in UIKit when the
Menu button is pressed
for UIKit apps it pops the child
view controller off the stack.
This returns you back to your
previous level of your menus.
Now you can do this successively
with each Menu button press
popping the child view
controllers off the
stack and then
at some point you have
one view controller,
your root view controller
remaining on the stack.
Now when there's only
one view controller left
on the stack the next Menu
button press minimizes your app
and bounces you back to
the Apple TV Home Screen.
Most games by comparison
are architected differently,
they typically have custom
in-game UI that's not written
in UIKit.
And they also typically
have scene transitions
between the different
portions of the game
that also aren't
written in UIKit.
And so for this reason
they typically can get away
with only having
one view controller,
the root view controller,
for the entire duration
of their game.
But by the rule that we just saw
because there's only one
view controller in the stack
at all points of your game
by default pressing the Menu
button will bounce you back
to the Apple TV Home Screen.
So you're going to need some
way to indicate to the system
when you want Menu button
presses to return you
to the Apple TV Home
Screen and when you don't.
Enter GCEventViewController.
This is a special view
controller we created for single
or rather for game
controller games
that have a single-view
controller.
So if your game is one of these
you're going to want to set this
as your root view controller.
Now this view controller
has a property called
controllerUserInteractionEnabled
and this is the key
that you have for controlling
when your app returns back
to the home screen for
Menu button presses.
When this value is false this
view controller effectively
traps the Menu button presses
and prevents them from going
up the responder chain,
effectively keeping
you in your app.
Incidentally, this is also
where your controller
pause handler is called
and I'll get to that
momentarily.
Now when this value is set
to true Menu button events
are allowed to proceed
up the responder chain as
normal, which allows your app
to be minimized and
takes you back
to the Apple TV Home Screen.
So your job as a game
developer is to manage the state
of
controllerUserInteractionEnabled
as a user goes back and forth
between different
parts of your game.
Let me show you with
a block diagram.
So here we are at the
Apple TV Home Screen
and we launch our app.
Some games have a splash screen
or some other introductory
sequence
and many games will
eventually land
on an in-game main
menu of sorts.
And for both of these
the user's expectation is
that when they press the Menu
button they will be bounced back
to the Apple TV Home
Screen immediately.
Therefore,
set
controllerUserInteractionEnabled
to true.
Now when the user progresses
to other parts of the game,
say active gameplay
or in submenus,
the user's expectations is
that Menu button presses
will not bounce you back
to the Apple TV Home Screen.
So in these cases set
controllerUserInteractionEnabled
to false.
And if a user transitions back
to the in-game main
menu remember
to set this back to true again.
So that covers our first
behavior when we return back
to the Apple TV Home
Screen and not.
And we still have the
two behaviors remaining.
We need to worry about going
back in submenus and pausing
and resuming active gameplay.
Basically all the dark
boxes on this diagram.
And the good news is that
those are both handled
in the controllerPausedHandler.
The controllerPausedHandler is
a block of code that you supply
to the controller or for
each controller rather
and this is code that runs
whenever the Menu button is
pressed and you're not
going to be bounced back
to the Apple TV Home Screen.
And it's a simple matter within
this block of code to check
if you're in a submenu go back
to the previous level
menu in your game.
If you're in active gameplay
toggle the pause state.
And that's it now
your game is set
up to properly handle Menu
button presses regardless
of where you are in your game.
So now let's talk about
MFi game controllers.
Some games can really take
advantage of the extended set
of controls offered by
wireless extended gamepads
and these are optional
accessories
that players may have.
Now by extended what
we're referring
to is the control
layout and it's a layout
that you're probably
already very familiar with.
It features a DPAD on the left,
it features four face buttons A,
B, X, Y in these
positions and in this shape,
the diamond pattern
on the right.
On the front of the controller
it features two thumb sticks
and on top we have two
shoulders and two triggers.
Now all of these buttons
that I've mentioned
so far are pressure-sensitive
and I'll cover that momentarily.
We also have a Menu button,
which I already discussed
and we have four
player indicator LEDs.
Now just like the Siri Remote
supports the GCMicroGamepad
extended game controllers
support the
GCExtendedGamepad profile.
And you'll notice on the left
here there's a table listing all
the properties.
Also notice the data types
GCControllerDirectionPad
and GCControllerButtonInput.
These are the same
data types you're used
to on the Siri Remote.
Now one thing I'd like to
point out is that the DPAD
and the buttons and
every single input
on this table actually
is pressure-sensitive.
So even those buttons and inputs
that are typically
considered digital only
in other controllers that
you may have encountered
like the DPAD and
the face buttons
and shoulder buttons they're
all pressure-sensitive
and so they can be read in an
analog and in a digital sense.
So let's look at code that shows
that analog digital duality.
Here we have the A button and
the first line is showing how
to access the digital state
of the button whether
or not it's pressed.
So if your game only concerns
itself in a particular situation
with whether or not a button is
pressed this is what you want
to use.
However, if you care about
how hard a button is pressed,
that's when you'd use
the value property.
And this is great to add more
nuance control to your game.
Maybe you're creating a
sports game and you want
to allow players to vary
the speed of their passes
from a soft gentle pass to a
fast bullet pass and you can do
that by reading how hard
the button was pressed
with the value property.
We also offer event
callbacks as you'd expect.
Now notice there's a
pressedChangeHandler,
which corresponds to
the press property.
This is for Boolean
state changes
or digital state changes.
And there's a value changed
property which corresponds
to the value or sorry, a value
change handler which corresponds
with the value property.
Now the value change
handler is called many times
in a typical button press
as the button progresses
down through its travel
range and back up again.
And for those of you looking
for guidance on whether
to use polling or event
callbacks, there's no hard
and fast rules, but
polling tends to be good
for reading those
inputs that change
over a longer period of time.
Like maybe the accelerator
on a racecar game being tied
to the trigger of a button
or rather the trigger
of the game controller.
And event callbacks
tend to work really well
when you're concerned about
edge transitions of buttons.
So maybe you have
an adventure game
and a player swings
their sword and you want
to activate the swing sword
animation the moment the button
is pressed.
Event callbacks are
great for that.
So by this point you
probably have an understanding
of the mechanics of
connecting and reading inputs
from the Siri Remote
and game controllers
and you're probably
starting to think
about which control types
your game is going to support.
Will it support just
the Siri Remote
or will it support the Siri
Remote and MFi game controllers?
Or as you heard on Monday,
games that have advanced
game mechanics
that can't be supported
by the Siri Remote can require
the use of a game controller.
Now how you specify
which controller types your
game supports is in Xcode.
In your target settings
there's a capabilities tab
and in there you'll find the
game controllers capability.
Enable this capability
and select which types
of controllers your
game supports.
Interacting with this GUI
changes the keys and values
in your info.plist
file accordingly.
And this is important for
app review because all games
that link the Game Controller
framework are going to
or rather these keys are going
to be looked for in app review
by all games that link the
Game Controller framework.
And where this really
matters is in the App Store
because your users are going
to be notified in the App Store
if your game has game
controllers as optional
or game controllers as required.
Additionally, the user may
be warned if they tried
to download a game
controller required game
when they haven't
paired a game controller
to that Apple TV before.
Now note that this
is only a safeguard
because it's very
possible that your game
that requires game
controllers may still launch
and find no game
controllers connected.
And this is a case that you
need to account for and handle.
It's very possible that maybe
the user merely forgot to turn
on their game controller.
So in this situation
notify the player
that no game controllers
were found
and to connect a
game controller.
Otherwise, the user may be
wondering why your game is
seemingly not controllable.
Now there's one other
place to concern yourself
with notifying the user in
this kind of manner and that's
on controller disconnections.
This is because the controller
or rather the controllers
available may pass your initial
check, but then somewhere
down the line while
your app is running one
of the game controllers
could disconnect.
And if this is the
only game controller
that was available then at this
point your game can't proceed
since it requires
game controllers
and again a place
to notify the user.
For more information,
see Designing for tvOS,
session 802 for more information
on requiring game controllers.
So let's talk about
something new now,
the Apple TV Remote app.
As you heard on Monday, this
is a new app and it's available
in beta form on
developer.apple.com.
This app allows you to
control your Apple TV
and it features a large
touch surface in the middle
of the screen and on-screen
buttons that you'll find
as well on the Siri Remote.
And importantly for our
discussion this can be used
as a game input device.
And the way that's done
on tvOS is it's surfaced
by the Game Controller
framework to your game
in a very familiar manner.
It's effectively an
emulated Siri Remote.
So it shows up as a
GCController instance
and it supports the
GCMicroGamepad
and GCMotion profiles
just like the Siri Remote.
In fact, it's indistinguishable
in the Game Controller
framework from the Siri Remote.
So the code you write for the
Siri Remote will work for both.
Now by default these
remotes are coalesced,
so if you have a Siri Remote and
a TV Remote app they will appear
as one game controller
by default
in your controllers array.
This means that button inputs
from both will be surface
to your game as if they
came from one controller
and the same thing
with DPAD inputs.
Now for motion we didn't want
the motion input form one
overwriting and fighting with
the motion input from the other,
so we take motion from
one controller or sorry,
from one remote at a time.
And the remote we take
it from is the remote
that last received intentional
user input either swipes
on the touch surface or
A or X button presses.
Now if you want you can opt-in
to separate these remotes
and have them show up
as distinct instances
in your controllers array.
To do this, go to
your info.plist file
and add the Boolean key
GCSupportsMultipleMicroGamepads,
set this to yes and
now the Siri Remote
and Apple TV Remote
apps will show
up as distinct controller
instances in your array.
Now I want to talk to you
about a special mode inside
of the Apple TV Remote app
called Game Controller mode.
This is a mode that users can
switch into and out of at will
in any game that links the
Game Controller framework.
Now this app is in landscape
orientation and as such,
the DPAD values are rotated
by 90 degrees before they
even get to your app.
So your app doesn't
have to do anything
to take advantage of this mode.
However, just note that if
your game manually rotates DPAD
values by 90 degrees
you're effectively going
to be doing a double rotation.
So our recommendation is if
you have a game that wants
to allow players to play
in landscape orientation
with the Siri Remote
and Game Controller mode
on the Apple TV Remote app
set allowsRotation to true
like we saw previously
in the talk and allow us
to handle the orientation
and DPAD changes for you.
Now one more thing to note,
the Apple TV Remote app's Game
Controller mode separates the
touch surface from the A button.
This is different
from the Siri Remote
where clicking the touch surface
it activates the A button.
Now mechanically this doesn't
provide any problems the user
can still simultaneously
enter input on both
and your game code
can still check
for simultaneous input on both.
But the key point is if you
have game code that assumes
that all A button presses will
also activate the touch surface
this won't work in the same
way on the Game Controller mode
for the Apple TV Remote app.
And lastly, I'd like to talk to
you about multiple controllers.
We get asked all the time how
many controllers does Apple
TV support.
And the answer is one Siri
Remote new for tvOS 10
up to four MFi game controllers
and the Apple TV Remote app.
Now we typically get
asked this in the context
of multiplayer gaming and
with the addition of up
to four MFi game controllers
for tvOS 10 this is going
to be great for multiplayer
gaming.
But something that may not
be initially obvious is
that this is very important for
single-player gaming as well.
Let me explain.
When your app launches you're
not sure if you're going
to find only one Siri Remote
connected or maybe you're going
to find a game controller
connected
or maybe you'll find one of each
or maybe you'll find
a Siri Remote,
multiple game controllers,
the TV Remote app.
You get the picture right?
So the key point here is on
Apple TV it's very natural
to receive inputs from
multiple controllers even
for single-player games.
And importantly, you
don't know ahead of time
which controller the
user is intending to use.
So you can't just assume
that the controller's
array index zero is the one
that the player wants to use.
So how should we handle this?
Well the key realization here is
that players can switch
controllers at any point.
Maybe they launched your app,
traverse through your
in-game menus and launch
into gameplay all with the
Siri Remote and then switch
to the MFi game controller
to actually start
controlling the gameplay.
And games that allow players
to switch freely and flexibly
between different
controllers without having
to prompt the user with
unnecessary confirmation dialogs
or without requiring the
user to exit gameplay
and reenter gameplay
with a different controller will
create a really great seamless
user experience.
So how should we do this?
Well one way to go about
this is to treat input
from all controllers
as valid input
for your single-player game.
So if you have a character
that moves onscreen
from the DPAD allow all
controllers that are connected,
allow their DPADs to control
the character movement.
Similarly with buttons, if
your character or rather
if your character jumps
by pressing the A button
allow all the A buttons
on all the connected controllers
to control the character.
And if a controller
connects in the middle
of your gameplay you can
silently start tracking
that controller too
and allow its inputs
to control your character.
Now this is working
really well we're able
to give the player a system here
in your game where they're able
to switch back and forth
between controllers.
And this is effectively a
manual coalescing strategy
where we're taking the
inputs from Siri remotes
and game controllers
and feeding them all
into our single-player
experience.
But there's one edge case
here that I want to talk
about and that's motion.
So let me explain
with an example.
If you have a game
that uses motion say
to control the attitude of
an airplane flying in the air
with the Siri Remote
you might also offload
that controlling the
airplane to a thumb stick
if the player is playing
with a game controller.
And that's perfectly fine
that works really well.
The key concern here though is
you don't want your thumb stick
that controls the airplane
with the game controller
to be overwritten by any motion
data that might be coming
from the Siri Remote when
you're manually coalescing them.
So in this case the code in your
game that controls the attitude
of the airplane should
gate on whether it's taking
that information from
motion or from thumb sticks.
So then back to our example
as I'm controlling my plane
with my Siri Remote if I pick
up my game controller any
intentional user input
on that game controller whether
it's DPAD or thumb sticks
or triggers or buttons will
start ignoring the motion coming
from the Siri Remote and
use the right thumb stick
to control the attitude of
the airplane and vice versa.
If I then pick up my Siri
Remote intentional user input,
namely swipes across
the touch surface or A
or X button presses will at
that point start listening
to motion coming from the Siri
Remote and switch to that.
In using this we have a control
scheme that's very flexible
for players and allows
them to switch
as seamlessly as possible.
Now I'd like to end
this section by saying
that maybe these techniques
that I've shown you here can
be directly used by your game
or maybe they're a good starting
point and you can tweak them
and customize them to suit
your game just perfectly.
But in any case, I really
want to encourage you
to go beyond the mere mechanics
of controllers connecting
and disconnecting and
reading button values
and really thoughtfully
consider how you're going
to integrate game
controllers into your game.
Because when you get
this right in the mind
of the player game
controllers just melt away
and it really allows them
to become immersed by
and enjoy the game experiences
that you've worked
so hard to create.
And that's what games
are all about right.
So we've talked about
a lot today.
To summarize, we talked
about the Siri Remote how it
supports the GCMicroGamepad
profile in the GCMotion profile.
I talked about DPAD
windowing and allowsRotation.
I also talked about
the Menu button and how
on Apple TV the expected
behavior varies depending
on the context of your app.
And how you can use the
GCEventViewController
and control or pause handlers
to control that behavior.
I also talked about
MFi game controllers
that these use the
GCExtendedGamepad profile
that they introduce
pressure sensitivity
and that they can
now be required
as a controller for your game.
I also talked about
the TV Remote app
and how that's an emulated Siri
Remote from the perspective
of the Game Controller
framework.
And I talked about
Game Controller mode
of the Apple TV Remote app
and design considerations
so that your game
works as intended
for the Apple TV Remote app.
And lastly, I finished
up by talking
about multiple controllers
and how it's great
for multiplayer gaming, but it's
equally as important to consider
for single-player gaming.
Namely, allowing your players to
switch controllers as seamlessly
as you can for your game.
Here's the URL for this session.
You can find the
video, documentation
and code samples here.
This is session 607.
Related sessions include
Mastering UIKit on tvOS
and Designing for tvOS.
There's also a tvOS lab
for more general questions.
Thank you so much
for your attention
and have a wonderful
rest of your show.