[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Good afternoon and welcome
to Game Technologies
for Apple Watch.
I hope you've had a great WWDC
and are as excited as I am
about all the great
new technologies.
Gaming in iOS has captured
the imagination of users.
As a longtime gamer, I've
marveled at the vast array
of games created by
developers like you.
We've heard that you're
intrigued by the potential
for games on Apple Watch
so today we're pleased
to present gaming for watchOS 3.
This session covers everything
you need to create a great game
on this most personal device.
We will first show you
how to use various inputs
on Apple Watch and provide
feedback to your users.
We will then introduce you
to our graphics frameworks
that allow you to create
vibrant 2D and 3D visuals.
In addition we will show you
how to integrate social gaming
and multiplayer into your app.
And finally, we will show
you all the tools available
to use during development,
as well as some
of the best practices.
watchOS provides a rich set of
tools to help you get started.
This includes some things
you may be familiar with such
as WatchKit and rich
notification.
Today, however, we will
focus on what's new.
In WatchKit we offer new
interfaces that allow you
to create your game in Xcode
using Interface Builder.
You can now use just your
recognizers in the Digital Crown
for precise control
over your game.
There's also haptic feedback
which we think is a good way
to make your experience much
more personal and immersive.
SpriteKit and SceneKit
are frameworks
that let you create rich
visuals to delight your users.
They provide good
places to add audio
and form a simple foundation on
which you can build your game.
Game Center provides API's
for adding social features
to your game including
achievements,
leaderboards, and multiplayer.
But now let me show an
example of what's possible.
This is a game built
with SceneKit
which is our 3D framework.
You start out with a collection
of blocks of various shapes.
Your goal is to rotate them
until they form a
familiar silhouette.
Now let's watch this
for a moment.
When the player, and now
that the player has won,
we're going to play another
round and I'll talk a little bit
about what's happening here.
We use pan gestures to control
the left and right rotation.
And when it is in the same plane
we'll use the Digital Crown
to rotate it into
place for the win.
So now that we've introduced
gaming on Apple Watch
and showed a demo, let's dive
into how we can make your
game interact with a user
in a much more natural way.
Apple Watch is our
most intimate device.
We use it up close, usually with
one finger touching the screen
or rotating the crown.
You can read motion
from the accelerometer
or you can even make it
vibrate with a haptic engine.
When used together this
creates the sensation
that you're using a
physical device that operates
and responds in an
almost tangible way.
Let's start with touch.
On watchOS 3 we offer four
types of gestures that work well
for different kinds of
interactions in your game.
And I'd like to go
through those one by one.
Tap is the simplest.
You touch the screen and
you can select a target
or a position to move to.
Pan is nice scrolling
or for, you know,
movement in a given direction.
Swipe is good when you want
to navigate to another screen
such as your inventory menu,
and you can swipe back to exit.
Long press is a recommended way
to access your game's main menu.
And here you can provide
options such as quit, resume,
or even show Game Center stats.
Now that we've showed
you some examples
of the four gesture types, let's
talk about the classes we offer
for you to adopt these.
So for tap, we give you
WKTap Gesture Recognizer.
For pan, WKPan Gesture
Recognizer.
And similarly for swipe
and for long press.
Now these gestures are available
from Interface Builder.
When you go into the
Object Library and search
for Gesture you'll find
the ones available.
If you select one, you
can add it to your scene.
And in our example we've
added tap, swipe, and pan.
These gestures are various
options you can configure
such making it a right swipe,
or a left, or up or down.
These other options
configure various behavior.
Now if you're using multiple
gestures, you should look
at this last option
because it is important
to specify the priority.
And this is because
gestures can conflict.
And what do I mean
by a conflict?
Well, a right swipe
could also be interpreted
as a tap followed by a pan.
So you, as the developer,
have to decide
which of these takes priority.
And in a game a tap and a pan
represent interactions directly
with your game world.
And we'd rather have that
take priority over a swipe
that would take you
to your inventory.
So going back to Interface
Builder you configure this Must
Fail First field for
in the swipe gesture.
And you set tap and pan.
And this reflects our priority.
Now that we've added gestures
to our storyboard you need
to implement an action method.
This action method takes
the corresponding class
and there are various properties
you can read, for example,
location In Object and Bounds.
And this last one, state.
And I think state is best
shown in a code example.
So from that puzzle app I demoed
we have a handle pan action.
And the first thing we do is we
get the location and the bounds.
And then we look at the state
and if we've begun the pan,
we're going to set
up our rotation.
If we're in the middle of a
pan, it's either change, ended,
or cancelled, we will update it.
So I'd like to finish
up with the gestures
with some considerations.
Since the user is
wearing Apple Watch each
of these gestures
require both arms
so it's a good idea
to keep them short.
It's also important to
note that in comparison
to our other devices,
your finger is relatively
large compared to the screen.
So please take this into
account and make sure
that content remains visible
as you're interacting with it.
And finally, you know, our
user interface guidelines,
it recommends that we make
our gestures discoverable
so you should follow them.
Now many of you are probably
familiar with gestures
but now let's talk about
something that is unique
to Apple Watch and that
is the Digital Crown.
The interface guidelines
say this is good
for selection and scrolling.
But as a gamer, this harkens
back to arcade machines
with a physical dial
that can turn
to rotate a spaceship
or move a paddle.
Or in this example we can
move a ball back and forth
until we decide where
we want to put it.
And when we're ready we can
tap to drop it into position.
Adopting the crown
is really easy.
You access this Crown
Sequencer which is available
on your main interface class
and there are properties
you can read,
such as rotation per second
or whether we're idle.
Or you can define a delegate.
And this delegate
provides two methods.
crownDidRotate which
takes a rotationalDelta.
This rotational Delta represents
the change in the crown
since the last time
this method was called.
And it is positive if it's
moving away from the user
and negative if it's
moving towards you.
And this is true
whether Apple Watch is
on the left wrist
or the right wrist.
When the crown stops rotating
crownDidBecomeIdle gets called.
So to recap, we think Digital
Crown is great for games.
It's also really easy to adopt.
And I can't wait to see
what kind of games you make
with this new kind of control.
Now the accelerometer
provides a means
to enhance other
interactions, for example,
adding tilt on a
game of pinball,
or to add spin to a pool shot.
You access the accelerometer
through the CMMotionManager.
And there are some
considerations here.
As you probably know,
when you hold your watch
up here the screen is visible.
But when you lower your arm
to the side it goes blank.
When this happens it's going to
put the app in the background.
So as you move your wrist
the screen may go blank
so you should account for
that in your game playing.
And a recommendation here is
to use background processing.
You can call the method
in NSProcessInfo performExpiring
ActivityWithReason
to give your game loop
some time to continue
and give your user
a smooth experience.
Now let's show an example
of how to use this in code.
The first thing we need to do
is access the CMMotionManager
singleton so we set it as a
property here to use later.
Then in willActivate in
our main interface we ask
if the accelerometer is visible.
If it is, we configure things
like the Update Interval.
And then we ask the
motionManager
to start sending
us update events.
We provide a block that receives
these events and we can send it
to our game to give
the user feedback.
When we are done we should
tell the motion Manager
to stop sending us updates so
we can conserve battery life.
Now to recap, we feel the
accelerometer is a good place
to enhance other interactions.
Be aware that the
screen may blank
so consider using
background processing.
And also make sure that
you use it when it's needed
and you stop listening
when you're done.
Now let's consider haptics.
On iOS you could only
make your device vibrate.
On Apple Watch you can create
a much more personal experience
through the use of
distinct haptic patterns.
Each haptic consists of
a vibration accompanied
by a brief audio tone.
By using the sense
of touch and sound,
in addition to visual
cues on the screen,
you can create a
much more immersive,
interesting game experience.
We offer nine types
of haptic feedback.
I'd like to go through
a few examples
of how they might be
used in your game.
This is the notification haptic.
These magenta triangles
represent the time
when the haptic is vibrating.
The waveform represents the
audio sound that's played along
with it.
Let's hear how this sounds.
[ Audio Tone ]
As this example shows, the
notification haptic is good
for alerting people when
something important has happened
that requires their attention.
Now you get this for free if
you adopt rich notifications.
But when you're in a game
and you're exploring the world
you might use it tell the
player, "Your village
is under attack."
The direction haptics, up and
down, are used to alert people
when an important
value has increased
or decreased significantly.
So in this example,
[ Audio Tone ]
Your health is low.
Or when you drink
a health potion,
[ Audio Tone ]
You feel better.
There's also a tone for
starting an activity
such as beginning a race.
Or when you wish to pause.
[ Audio Tone ]
The success haptic provides
a confirmation tone.
And this is good for
something like --
[ Audio Tone ]
You won. Or if you didn't
make it, please try again.
And as a final example, there's
a very subtle click haptic.
This haptic is a bit special.
As you can see, it's
much quieter
and shorter than the others.
In fact, I'm not sure if you'll
be able to hear the audio
but let's give it a shot.
This haptic provides the
sensation of a dial clicking
at defined increments
or intervals.
In a game this might be nice
for picking a lock on a chest
or giving the user feedback
that they have bumped
into an obstacle.
Now that I've given some
examples I want to just point
out that it's really easy to
adopt these haptic events.
You call play and you pass
in the constant for the type
that you desire and the
feeling you wish to evoke.
And let me finish
up with haptics
with some considerations.
The Taptic Engine differs
from conventional audio
in that you can only play
one haptic at a time.
Also note that these
effects serve
to draw attention
to important events.
And their effectiveness
diminishes if you have
to make the watch
vibrate constantly.
So please exercise restraint
and I think you'll have a
really awesome experience here.
So to recap, we discussed
gesture recognizers
and some ideas for
using them in the game.
We showed how you can
incorporate the crown
for compelling game play.
We described how to incorporate
the accelerometer into your app.
And finally, we discussed
using haptic feedback
to make your game
more immersive.
And now I'd like to hand
it off to Fatima to talk
about our graphics frameworks.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Christy.
Hi, everyone.
My name is Fatima and in this
section we're going to talk
about our graphics frameworks,
SpriteKit, and SceneKit
that you can use to make really
cool games on Apple Watch.
So what are SpriteKit
and SceneKit?
SpriteKit and SceneKit are
Apple's 2D and 3D frameworks
for games and graphics.
You can use either
framework in your game
or you can even combine
them together.
They are easy to
use and they come
with great integrated
tools and editors in Xcode.
They are available
on macOS, iOS, tvOS,
and this year they are
available on watchOS.
On Apple Watch SpriteKit and
SceneKit are bringing you
for the first time
GPU accelerated,
real-time rendering.
And this will enable you to
make really dynamic content
and also make your games
really interactive.
So now let's look at
some of the cool features
that you can use on Apple Watch.
And we're going to
start with animations.
You can create 2D animations
in SpriteKit with SKAction.
And you can create 3D animations
in SceneKit with SDNAction
to make your games interactive.
You can use actions to move,
rotate, and scale your objects
by either applying a single
action or applying a sequence
of actions to make more
complex animations.
Next we have particles.
You can create particle
simulations in both SpriteKit
and SceneKit to add interesting
effects to your game.
Using particle simulations you
can simulate fire, snow, rain,
and many, many other
interesting effects.
Next we have physics.
Both SpriteKit and SceneKit
have integrated physics
to make your game
even more interesting.
You can turn on physics
for your object
and then define properties
on them like mass,
velocity, and friction.
These properties will then
define how your objects move,
how they respond to
collisions, and how they react
to forces in your simulation.
Next we have lighting.
You can also add light
sources to your game.
And lights is just
another node in your scene.
So now you can apply actions
on it to move it around.
And one cool feature here
that we have for lighting is
that you can automatically
generate your normal maps
using SKTextures.
Next we have camera.
Both SpriteKit and SceneKit
have a camera that you can use.
And if you decide
to use a camera,
then we will render the scene
from the camera's position.
So the camera is really the
center of your viewport.
And the camera is also just like
any other node in your scene.
So now you can move it around
by applying actions on it.
Next we have shapes and text.
Text can be added as
a node to your game.
So now it is really
easy to display text
and also apply actions
and physics on it.
We also have shape nodes so
now you can also create dynamic
and geometric shapes
in your game.
And we also have
programmable shaders
in both SpriteKit and SceneKit.
You can create shaders
in SpriteKit
and you can create shader
modifiers in SceneKit
to achieve most custom
looks to your game elements.
So now that we have seen
some of the cool features
that you can use, let's
see how exactly SpriteKit
and SceneKit are
different on Apple Watch.
And I'm going to
start with SpriteKit.
So in SpriteKit we
have an SKView
that we use to present
our scene.
And our scene can
contain many nodes.
For example, we have
SKSprite Node to add sprites.
We have SKLight Node
to add lighting.
And we have SKEmitter Node
to create particle systems.
On watchOS a few
things are different.
First, we don't have an
SKView but now we have
to use WKInterface SKScene
to present our scene.
We also don't have CIFilters but
we can achieve the same effects
with using an SKShader.
We don't have positional audio
but we can play sounds just
like any other platform
using SKAction playSound.
And finally, we don't
have SKVideo Node
but we can use WKInterface
Movie to play a video.
And this table summarizes the
differences for SpriteKit.
For SceneKit we almost
have the same differences.
Instead of SCNView now we have
to use WKInterface SCNScene.
We don't have positional audio
but we do have standard audio.
And we don't have
access to CIFilters
but we can use Shader Modifiers
to achieve the same effects.
So now let's walk
through an example
of creating a game
target on Apple Watch
for an already existing
iOS game.
And here I am using the
SpriteKit template on iOS.
On the left we can
see our project files
and we can take a look
at our game scene.
And we can see here that we are
using a really simple scene.
We can also take a look at
our GameView Controller.
And we can see here that
we are using an SKView
to present our scene.
Now to create a game target on
Apple Watch all we have to do is
to click File, New Target.
Choose the Game App
template under watchOS.
Give it a name and
then press Finish.
Now this template created two
folders for us: The app folder
which contains our storyboard
and our extension folder
which contains our Interface
Controller and our game scenes.
So now let's take a
look at our storyboard.
And this is our storyboard
and we can see
that we have our interface
object in the middle.
And our interface
object was selected
from our object library.
And here we can see
that we have the options
between choosing
a SceneKit Scene
to display SceneKit content
and a SpriteKit Scene
to display SpriteKit content.
Also our interface object
has an outlet defined
in our Interface
Controller so we can use it
to present our scenes.
So let's take a look at that.
And this is that
Interface Controller.
And now let's take a
closer look at this code.
And here we see that we
have our interface object
and in awake(withContext
we can see
that we are loading
the scene just
like the way we do within iOS.
And finally we are using
the interface object
to present our scene
just like the way we did
within an SKView in iOS.
And these are all the steps that
you need to create a game target
on Apple Watch for an
already existing iOS game.
And now I'm going to
hand it over to Christy
to go over social gaming.
[ Applause ]
>> Christy Warren:
Thank you, Fatima.
Now let's talk about
Game Center.
Today games are a lot about
encouraging engagement
and competition with friends.
Game Center makes it easy to
share achievements and scores
or even play a game together.
For multiplayer on
Apple Watch we'll focus
on turn-based gaming.
Turn-based gaming is something
that we think is a really
excellent match for Apple Watch.
It supports brief
interactions and there's no need
for both players to be present.
I can take a turn and when
I'm done I can pass it to you.
You'll get a rich notification
and you may take the
turn at your leisure.
There are various details on how
to implement a turn-based game
that we've talked
about in past years.
But today we'll highlight
what is unique to Apple Watch.
For other details please
review our documentation
or view past sessions.
I'd also like to call out
some great new features
for Game Center in iOS 10 that
were covered this morning.
And if you didn't catch that,
I'd encourage you to
watch it on video.
To get started on making
a turn-based game let's
talk authentication.
It is simpler than iOS
in that you do not need
to enter a password
on the Apple Watch.
When you sign in on the phone
you're automatically signed
in on Apple Watch.
Also if you're familiar
with Game Center for iOS,
you may be aware of a View
Controller that you get
and you have to present
under some circumstances.
On iOS -- I mean on Watch
OS -- that is not necessary.
Now let's show this in code.
For those of you not
familiar with Game Center,
there is the GKLocal Player
singleton which is sort
of the focus of our API's.
In this case we sent an
authentication Handler
and this gets called
when authentication
completes either successfully
or with an error.
If you succeed, you can
give the user feedback
if they have signed in and
you can start game play.
Now that we've authenticated you
can create a turn-based match.
An important decision
here is how to match
up with other players.
Now the easiest way here is
to let Game Center pick
the other player for you
and this is called Automatch.
Alternatively, you can load
a list of recent players
and invite one programmatically.
So let's start with Automatch.
Here you create a
GKMatchRequest.
You pass it to the method find,
the class method find
on GKTurnBasedMatch.
And when this returns it gives
you a new turn-based match
instance that you can use
to store your data
and play your game.
Now please be aware that
this may be a new match or,
if Norman created a
game and took his turn,
I may be joining his
game in an open slot.
So your game needs to take
into account both cases.
So let's show this in code.
You create your Match
Request and you set parameters
such as the maximum number of
players and you call a find.
When that succeeds you
can start your game.
It's really that easy.
And programmatic invites
are almost identical.
You just set another parameter
here which is recipients
and that is from a list of
players that you've chosen.
However, to do this you need
to access a list of players
who you can play with.
So I'll show you some
sample code for this.
This shows you how to access
the recent players list.
And a good place to -- and
let's suppose you have a class.
There's a player picker
that will let you
pick from this list.
So in awake we can call
on the Local Player
singleton loadRecentPlayers.
And this assumes that you've
previously authenticated
in your main interface.
And we call loadRecentPlayers
and you receive a list
of players that you, you know,
you have played with recently
on phone, or pad, or on
watch through Automatch.
Now it's important to mention
that once we've loaded this
and saved it away you need to
pick it, pick your opponent.
So in order to help you
present this list of players
and give you a head start on
building a turn-based game,
we've created a sample
app, HelloGameKit,
that implements the basics
of a turn-based game.
It's also built on the
new SpriteKit template.
And as a bonus it
will demonstrate how
to use gesture recognizers.
So I'd like to walk
you through a brief,
briefly walk through
this example.
When you launch the app it
brings up a screen like this
and it says, "Authenticating."
When the authenticate completes
it shows your display name
on the top and gives you a place
to pick your opponent
on the bottom.
This counter in the middle
counts the various taps
that you've made
and records them
and saves them into
the game model.
This is just a simple thing
that will save an error
in turn-based match.
Now if you've tapped Pick
an Opponent on the bottom,
it'll bring up a player
picker that loads the list
of recent players and
lets you pick one.
It also gives you the
option to Automatch
but in this case I
want to play with Alan.
So now he's playing with me.
If I want to access the list
of matches, I can swipe left
and I'll get the Match Browser.
Here I can create a
new match with Alan
or I can pick an existing game.
So I'm going to go
back to that game.
And finally, I can end
my turn with a long press
and that will pass it to Alan
and he can take his turn.
So that's HelloGameKit.
You can download it under
the developers' site
under Session 612.
Click on the Resources
tab to find that sample.
So to recap, Game Center
in watchOS gives you
streamlined authentication.
It is a programmatic API but
we give you the sample app
that has UI for all the
things that you need to do.
So we hope that will
give you a good start.
So with that I'd like to
hand it over to Tyler to talk
about tools and best practices.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Christy.
So now you've been
introduced to some
of the frameworks you have
available on Apple Watch.
Let's talk about tools.
Many of you may be
familiar with our rich set
of game tools already
available inside of Xcode.
And I'm happy to
tell you that all
of these tools are
also available for you
for your Apple Watch
development.
This includes our scene
editor which takes the process
of setting up and laying
out your scene from code
and moves it into a visual
editor right inside of Xcode.
So instead of repeatedly
compiling and iterating
on a positioning of your
scene, you're able to see
and manipulate exactly where
your nodes will be placed.
And on top of that you're able
to easily manipulate
the hierarchy
of your scene using the scene
outline views, and create
and modify your physics
bodies for your nodes,
all without touching
a single line of code.
Now our scene editors
also include a built
in action editor.
This lets you easily
create, modify,
and preview complex reusable
animations right inside
of your level.
So whether you're creating
a complex cut scene
to introduce your level
or a character animation
that you'll be reusing
throughout your code,
it's all easily possible
with this action editor.
Now as you're developing
your game you're going
to find the powerful particle
engines of both SpriteKit
and SceneKit are going
to play an important role
in bringing your game to life.
But creating that
perfect particle
for your game can be difficult
if you're not able
to visualize it.
And fortunately we provide you
a flexible tool for creating
and visualizing your particles.
So you're allowed access to
the huge number of properties
that we have on our particles
so that you can see
their effect immediately
as they are changing them.
And we also have tools to help
you maintain great performance
in Apple Watch.
This includes our
texture atlases.
When you place your images
within a Sprite atlas
we'll automatically rotate
and reposition them to
form a single image.
This reduces the number of draw
calls your game needs to make.
And what's great about this is
that nothing changes
for you in code.
You're still able to
operate on these textures
as if they're individual files.
And when your game is running
we now provide you an SPF
Performance Gauge.
And at the top of the report
you're provided a number
of real-time statistics.
This includes your
current frame rate,
as well as your GP
utilization to see which parts
of your GP are being
used the most.
And your frame time for
both the CPU and the GPU.
And this will help indicate
whether you may CPU bound
or GPU bound.
Now in addition to
real-time statistics,
we also provide you
a timeline history
of our CPU and GPU frame times.
And what's great about
this is that will break
down your CPU frame times
into their individual parts
so you're able to see
exactly how much time it spent
rendering, or running
your update loop,
or evaluating actions
in physics,
as well as how much
time is spent idle.
And when your app is paused you
can scroll through the history
of your app's performance so
you can see how it evolves
as you progress through
your game.
And if there's a particular
interest you can dive deeper
and examine details on it
and get some exact timings.
So now there's some best
practices that you can take
to make sure that you're going
to get great performance
on Apple Watch.
A great way to reduce your
battery consumption is
to avoid updating your
scene unless you need to.
Both SpriteKit and SceneKit will
now automatically skip rendering
if we detect nothing has
changed within your scene.
And if you're working with large
assets, you should load them
at the start of your scenes
but you don't experience
any hiccups due
to loading those
assets throughout parts
of your game you
expect to be fluid.
And you should also aim for
a frame rate that's going
to provide a consistent
experience for your users.
And you can do this
by explicitly setting your
interfaces' preferred frames
per second.
Now if you do find that you're
experiencing performance issues,
there's a number of measures
that you can take to address it.
And the first being to reduce
the number of particles present
within your scene
at any given time.
You'd also try reducing
the details of your assets
that may be far in the
distance or scaled greatly.
And what' great about this is
you often won't see any change
in your game's visual fidelity
by making that reduction.
And if you're still
seeing issues,
try reducing the complexity
of your scene until you find
that right balance between
performance and content.
Now as you're developing
your game
on Apple Watch there's a number
of design considerations
you should keep
in mind throughout
your development.
Apple Watch, you shouldn't
simply be taking your iOS games
experience and scaling it down.
We want you to be
rethinking the experience.
And the Apple Watch
really lends itself
to lightweight interactions.
Users love to be able
to see the progress
of their game at a glance.
And you should be
designing your interactions
around someone who is on the go.
In addition, you're going to
want an interface that's concise
and simple, and should avoid
displaying too much information,
or being too busy on
the screen at once.
You may even want to
spread out your interactions
across multiple screens so
that you can maximize your
screen space.
And if you have any
buttons or touch targets,
make sure they're large enough
so that your users can
comfortably interact with them.
And you should also aim
to maintain visual
continuity with your app.
What that means is
transitioning from one app
into yours should feel like
a consistent experience.
And part of that can be
to select a color tint
that supports your game's brand
to use throughout your game.
Now we also recommend that
when possible you use a black
background for your game.
And what's great about this is
that the black will
blend seamlessly
with Apple Watch's bezel and
create this great illusion
of having an edgeless screen.
So now you've been
introduced to some
of the awesome input you have
available on Apple Watch,
and the great frameworks
that you can use
to develop your game, and a rich
set of tools that you can use
for your development workflow.
We can't wait to see
what kind of exciting
and fun games you're going to be
making on Apple Watch this year.
If you'd like more information,
please visit the Developer Site
and you can find us
under session ID 612.
And there's been a lot
of great information
from sessions previously
in the week.
This includes What's
New in SpriteKit,
What's New in Game Center,
Advances in SceneKit Rendering,
and Quick Interaction
Techniques for watchOS.
So if you want to dive
deeper into any of the areas
that we touched on today,
we highly recommend you
take a look at these.
And thank you and I
hope you enjoy the rest
of your conference.
[ Applause ]