[ Music ]
>> All right.
Welcome. My name is Eric Tamura.
I'm accompanied by Dominic
Giampaolo and we're going
to tell you a little bit
about Apple file systems.
[ Applause ]
All right so this is going to
be a little bit of our roadmap
for our presentation today.
I'll tell you a little bit about
introduction and motivation.
Why we decided to build this.
Some of the new features
that we've added
as part of Apple File System.
We'll do a short demo,
some of the new features.
And then we'll wrap it
up with some new APIs
that you can use in your apps.
Okay, let's start it.
So as Sebastian mentioned,
Apple File System is available
in the WWDC build
of macOS Sierra
that you all got yesterday.
And it will be available as a
developer preview technology
in macOS Sierra once it
finally ships this fall.
So what is Apple File System?
It's our next generation
file system
that we've been building
for Apple products.
And you might care about
this because it will run
on watchOS, iOS, tvOS and macOS.
So as far as the
intended audience here,
we expect that some of you may
be either new to the platforms,
or you're a long time developer,
but we intend to cover all
of the high level of the new
file system in enough detail
so you can follow along.
So, one of the hallmarks of
this product is that we wanted
to scale from an Apple Watch
all the way up to a Mac Pro.
We also wanted to take advantage
of Flash and SSD storage,
because nearly all of
our products use SSDs.
And finally it's been built with
encryption as a primary feature
from the very beginning as we
brought this idea to fruition.
So you might be wondering
what about HFS+.
Well, we are currently shipping
HFS+ as our primary file system.
But its original design
is almost 30 years old
at this point.
So how many of you would like us
to ship HFS+ for
another 30 years?
Great. So HFS+ which
was designed in an era
where floppies and hard
drives were state of the art,
and the world has
changed since then.
We now use SSDs and other next
generation storage technologies
evolving as well.
The data structures in HFS+ were
also relatively single treaded,
so our B-trees are relying
on a big block in order
to access or mutate them.
And the data structures
are also relatively rigid.
And by this we mean things
like the file record,
or catalog record in HFS+,
which is more or less equivalent
to an inode in other filed
systems, is fixed in order
to add new fields, to
expand the file system,
give it new features, we
would have to incur the cost
of a backwards, incompatible
volume format change.
And by this we mean what happens
if we add a new feature to HFS+
and take it all the way back
to 10.5 and try to attach
that same file system?
What will happen?
So if we're concerned about
backwards compatibility as well
as forwards compatibility
we're starting to think
about well maybe it makes sense
to build something
completely new altogether.
And so we thought
about something new.
So we wanted something
that was designed
and tuned specifically
for Apple products.
And other file systems
serve other purposes
and they do it well.
In particular filers
or enterprise level storage
servers have a lot of features
that might not make
sense on Apple products.
We typically use a
single storage device all
of our products.
And we have a wide
range of scale.
So on an Apple Watch, you have
significantly DRAM and storage
than does a Mac Pro, which
has tens of gigabytes
of DRAM potentially, and
terabytes of storage.
So we wanted something
that's flexible and dynamic
and that's the platform
on which it's running.
So other things we wanted to
build, we wanted to add new
and enhanced security
capabilities.
So on iOS today we already
shipped a version of HFS+
that uses per file encryption.
So every file is
encrypted differently
on storage form every other
file on the file system.
We want to take that a step
further and we'll dive into some
of those features a little bit
later on in the presentation.
And finally, we just wanted
to add some new general
file system features
that have been requested
and that we learned
were really important
for the future of our platforms.
So before we get into these
new features, I just wanted
to give you a brief
view of the landscape
of what storage software
looks like at Apple.
And so in terms of file systems
and storage, we talk about HFS+,
but it's actually not just HFS+
in the little small bubble,
there's actually many
ancillary technologies
that comprise our
storage software.
So in the beginning, we
had HFS standard, almost,
you know over 30 years
ago at this point.
We then added HFS+, some
number of years later.
But we added crash
protection to it.
So we gave it a journal of
case sensitive variant as well.
We also added core storage which
gives us full disk encryption
as well as our fusion drive,
which combines the speed
of an SSD with the
capacity of a hard drive.
And let's not forget all of
the iOS specific variants.
We have an iOS specific
variant of HFS+ as well as one
that supports the
per file encryption
that we just discussed.
So our intention is that all
of these technologies will
get replaced by one thing,
which is Apple File System.
So, let me tell you a
little bit about some
of the new features
in Apple File System.
So, this is a brief view of
what we've got on deck here,
so we've got some improved
file system fundamentals,
HFS compatibility, Space
Sharing, cloning files
and directories, snapshots,
and reverting to snapshots.
A feature we're calling
fast directory sizing.
Atomic safe save
primitives and encryption.
So you don't have to
memorize all of these,
we will go into greater
detail of all of these
in the upcoming slides.
So, first let's talk about some
of the improved fundamentals.
So first it's been
Flash and SSD optimized.
So on all of our devices, you
know on all of our iOS devices,
but a lot of our Macs we ship
with SSDs so we want to be
as friendly to the solid
state drives as we know how.
It's also crash protected, APFS,
or Apple File System
employs a new and novel copy
and write metadata scheme so
every metadata write is written
into a new location
on stable storage.
We combine this with a
transaction subsystem
which ensures that if you lose
power, if the machine panics,
or anything bad happens, you'll
either see a consistent view
of what was on disk or you
won't see it at all, the change.
We have modern 64-bit
native fields,
so the inode number has
been expanded to 64-bits.
We have timestamps
that are now 64-bits.
We support nanosecond
time stamp granularity.
We also support Sparks
Files for the first time
on an Apple File System.
And all of our file and
directory records that point
at where the blocks
actually live
on disks have been
expanded to 64-bits.
Our data structures
were also expansible
and allowed for future growth.
So one thing that we
talked about HFS+ is
that its data structures
are relatively rigid.
And at APFS, or Apple File
System, the data structures
that represent the core
inode are now flexible.
So fields are either optional,
or we may not have
invented them yet.
So new fields that we may
choose to add down the line,
will be correctly
recognized as not supported,
or I don't understand if
you attach that storage
to today's version
of macOS Sierra.
In this way we can add
new features without fear
of harming backwards
compatibility.
This also allow us to
have optional fields.
So on some systems,
having the mere presence
of a file is enough to
convey some information.
And so if you have a 0-byte file
you don't necessarily need all
the machinery that points at
which blocks live on disks,
because they're needed.
So those fields are optional.
It's also been optimized for
our Apple Software ecosystems.
So we wanted to add features
and optimize the APIs
that are extremely compelling
for our platforms
moving forward.
And we also have a
low latency design.
And typically in file systems
latency is often a tradeoff
between latency and throughput.
And we've chosen to lean
on the side of latency.
And we do this because we want
your apps when a user clicks
on them on the desktop,
or they tap on them
on your phone you want it to
come up quickly and responsively
and have very crisp animation.
And the reason for that is when
you go down to the file system,
we want to ensure that we
get you the answers you need
as quickly as possible.
And finally we have native
encryption support built
into the file system.
On HFS+ as we mentioned, it
uses per file encryption,
but those are stored on disk
through extended attributes.
On Apple File System that's not
the case these are now first
class citizens, first class
objects inside the file system.
So that's a bit about
the fundamentals.
So HFS compatibility, if all
of you have apps that run
on HFS+ just fine, we intend
for those to continue to run
without any changes
whatsoever on your side.
So Apple File System
will support
and replace HFS+ functionality.
And there's an asterisks there
because there's three things
that we will not
support moving forward.
One of them is exchange
data, the other search FS,
and the third is directory
hard links for time machine.
But every other API and
behavior will be supported just
as it is on HFS+.
So now I want to tell you a
little bit about Space Sharing
which is one of the
features that we've added
into Apple File System.
So let's take a quick
poll how many of you
in the audience have a
Mac or have used a Mac
with more than one partition?
Okay, great.
We do as well, one of the
things that we do internally,
is we want a development
version of OS on one partition,
and we want you know the stable
released version on another.
Or you might choose to have
your home directory on one
and other different data that
you don't care about in another.
But one of the things that we've
learned through our analytics
that come back when users
opt in to data collection
and reporting their
statistics to Apple machines is
that most end users
don't do this.
They just have the
one partition.
And the reason they don't
is because it's hard.
You have to know exactly
how you're going to lay
out your disk at the
time you set it up,
and changing it is
relatively expensive.
Moreover, free space
on one partition,
as you know does not translate
into available free space
on another partition.
So we're solving this
with a feature we're
calling Space Sharing.
So let's take an example
here, we'll work through this
as we kind of explain
the feature.
Let's say you're
downloading the latest
and greatest cat video you
just got of the internet
from your friend
over at AirDrop.
And let's say that file
grows, and it gets bigger,
in fact so big that you've
completely run out of space
on the partition on
which you're running.
Well there's not a whole
lot you can do in this case.
If you're out of space,
you're out of space.
One thing you could do though is
completely destroy the partition
immediately afterwards
and then grow partition 1.
So let's look at that.
We can destroy partition
2, partition 1 grows,
and now you have enough space to
continue growing your cat video.
But this is also inflexible
and presents a little bit
of a problem if the file that
you're downloading wasn't
on partition 1, but it was
in fact on partition 0.
So in this case, you're going
to grow the file,
it will get bigger.
And then even if
you have free space,
or content that you're willing
to destroy on partition 2,
we could destroy it, but then
partition 0 couldn't grow,
because it's not adjacent
to any of the free space
that we just made available.
So we think this is something
that we can solve
with Space Sharing.
So in Apple File
System we've come
up with this base concept
we're calling the container,
applicably named because
it contains volumes
or individual file systems.
So, in this instance, Apple File
System containers represent the
lowest level of functionality.
And this is what encapsulates
our block allocator,
as well as our crash
protection subsystem.
So let's say we have volume
0, which occupies some amount
of free space in the partition,
volume can grow,
or it can shrink.
But in all these cases the free
space will dynamically resize
to what's currently available
at the time that you request it.
You can also create more than
one volume in the container
which will occupy
incrementally more space.
And then if you wanted to
grow partition or volume 0,
at this point you could do so.
And now if you ask for how
much free space is available
on the system you will
get the area that's
in the green rectangle
at the bottom.
So developers take note, this
is something that's a little bit
subtly different from how you
may have computed free space
in the past.
If you're using some paradigm
like taking a total storage
size, subtracting the used space
to get the free space,
that will no longer work,
because other volumes
on the container are also
participating in Space Sharing.
Additionally, you can't
necessarily add up all
of the used space either.
So, next, I'm going to invite
Dominic up and he will tell you
about cloning files
and directories.
[ Applause ]
>> Hi. Again my name is
Dominic and I'm going to walk
through a couple of the
other higher level features
that we have in APFS.
First, we're going
to talk about cloning
of files and directories.
So here we have a file, TOP
SECRET APFS.key, that Eric has
in his home directory.
And it has references
to two blocks of data.
Now if Eric wanted to make an
archive of this presentation
as it existed at this point in
time, he could copy the data
by reading it all in,
and writing it back out.
That has obvious
costs in terms of CPU,
power, and disk space usage.
Instead with APFS you
can clone the file.
By cloning the file,
you copy the references
to the data instead
of the actual data.
So it's obviously much faster
and if it's a large file,
you're not using twice
the amount of space,
you're using exactly
the same amount
of space plus a small
incremental amount
for the additional
references to the data.
What a clone guarantees
in the file system is
that if a modification is
made to either the original
or the clone, the
file system will write
that data to a new location.
So the clone remains untouched.
So this is an important
point to be aware of.
When you have clones, you
will, at the time of the clone,
you're not using any
additional space.
As you continue to make
modifications, you will start
to use more and more space.
In addition, because APFS, or
iOS and macOS support document
in application bundles,
APFS will also allow you
to clone an entire
directory hierarchy.
So a document bundle is a
directory which contains a set
of files inside of it.
APFS can clone that
atomically as well.
Next let's talk about snapshots.
Here, we have another
representation
of a file system
with two files in it.
BikeRacing and CoffeeOrigins.
BikeRacing has two
blocks of data.
And CoffeeOrigins has one.
If we take snapshot of the file
system, we now have a separate,
independently mountable, read
only copy of the file system
that represents this data the
file system at the point in time
that the snapshot was taken.
Much like with clones,
if a write comes
into the live file system, the
file system will put that data
in a new location preserving
the integrity of the snapshot.
Likewise, if we were to delete
CoffeeOrigins.key to try to free
up some space, the file system
can't reclaim those blocks
because as you can see
the snapshot continues
to refer to those blocks.
This is an important
consideration
that developers need to be aware
of when working with snapshots
because when a file is deleted,
if it was present at the time
of a snapshot, the
blocks aren't reclaimed.
So snapshots can cause you
to use all of your disk space
if you don't harvest
them periodically.
We expect that developers
will probably use snapshots
for the purposes of having a
stable read only copy from which
to perform a backup, but we're
looking for other feedback
from developers on other uses
that they might have
for snapshots.
So please come see us
in the lab at 12:30.
Let us know what you would
like to do with snapshots.
Now let's talk about
reverting to a snapshot.
And this is another
feature that APFS supports.
So we have the same state of the
file system here but we decide
that well, we don't like
this, we'd like to revert,
essentially a global undo.
We want to go back to the point
in time of the file system
at the time the snapshot
was taken.
So you can flag a
file system to revert
to the state of a snapshot.
And the next time it's mounted,
the file system will rewind,
essentially to the point it was
at the time of the snapshot.
And then allow you to
continue making changes
from that point forward.
So, again, you can see that
CoffeeOrigins.key came back
and the change that was made
to the other file
has been discarded.
The snapshot continues to
exist and you can revert
as many times as you would like.
All right.
Now let's talk about
fast directory sizing.
This is an answer
to the question how much space
does a directory hierarchy use.
Now applications frequently
need to compute this size
for sizing an operation to
provide progress to the user.
And the obvious way
to do this is
to open the directory hierarchy
iterate all the contents
recursively and look at the size
of all the items
to add the size up.
Of course users would
really like to know
that answer a little
bit more quickly.
On this next slide, if you focus
your attention on the left side
of the screen, when the
get info panel comes up,
you'll see it says,
calculating size.
And after a couple of seconds
it populates with the size.
That's what we're
looking to improve.
So, the file system
could keep track of this.
Obviously you could store the
size of the directory hierarchy
with the directory itself,
but that has one main issue,
how do you safely
update copy your parent
and its parents on up the chain.
So we're just delving a little
bit into file system internals,
but when you have a lock on a
child when you're modifying it,
you can't also lock your parent,
because that's a
lock order violation.
File system always lock
from the parent to child,
never from the child
to the parent.
And so if you start doing it
the other way you have deadlock.
So APFS instead sidesteps
the problem.
If the problem is storing
the size with the directory,
well let's store the
size somewhere else.
So by storing the
size separately,
we can use atomic
operations to update the size
in a separate record that's
maintained by the file system.
And we don't have any
lock order violations.
This comes at a small
incremental cost
for the additional size records,
but that's basically lost
in the noise with the IO.
All right.
Next, we're going to talk about
atomic safe-save primitives.
The first example is
just a basic file.
This is how safe-save works
for a regular file today.
So here I have
MakeMonneyFast.key.
And I come up with some
brilliant new scheme
for making money fast.
And when the application
saves that data, it's written
to a temporary location
off on the side.
When the application is happy
that everything has been written
and is safe out on disk,
it will ask the file system
to perform a rename.
Now renames of files
have always been atomic.
The file system guarantees that
it either happens completely,
and it's safe, or it
doesn't happen at all.
In addition, the file system
will handle deleting the
previous version
of the document.
So that's great for regular
files, but what happens
if you have a document bundle?
So here we have a document
bundle ClutchConcertReview.rtfd,
which is a directory
that contains the assets
of the document inside of it.
And what happens today is
let's say I go see Clutch play
and they play a really great
show and I update my review,
that change is written out,
but now what commences
is there's no way
to do an atomic rename
of a directory over top
of another directory, because
POSIX semantics don't allow
that if the destination
has something inside of it.
So, we begin playing
a shell game.
First, the document is moved out
of the way, the live document.
So at this point, if
something were to go wrong
and the application crashed,
or the system lost
power, users data is gone.
Then, the application moves the
data into place, and last it has
to handle deleting
the previous version
of the directory,
the document bundle.
So this is not atomic
and it's not safe.
And this is something
that has kind of bugged us
for a very long time and
we wanted to improve it.
With APFS we introduced a
new system called renamex np
for non POSIX, which
allows an atomic safe-save
of the directory.
So now, when the
application writes the data
to its temporary location,
and asks to perform the
rename operation APFS
with atomically handle the swap
and deleting the previous
version of the document.
So this is now atomic and safe.
Of course as a developer, you
probably won't have to resort
to this low-level of system call
because it's already been
adopted by Foundation for you.
So you just get the benefit of
this improved behavior on APFS.
[ Applause ]
Next, I'm going to
talk about encryption.
So as Eric mentioned, with HFS+,
on the Mac we use a
layer called Core storage
that sits beneath HFS,
and provides full disk
encryption among other things.
It's a rather sophisticated
layer,
and it does a lot of things.
On iOS, we have a
different variant
that stores encryption keys and
extended attributes that work.
And those encryption
keys work in conjunction
with the accelerated AES
hardware found on iOS devices
to provide per file encryption.
It's a kind of complicated story
with two rather different
code bases.
And with APFS, we
were looking to try
and provide a more
complete story
across all of our products.
So APFS supports multiple levels
of file system encryption.
But first, the easiest level
we got this working day one,
is no encryption.
All data is written in
plain text, all data
and metadata is written
in plain text to disk.
The next level is to
have one key per volume.
So all sensitive metadata
and data are encrypted
with the same key.
This is essentially
the equivalent
of full disk encryption.
The most sophisticated level
that we support is
multi-key encryption.
Here, sensitive Metadata
is encrypted
with a single key that's
distinct from the per file keys
that are used in
encrypting individual files.
In addition, because of how
snapshots and clones work,
APFS supports per
extent encryption.
So each region of a file can
be encrypted with its own key.
This is unique and
no other file system
out there supports
anything like this.
In addition, this allows us
to unify our encryption story
across all of our platforms.
All right and with that I'll
turn it back over to Eric.
[ Applause ]
>> Okay so now I'm going
to show you a quick demo
of Apple File System on MacOS
Sierra using the WWDC build.
So probably the easiest
and fastest way
to start experimenting
with Apple File System
is to use a disk image.
So we're going to do that first.
So, you can see on the command
line here I've typed hdiutil
create-fs APFS which specifies
create me a disk image
of type APFS, we give it
a size and we're going
to do a sparse bundle.
So it's going to warn you here,
because this is an
in-development project
and we want you to be aware
that you are using something
that's not completed 100% yet.
So, at this point it will
prompt me, I'll say yes.
And you've created the disk
image, which if I attach.
You can examine that on
the desktop, do a get info.
You can see that in fact the
file system type is the APFS.
So that's probably the
easiest way if you want
to just get something
and try it out.
So next I want to show
you some of the other,
more advanced features
that we've added.
I'll close that.
So here I have two thumb sticks.
These are just ordinary
thumb sticks.
You can get them at any
standard office supply store.
So I will plug in one.
One is formatted as HFS+
and the other is formatted
as Apple File System.
So we'll also do
a get info on both
so you can watch the free
space as it manipulates.
So at this point I have some
demo photos of a trip to Italy.
And there's a good
amount of storage in both
of those directory hierarchies.
But first we're going to start
by copying this latest copy
of iTunes in the HFS volume
and then we'll do the
same thing in APFS.
So start the copy, as that goes.
You can see the progress
bar there,
but APFS already finished.
Because it uses the
clone under the cover.
So finder has already adopted
all of the new cloning behavior.
So if you do a copy and finder
it will automatically clone
for you behind the scenes.
And HFS still hasn't
finished yet.
[ Applause ]
Okay, so I could do the same
thing with the demo photos,
which you can look in here,
there's several photos,
they're all several
megabytes in size.
Pay attention to the free space
up here, 3.35-gigabytes free.
So if I do a copy, it's actually
going to do a clone for me
and you notice the free space
actually did not decrease
at all.
So next, I'm going to
show taking a snapshot.
So this uses the tool
called SnapshotUtil
which will be available
in the public data once
that releases to everybody.
Oh, sorry this needs
to be run as root.
Okay so now I've
created a snapshot,
I can examine it
with Snapshotutil-s.
And you can see that it
now knows about APFS Snap.
So I've created a map point,
already before this session.
So I will mount this
snapshot at this time.
And you can see that
the snapshot showed
up on the desktop and this
contains a read only view
of the file system as
it exists at the time
that I just took it, so.
[ Applause ]
So now in the APFS volume,
I'm going to create
a temporary file,
hello I am a temporary file.
Save that, close it.
You can see that
it showed up here
in that APFS volume this
is mounted read write.
But it's not there
in the snapshot.
Correspondingly, I
can also delete some
of these demo photos.
I'll move them to the
trash and then delete them.
The free space actually
still does not decrease,
because now they're pinned by
the presence of the snapshot.
So if I wanted to delete
them I would also have
to delete the snapshot.
Okay, so that's just
a quick peak
of Apple File System in action.
[ Applause ]
Okay, so let's talk about some
of the new APIs that we've added
to support Apple File System.
So first, is one that
we probably expect
that you're familiar with.
If you're using the Foundation
or the FileManager these have
both been Swift enhanced.
So is use copy item or replace
item they will adopt either the
clone or the safe-save
semantics that we just described
for you automatically, you
don't have to do anything
so it just comes for free.
It automatically figures
out if the file system
you're suing is HFS+
or Apple File System and
will use the behavior only
when it is appropriate.
If, however you decide
that the Foundation
or the FileManager doesn't
provide exactly what you need,
you can go a little bit lower
and we have a library
called libcopyfile.
And this supports the
copying of deep hierarchies
and this is what we
used for a number
of years before we had cloning.
So copy files supports a new
bit, called COPYFILE CLONE.
It's equivalent to the 5 or
6-bits that are below it.
And we decided to
make this opt-in
because if you're using
a specialized library
like this you may not
necessarily want your
[inaudible] and extended
attributes and everything else
to be copied exactly
as they are.
Whereas cloning will implicitly
copy all of those things.
Again, this library will also
automatically call clone for you
if the backend file
system supports it.
And if not it will continue
to do what it's always done.
These are the new
safe-save APIs, so renamex np
and renameatx np are
the new system calls
to support the safe-save
primitives.
These are available in the
Man Pages in your version
of macOS Sierra that you have
so if you'd like to take a peek
at the Man Page,
they're right there.
And these are the
cloning APIs as well.
So clone files and its
variance, support the cloning
of files and directories.
So a word on compatibility,
we expect that the easiest way
to get access to an
Apple File System images
to use hdiutil as I showed you.
It's currently available
in the command line only
for macOS Sierra so as a
developer preview technology has
not been fully wired up into
disk utility intentionally.
So the fastest way
to use something
like this hdiutil create-fs APFS
and you can get a disk
image and attach it.
You can also use diskutil
apfs to add a container,
delete a container, add a
volume, delete a volume.
Whatever lower-level
manipulations you want to do
to the container itself.
And finally, we also
have an FS check
that we've been working
on as well.
So this will be able to
validate the file system
as well as perform repairs.
So that's also continuing
to be in development.
So, some current limitations
of Apple File System file
system in macOS Sierra.
This will be supported
on data volumes only.
We don't support booting from
Apple File System right now.
Time machine backups with Apple
File System are not supported
right now.
File vault and fusion drive
support is still forthcoming.
And currently the volume
format is case sensitive only
right now.
So if you're not sure that your
app requires case insensitivity
please give it a try, create
a disk image or set it
up on a partition on your
Mac, try substantiating it
and running your app
from Apple File System
and let us know how it's doing.
Some other compatibility notes.
Apple File System cannot
be shared over AFP.
So if you want to use
file sharing, we recommend
that you use SNB instead
as a preferred file sharing
mechanism moving forward.
OS X Yosemite or earlier
will not recognize Apple File
System volume.
So please do not take an Apple
File System instance all the way
back to OS X Yosemite
or earlier.
You will inevitably
get a dialogue
that you don't want
to respond to.
So, [laughter].
macOS Sierra will have
a developer preview
of Apple File System.
And it will be a developer
preview technology once macOS
Sierra ships this fall.
So now you might be wondering
what's our roll-out plan.
How do all of you get access
to Apple File System
on your machines?
We'll talk about that.
So upgrading to Apple
File System.
So you want these
great new features
that we've shown you,
how do you get them?
Well one way we could do
this is to require everybody,
all users to back up their
systems, save it away,
make sure everything's
completely safe
and then erase the
volume, erase the device,
restore it put a new OS back on
and then restore from backup.
A process which will
take several hours,
and hope that everything's
exactly as it was
after you've restored it.
Well, we're not doing that.
Instead, Apple will provide
an in-place upgrade path
from HFS+ to Apple File System.
[ Applause ]
In doing this, the user data
will remain exactly where it is
and we will write, or Apple
will write the APFS metadata,
brand new, into the
HPF+ free space.
And we're doing this
for crash protection.
This is a multi-second
to multi-minute operation
potentially.
And over that time, if the
device loses power, panics,
anything bad happens we want the
data on the device to be safe
and sound as if nothing
had ever happened.
So the Apple File System
Converter will try to be
as atomic as possible.
It's not completely
instantaneous,
but as the operation is
ongoing, if the device crashes,
we intend for it
to be completely
as if nothing had ever happened.
So Apple File System will ship,
by default on all
devices in 2017.
[ Applause ]
So to summarize, Apple File
System will be the default file
system for all Apple products
2017, it's ultra-modern,
it's crash protected, it
supports Space Sharing,
we support cloning
and snapshots.
Enhanced data security features
like the multikey encryption
that we just discussed.
It's also been tuned and
designed specifically
for the Apple ecosystem
in all of our devices.
So you can get more information
about Apple File System
at this URL behind me that will
have a developer guide as well
as some sample code so that
you can see cloning of files
and directories in action.
So some takeaways for all
of you in the audience.
Apple File System
is coming soon,
2017 will be here
before we know it.
I want you to please test your
apps against Apple File System
with the macOS build
that you got yesterday.
Try running your apps
on Apple File System.
Please let us know
how that process goes.
If you report any bugs, please
report them through Bug Reporter
through traditional means
so that we can investigate.
We all want you to love
it as much as we do.
So, some related sessions.
If you're interested in
learning more about some
of the security features on
our platform, specifically iOS,
we recommend that
you can take a look
at How iOS Security
Really Works, which will be
in this room today at 4 o'clock.
And with that, that's Apple
File System, we can't wait
to see how you're
going to use it.
[ Applause ]