[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Good morning everybody
and welcome to our session,
Introduction to Notifications.
I'm Kritarth Jain an engineer
on the iOS Notifications Team,
and today I'll be joined
by my colleague Julien
for the later half
of the session.
Now the team's been
working really hard
over the last one year to
give you guys a great release
for notifications for iOS
X and we're really excited
to share it with you today.
We're going to start
out by doing an overview
of notifications.
And today we're existing
a brand new framework
for doing user notifications.
As part of this, we're
going to cover registration,
content creation, scheduling
these notifications,
managing them, and action
handling on these notifications.
And lastly, we're going
to introduce a brand new feature
today called service extensions
that we think you're
really going to like.
But there's a lot more to cover
with notifications in iOS X
and we're not going to get
to all of it in this session.
So there's going to be an
Advance Notification Session
following this one
right in this very room.
So do make sure to check it out.
So let's begin by talking
about user notifications.
Now I'm sure all
of you are familiar
with what a notification
looks like.
This is how your
application sends information
to your app users when your
app is not in the foreground.
It's a push mechanism
of sending information,
versus a pull mechanism where
your app user actively goes
to the application to get the
content or the information.
Now, you as app developers,
have different ways
in which you can send these
notifications to the user.
They can be visual alerts,
where the notification rolls
down from the top as a banner.
You can do sound and
vibration alerts associated
with your notifications as
well as badge the app icon.
So that the user knows
which application has
data available for them.
Depending upon the
user's context,
there're different ways how
they see that notification.
If the device is unlocked
the notification rolls
down from the top as a banner.
While the device is locked,
the notification comes right
on the user's lock screen.
And if the user ever
misses these notifications,
they can always go to
the Notification Center
and see all the pending
notifications waiting
for them there.
So what are the different
types of notifications that you
as app developers can use for
sending these notifications?
Mainly there are two types.
Local notifications and
remote notifications,
depending on their
source of origin.
So let's look at
these individually.
Now local notifications
are the ones that are used
by applications that
are on the device.
Examples of local notifications
use time based triggers,
or location based triggers,
where your application
schedules this notification
with the system showing
the notification
to the user's device, and
when the user handles this
notification, your
application gets a callback.
As I mentioned, examples
of these can include
task reminder alerts,
calendar alerts, or
location based triggers.
Now, not all your
applications are contained
on the user's device.
A lot of them have a
server-side component as well,
where your server-side
application lives
across the network
on your servers.
So to facilitate notifications
for that we have
remote notifications.
Let's take a look at how
remote notifications work.
The main piece involved in
this exchange is the Apple Push
Notification Service,
or APNs for short.
It's part of remote
notifications.
Your remote site application
sends the notification payload
to APNs, which then does
a best-effort delivery
of this notification to the
user's device, showing them
that notification and then
forwarding your application
to be handled when the
user interacts with it.
Examples of remote notifications
can be news alerts,
where your server-side
application gets the latest
breaking news and then
forwards all these notifications
to the different devices
on all the clients
that have your application
installed on their device.
Instant messaging alerts as well
where the database is managed
on your servers, and when a new
message comes in you just pass
that notification along
to the user's device.
Now remote notifications in turn
have two different components,
they can be either
user-facing or silent updates.
Now user-facing notifications,
as the name suggests are
the ones that are displayed
to the user on the device.
And by setting up your
notification payload the right
way, you can add this content
to be shown to the user.
As opposed to user-facing
notifications,
we also offer silent
update notifications.
Now, these silent
update notifications work
where your notification payload
includes the content available
flag when this notification
is received on the device,
the system knows to wake your
application up in the background
to perform a background
app refresh.
So then your client-side
application can go and talk
to your remote server
application
and get the latest
greatest content available
so that the next time your
application users come
to your device they see the
latest information available
to them giving them a
very good user experience.
So that was in a nutshell
the different notifications,
type of those notification
that you can use.
Now before we proceed,
let's do a quick overview
of the existing API
for notifications
that we have in iOS.
Now, you use UI application for
registering your application
and then scheduling
notifications
that your application
wants to send.
This is part of the UI kit
framework that I'm sure most
of you are familiar with.
However, there were some
issues with the existing API.
For example, there are
different callbacks for local
and remote notifications
which could lead
to the duplication of code.
There's also limited control.
After your application has
already sent the notification
to the user and there's
different support
for notifications across
the multiple platforms
that Apple supports today.
So we really wanted to
address these issues, and more,
and on top of that give you
guys some great new features
for really elevating the
notification experience
for your app users.
So today we're really excited to
announce a brand new framework
for doing user notifications.
Let's take a look at what's
this new framework includes.
To start out, it has a very
familiar API with feature parity
with what exists today.
So transferring your code
from the existing API
to the new framework
will be very easy.
We've also expanded the
content options that you can set
on the notifications for having
richer notifications sent
to your user.
We've combined the
code pack for local
and remote notification handling
so that you have lesser code
for handling the notifications.
[ Applause ]
We've also simplified
the delegate methods
that your application gets
now when the user interacts
with actions on these
notifications.
We've also included better
notification management.
What this means is that
your apps now have access
to notifications that are
either pending delivery
or already delivered to the
user, allowing you to remove
as well update notifications.
We'll take a look at all of this
in more detail in the session.
Starting in iOS X we now
allow your applications
to do in-app presentation
of notifications.
[ Applause ]
So now, your apps get the
exact same look and feel
as the system supports
right in your applications.
You can now also schedule
and handle notifications
right to your extensions.
And lastly, we've
added extension points
to notifications themselves,
but more on that later.
So what this new
framework also allows us is
to have a single notifications
API across multiple platforms
that Apple supports, including
iOS, watchOS, and tvOS.
Let's take a look at what
this means individually
for all these different
platforms.
On iOS, we give the full
support for managing
and scheduling notification
that the new framework supports.
On watchOS, we continue
the existing support
of forwarding notifications
from the user's device
to their Watch, but
starting with watchOS 3,
we now let your WatchOS
applications
to do local notification
on the Watch itself.
What this means is that
your Watch does not have
to be connected to your device,
and your applications can
still do notifications.
For example, you have the
workout application and the user
of your application
is out on a workout,
but forgot their device behind.
You can still send
them notifications
of when they meet
their workout goals
or when their workout time is
up right on the Watch itself.
For more information about
how to do notifications
on WatchOS we have a Quick
Interaction Techniques
for WatchOS session.
And continuing, for
tvOS, we now give support
to badging app icons for both
local and remote notifications.
This can be used
in different ways.
For example, if your
application wants
to let the user know the number
of unwatched episodes they have,
you can just badge the
app icon with that number.
Or for a turn by
turn based game,
if the user has a
pending user turn,
then badging the app
icon lets them know
that that's waiting for them.
So that's in a nutshell summary
of what this new
framework allows you to do
on all these different
platforms that Apple has.
Let's continue and dive into
notification delivery on iOS.
How does your application
actually send this notification
to the user's device
for them to see it?
Well, even before you can
do this, the very first step
that your application needs
to do is registration.
Let's take a look at
what registration means.
Now notifications are an
interruption for the user.
So it's very important you
get the user's authorization
and permission before you
send them these notifications.
So you can ask them permission
for banners, sound alerts
or badging the app icon and the
very first time you do this the
user gets prompted
with this message.
You need to do this registration
for both local as well
as remote notification.
And performing this registration
in code is as simple
as calling request authorization
on the UN user notification
object associated
with your application,
passing it the right parameters
that you want registration for.
However, do note
that the settings
that the user might
approve right now are highly
configurable in the settings
menu per application.
So your application users can
always go back and turn these on
or off depending on
their preferences.
In iOS X we now give
you the ability
to access these user
settings in your application
so that you can be smarter about
the notifications that you want
to send to the user depending
upon their preferences.
[ Applause ]
But registration
doesn't end here.
For remote notifications,
there's another step
for token registration,
which uses the existing
API on UI application.
So you register for
remote notifications,
you need a network connection so
that the system can then go talk
to APNs for this registration
for your device and
your application.
This token gets returned to
your client-side application,
which then you need to forward
to your servicer-side
application.
Now this is important because
this token needs to be included
as part of the notification
payload
that your remote side
application is passing
through your APNs.
Because this token acts as the
key for identifying your device
and the application to which it
wants to send the notification.
So that was registration.
Now your application is ready
to start sending
notifications to the users.
So the first thing
that you need to do
after that is create the
content of that notification.
Now I'm sure all of you have
seen the brand new notification
looks that we've
introduced with iOS X.
We're really excited about
what this allows you to do.
To start with, we now show the
title of your notifications
in all iOS notifications.
[ Applause ]
We've also included an
extra field for the subtitle
so you can have more
dexterity in the type
of information you're
sending to the user.
And of course, there's
the body of the content.
Let's take a look at how
to set this up in code.
So it's as simple as creating
a UNmutableNotificationContent
object and setting the different
properties on it, that's it.
For remote notifications,
it's fairly similar.
Your notification payload
is structured as shown here,
and again you set the
different properties
of your payload before
sending it to APNs.
However, that's not
it for content,
we decided to go one step
further, and starting
in iOS X we now let all
applications do media
attachments right in
the notifications.
[ Applause ]
So now you can have much richer
and colorful notifications
that your users see.
For more on media attachments,
we'll be doing a walkthrough
on how to set these up in the
Advance Notifications Session.
So now that your content
is ready, the next thing
that your app needs to
determine is when it wants
to send the notification.
And for that there are triggers.
In iOS X we support four
different triggers, mainly push,
timer interval, calendar,
and location based triggers.
Now the push trigger is
associated exclusively
with remote notifications
when your remote side
notification sends the
notification to APNs it
arrives on the device associated
with the push trigger, all the
other triggers are the ones
that are associated with
local notifications.
Now, time interval based
triggers lets you schedule a
notification at a certain time
interval starting from now.
For example, if you wanted
to send the notification
in two minutes from now,
or you want to send it every
hour starting from now.
This also lets you schedule
the notification immediately
by setting the time
interval to zero.
Now as opposed to time interval
based triggers there are
calendar triggers that
lets you set a notification
at a specific date and
time in the future.
So you have more
control of exactly
when the notification gets sent.
Example of this can be at a
certain time tomorrow morning
or repeating it on a certain day
of the week at a certain time.
And lastly in triggers, we
have location based triggers,
which uses your devices absolute
location, or its location
in relation to Bluetooth
beacons and determining
if your device is entering
or leaving the region you can
send notification to the user.
Examples of this is when the
user is leaving their home
and the device is
leaving that proximity,
or say that the user
is at a grocery store
and your application wants
to send them a coupon
for a discount.
So those are the different
triggers that we have as part
of this new framework.
Now that your content's ready
and you know when you want
to send the notification,
the next step left is
scheduling the notification
with the system.
For local notifications this is
as simple as calling addrequest
on the UUserNotificationCenter
object.
Which then on the trigger
the system then displays the
notification to the user.
And for remote notifications,
your service-side application
passes the payload to APNs,
which does a best effort
delivery sending the
notification to the
user's device.
So let's summarize this
whole delivery mechanism
that we've talked about so far.
Your application starts out by
registering with the system.
Then it creates the content,
determines when it wants
to send the notification
and finally schedules
the notification
with the system leading
to the notification getting
shown to the user's device.
It's as simple as that.
Let's take a look at
the summary in code.
Start out by doing registration,
by calling requestAuthorization,
you create the content
of that notification.
You create the trigger, in this
example a simple time interval
based trigger, and then
you package all of this
in a UNNotificationRequest
object,
passing a unique identifier,
which will be important
we will talk
about later in this session.
And then you schedule this
notification with the system,
completing the notification's
delivery.
So, so far we've talked
about what happens
to a notification while your
app is in the background
and the user's not
interacting with it,
but what if your application
is in the foreground
when it receives a notification?
And for this we do offer support
for notification handling while
your app is in the foreground.
Your application needs
to implement the
UNUserNotificationCenter
delegate.
And it has a method of
willPresent notification,
which lets you get the
notification content as part
of the UNNotification object
passed with this method.
Now this method also
has a CompletionHandler,
which must be called at
the end of this function.
One thing to note is that
the CompletionHandler takes
presentation options parameters.
Now, what this enables you to
do is the in-app presentation
that we talked about earlier.
Let's see an example of how
you can configure it up.
So, say your application still
wants to show the user the view
as well as your sound alert
while your application is
in foreground.
So this is as simple as
calling the handler block
with these different parameters.
And if you don't want
in-app presentation,
you just don't pass
any parameters.
So that was notification
handling while your application
is in foreground.
Let's move on and talk about
notification management.
Now notification management
is new with this framework
and what this allows you to do
is have access to notification
that are pending delivery
for your locally scheduled
notifications, as well as access
to delivered notification
that the user might
never see while local
or remove notifications.
Now you can also
remove notifications
that have already been sent
to the user, as well as update
and promote these notifications.
And important piece
of notification management
is the request identifier.
Now, in the summary you saw that
the request identifier is set
on the notification
of the request object.
And for remote notifications
there's a new request header the
APNs collapse id that you
need to set on your payload.
The system uses this
request identifier to know
which notification
you're requesting
to be removed or updated.
Let's take a look
at notification management
with an example.
Say your application wants to
send notifications for a game,
and it wants to send
notifications
for the start time of the game.
So you start out by creating
your UNNotification request
and scheduling it
with the system,
but say that the
game was cancelled.
So this is as simple as calling
removePendingNotification
Request, passing it the
exact same game identifier
that you created for the
initial notification.
But what if the game
time was updated?
Then you create a new request,
giving it the exact
same identifier
for the initial request,
setting the new trigger time
and just scheduling
it with the system.
And this in turn leads to
updating that notification.
Let's continue this example
for delivered notifications
and talk about score updates.
Again, you just start
out by creating this
notification request
and sending it to the system.
But say that the wrong
score was updated,
then you can simple
remove that notification
by calling
removeDeliveredNotification
giving it the same identifier.
And what if the score
gets updated
which of course is a very
common case for games.
So all you can do in
this scenario is create a
notification request, giving
it the same identifier,
passing it the new
score content,
and then simply scheduling
it with the system.
Now, what this means, let's
take a look at it as an example,
say that notification
was already there
for initial score update.
So by calling update, as I
showed in code, what this leads
to is that that notification
gets updated right
in the notification list,
replacing the original
notification,
so that you're not cluttering
the user's notification list
at all.
[ Applause ]
And you can use this in multiple
ways for aggregating information
that is right for
your applications.
So that was notification
management,
it really gives your
applications a lot of control
on the notifications that
have been sent to the user.
So so far in this
session we've talked
about how your application
sends these notifications
to the users.
But what about the other
side of this exchange?
Notifications are very
intractable in the form
of default actions as
well as custom actions
that your applications
can set on them.
So, to talk about notification
actions let me invite my
colleague Julien to
continue this session.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> Hi everyone.
I'm Julien.
I am a software engineer
in the Frameworks QA Team.
Kritarth showed you the web flow
with the current user
notifications framework
from registration up to the time
when notifications are
delivered to the device.
So now let's talk
about the actions
that the user can take
on the notifications.
There are three types of actions
that your applications
can be aware of.
The first one is
the default action.
It is when the user opens
your app from a notification.
This can be done when
the device is unlocked
and the user receives a
notification, they can tap
on the banner, which
will open your app.
It can also be done from the
lock screen when the user swipes
from left to right, as well
as in the Notification Center
when the user swipes down to
present the Notification Center,
they can tap on any
of your notification
to open your application.
Now the second type of
actions are custom actions.
And they are within the
actionable notifications.
We introduced actionable
notifications in iOS 8
and they provide
the user a quick way
to execute an action
directly from the notification
without the need of
launching your app.
Now these custom actions,
they appear as buttons
with customizable title below
the notification content.
In iOS 9 we introduced
text input actions
so that the user can for example
quickly reply to a message
of directly from
the notification.
And these custom actions can be
either background or foreground.
A background action will
dismiss the notification
and give you a short amount
of time in the background
to process that custom action
that the user selected.
On the other hand, a foreground
action will dismiss the
notification and launch your
application in the foreground
so that you can process
that custom action.
Now these custom
actions are available
on both iOS and watchOS.
So first, let's take a look
at what it looks like on iOS.
Here we have an example
of an iPhone 6S.
On this device, the
user can use 3D touch
to expand a notification.
When they do so the custom
actions will appear below the
notification content.
And some of these actions,
as you can see can
be text input actions
so the user can quickly
reply to a message.
Now on watchOS, same
thing, the custom actions,
appear below the
notification content,
and some of these actions can
also be text input actions.
And on the watchOS, you
have the opportunity
to provide some suggestions that
the user is likely to choose
for your text input action.
Now for more information
about notifications
on watchOS you can attend the
Quick Interaction Techniques
for watchOS Session later today.
So now that we've talked
about what the custom
actions look like.
Let's first talk about how you
can register your custom actions
and then present
them to the user.
So for registration, the first
thing you will need to do is
to create an action object.
You give it a unique
identifier, as well as a title.
The title will appear on
the customizable buttons
that we previously saw.
Action will be by
default background action,
but you can also provide some
option such as if you want it
to be a foreground action.
Now, all your actions they need
to be associated
with categories.
The category requires
a unique identifier.
You give it all the
actions you want.
You can also provide now
some intent identifiers,
for more information
about intents,
you can attend the
Introducing SiriKit Session.
There are also some options
that you can provide
for the category.
We will talk about one
of them in a few moments.
Now, once you've
created all your actions
and all your categories, the
only thing you need to do is
to register them
to the UNUserNotificationCenter
object associated
with your application.
Now let's talk about how you
can present these custom actions
to your user.
You can do so from both remote
and local notifications.
So first for remote
notifications,
the only thing you need to do
is to set a category identifier
in the APS dictionary of the
remote notification payload.
Now this identifier needs to
match one of the identifiers
for the categories you
previously registered.
For local notifications
you just need
to set the category identifier
on the mutable content
that you created.
Same thing this identifier
needs to match the identifier
that you [inaudible] before.
Now let's talk about
the third type of action
that your app can be aware
of is the dismiss action.
Now the dismiss action
is new to iOS X and it is
when the user dismisses
a specific notification.
You could use this
if, for example,
you have a calendar application
and let's say you send a remote
notification to your user
about an upcoming meeting.
The user looks at
the notification
and decides to dismiss it.
When in this case you might want
to stop sending other remote
notifications to other devices
of this user since they have
seen the notification already.
Now, how can the user actually
dismiss the notification?
Well they can do that on
the lock screen by swiping
from right to left, and
tapping on the Clear button.
They can also do that from the
Notification Center by swiping
from right to left as well,
and taping on the Clear button
which will dismiss
the notification.
Now since this is not the
common case you will need
to update for it.
So remember earlier
when we talked
about the different categories
that you could register,
we talked about some
options, this is one of them,
the customDismissAction option.
So let's look at the
code we used earlier
to register our category.
The only thing you
need to do here,
is simply add the
customDismissAction
to the options of this category
and your app will
receive the actions
when the result dismisses
specific notification
with this category.
So let's summarize the actions
that we talked about today.
The first one is
a default action,
when the user opens
your application
from the notification.
The second one where
the custom actions
within actionable notifications
to provide a quick way
for the user to execute
an action directly
from the notification.
And finally the third one
is the dismiss action,
it is new to iOS X and
it allows you to know
when a user dismisses a
specific notification.
[ Applause ]
Now let's talk about how you can
actually handle the responses
from these actions
in your application.
So until now we had
several methods based
on if the user opened the
app from a notification,
or if we had custom actions or
text input actions, or if it was
from a remote or a
local notification.
Well now with our new user
notifications framework,
we have a single method
to do that and it is part
of the UNUserNotificationCenter
delegate protocol.
The method you will need to
implement is didReceive response
with CompletionHandler.
Now let's take a closer
look at the response object
and what you can do with
it in your application.
Your response object has
an action identifier,
which can either be the
default, the dismiss action,
or any of the custom
actions that you created.
It can have a user
text property in case
if it was a text input action.
It can also have a notification
object with the request object
and the identifier of
the notification as well
as the trigger and the content.
Based on the type of trigger
you can figure out if it was
from a local or a
remote notification.
So this is all with the new
user notification framework,
you can handle your
responses of actions.
Now, let's talk about
remote notifications.
This is your current
workflow, the workflow
with remote notification that
we saw earlier in this session.
You have your service
identification,
which sends a remote
notification to payload
to Apple push notification
service.
And then it is delivered to the
device and shown to the user.
Now, maybe some of
you are in a situation
where you have your server side
application and you communicate
to your iOS application
maybe using some
end-to-end encryption.
Well, wouldn't that be great
if you could use that same end
to end encryption for your
remote notification as well?
Well for that in iOS X
we are introducing the
service extension.
So now we are going to talk
about what the service
extension is
and then how you can
actually implement it
in your application.
Now the service extension is
a non iOS extension available
on iOS X, which means it
runs in the background.
And its main purpose is to
augment or replace the content
of visible or remote
notifications before they are
displayed to the user.
So let's take a look again
at your current workflow
for remote notifications.
So you have your server-side
application, you send a payload
to Apple push notification
service
and then it is sent
to the device.
Well, now with the extension,
you're able to modify
the content
between the time you sent it
from your server-side
application
and the time it is displayed
to the user on their device.
As you can see in this
example, I did a title,
as well as a subtitle,
and I modified the body
of the notification.
Now a few more details about
that service extension.
You will get a short execution
time, which means this is not
for long background
running tasks.
And in case you fail to
provide some updated content
in a timely manner, you
will get a fallback method.
In case you still fail to
provide some updated content,
we will show the original
remote notification
that you sent to the user.
Now some potential uses of
that you could use end-to-end
encryption for your remote
notifications and you could
as well add some attachments
to your remote notifications
to make them even richer.
Now there will be a
detailed example on how to do
that in the Advance
Notification Session.
Now let's talk about how you
can actually implement this new
service extension
in your application.
The first thing you would need
to do in your Xcode project
to add the new target.
You can use the template,
which is located
under the application
extension section.
And it is known as the
notification service.
Now this template
has one main class.
So we are going to take a look
at a simplified version of it.
So this class, is a subclass
of the UNNotification
service extension
and it has two main methods.
The first method is
didReceive with ContentHandler.
Now this method will give
you the current request
which has the identifier
for the notification
as well as the content.
Then we have the ContentHandler.
You will need to call this
ContentHandler when you want
to present the notification
to your user, and you need
to provide some content for it.
Now, the second method is
service extension time will
expire, and this will be called
if you cannot provide updated
content in a timely manner.
So now remember if you fail
to call the ContentHandler
in this method, we will show
the original remote notification
content that you sent.
So now let's talk about how you
can actually trigger this code
from a remote notification.
Here, we have a very
simple example
of remote notification
payload with an alert.
And as you can see we have a new
key, the mutable content key.
Now, you will need to use this
key to let the system know
that you want the service
extension to be launched
to update the remote
notification content.
You do not need to use
this key every time,
only use it when
you actually want
to replace the content
of the notification.
Now you can see that I also
added some encrypted content
of my own.
So let's take a look at some
code, which will be able
to process this remote
notification payload.
So you can see here we have
our didReceive( request method,
and the first thing I do here is
I decrypt the encrypted content
of the remote notification
payload.
I then create a
MutableNotificationContent
object and I assign the
body of this notification
with the decrypted content
that we previously set.
And finally we call
the ContentHandler
to present the notification
content to the user.
Now, this is how simple it is
to implement the new service
extension in your application.
[ Applause ]
Now let's recap what
we've talked about today.
We saw an overview of
notification with local
and remote notifications.
We showed you the new user
notification framework,
where is available on
iOS, watchOS, and tvOS.
We talked about how you can
register for notifications,
as well as how you can
create your content.
How you can schedule
your notifications,
either local or remote.
We also talked about the new
management that you can do
on the pending and
delivered notifications.
And then we talked about
the different actions
that the user can take
on your notifications
and how you can handle the
responses of these actions
within your application.
Finally, we presented the
brand new service extension
which allows you to augment
or replace the content
of visual remote notifications
before they are displayed
to the user.
For more information,
you can visit this link
on developer.apple.com.
We will have some
related sessions.
There is an Advance Notification
Session right after this one,
we strongly encourage you
to attend this session
if you are interested
in notifications.
There is also if you want more
information on notifications
on the Watch you can attend the
Quick Interaction Techniques
for watchOS Session.
Thank you everyone.
[ Applause ]