[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Hello and welcome.
My name is Kushal Dalmia, and
I and my colleague, Terry Long,
I'm going to be representing
optimizing I/O
for performance and
battery life.
In this talk, we're going to
take a look at what an I/O is,
how it affects your app, and
how you can improve your app's
performance by improving
its I/O performance.
So let's begin.
As we all know, devices
are getting bigger
and better every year.
Screen resolutions
have gone up by as much
as 16 times in the past decade.
Similar improvements
in [inaudible] technologies
allow us to capture 4K HD videos
and amazing high-quality
images from our mobile devices.
All these improvements have led
to richer media being produced
and consumed every day.
Just to put it in perspective,
let's take a look at the trend
of the iPhone wallpaper size.
If you look at the size of the
iPhone wallpaper across device
and generations, you notice that
the growth has been exponential.
The size of the wallpaper on
an iPhone 6s Plus is as much
as 14 times its counterpart
on the iPhone 3G.
And there's a similar trend in
all of the phones' data as well.
We build and use
complex apps for gaming,
messaging, and social networks.
We work and store richer
documents like PDF's.
And we all share and
capture high-quality audio
and video files.
Now to manage this
data explosion,
apps need to be really efficient
in their system resource usage,
and the main system resources
are CPU, memory, and I/O.
For CPU and memory, I'll refer
you to last year's WWDC talk,
Performance on iOS and watchOS,
and today we're going
to talk about I/O.
I/O, or input/output, are
operations that interact
with the local file storage
or network-based servers.
Operations that interact
with the file system and deal
with reading or writing files
are generally considered an I/O.
Talking to a web
server is a good example
of network-based I/O.
Now one of the reasons
I/O's are so interesting is
that there is a huge variation
in the I/O technologies
and the performance
characteristics.
Consider the latency to do
a one megabyte write to some
of the most common I/O medium
such as the SSD, a hard disk,
and a common Wi-Fi network.
As you'll notice here, the
same operation takes anywhere
from a couple of milliseconds to
hundreds of milliseconds based
on the I/O medium
you're interacting with.
And the reason I/O
is so important is
that the I/O performance of your
application has a direct impact
on user experience.
Latency variations in your
app's performance can show
as responsiveness issues.
Since I/O is a shared
resource in the system,
your app's I/O performance
could affect overall
system performance.
And as we'll see shortly,
I/O significantly impacts the
battery life of the device.
Now to help you reason about
the I/O usage of your app,
we've come up with our
own I/O philosophy,
and the I/O philosophy
has four main pillars.
Reduce the amount of I/O
your application does,
use the right thread to do
these I/O's, adopt appropriate
and efficient API's to do
these I/O's, and, lastly,
test and measure your
application for I/O performance.
As we move through rest of the
doc, we'll look at each one
of them in further detail.
Now the best way to
improve the I/O efficiency
of your application is to reduce
the amount of I/O it does.
Every I/O operation interacts
with multiple hardware
competence on your device.
Here's a simple block diagram
of a modern device with some
of its competence and their
impact on battery life.
When your app is using I/O,
it runs on code on the CPU,
accesses memory, and
ultimately fetches data
to or from the disk.
If the network is involved,
the network-based radios
are interacted with as well.
The combined power cost of all
of these competents makes
I/O a heavy operation
in terms of battery usage.
Since I/O has such an adverse
effect on the battery life
of the device, let's
take a look at a couple
of best practices you can
use to reduce the amount
of I/O in your application.
And the first one is caching.
The main idea here is to
create an in memory copy
of your data rather than going
out of the disk for
every operation.
To decide if your data
should be cached in memory
in your application,
you should look
at the access patterns
of your data.
Data which is frequently
written to
or updated might
be a good candidate
to cache in your application.
Also, data which [inaudible]
from the disk needs an expensive
processing step, for example,
decompressing an image file
might be a good example
of data you should cache.
Having said that, you should
be aware of the tradeoffs
between memory and I/O.
Just like I/O, memory is a
shared and limited resource
in the system, and
you should be careful
in your user [inaudible].
If you do decide to create
caches in your application,
we would recommend
using the NS cache API's
since they handle memory
pressure conditions
appropriately for you.
The next best practice
is coalescing your I/O's,
and the main idea here is to
defer your I/O's to a later,
more suitable time
in the system.
Due to the way I/O
technologies work, larger,
fewer I/O's are always more
efficient for the system.
One of the ways to do that is
to use the application app
state change notification,
for example, application
data in the background
to schedule your I/O's.
On macOS, you can use the
centralized task scheduling
API's to schedule your
maintenance and backup tasks,
and the system will figure
out an optimal time
to run these for you.
To learn more about these API's,
we would recommend looking
at WWDC 2014 talk Writing
Energy Efficient Code.
Now that we've taken a look
at a couple of best practices
to reduce the amount of
I/O in your application,
I'd like to introduce our
sample application which Terry
and I have been working on,
and we'll use this application
for the rest of the talk
to demonstrate the
practical implications of some
of these best practices.
And that app is called ImageBox.
ImageBox is our amazing
app on iOS and macOS
that lets you add
and browse images.
For each image, it
shows you a thumbnail,
shows you associated
badges such as favorites,
or whether it has
notes associated
with the particular image.
When you tap on a
particular image, it takes you
to a detailed view, which
lets you mark the image
as a favorite, unfavorited,
or add a note to it.
Now that we've created
this app, we want to know
if our app is I/O
efficient and does well
in terms of I/O performance.
So I'm going to talk about
the tool that you can use
to decide this for
your own application,
and the tool is the
Xcode debug gauge.
So let's see how that works.
In order to use that tool,
simply run your project
from the Xcode UI.
This launches the
project or the application
on the device or the simulator.
Click on the Xcode
debug navigator.
Now this shows you live data
from all, from your application
about all the system resources
your application is using.
You have CPU, memory,
energy, network, and disk.
Since we're interested in the
I/O activity or I/O performance
of our application, let's
go ahead and select disk.
Once you do that, you notice
that it shows you live data
about the reads and writes
being done by your application,
and it looks like our
application is doing a lot
of writes every few seconds even
though there is no user activity
to it.
Now to investigate this further,
we want to dig into instruments,
and use instruments to
find out what's happening.
So let's go ahead and click
on profile in instruments,
and hit the restart button.
Once you do that, instruments
provides you a set of templates
that you can choose from for
analyzing your application.
And since we're interested
in the I/O activity
of our application, we go ahead
and select system usage,
and next hit choose.
Doing that opens a new
instruments template that's
ready to record the I/O
activity for your application.
So let's go ahead
and start recording.
As you now notice in
the detail section,
this template shows you
all system calls being done
by our application which does,
which do I/O on your behalf.
It shows other useful
information such as the actual
and requested number of bytes
for those reads and writes
and the file path
associated with them.
I'll go ahead and stop
this recording now.
Now in order to find out the
large writes that we were seeing
in the Xcode debug
gauge, we sort this data
by the actual number of bytes
that are being read and written
and identify the large
write that's near the top.
Once we have that,
we can actually go
into the extended detail viewer
and see the exact backtrace
of the piece of code doing
these I/O's in our application.
It looks like it's our
app delegate method.
Double clicking on that takes
you to a source inspector
which shows you the exact block
of code doing these I/O's.
If you click on the Xcode
icon in the source inspector,
it takes you back to Xcode
project and highlights the piece
of code doing these
I/O's for you.
So let's take a look at this
piece of code in further detail,
and the code in question
is our implementation
of the application
didFinishLaunchingApp
delegate method.
As part of its implementation,
we create a new timer
DispatchSource,
schedule it to file
every five seconds,
and as part of the event
handler for that timer,
we write out our
entire data store.
Now a lot of us write code
like this because we want
to make sure that the
application data is being saved
out consistently and regularly.
However, there's a more I/O
efficient way of doing this,
and to fix this code,
the first thing
that we'll do is eliminate the
repeating nature of the timer.
So let's get rid of that.
Instead, we create a new method
called dataStoreDidChange,
which is culled from
various places
in the application
whenever there is a change
to the to the data store.
As part of this implementation,
we push out the timer
dispatch source
by 15 seconds into the future.
This way, we collect all updates
for our application's data
store update and push them
out into the future and
coalesce and write them.
Once the timer eventually
expires,
it has basically
collected a bunch of updates
that were frequently
done, and we'll write them
out as a single I/O operation.
So let's see what these code
changes do for our application.
We run the application again
using the Xcode UI's run button.
Go to the debug navigator
and select the disk gauge
to find the I/O activity.
As you'll notice here that the
application is not doing those
writes anymore.
Since it's completely idle and
the user is not interacting
with it, this is
exactly what we expect.
We've effectively
coalesced the amount of I/O's
that our application does, and
improved its I/O efficiency.
Now that we've taken
a look at a couple
of best practices you can use
to reduce the amount of I/O,
let's take a look at what
trends you should be using
to do these I/O's, and for that,
I'd like to invite
Terry on stage.
Terry.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Kushal.
So we just saw some great
ways that you can reduce I/O
in your applications to
avoid negatively impacting
battery life.
Now let's move on to the second
pillar of our I/O philosophy.
I'll explain some ways
that you can use threads
and queues effectively
in your application
for great I/O performance
and efficiency.
Every thread or every
application on the system starts
with a single thread
called the main thread.
This thread is special, and
it has a few primary purposes.
The first purpose of the main
thread is to handle input.
So if I tap on a button
in my application,
the main thread is
responsible for handling
that input and responding to it.
Additionally, the main
thread is responsible
for updating your interface.
This is for doing things
like drawing your views,
doing layout, or animating.
When your main thread is
idle, it's ready and available
to respond to input or
update your user interface.
But if you're doing other
things on your main thread,
such as executing lengthy
tasks, this could be something
like expensive image
processing, doing this type
of work keeps your
main thread busy,
which means it won't be idle,
you won't be able to respond
to input, or update your UI.
Additionally, what
we'll focus on today,
you should avoid doing
I/O on your main thread.
As we've already seen, I/O is an
expensive resource on the system
that needs to be
managed properly.
If you're doing I/O
on your main thread,
someone using your application
could notice some problems.
The first example
of this is on macOS.
Someone may see the
spinning cursor.
The spinning cursor indicates
that your main thread is busy
and that you won't be able to
interact with the application.
Additionally, on iOS, a
busy main thread may appear
as a frozen or just
unresponsive application.
And, lastly, doing I/O on your
main thread can cause issues
for animations.
For example, if I do a
large scroll in a table view
in my application and then do
I/O on the main thread to load
in more data, the time that
my application spends doing
that I/O is time that it doesn't
have to continue animating,
which can cause issues
like stutters.
I'd like to mention, again,
the talk that Kushal pointed
out earlier, Performance
on iOS and watchOS.
This talk also has
some great information
about using your main
thread effectively.
Now I'd like take a look at our
ImageBox sample application,
this time running on macOS.
I've been noticing an issue
when trying to add images
to the main collection view.
So let's take a look.
First from Xcode, I'll
click on the run button.
Xcode launches my application,
and then I'll click
the add button
on the right side
of the toolbar.
Then I'll select an image from
the open panel and click open.
As you can see, the open
panel doesn't disappear,
and we see the spinning cursor.
Eventually, the open panel
disappears, and the image
that we selected shows up
in the main collection view.
So what might be going on here?
Well, as we already saw, the
spinning cursor indicates
that your main thread is busy.
So something must be running
on the main thread that's
preventing it from being idle.
So we won't be able to
interact with the application.
We need to figure out what's
going on, and to do that,
we can use instruments.
Back in Xcode, we can choose
profile from the product menu.
Xcode recompiles our
application for profiling
and then launches instruments.
This time, I'll choose the time
profiler instruments template.
Time profiler is great
for seeing how much
time different parts
of your code are
spending executing.
So we can use this to figure
out why our main thread is busy.
Now I'll click choose, and
instruments opens a new,
blank time profiler document.
By default, instruments time
profiler only shows time spent
while the CPU is
actively executing code.
Other things like I/O aren't
actively executing on the CPU.
The CPU's just waiting
on the I/O to complete.
So to also see those
types of operations
in our instruments trace,
first we need to click
on the record waiting
threads option
under the record settings.
Now instruments will also show
us time spent while we're doing
things like waiting on I/O.
So let's get started and
click the record button
in instruments.
Instruments launches
our application,
and then I'll take the same
actions that I took before
to reproduce the problem.
First, clicking the add button,
selecting an image,
and hitting open.
Again, we see the issue.
So now we can hit
stop in instruments
and see what's going on.
Before I continue, I'd like
to reduce some of the noise
in this output by focusing just
on the code that I've written
and not any other
system libraries.
And to do that, first, I can
click on the display options
on the right side
of instruments.
Then click on hide
system libraries.
Now instruments will only
show me code that I've written
and not any other
system frameworks
that I might be calling.
So now let's take a look at the
main detail view of instruments.
Instruments shows all
the different threads
in my application,
and the different time
that they're spending executing.
In this case, we know that we're
interested in the main thread.
So I can expand the
main thread section
and find the heaviest stack.
In this case, I can see that
we have an open panel callback
in our application, which
is calling an add method
on our data store.
That add method is then
saving our entire data store
out to disk.
And instrument shows us
that saving is taking
almost seven seconds,
and that's really bad.
I happen to know that this
save method is writing
out a pretty big Plist, and
that could be contributing
to the problem.
Kushal will mention some
ways later in the talk
on how we can optimize
our data store operations
so that this is really fast,
but for now, I'd like to focus
on how we can fix this problem
so that no matter how long
that operation takes,
our application is still
extremely responsive.
To do that, let's take
a look at the code.
Here I have the open
panel callback.
It's waiting for a response.
Once it receives that response,
it validates that it has URL
that points to a valid image.
Then it creates a new item
for our collection view
from the image and tries to
add it to our data store.
If that was successful, it
tells the main collection view
to reload its data so
that we can see the image
that we just selected.
As we saw earlier, and what
instruments verified for us,
calling that add method is
expensive because it's saving
out all that data to disk.
So let's see how
we can fix this.
To recap, our application
has a main thread.
The main thread is running
the open panel callback.
That callback then calls the
add method on our data store,
and this is where we
see the spinning cursor.
Once that work is done,
we finally update our
main collection view,
and this is obviously
not what we want.
This entire time, the
main thread is busy,
and we can't interact
with our application,
and we can't update any UI.
So one way that we
can fix this is
by using Grand Central
Dispatch, or GCD.
With GCD, we can create
a new dispatch queue.
Dispatch queues are a way
to run code concurrently
to the main thread.
We can use this to move our
expensive I/O related work
onto this queue, leaving
the main thread idle.
To do that, we can call the
async method on the queue
and push that expensive work
onto our queue rather
than the main thread.
Finally, since UI related
work has to happen back
on the main thread,
we can asynchronously
dispatch back there
to finally update
our collection view.
And now this is exactly
what we want.
Now the expensive I/O work is
happening on a separate queue,
which leaves the main thread
idle, which means we'll be able
to interact with the application
and continue using it.
Let's see what this looks like
if we implement it in code.
Here I have the same open
panel callback from before.
To get started, first I can
create a new GCD dispatch queue
and provide a descriptive label.
In this case, I've created a
queue that I can reuse for all
of my data store operations.
Next, we can move the
expensive work when we're adding
that image onto this queue by
providing that code as a block
to the async method
on the dispatch queue.
Finally, to update our UI,
we can call dispatch
queue.main.async,
and pass it in a block that
has all of our UI related work.
Now that we've done that,
let's see what this looks
like if we rebuild and run
our application in Xcode.
So first I'll click the run
button, wait for the application
to launch, and then try
adding an image again.
Click the add button,
select an image
from the open panel,
and then click open.
As you can see, the open
panel disappears immediately,
and we can continue
interacting with the application
and adding more and more images.
You'll also notice that I've
added some placeholder images
in the main view.
This is just to give
an indication
that we're currently
processing that data
and saving it out to disk.
Once all that data is done
being added and saved,
all the images show up in
the main collection view,
and now this entire time,
our main thread was idle,
which means their application
was extremely responsive,
and that's exactly what we want.
So now that we've moved that
work from the main thread off
to a dispatch queue, we should
consider telling the system the
intent of that work so it can
manage resources on our behalf,
and to do that, we can use
something called quality
of service.
Quality of service is a way
to tell the system the intent
of the work that
you're performing
so that it can properly manage
resources like CPU or I/O.
It manages these resources among
the different processes running
on the system and
the different threads
within your own application.
When thinking about
quality of service,
keep in mind three attributes of
the work that you're performing.
The visibility, importance,
and expectation.
Ask yourself three questions.
Is the work that you're
performing visible
to someone using
your application?
Secondly, what is the
importance of that work?
Is that work required
to complete before someone can
continue using your application?
And, lastly, how long is
that work expected to take?
Is this something that happens
immediately or something
that you might assume takes
a longer amount of time?
Before I continue, I'd
like to mention a talk
from last year's WWDC
called Building Responsive
and Efficient Apps with GCD.
This talk goes into a lot
of detail about GCD and how
to use quality of service,
and I highly recommend
that you go watch it.
So once we've thought about
these three attributes
of our work, we're
ready to choose from one
of the four quality
of service classes.
The first quality of service
class is user interactive.
User interactive is
designated for your main thread.
This is for doing
things like responding
to input and animating.
All other work that
happens asynchronously
from the main thread
should be using one
of the other three quality of
service classes, and the first
of those is user initiated.
User initiated work is visible
to someone using
your application,
and they're expecting immediate
results from that work.
They probably also
need that work
to complete before they
can continue interacting
with your application.
A good example of that is if
I click on a button to switch
to a new view, I may need
to load some resources
on a different queue in
order to display that view,
and that work should be
happening at user initiated.
The third quality of
service class is utility.
Utility quality of service is
often associated with things
that have progress bars or
other activity indicators.
This work generally takes
a longer amount of time,
and it's something
that's still visible
to someone using
your application.
A good example of this
is rendering a movie.
This is something that doesn't
block someone from continuing
to use your application,
but it's going
to take a longer amount
of time to complete.
And the final quality of
service class is background.
Background work is not visible
to someone using
your application.
In fact, they may not even
be aware that it's happening.
A good example of
that is indexing work.
Indexing is usually
important for the performance
of your application,
but it's not something
that someone using
your app is aware of.
All of these quality of
service classes are important
because if you, when you choose
the quality of service class,
it helps inform the system
how it should manage resources
so that less important work
like background operations
and indexing doesn't adversely
affect more important work
like animating, even if
that work is happening
in a different process.
So once we've chosen from one of
the quality of service classes,
there are two main ways that you
can specify quality of service
in your applications,
and the first way is
by supplying an optional QOS
parameter to the async method
on the dispatch queue.
In this case, I've
specified QOS background.
This means that when
the supplied block
of code is running
asynchronously,
it will be using the
background quality of service.
Additionally, if you're
using the operation queue
or operation API's, both
of those have a quality
of service property that you
can set, such as utility.
So now that we know a little
bit about quality of service
and how we can specify
it, let's go back
to our ImageBox application,
and see if we can choose
an appropriate quality
of service for adding images.
And to do that, we can think
about the three attributes
of this work: The visibility,
importance, and expectation.
Well, adding an image is
something that is visible
to someone using
our application,
but it's not necessarily
required
to complete before we can
continue doing other things
like browsing images
or adding more images.
Additionally, because we are
showing that placeholder image,
we've given an indication
that this is an operation
that could take a
longer amount of time.
For all of those reasons,
the utility quality
of service may be an appropriate
choice for this work.
So now that we know some ways
that you can move
expensive work, like I/O,
off of your main thread and
onto a separate dispatch queue
and how to specify the intent
of that work using
quality of service.
Let's take a look at the third
pillar of our I/O philosophy,
adopting appropriate API's,
and the first one that I'd
like to mention is
Asset Catalogs.
If you're not already aware,
Asset Catalogs are a way
to easily manage resources in
your application, like images.
They're used to store
things like your app icon
and launch images and
also all of the images
for the different devices that
you support and scale factors,
like retina or non-retina.
When building games
with SpriteKit,
Asset Catalogs are also the way
that you guild Sprite Atlases.
And you can use Asset Catalogs
to tag resources for use
with the on-demand
resources feature.
And another good example of how
you can use Asset Catalogs is
for storing resources for
your watch complications.
So why are Asset
Catalogs great for I/O?
Well, Asset Catalogs
have some great storage
efficiency properties.
First of all, because
Asset Catalogs store all
of their images in a single
optimized format rather
than many individual files,
you can have a lower
on-disk footprint
by using Asset Catalogs.
Additionally, with features
like app slicing on iOS,
when you download an
app from the App Store,
it uses the metadata in your
Asset Catalog to determine
which resources it should
download to your device.
For example, if I download
an app to my iPhone,
the App Store knows
that it doesn't need
to download any resources for
an iPad or for any iPhones
with different screen
resolutions,
and this can save a lot
of space on my device.
Furthermore, Asset Catalogs
can be great for performance.
Because of this optimized
format that they're stored in,
image loading can be faster.
And if you're using them to make
Sprite Atlases for your games,
since cheap user much better
at managing a single
larger resource rather
than many tiny resources,
these Sprites Atlases
can improve your texture
rendering times.
And, lastly, if you're
using Asset Catalogs
on hard-drive machines
running macOS,
you can also improve
your app launch time.
In fact, we've seen up to
a ten percent improvement
in app launch time on
these machines just
by switching to Asset Catalogs.
And you might be thinking to get
such a big performance
improvement,
this must be difficult or
time consuming to switch
to Asset Catalogs, but, in fact,
if you're already using
the standard NS image
and UI image based API's,
switching to Asset
Catalogs is easy,
and I'd like to demonstrate that
now with an example project.
Here I have a project
that hasn't
yet adopted Asset Catalogs.
To get started, first
we can choose new file
from the file menu.
Then, from the resource
category,
select Asset Catalog
and click next.
Xcode creates a new, sorry.
When prompted, enter a name
for your Asset Catalog
and the location.
Then you can click create,
and now Xcode creates a
new blank Asset Catalog
in your project.
To move all of your existing
assets from your project
into this new Asset Catalog,
first open the add menu
at the bottom of the screen,
and choose import from project.
Xcode displays a list of all
of the images in your project,
and when I click import,
it will move all of these
into my new empty Asset Catalog.
Xcode automatically
figures out which images are
for which devices and
which scale factors.
Now when I rebuild
my application,
it will be using this new
Asset Catalog, and that's it.
It took less than a
minute, and I didn't have
to change a single line of code.
So it's really easy, and
I highly encourage you
to adopt Asset Catalogs
today if you haven't already.
One more thing I'd
like to mention
with Asset Catalogs is
a new feature this year,
and that's image compression.
By default, images in your
Asset Catalog are lossless,
but new this year, you
can choose from one
of the lossy image
compression formats.
These formats have hardware
accelerated decompression.
So they're really fast,
and because of the compressed
format, they can result
in lower memory footprints.
If you have a lot of
assets in your application,
you may benefit from
the potential memory
and space savings by
using image compression.
So let's see how we can
use image compression back
in the project that I just
converted to use Asset Catalogs.
First, let's click on
an image in our catalog.
Then open the utility sidebar
on the right-hand side.
And then click on the
attributes inspector.
New in Xcode is a
compression popup menu.
When I select that,
it displays all
of the available image
compression formats.
In this case, I'll
choose lossy automatic
so that Xcode can choose
a good format for me.
So that's a little bit about
how you can use Asset Catalogs
in your applications,
adopt them,
and use the new image
compression feature.
Now I'd like to hand
it back to Kushal,
who's going to tell you
more about some other API's
that you can adopt
for storing your data.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Terry.
Asset catalogs are an
easy and efficient way
to manage your app's assets.
Another thing that a lot
of us think about is how
and where our application
data lives on device.
A lot of us are familiar with
the serialized data formats.
For example, Plists,
XML, and JSON.
The reason these data
formats are popular are
because of their
simplicity and ease of use,
and they have been made popular
as data interchange formats
in a lot of web-based services.
These data formats are good
for small read-only data
such as configuration
information
in your Info.plist file.
However, they are
not a database,
and the biggest reason
they are not a database is
that minor updates to these
files causes the entire data
file to be written
out of the disk,
which is really bad
for I/O efficiency.
For all your data storage needs,
we would recommend using Apple
SQLite database framework
core data.
Core data is the, is a Cocoa
application development
framework for managing
your application data.
It handles your data persistence
by using SQLite as
a backing store.
It automatically manages
objects, objects graphs,
and relationships between
those objects to allow you
to manage your data
easily and efficiently.
It also does change tracking,
will let you do, undo,
and redo operations
on your data models.
And core data is
completely integrated
with the Xcode tool chain
so that you can build
and visualize your data model
directly from the Xcode UI.
Now that we're aware of this
amazing tool and framework
to use for designing or
writing our data model,
let's think about how to
design our data model.
And the best way to do that
is to base your data model
on the UI needs of
your application.
Let's go back to ImageBox,
which up until now has been
using a giant Plist to write
out all the files and
all the images associated
with the application,
and instead move it
to a core data model.
Now if you think
about the application,
there are two main
entities for ImageBox.
The first is the list
of items that's there
in the collection view, and
secondly is the notes associated
with each of these items.
So let's go ahead and put
them in a table of their own.
And the first table is BoxItem,
which represents a particular
item in the collection view,
and the second table is notes,
which represents
the notes itself.
The BoxItem table
contains a Boolean
which represents whether the
image is a favorite or not
and contains the full
resolution image of the image
that you need to represent.
The Notes table contains a note
body for all notes associated
with the BoxItem, and we relay
these two tables using a simple
one is too many relationship.
Now when we use this data model
and looked at the performance
of our application, we noticed
that the app launch
performance was really slow.
We investigated using
instruments, and we found
out that app was spending most
of its time fetching the core
data model on the launch pad.
So we need to take a look at
application launch performance
from core data's
perspective, and,
luckily core data
lets us do just that.
It has a set of tools that let
you investigate how core data is
doing on your behalf.
For example, you can
set a launch argument
on your application which
is Apple.CoreData.SQLDebug
with a velocity level that
lets you see how core data is
interacting with its
SQLite backing store.
The core data instruments
template lets you see
[inaudible] patterns
in terms of fetching
and loading too much data.
And, lastly, the standard set
of SQLite query analysis tools,
for example, explain
query, are available
which lets you dive deep
into a particular query
and find out its performance.
To learn more about these tools,
I would recommend you watching
last year's WWDC doc What's New
in Core Data.
Now that we have these tools,
let's use one of them to find
out what's wrong
with our data model.
In order to do that,
click on the project
and click edit scheme.
In the window that opens,
we're going to select
the arguments pane,
and then add a new argument
com.Apple.CoreData.SQLDebug
at the highest velocity
level of 3.
Once you are done with that,
we'll go ahead, and click close.
And now we simply launch our
application from the Xcode UI.
This should rebuild
your project, load it,
and launch the application.
As you'll notice here, the
console shows various logs
from core data about
its performance
in terms of the data model.
Another thing you
should notice is
that the app is taking
multiple seconds to launch,
and it still hasn't
finished launching.
We see some more data from core
data on the log output, and,
finally, the app launches.
If you go back to the Xcode
UI, you can dig through all
of these logs and figure
out what was wrong
with your data model.
So let's go ahead and do
that for our application.
Now one of the first
logs that you see here is
that core data is doing
a fetch of all the rows
from the SQLite database for
the BoxItem table, and it,
that is exactly what we expect.
However, the next log tells us
that that fetch took almost nine
seconds, and that's really bad,
and one of the biggest reasons
of our app launch slowness.
Now if you go back to the
previous query that was executed
to fetch all this data,
one thing you'll notice is
that we are fetching the full
resolution image for each
of the items in the BoxItem
table even though we just show
thumbnail images on
the launch screen.
Moving on, we also notice
that core data is doing a join
between the BoxItem
table and the Notes table
for every item it fetches
from the BoxItem table.
And the reason it's
doing that is
because there is a one
is too many relationship
between these two entities,
and we need to show a UI batch
in the launch screen
to represent whether
there are notes associated
with the BoxItem.
So let's go ahead and
fix our data model.
The first thing we'll
fix is to avoid the join
between these two tables,
and the reason the core data
was doing this join again was
because it needs to show the,
and we need to show the UI
for whether notes are present
with the BoxItem or not.
So to improve this model, we
can simply add another field
to the BoxItem table, which
is called notes present.
The presence or absence or
[inaudible] for false value
of this particular field
tells us whether we need
to put a UI badge on
the launch screen.
The next problem with
our data model was
that we were fetching the
full resolution images
at the launch screen.
So let's go ahead and fix that.
We replace the image
data with thumbnail data,
and instead move the full
resolution image data
into a table of its own,
and we link these two tables
by a simple one is
to one relationship.
Now as lot of you know, these
images can become really large,
and it might be a good
idea to store these images
as a separate file on the file
system rather than putting them
in the SQLite database.
So we're going to replace the
full resolution image being part
of the database itself
with the image URL
and store the images
directly on disk.
Now let's look at the
launch performance
of our application once
we made these changes.
Again, we run the
project from the Xcode UI
with the new data model that
builds it and launches it.
As you saw there, the
application launched four
to five times faster just
by changing the data model.
So basing your data model
on your UI needs has significant
impact on your launch
and overall performance
of your application.
Now that we've taken a
look at ways you can reduce
and optimize the amount of
I/O's your application does,
let's see how you can test
your app for I/O performance.
One of the things we
recommend is to test your app
on a variety of devices.
If your app shifts on this,
on multiple platforms,
it might be a good idea to test
your application on a variety
of devices from all
those platforms.
Even if your app shifts
on a single platform,
it might be a good idea to
test it across generations
because I/O characteristics
vary widely.
Now another thing that can
vary between your environment
and probably your app user
environment is the network
condition, and to help you
test your network conditions
or the worst-case
network conditions,
we provide a tool called
network link conditioner.
In order to get to the
network link conditioner,
open the settings app, scroll
all the way to the bottom to get
to the developer settings,
and tap on developer settings
which brings you to this menu.
Now as you see here, we have
the network link conditioner,
and tapping on that
opens up this menu
which shows various kinds
of profiles you can
install on your device.
We have 3G, high latency DNS,
and my favorite,
very bad network.
So let's go ahead and use that
by picking very bad network
and enabling it with using
the toggle switch on top.
And that's it.
Your device will now behave as
if it's in a very bad network,
and you can test your
application against it.
Another factor to remember is
that I/O is a shared
resource on the system.
So the I/O performance of your
application might be impacted
by other system resources
or other I/O's happening
in the device.
For example, if there
are other applications
that are running
due to multitasking,
your app's I/O performance
might be affected.
So it's a good idea to
test your application
in the presence of other apps.
Also, the system tries to
maintain a fair balance
between its memory
and I/O usage,
and under memory
pressure conditions,
your I/O latencies
might be affected.
So we would recommend
testing your app
under memory pressure
conditions as well.
Lastly, the system maintains
a bunch of caches by default
on your behalf to
help you access
and store your data better.
The state of these caches
could affect the system or,
and I/O performance
of your application.
And to test the worst-case
behavior for that,
we would recommend rebooting
your device on an iOS device,
and on macOS, you can
use the merge command
which flushes all these caches
and simulates worst-case
behavior for our application.
To make sure that
your app is robust
against all these
environmental variations,
we recommend following
the I/O philosophy
to reduce an optimize
your I/O's.
So here are some key
takeaways from the talk.
Reduce the amount of I/O's
your application does
since that significantly
impacts battery life.
Move your I/O heavy workload
off the main thread and keep
that main thread idle
for UI and animations.
Specify proper quality of
service to specify the intent
of work you're performing.
Switch to Asset Catalog
since they're an easy
and efficient way to
manage your app's assets.
Use core data for all your
database needs, and, lastly,
test and measure your
app for I/O performance.
For more information,
go to www.apple.com,
and the session ID is 719.
Here is some related sessions
that happened during the week
that you can refer to for
more details on the API's
and tools we mentioned.
And thanks for your time.