[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Welcome all of you
to the Unified Logging
and Tracing Activity session,
Logging for the Future.
And I'd like to thank
all of you for turning
out this late on a Friday.
So my name is Steve
Szymanski, yes.
[ Applause ]
Certainly, didn't expect
a full room at this time.
So my name is Steven Szymanski
and I'll be doing most
of the talking and a little
bit later I'll be assisted
by Matthieu Lucas.
So let's get into this, there's
a lot to talk about here.
I'm going to start with a
little bit of an introduction
and then go into some
of the basic concepts behind
the new logging system
that we've introduced this week.
There will be a short demo, then
I'll come back and start talking
about how to actually use it.
How to use the APIs,
how to use the tools,
and then some discussion of what
we think is the best practices
of how to use this.
A little talk about how
to gather the logs once you've
created them and then finally,
some talk about some
deprecated interfaces.
So let's get started.
A little bit of background.
For those of you who have been
around for a while you'll know
that back in 2014,
Apple introduced the
concept of Activity Tracing.
This is the ability to
keep track of all the work
that is done throughout
the system
on behalf of some operation.
Whether that work is done
inside of an application,
inside of a library of
framework that's called
from that application
or even work that's done
in a separate process on
behalf of the application.
Another thing we introduced at
that same time was the concept
of Faults and Errors, which
are special kinds of log events
that will trigger additional
work to be done by the system
to collect additional data.
The last thing I
want to say by way
of introduction is we recognize
that Apple has several logging
APIs already and hopefully
by the end of this talk you'll
understand why we're introducing
this new API and how that
interrelates with the others.
So what are the goals
of this project?
First and foremost,
what we wanted
to do was build one common
efficient logging mechanism
across the whole system
that could be used
in both user mode
and kernel mode.
One of the purposes of this
was to maximize the amount
of information that we could
collect while minimizing the
observer effect.
By observer effect I mean
the experience that all
of us have had as developers
where you have some problem,
you stick some logging
into your code
and suddenly the
problem stops happening
because you've changed
the timing.
We want a very, very low
footprint logging interface
that has minimal impact on your
code as you go off and call it.
So the way we accomplish
this as I'll go
into more detail in this talk.
First off, we compress the data.
So you can fit a whole lot
more information on the disk
without using up more space.
Another thing we do that's very,
very important is we
defer a lot of work.
As anything that we
can do at the point
at which you display the
information instead of the point
at which we collect it we
try to defer to that point.
That's one of the key ways
that we avoid observer effect.
And then another thing we do is
we manage the message lifecycle
in new ways.
The idea being that different
kinds of messages may stick
around in the system for
different lengths of time
to maximize the chance
that the messages
that you want will
actually be there
when you actually go
off and look at them.
The background of all that is
that we want to be able to have
as much logging turned on
all of the time in the system
without having to go back and
say, oh can you turn this on
and give me a new log.
We want it all on
as much as possible.
The other thing that
motivated this is we want
to design privacy into the
system from the ground up
and I'll talk more
about that as well.
So what are the key
features of the new system?
There's new and improved
ways of categorizing
and filtering log messages.
So there's some new tools that
we're going to be providing
to you for you to
categorize your log messages,
so when it comes around to
looking at the logs it's easier
to find log messages
that you care about.
Another important thing is
logging system collects caller
information for you, so there's
no longer any need for you
to pass file, line to identify
where this is called from.
We are automatically
collecting that for you.
[ Applause ]
There's also a whole bunch of
new built-in type specifiers
that allow us to format binary
data for you so you don't have
to spend the time doing it.
There's a new Console
application
and a new command
line tool that we use
to access all of these features.
This is supported across all
of our platforms macOS, iOS,
watchOS, tvOS, and
all the Simulators.
It is supported in the
release this week in C, C++,
and Objective-C and support
for Swift is coming real soon.
So to give you a little
foretaste of what's coming.
This is the current Console
application that you see here
and this is what the
new Console looks like.
Now one thing I want to point
out to you here is take a
close look at the section
that I highlighted there.
That is a tree showing you
the graph of a given activity
as it flows from process
to process to process,
so you can see visually all
of the work that's been done
on behalf of some
operation that you requested.
So now let's back up and
talk about the theory
and the abstract
concepts behind us.
First off, adoption.
If you want to use the new
unified logging system all you
need to start doing is
building with the new SDK
that was released this week.
What'll happen if you do that is
all of the legacy APIs, NSLog,
asl log, message syslog,
all of those will get
redirected into the new system.
You don't have to
change a line of code
to start using the system.
Now obviously to use some
of the features you need
to start using the new APIs, but
out-of-the-box if you just build
with the new system
it'll all get directed
into the new logging
architecture.
On the other hand, if for
some reason you don't want
to start using the new logging
system continue to build
with the old SDK and there'll
be no changes in your system.
So new file formats.
In this new system
logging data is kept
in a compressed binary
format on disk,
it's called a .tracev3 file.
Those files are now stored
under /var/db/diagnostics
with additional supporting
files in /var/db/uuidtext.
There are new tools
to access that data,
there's a new Console, a new
log command line tool and one
of the things you have
to keep in mind is
because the data is now stored
in a binary format you must
use the new tools to access it.
So you can no longer grep
through logs you have
to use our tools to do
the surfing through it.
There's also another new
type of file the .logarchive,
which is there for
portability of log data.
Essentially a .logarchive is
a collection of information
out of /var/db/diagnostics and
you uuidtext collected together
into a single file that's
easier to transfer to email,
to attach to bug
reports and the like.
Another new concept that comes
in with this system is
subsystems and categories.
Log messages can
now be associated
with a subsystem and a category.
They can be used to control
how log messages are filtered
and displayed.
A subsystem can in fact maintain
several different categories
and you can use as
many subsystems
and categories as you need.
So as an example, you
may have some application
and you might define
a subsystem com.
your-company.
your-application that has
three categories in it setup,
inprogress and teardown.
In that same application you can
define another subsystem com.
your-company.
test.your-application with a
single category of test in it.
And you can then use those
to control how the log
messages get displayed.
Logging behavior, this is kind
of the heart of the system here.
Each log message has a
level determined by the API
that you used to create it.
There are three basic levels
Default, Info and Debug
and there are two special
levels Fault and Error.
Each basic level has
two characteristics
that can be set either
system-wide
for a specific subsystem
or for a specific category
within a subsystem.
The first of those
is, is it enabled,
if you make the call does it
actually generate a log line.
Note that the fault
messages are always enabled,
you can't turn off
default messages.
The other characteristic
that you can set at all
of those levels is, is it
stored to disk or to memory.
Now storing to disk it's
kind of obvious what we mean,
but what I mean by
storing to memory.
Well the new Unified Logging
System maintains a large set
of in-memory circular buffers
to which some log
messages can be directed.
These messages are then saved to
disk only on a Fault and Error.
This is very useful for messages
that grow stale quickly.
So if you have a
message for instance
that basically the
information becomes stale
and all you ever look
at is the last version
of that message whenever you
get a log, there's no reason
to store hundreds
of different copies
of that log message on disk.
Instead, send it to the memory
buffer and then get it captured
on a Fault and Error and
you'll get that last version
that you need without a lot of
extra things getting stored.
The levels here are
hierarchical, so what I mean
by that is if you set Debug
to go to disk that implies
that info will go
to disk as well.
And all this behavior
can be customized
by installing profiles or on
macOS using the log command.
So what's the standard
behavior out-of-the-box
if you don't install
a special profile?
Well, default level
messages are always enabled
and by standard configuration
they go to disk.
Info level messages are
enabled, but they go to memory.
Debug level messages
are standard off,
they're not enabled
and of course,
since they're off they
don't go anywhere.
So the other two
kinds of messages
that occur are Faults
and Errors.
Faults and Errors are always
enabled and always go to disk.
So let's talk a moment
about privacy.
As you know, Apple values
customer privacy a great deal.
As a guiding principle
in everything we design
in our apps, in our services, in
our new versions of the OS users
about their privacy respected.
And all developers, including
everyone in this room shares
that responsibility with us.
So how does it apply to logging?
What we want to prevent
is the accidental logging
of personally identifiable
information in the logs
where someone can actually get
at it through the log data.
So to that end, dynamic strings,
collections, arrays, objects,
and the like are assumed
to contain private data.
Static strings and scalars
are assumed to be public.
And I'll get into
a little bit later
about how you can control that.
Okay, Faults and Errors.
I talked earlier about how
as part of the activity
of Tracing Release,
we introduced the concept
of Faults and Errors.
One of the basic ideas
of Faults and Errors is
that we do additional work
on doing it Fault and Error,
we save additional information.
So an Error represents
an issue discovered
within the different
application or library.
On an Error what
we do is we look
through the in-memory
buffers and we collect all
of the log messages that were
from that process and save them
out to disk as part
of the Error.
Alternatively, Faults
represent more global problems
in the system where
something larger has happened.
On a Fault we again look through
the memory buffers and collect
up all the log messages from
that process and every process
that was involved
in the activity.
And we also we actually collect
some other additional system
information that
might be useful to us.
Faults and Errors and all of
the log data that's collected
as part of them are
actually captured
into a separate set
of log files.
We do that so that normal
logging won't push them out
and cause them to
exceed their quotas
and cause us to reclaim
the space.
So the idea is the Fault
and Error data sticks
around even longer than
normal logging data.
So okay, I'm going to give a
very, very eyelevel overview
of how the system works with a
whole lot of details missing.
So this is like a
broad brush discussion.
Okay within each process there's
a collection of small buffers
into which we log messages.
These buffers are actually
in memory that's shared
with the logging daemon.
As these buffers are filled up
the logging daemon is triggered
to compress that data into a set
of larger buffers
that it maintains.
As those larger buffers are
filled up we either save them
out to disk or we
recycle them as part
of the memory only buffers.
So the other activity
that ends up happening is
if you request livestreaming
of log data,
so you're on the Console
and want to see the logs
that are happening
as they occur.
The way we implement that
is we immediately do an IPC
over to the diagnostic daemon
who then distributes those log
messages out to all the clients.
The side effect of that is
that there is a significant
performance impact
of livestreaming of log data.
Basically, a lot of the work
that we've done to save effort
and speed up logging so it
doesn't have an observer effect
on your code goes away
because we're doing an IPC
on every single call.
The other thing to note is how
individual kinds of messages
from applications or
particular subsystems get routed
through this can be changed
by profiles and such.
So enough of me talking
for a little bit,
at this point I will
invite Matthieu Lucas
up to give a demonstration
of this
in action using the Console app.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks Steven.
So as Steven mentioned
earlier in this talk,
this year we introduced
a brand new Console app.
So we wrote it from
scratch using Swift.
We wanted to leverage
a new logging system
and making your developing
experience easier.
Let's look at the app.
So here's the new look.
As you can see, the layout
hasn't really changed.
You still have your mainstream
on the center, different action
on top, and then different
sources on the sidebar.
Let's look at the
sidebar for a minute.
So you can still see your
different reports, the system
or user reports, the
different legacy logs
that you may have
the system routes.
But here you can see that
there is a new section.
Now we display all the
devices that are connected
to your machine and we also
show the current machine.
So we support iOS, tvOS,
and watchOS devices in here,
so you can plug every
device you have.
So let's just look at the
mainstream for a minute.
So now the log stream
is made of two views.
You have the messages view
and the activities view
as Steven mentioned earlier.
So in the activities view
you can see the [inaudible]
activities and the related
messages if there is any right
in the details it tells
you in the bottom here.
Let's switch to the
messages now.
So here you can see
a bunch of messages,
so in order to include Debug
and Info messages you need
to manually do it in the
Action menu, so that they show
up along the default stream.
So now we should see more
-- I just launch a few apps,
so let's create some logs.
So here now you can see that
we have much more information.
So you can see the
different message type
through those color dots
on the type columns here.
So the gray one are
the Info messages,
the yellow ones are the Errors,
there is a red one for Fault
and the dark gray
are the Debug ones.
Whenever there is no dots
that's just the default type.
So you can also expand
or collapse your messages
directly inline using your left
or right arrows or using the
View menu item here Expand
or Collapse.
Then whenever you are
on the single message you
can now see all the details
of a specific message directly
in the details view
in the bottom.
So we are able to show you all
the information that we have
about a specific log, that's
part of the new logging system.
So now we can show
you the process,
the library where it comes from.
So as you can see for this one,
we can see that it's coming
from accounts D and then
from the account framework.
You can also see
much more information
as we gather during
all the new logging.
So you can see we have now
the subsystem, the category,
the activity ID, the
thread ID or the PID.
Now let's switch to the
iPad that I have here.
So I connected an iPad where
I have just a very basic app
that has some figures and we'll
try to find yours by going
through the different features.
So first, we can start by just
minimizing the column layout,
so to do so I can right
click on the top here
and then include or
add some columns.
So I'll just add the subsystem,
I also add the category,
and then I will just
move that here.
So this layout is
then persistent,
so you won't have
to do it twice.
So now we can see
that we have a bunch
of information from this device.
So in order to refine your
search here you have two ways
to do it.
You can first right click
on a specific message
and then you'll get option
to mute the subsystem,
mute the process or
show a specific process.
So in that case we
can just start
by muting a specific category.
Let's say that we
want to mute widgets.
Now you can also the second way
of just refining is
to just [inaudible].
So as you can see, we just
added a custom token for widget.
Let's say that I want to
just see the Bookmarks app,
that's the app that
[inaudible] on my device here.
So by doing so now I have only
messages coming from Bookmarks
without the category widgets.
Let's just add another token
to show only the Error type.
So now we only have messages
coming from Bookmarks
without the category widgets
and that has an Error type.
So we can see that we have
different Errors coming
from the web view, so
that's [inaudible] for now,
we relate it down to
what we're looking for.
So in order to reuse it later
you can just save it by clicking
on the Save button
on the top right.
So I'll just name
it Bookmark Errors.
So you can see that all your
saved searches will appear
in this section here.
So you can reorder those as
you want, you can remove those
if you want and you also have
two saved searches by default,
which are All Messages
and Errors and Faults.
Now let's switch to
the activity view see
if we can find more context
about those logs and see
if we can reproduce [inaudible].
So here we can see that we
have different activities.
So the activities view is based
on the same search mechanism,
so we could apply
the same features
and then save it as well.
So here we can see that we
have a Bookmarks activity
with different children.
So we can see that we were
preparing for transition,
then we retrieve an object and
then we push the detail view
and then we configure
the detail view
and then we load the web view.
So as you can see now, the
messages appear directly
in the bottom of this
view, the messages
that are related
to this activity.
So this message was written
in this specific activity,
so it showed up here.
Now we can see that
those messages,
those two failures were part of
the loading web view activity.
So now we know that we
have all these contexts
of what happened to this Error.
So now we also added the
sharing option to Console,
so you can just select a bunch
of activities or messages
and share it directly
to someone or to a note.
So I'll just add it as a note
so that I can debug it later.
Now the next.
[ Applause ]
The other input that we
can use is a log archive.
So [inaudible] log archive
that was previously
generated from another device.
So if you do have one too you
can just double-click on it
and Console will open it.
So as you can see whenever you
click on it and then open it,
it just loads everything.
And then you can see that we
also have the same [inaudible]
filters as we just said before.
So in order to see if this
specific log archive has the
same -- contain the same Error
messages as the current device
that we stream we
can just click on it
and it will automatically
reapply the same filters.
So we can see that we have the
same errors and we can also look
at the activities view to see
the same activities and so on.
So that's it for Console
and I'll let Steven
go back on the slides.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> So thank you very
much Matthieu.
I really like the new
Console, it is glorious to use.
So let's talk about the
new Unified Logging System
and how you actually use it.
So to start off with
here's a summary
of all the new APIs
that you'll have.
Os log is your basic logging API
that logs something
with default mode.
Os log info is the call that
by default sends log messages
into memory and that's for the
additional timely information
that you want to gather.
Os log debug is for your
high-frequency debugging.
And then there's os log
error and os log fault
for generating a
fault and an error.
And the last call
here is os log create
that creates a log
object you can then use
to customize your behavior.
So let's dive into that
one a little bit more
because it's probably the one
that's least familiar in terms
of analogy to other stuff.
So we have a call os log
create it takes two parameters,
the name of the subsystem
and the name of the category.
And what it does is it creates
a thread-safe singleton object
that controls the behavior
of the log calls
that you pass it to.
So by default it ends up having
the system-wide behavior,
but you can customize it to
have specific behaviors using
profiles or the log
command line tool.
The way you use it is you simply
pass it as the first parameter
to all of the other calls.
So here I call os log and
that first parameter is log,
which is the value that got
returned from os log create.
What that does is it causes
a reference to the category
and subsystem that was
defined with that log object
to be stored with every log
message that it's used with,
which then can be used
on the backend as you saw
to filter and display messages.
So if you don't care about
having your own subsystem
and category, then
the other option is
to simply pass an
os log default,
which is a default log object
that we always provide.
It doesn't have a subsystem
or category, but it's useful
if you really don't care
about that kind of control.
Built-in type formatters.
We all spend way
too much code trying
to convert binary
information into strings
so that we can log them.
The Unified Logging System takes
over much of that work for you
by providing built-in
formatters for well-known types.
What's even more
important is that we save
that conversion work until
we display the log message,
so you don't have to
pay for that conversion
at the time you generate
the log message.
Avoiding all of the different
kinds of observer effects.
So just to talk a
little bit about it.
There's built-in decoding
for some common values.
The syntax is instead of doing
%d you would do %(time t)d
and that basically says
that that decimal value
that you're passing in is
actually a time t and that
when it gets printed it should
be printed as a time string.
Likewise, for errno, if you
do %(errno)d it converts
that into a human readable
form of that errno.
We also have a new basic time
format % capital P not lowercase
P, which has been around
for a while that you can use
to display arbitrary
binary data.
And there's decoders for
all sorts of common type
so for instance %(uuid t).
And in fact, here is a list
of all of the current codes
which we have, so all the
different kinds of time values,
errno, uuids, all the
different kinds of network IDs.
And we do anticipate having more
coming out in future releases.
So Per Parameter Privacy.
Privacy is now handled on a
parameter by parameter basis,
scalars and static strings
are assumed to be public.
On the other hand, dynamic
strings, collections
and objects are assumed
to contain private information
unless you tell us otherwise.
So that behavior
can be overridden
on a per-parameter basis.
So instead of doing %@ to say
oh this is an object that I want
to include in my log
you do %(public)@
to tell us it's an
object and everything
in that object is public, so you
don't have to worry about it.
Alternatively, if you
happen to have a case
where you have some integer
that for some reason is secret
you could do a %(private)d
to log that data as being
private information.
You can by the way, combine
privacy and formatting.
So I could do %(public,
uuid t).16P to basically
say there's a uuid,
it's public information and
it gets formatted as such.
So let's give a little
bit of example
of what the difference this
makes to you as you code.
So log message simplification.
Okay, here's the old
way of doing things.
All right, first off
you have to check
and say is the current log level
enabled before you call anything
and then let's say you have a
uuid that you need to display.
Well the first thing you
have to do is call unparse
to convert that into a string.
You also happen to have a socket
address that you then need
to also convert into a string.
Then you call NSLog with all
that stuff that's been
converted, but also of course,
you have to pass the
function name and the file
and the line number for you.
And then when you're done
with that don't forget
to free the string that was
created for the socket address.
And you're done.
Now here's the new way.
You simply call os
log info it takes care
of checking the log
level for you.
In this case I'm passing
the default log object.
I specify in my format string
that a given parameter is a uuid
and a socket address, so I
don't do any conversions then.
None of the work happens now the
work happens when we display it.
And then I simply pass the
parameters, it's that easy.
[ Applause ]
While I'm doing examples let
me give a little bit more
of an example of using
some of the other APIs.
So here I do a log create
and I specify a subsystem
and a category.
The subsystem is
com.apple.logging.example
and the category is general
and so this is my
general log object.
I do the same thing, but
this time I create one
with a category timestamp.
You know, the basic
simple call, I call os log,
I use the general log object,
pass it a string,
it gets logged.
Here's a little bit more
of an interesting case.
I call os log info, so this is
something that's going to go
into the memory buffer
and only get saved
if there's a Fault or an Error.
And then in my format
string I specify %(public)s
for the filename because the
filename is a dynamic string
and we would assume that it's
private information unless you
tell us that it's public.
A little bit more
complicated case.
I open the file, I
check on an error
if it returns an error
I then call os log error
and in my format
string I again say
that the filename is
public information and I say
to format the errno as an errno.
Another very example, this
time I'm calling fstat,
but gee I'm calling fstat after
I already have the file open,
so maybe something
weird is happening
if I'm getting an error on that.
So I call os log fault,
same kinds of parameters.
And then the very last
thing is I call os log info,
but this time I pass
my timestamp log object
and then I basically dump all
the timestamps from that file.
What that means is
when I go off and look
at the Console I can
basically simply filter it
and say all I want to see
is that timestamp data
or I don't want to see
that timestamp data
because I'm looking
at something else.
So the new Unified Logging
System isn't the only change
in this release.
There are also some improvements
to the Activity Tracing System.
Activities are now
first-class objects
that can be stored and re-used.
And the act of creation
gives you control
over the relationships between
the various activity objects
at the point at which
you create them.
There's also some new APIs
that scope the activities
within your code.
So here's all of the new APIs.
So there's a new os activity
create that works just
like os log create to create a
log object only this time it's
identifying an activity.
There's two calls that
you can then use to apply
that to your code os activity
scope and os activity apply.
I'll show you examples
in a moment
about how they work differently.
And finally, there's os
activity label useraction
that labels an activity
as a user action UI-based
activity basically.
So let me give an
example of doing this.
First off, I call os activity
create to create an activity
that I'm calling init.
Notice that the second parameter
of this function is a
constant os activity current.
That's basically saying this
init activity is subordinate
to whatever happens to
be the current activity.
Now I go off and do os activity
create for a verify activity,
but my second parameter is the
init activity I just created.
So now I've created
the hierarchy
between these activities
manually.
So now I have a block of
code, you know, if it's ready
and then I have some code
between a couple of braces.
The first thing I do is
I call os activity scope
and I'm passing in this
case the verify activity.
What that does is it means
all of the rest of the code
in that block is considered
in scope of that activity
until I hit that closing brace.
There's no need to have to
remember to call os activity end
at the end it just
automatically does it for you.
And as soon as you leave
that scope you're now no
longer part of that activity.
The other call that we're
providing is os activity apply,
you pass the activity object
and then you pass it a block
and then it basically
executes that block
with that activity as the scope.
Tools, so Matthieu already
gave you a great demo
of the new Console,
I'll just run
through the functionality
very quickly.
You can view live
content from the system.
You can open log archives.
You can use the new activity
centric view of logging tracing.
You can use advanced
filtering and searching
and you can see logs
from your devices.
Now let me talk a little bit
about the new log
command line tool.
It provides all of the same
exact functionality as Console,
but from the command line.
So you want to stream live
log messages you simply do
log stream.
If you want to get fancy,
you can do log stream--
predicate eventMessage contains
my message and what it will do
for you is it will stream
all of the log messages
that contain the
string my message.
Just like the Console it could
let you open up a log archives.
You can display a log
archive using the log command.
You do log show and then
give it the name of the file
and it displays the
contents of that log file.
Another thing you can do on
macOS is use the log command
to actually change
the configuration
of your subsystems
and categories.
So here's an example,
I do log config --
mode level:debug and then
-system com.mycorp.myapp
and what that does is it
basically enables logging
on that subsystem for
you on your macOS.
So coming soon.
We do appreciate that
many of you are going
to be developing applications
iOS 10, but sticking
with macOS 10.11 on your
Macs, i.e. El Capitan.
Tools for being able to access
the new logs from El Capitan are
in fact coming, but in the
meantime there is a sort
of a hackish workaround, which
is you can run the new tools
from inside the simulator.
So xcrun simctl spawn booted
and then you give log show
system logs.logarchive
and you can run all
those commands just
like you would otherwise.
The alternative is
coming at some point.
[ Applause ]
So let me talk a moment
about best practices,
logging etiquette.
Try to ensure that your messages
only contain really useful
information, don't have
a lot of extra whitespace
or filler data in there.
Try to keep it compact.
Let us do the formatting,
leverage the built-in
formatters that we provided.
The more work you do
to format your strings
in advance the more that's going
to slow down your app as opposed
to letting us do the
formatting at the point
at which it gets output.
Avoid wrapping os log
APIs in other functions.
If you wrap it in another
function you then lose our
ability to collect the file
and line number for you.
If you absolutely have to
wrap our APIs, then wrap them
in macros and not in functions.
Only log what's needed from
dictionaries and archives.
Dictionaries, I mean
dictionaries and arrays.
They take up a lot of space on
disk, which means they're going
to pushing out other log
messages that people may need.
Try to only log the parts
of those that you really,
really need for your logs.
And avoid logging in
tight loops in code.
So a brief word on what
we think the best uses
of our new APIs are.
Os log to log basically
details on your basic details
on logging information.
This is the kind of information
you may need from hours ago
to help debug your problem.
Use os log info for
additional information
that is very, very timely.
So use this first
stuff that's going
to get stale very, very quickly.
Use os log debug for high volume
debugging during development.
Error in the case that you want
additional information collected
and captured for your app.
And fault if you want additional
information you want collected
about the system.
A quick word on gathering logs.
Sydiagnose is the
preferred method
to capture data for bug reports.
If you do sysdiagnose
the logging data
in the system I've just
described will appear
within that archive as a file
called system logs.archive.
You can use key-chords
to trigger sysdiagnose.
If you do a sysdiagnose on an
Apple watch it will trigger
on both the watch
and the paired phone.
And then you can use iTunes
to transfer that archive
over to your Mac to
do something with.
This is the file that Apple
is going to be wanting to have
from you when you talk
to us about a problem.
So either attaching it to
the radar or delivering it
to developer technical support.
So here's the various
key-chords.
Shift + Control + Option
+ Command + Period (.)
for Mac OS.
Volume up + Volume
Down + Power for iOS.
On the phone you'll get a slight
vibration, on iPad you won't.
On watchOS it's press and
hold the digital crown
and side button for
a full second.
If you don't present it long
enough you'll actually get a
screenshot instead.
There will be a slight haptic
vibration when you trigger it.
Play/Pause + Volume Down tvOS.
Note that on older remotes
for the Apple TV you have
to actually hold it down
for five seconds to trigger.
Deprecations, so as part
of this there be some APIs
that we're going to
be saying farewell to.
First off, all of the ASL
logging APIs are now superseded
by these new APIs
and, therefore,
those old APIs are deprecated.
There is an interesting
edge case though.
A new API for searching
the log data is not going
to be made public
in this release.
What that means is that
there's no equivalent
to asl search functionality.
If you absolutely depend on
asl search in your system
that may be a reason to wait for
adopting the new logging system.
There's also some
APIs from activities
that are being deprecated.
Instead of doing
os activity start
and os activity end we now have
you do the os activity create
as I showed you and then
call either scope or apply
to apply it to a block of code.
Os activity breadcrumb
gets replaced
with os activity user label.
Os trace with payload
gets replaced
by any of the os log calls.
Note that these functions as
of this release are now no ops.
So if you continue calling
these they're not going
to do anything.
So in summary, the new logging
system is faster, easier to use
and gives you more control,
but it does require using
new APIs and new tools.
Related sessions, I've
mentioned a few times back
in 2014 Activity
Tracing, this is the talk
in which we talk about that.
So if you want go
back and look at that.
And if you want to
get more information
about this talk, that's the URL.
Thank you very much.
[ Applause ]