[ Music ]
>> Good afternoon.
Welcome to What's New in tvOS.
My name is Hans Kim, and I'm one
of the engineers on the tvOS
team.
I'm thrilled this afternoon to
tell you about some of the new
features in tvOS 12.
We're going to talk about
Password AutoFill, and we'll
take a look at some new
enhancements in tvOS's focus
engine.
And, we'll conclude with some
exciting news about some new UI
patterns on tvOS.
We have a lot of ground to
cover, and we have some great
demos, so let's begin.
And, to get us started, I'd like
to invite my colleagues Alex and
Conrad to tell us about helping
your customers sign into your
app.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Hans.
Hello everyone.
My name is Alex Sanciangco.
And, today I am so excited to
talk to you all about Password
AutoFill.
Signing in is a common
experience that users have with
apps.
For instance, here's an app I've
been working on called "shiny,"
that shows our users an adorable
photo of their favorite dogs
every day when they log in.
In order to make logging in as
smooth as possible, we've
brought Password AutoFill to
tvOS 12.
With an experience just as
familiar and easy as Password
AutoFill on iOS.
Let me show you what I mean.
First, I'd like to show you
continuity keyboard.
As you might remember,
continuity keyboard is an iOS
feature that allows users to
enter text on the Apple TV,
using their iOS device.
Let's see it in action.
I'm going to navigate to that
shiny app, and I'll select the
email field.
As I expect, I see the
continuity keyboard notification
appear, which has now been
enhanced to offer Password
AutoFill as well.
So, I'll open that up now.
And, I see that my username and
password are suggested for the
shiny app right there on the
QuickType bar.
And, I know that with one tap,
it'll be automatically filled
into the TV, and I'll be signed
in.
So, I'll do that now.
Aw, look at that guy.
[ Applause ]
So, I got the notification on my
iPhone because my iPhone and
Apple TV are on the same iCloud
account.
And, if you're a user of the TV
remote and control center, or
the TV remote app, the
experience is similar there as
well.
But, we have something else
brand new we want to show you
today, that shows just how easy
we've made signing in, even for
a guest that might not have ever
used your Apple TV before.
And, to demonstrate that, I'd
like to invite Conrad up to the
stage.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Alex.
Now, suppose that I'm Alex's
cousin.
I'm visiting for the week.
Now, his puppy's pretty cute.
But, I really want to sign in to
shiny so I can see pictures of
my own dog Max, or maybe his
adorable sister, Min.
Now, I've never used his Apple
TV before, so I don't have any
of the keyboard options
available that he just
discussed.
Furthermore, since I use a
strong password saved in iCloud
keychain, I haven't memorized
it.
I expect that I'm going to have
to look up my password, and then
type it in character by
character on the Apple TV.
Well, let's see what happens.
I'm going to go over here.
I'm going to go to my phone.
And, let's sign in.
Oh, and even before I can open
settings, or ask Siri to look up
my password, my iPhone is
already offering to help me
AutoFill my password.
So, I'm going to open up this
notification.
There we go.
And, by entering a PIN I know
that I am securely connecting to
this Apple TV.
Going to Touch ID.
And, my shiny credential appears
right at the top, with one tap
I'm signed in.
Super easy.
[ Applause ]
Aw. Sorry, it's just-- it's Min.
OK.
Now one thing you might be
wondering is how did that work
without all the iPhones in the
room showing a notification?
I think this is really, really
cool.
The Siri remote is able to
locate nearby iPhones on which
to offer AutoFill.
So, in this case, only my iPhone
showed a notification.
And that is Password AutoFill
for tvOS.
I'd now like to thank-- sorry,
I'd like to invite Alex back up
to the stage to show you just
how easy it is to make this work
flawlessly in your apps.
Alex?
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Conrad.
Man, I love that demo.
I just think that feature is so
cool.
Password AutoFill for tvOS is
part of a suite of features that
you might have heard about on
Monday, meant to simplify the
password experience.
These features integrate into
existing apps, without you
having to make any big changes.
And, there's a few things that
you developers can do to ensure
that Password AutoFill is as
great as possible.
Let's go over those briefly now.
First, you'll want to ensure
that the QuickType bar appears
for your text fields.
Next, you want to make sure that
your app's credentials are
suggested on the QuickType bar.
And lastly, you want to enable a
one-tap sign in experience.
Now, let's look at how to do
this in more detail.
To ensure the QuickType bar
appears for your text fields,
you want to adopt
UITextContentTypes.
tvOS will automatically try to
detect username and password
fields, and you can help this
process by explicitly marking
your text fields.
This is as easy as setting a
single property on those text
fields.
Simply set, for your username
text fields, it's
textContentType to .username,
and similarly for your password
field, you'll set its
textContentType to .password.
Very simple, and this can be
done in Interface Builder as
well.
So, after adopting the
textContentTypes, here's what
viewers would likely see in that
continuity keyboard
notification.
And, this is good, because it
gives users access to their
passwords.
But, it's behind that key icon.
Too many taps away.
What we really want the user to
see is this: your app's
credentials suggested right on
the QuickType bar.
The way you get this behavior is
by adopting a technology called
Associated Domains, which
securely tells Password AutoFill
which domains to suggest on the
QuickType bar.
Associated Domains is a powerful
technology that enables other
features, such as universal
links and Handoff.
It creates a secure relationship
between the domain the user's
accessing and the app that they
have downloaded.
Password AutoFill then uses this
relationship to suggest the
exact right credential, right on
top of the QuickType bar.
To learn how to adopt Associated
Domains, I highly recommend
checking out "Introducing
Password AutoFill for Apps" from
WWDC of last year.
This talk contains a
step-by-step guide for how to
adopt Associated Domains for iOS
apps, and the steps are
identical for tvOS apps.
So, after adopting Associated
Domains, this is what the user
will likely see on the shiny app
after tapping your credential on
the QuickType bar.
And, this is awesome.
The user has their username and
passwords on their Apple TV
without having to type a single
character.
But what we really want the user
to see is this.
Being automatically signed in
and seeing their pupper of the
day, because they've been signed
in with one tap.
You can get this behavior by
implementing the
preferredFocusEnvironments API.
So, after filling in a password,
a focus update occurs.
And, Password AutoFill will
perform the action of the
focused button if one is
focused.
So, you should implement the
preferredFocusEnvironments API,
so you can provide your login
button to the focus engine.
Let's look at how you might
implement this.
Here I have a sample
implementation of the
preferredFocusEnvironments API,
which returns an array of
UIFocusEnvironment objects.
First, we'll try to grab text
out of our username and password
fields.
And, if we can, we'll just
return that login button to the
focus engine.
If we weren't able to grab any
text, that just means the user
hasn't entered any yet.
So, we'll return the username
text field to be focused.
Super simple.
So, let's recap some of the
major takeaways of Password
AutoFill.
For customers, Password AutoFill
reduces the friction within your
app by enabling a one-tap sign
in experience.
If any adoption is needed on
your part for developers, this
is super simple.
You simply have to just adopt
UITextContentTypes, adopt
Associated Domains so that your
apps credentials are surfaced to
the QuickType bar.
And, lastly, implement
preferredFocusEnvironments to
enable that one-tap sign in
experience.
And that's Password AutoFill for
tvOS.
We cannot wait for you and your
users to get your hands on it.
Next, I'd like to invite up Ada
to talk about focus
enhancements.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Alex.
Hi, my name is Ada Turner, and
I'm really excited to talk to
you today about some
enhancements that we've made to
Focus in tvOS 12.
Focus is a great way for users
to interact with your apps on
tvOS.
It allows them to gracefully
scroll through content and
provides playful movement
hinting as they interact with
the touch surface of the Siri
remote.
Apps built with UIKit,
SpriteKit, and SceneKit, all
have native support for focus.
However, apps that use
alternative methods to render
their content have not been able
to directly support the focus
engine.
Today, I am pleased to announce
that in tvOS 12, the focus
engine, now supports apps
regardless of how they are
rendered.
[ Applause ]
This means that apps written in
frameworks such as Metal can now
adopt focus directly into their
interaction model.
This is accomplished by allowing
you to conform your own classes
to focus protocols, even if they
don't inherit from UIKit
components.
Now, what this means for your
apps is they will get state
management of what's currently
focused.
Geometric determination of where
focus can and cannot move.
Full accessibility support, and
focus movement, hinting, and
scrolling that feels just like
native tvOS apps.
Before we take a look at the new
focus API's, let's briefly
refresh ourselves on some
existing focus components.
First, we have
UIFocusEnvironments.
This protocol manages state
where focus interactions can
take place.
It is notified when focus
updates occur, and can influence
focus update behavior.
In UIKit, UIViewController is a
great example of a focus
environment.
Next, we have UIFocusItem.
This protocol inherits from
FocusEnvironment, and adds the
ability for focus items to
actually be able to become
focused.
UIKit's UIView, and SpriteKit's
SKNode are great examples of
focus items.
And, finally we have the
UIFocusSystem, which provides
the famously useful
functionality of being able to
register custom sounds to play
during focus interactions.
For more information on how to
work with these components, and
debug focus, I highly recommend
that you watch "Focus
Interaction in tvOS 11" from
last year.
And now, I'm really excited to
introduce some new components to
the focus engine.
First, starting in tvOS 12, we
are expanding the functionality
of the focusSystem object.
You may now retrieve a
focusSystem for a given
environment, and access the
currently focused item off of
the focusSystem.
Next, we are introducing a new
protocol, called
UIFocusItemContainer, which
provides geometric context to
Focus items.
A focusItemContainer is owned by
a focusEnvironment, and can
locate focus items within
specific regions, allowing the
focus engine to move focus to
the best candidate.
Next, we have a special type of
focusItemContainer, called
focusItemScrollableContainer,
which adds support for
automatically scrolling through
content as focus is moved.
And, finally, we now supply
focusItems with movement hints,
which contain raw values that
you can use to create visual
effects that suggest what
direction focus is about to move
in.
Now, let's take a closer look at
how we can form our own classes
to these protocols.
Let's start by implementing a
custom focusEnvironment.
In order for the focus engine to
find your environment, and its
child environments or items, you
must supply a parent focus
environment, and a
focusItemContainer.
For example, UIViewController
might provide its parent
viewController as its
parentFocusEnvironment, and its
view as its focusItemContainer.
FocusEnvironment provides
several methods you can use to
control and react to focus
updates.
For example,
preferredFocusEnvironments
allows you to guide the focus
system in selecting what item is
focused after view
initialization, or a
programmatic focus update.
I'd like to call your attention
to two specific methods on the
focusEnvironment.
SetNeedsFocusUpdate and
updateFocusIfNeeded.
Your implementation of these
methods must call to a specific
method on the focusSystem.
Next, let's implement a custom
focusItemContainer.
First, you will need to provide
a coordinateSpace.
UIView provides itself as a
coordinateSpace.
If your container is more
abstract, you may return an
existing coordinateSpace or
implement your own.
Next, you will need to implement
focusItems in rect.
This method must return any
contained focusItems whose
frames intersect with the
provided rect.
Note that the rect passed to
this method is expressed in the
coordinateSpace of the
container, and the frames of
each focusItem you return from
this method must also be
expressed in that
coordinateSpace.
Next, let's implement a custom
FocusItem.
Remember that this protocol
inherits from FocusEnvironment,
so you will need to implement
all of those methods as well.
In order for the focus engine to
move focus onto your item, it
must return "true" from
canBecomeFocused.
DidHintFocusMovement is an
optional method that is called
whenever the user moves their
finger on the touch surface of
the Siri remote.
It provides the focusItem with a
movement hint that contains raw
values you can use to create an
effect that indicates what
direction focus is about to move
in.
Finally, you will need to
provide a frame.
As I said before, this frame
must be expressed in the
coordinateSpace of the
containing focusItemContainer.
For example, UIView expresses
its frame in the coordinateSpace
of its superview, which is also
its containing
focusItemContainer.
Now, let's take a closer look at
the focusMovementHint object.
Movement direction is a vector,
whose values range between
negative 1, negative 1 and 1,1
representing how close focus is
to moving in a particular
direction.
This value is tied to the path a
user's finger creates on the
touch surface of the Siri
remote.
Perspective, rotation, and
translation are all values you
can use to match tvOS's native
interaction hinting.
And, interactionTransform
combines all three of these
values into a single 3D
transform.
Next, let's look at how to
implement a custom
focusItemScrollableContainer.
This is a special type of
focusItemContainer, and by
conforming to this protocol,
your container signals to the
focus engine that it supports
scrolling.
For example, UIScrollView
conforms to this protocol.
It provides three additional
properties that allows the focus
engine to manage its scrolling
behavior.
First, we have contentOffset,
which is a read/write property
representing how far the
container has been scrolled.
This property will automatically
be set by the focus engine as
focus is moved in order to keep
the currently focused item on
screen.
Second, we have contentSize,
which represents the total size
of your scrollable content and
third, we have visibleSize,
which represents the onscreen
size of your container.
This property is analogous to
bounds.size on the UIScrollView.
It is important to remember that
contentOffset will be set
automatically, and it is your
responsibility to update your
rendered content as appropriate
whenever this property is set.
Now, let's talk about adding
accessibility to our custom
rendered apps.
It's actually incredibly easy.
By implementing
focusItemContainers, focusItems
in rect method, you are
providing the focus engine with
enough information to allow
voiceover to assist your users
in navigation.
Remember to set accessibility
labels and accessibility hints
on your focusItems in order for
voiceover to give your users the
best experience.
I highly recommend that you
watch "What's New in
Accessibility" from WWDC 2016
for a more in-depth look at how
focus and voiceover work
together in tvOS.
And now, I'd like to invite my
colleague, Paul, to give us a
demo on how to create a
focus-powered Metal app.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Ada.
So, I'm working on the setting
screen for a Metal-based game.
At the bottom of the screen,
there's some standard UI
buttons.
And, up at the top are some
tiles for selecting levels.
These tiles are actually
rendered by the game engine
itself.
I'm sure you can tell by the
incredible 3D graphics that you
see up there.
So, I want to be able to select
the tiles using the remote.
Previously, I would have had to
handle events from the remote
myself, and implement my own
navigation, trying my best to
match the feel of the focus
engine.
In tvOS 12, I can connect these
tiles directly to the focus
engine.
So, let's go ahead and do that.
The first thing I'm going to do
is extend my LevelTile class to
implement the UIFocusItem.
This is what will allow it to
become focused.
There's a few methods here.
I'm just going to direct your
attention to a few at the top.
It canBecomeFocused, I'm going
to enter in "true."
That's straightforward.
For parentFocusEnvironment, I'm
going to return the MetalView
that renders these items.
Finally in didUpdateFocus in
context, I'm going to set the
tile to draw itself in an active
state when it becomes focused.
Next, I need to tell the focus
engine about these new items.
To do that, I'm going to extend
that MetalView that renders
them.
The view is already in the view
hierarchy, and the focus engine
already knows about it.
So, it's a great place to hook
in.
And, because this is a UIView,
it already conforms to
UIFocusItemContainer.
And, it provides itself as a
coordinatespace.
The only thing I have to do is
override FocusItem in rect to
return my level tiles, which of
course are now UIFocusItems.
And, I can get a performance win
here, by only returning the
tiles these frames intersect the
path in search rect.
Yikes.
Let's take a look and see how
that works.
So, now you can see that the
tiles are focusable, and the
system even plays a standard
sound when they become focused.
I can even move focus in between
my custom tiles, and the
standard UI buttons down at the
bottom.
There's a problem here, though.
The tiles extend offscreen.
If I move focus offscreen, I
can't see what I'm interacting
with.
Of course, what I want is for
the tiles to move onscreen as
they become focused.
So, let's implement that.
I'm going to extend that
RenderView again, this time to
implement
UIFocusItemScrollableContainer.
Now, the important thing here is
to adjust my rendering by the
contentOffset.
The focus engine will set my
contentOffset as focus moves to
keep the currently focused item
onscreen.
Because this is a UIView, I'm
going to also update by
bounds.origin so that the
coordinateSpace conversion
continues to work correctly.
See how that works?
So, now you can see that as I
focus a tile, it moves onscreen.
If I keep going, I get nice,
smooth scrolling with the same
momentum-- thanks-- nice, smooth
scrolling with the same momentum
and animation as if this was a
UIScrollView.
So, this is looking pretty good,
but I think we can do even
better.
What I really want is for these
tiles to come alive when they're
focused, just like the system
elements.
Let's go ahead and do that.
Going to go back up to
LevelTile.
And, I'm going to implement an
optional method,
didHintFocusMovement.
I'm going to take the suggested
perspective, rotation, and
translation values from the
UIFocusMovementHint, and apply
them when I render the
focusTile.
Let's see how that looks.
Now, as I move my finger on the
trackpad, the tile interacts
just the way I'd expect.
So, now I've added focus support
to my custom Metal objects, and
they feel just as familiar as if
they were written using ULikeIT.
Back to you, Ada.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Paul.
Wow, that was a really Metal
demo.
With just a few lines of code,
we were able to give our Metal
user interface beautifully
smooth focused movement and
scrolling, and delightful
interaction hinting, just like
native tvOS apps.
Now, let's recap all the awesome
new focus features we learned
about today.
First, we learned how to
implement custom
focusEnvironments and
focusItems, even if they don't
inherit from UIKit components.
Second, we learned how to use
focusItemContainer, so that when
users move focus through our
apps, it feels just like native
tvOS apps.
Third, we learned how to use
focusMovementHint to make our
interface come alive as people
interact with the Siri remote.
Fourth, we learned how to use
focusItemScrollableContainer to
allow people to scroll through
our apps content with that
smooth, familiar, native
feeling.
And, finally, we learned how to
give our apps full accessibility
support simply by adopting these
protocols, and providing
accessibility labels and hints
so that everyone can enjoy our
apps.
All of these awesome new
features are available today in
the Developer Beta, and I highly
recommend that you download it,
and find out just how easy it is
to add focus support to your
custom rendered apps.
And now, I'd like to invite Hans
back on the stage, to tell us
about some awesome UI patterns
on tvOS.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Ada.
Focus interaction is integral in
how we feel connected to the
screen across the room.
And, tvOS has many common UI
patterns that make the most out
of it.
One such example is a label that
animates its text when it's
focused.
Internally scrolling text, or
marquee animation, is a useful
technique in presenting variable
length strings without altering
the label's external geometry.
It's also very effective in
visually highlighting where your
current focus is.
This behavior is very widely
used across tvOS, but there's
not an easy way to do this.
That is, until now.
tvOS 12 makes it really easy.
All you have to do is to set a
new property on your label,
enables
MarqueeWhenAncestorFocused to
"true."
[ Applause ]
Then, when a view containing the
label comes in focus, and the
label contains a string, it's
too long for the width.
It will animate the string
horizontally in a loop.
We've used this API ourselves,
and we think you will really
like how simple it is to adopt
the behavior.
So, that's text scrolling in UI
label.
But, tvOS has many more idioms
and patterns, such as an image
and a label when come alive when
in focus, an arbitrary view
hierarchy that floats as one
solid unit, buttons with
customizable focus movement and
content,
and widgets for representing
people.
And, as you can see, these
patterns are ubiquitous across
tvOS and Apple's own apps.
And, since they've been
available in TVMLKit, we see
them adopted in your apps as
well.
But, what if your app is based
on UIKit?
Well, we're really thrilled to
share with you that tvOS 12 will
make several of these available
for your UIKit-based apps.
[ Applause ]
And, we do this through a new
lightweight framework, TVUIKit.
The first four elements in
TVUIKit are poster, caption
button,
card, and monogram.
Let's take a look at each.
Poster view is about images.
And, TVPosterView is a composed
view specializing in presenting
an image, and a footer, which
itself is composed of up to two
labels.
When a poster view is in focus,
the image grows in size, and the
labels move out of the way to
give room.
When it relinquishes focus, the
image and labels come back to
the normal layout.
When you program an image to a
TVPosterView, it works out just
the right amount by which the
image grows.
And, TVPosterView is an ideal
API for creating a UI like this.
It's really easy.
And, that's TVPosterView.
Next, is caption button.
Caption button is about
call-to-action.
And, TVCaptionButtonView is a
composed view specializing in
presenting a button-like
content, and a footer, which
itself is composed of up to two
labels.
The content view has a blurred
background, and can either have
an image, or a text.
When a CaptionButtonView is in
focus, it floats and unlike the
PosterView, it increases its
size only in the leading, top,
and trailing directions.
You can also limit the floating
motion to horizontal only or
vertical only.
And, when you use multiple
TVCaptionButtons and give them a
consistent motion direction, you
can create a sense of grouping.
And, TVCaptionButton makes it
really easy to do this.
Next, is CardView.
CardView is about custom views.
And, TVCardView specializes in
presenting arbitrarily composed
view hierarchy.
When a CardView is in focus,
it's content view floats and all
of its subviews move in unison
as part of the floating content
view.
TVCardView is a great way to
create a UI like this.
It's really straightforward.
Next, is monogram.
MonogramView is for representing
people.
And, TVMonogramView has a
circular content image, and a
footer, which itself is composed
of up to two labels.
When you don't provide either a
person name, or an image,
TVMonogramView provides a
generic silhouette.
If you do provide a person name,
TVMonogramView will create a
monogram from the initials.
And, of course, when you provide
an image, it doesn't question
it, we'll just use it.
When TVMonogramView is in focus,
the labels move out of the way
for the image to grow in size.
When you use a TVMonogramView,
creating a UI like this becomes
really straightforward.
Now, you might have noticed that
there's a consistent pattern
among these four elements.
Namely, there's a main content,
and an optional header and
footer.
And, when this composition comes
in focus, the header and footer
move out of the way, and the
content to grow in size.
This common behavior is
encapsulated in a base class,
TVLockupView.
Some of the things you can
customize in a TVLockupView are
the explicit content size.
This is really helpful when
you're laying out multiple
LockupViews.
Another one is the content-- the
size by which the content grows
when it's in focus.
These are directional insets, so
you can even specify different
amount in all four directions.
You may recall that the
CaptionButtonView is actually
using this.
When you're providing your own
content to the TVLockupView, you
can take advantage of
TVLockupViewComponent protocol.
Whenever TVLockupView state
changes, it will call
updateAppearance
forLockupViewState method on all
of its subviews that implement
it.
This is your subviews
opportunity to update its
behavior, or customize the
appearance based on the state.
You can use TVLockupView to
create your own widget that
responds to focus interaction,
or further customize the four
special purpose subclasses we
just discussed.
So, that's TVLockupView and its
subclasses.
Finally, you may recall seeing
something like this.
It's simple, but its simplicity
disguises just how difficult it
is to implement this screen.
TVUIKit makes it really easy to
do this, and that's with
TVDigitEntryViewController.
TVDigitEntryViewController
manages a fullscreen view that
presents a title label, prompt
label, a digit view, and the
numeric keyboard.
Among the things you can
customize in a
TVDigitEntryViewController are
the number of digits, and
whether the entry is secure or
not.
And, a completion handler that
allows you to process the
entered digits.
Instead of just talking about
it, I'd like to invite my
colleague Marshall over to give
us a demo.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Hans.
My name's Marshall, and today
we're going to take a look at
how you can use
TVDigitEntryViewController to
collect numerical data from your
users.
So, I have an app here that we
call Top Movies which allows me
to watch my favorite content,
but not all this content may be
appropriate for everybody in my
household, so what I'd like to
do is protect it behind a PIN
code, so I can restrict who's
allowed to watch it.
So, what we have here is a
collection view, full of some
TVPosterViews that Hans
introduced.
So, if we dive in to our
collection views:
didSelectItemAt indexPath.
First thing we want to do is
vend a
TVDigitEntryViewController, and
send appropriate title and
prompt text, let the user know
they should enter a 5-digit
passcode.
We set the number of digits to
5, and we set the isSecure entry
to "true" since we are
collecting a passcode.
Next, we're going to implement
the entryCompletionHandler.
This returns a string, once the
user has filled in the total
number of digits in the digit
view.
So, here for now, since I'm
working on the app, we're just
going to check to see if it's
all 1's.
If it is, we're going to dismiss
the view controller, and play
the content.
Otherwise, we're going to update
the prompt text, let the user
know that it was an invalid
passcode, and we're going to
call the clearEntry animated
true.
What this will do is clear out
all the digits, and shake the
digit view to let the user know
that something went wrong.
And then, finally, we're going
to present the viewController.
And, since this is just a
viewController, we can use
custom presentation styles.
So here we're going to use the
blurOverFullScreen, which was
introduced in tvOS last year.
Let's run this and see how it
works.
So, I'm going to select my
movie.
And, we see we get the
blurOverFullScreen animation,
and we get prompted to enter our
passcode.
Now, we know that it's all 1's
right now, so let's see what
happens if I enter all 2's.
We see that we get a nice shake
animation, and we update the
text.
Now, we go enter all 1's.
We know that's the correct
passcode, so we dismiss the
viewController and we can play
our content.
Now, if the user wants to use--
they most likely want to use
their own passcode, so what
we're going to do is we're going
to take this settings button
here, and we're going to allow
the user to set their own
passcode.
So, I've got my [inaudible]
action down here.
And, again, we're going to vend
a TVDigitEntryViewController,
and we're going to set the title
text to let them know that we're
collecting a passcode that will
restrict which content can be
watched, and again, set the
number of digits to 5.
Next, we're going to implement
the entryCompletionHandler
again.
Now, I have an extra variable up
here, a optional string called
passcodeToVerify.
What this is going to do, is
it's going to hold the passcode
the user enters the first time
so we can verify it to make sure
that they actually entered the
correct passcode.
So, we see that when our
completionHandler gets called,
we check to see if the
passcodeToVerify is nil.
If it is, this is the first
time, so we're going to ask them
to verify their passcode, and
we're going to call the
clearEntry animated, except this
time false.
We don't want to shake it,
because they didn't do anything
wrong, but we want to clear it
so they can enter it again.
Otherwise, if there is a value
stored in the passcodeToVerify,
we know they are verifying it.
And, we check to make sure
they're equal.
If they are, we save the new
passcode, and dismiss the
viewController.
Otherwise, we reset the prompt
text back to what we originally
asked, clear the entry, and then
set the passcodeToVerify to nil
so they can try again.
And, finally we present our
viewController.
So, now we're going to go to
Settings.
It's going to ask us to please
set a passcode.
Let's go ahead and set it all
1's first.
Now it's asked us to verify.
But, this time I'm going to
enter all 2's.
Since we know that was
incorrect.
So, now let's do it correctly
this time.
We've got five 1's, we're going
to verify our PIN code.
And, we can save the PIN code so
the user can use it when they
need to.
And, that's how you can
implement
TVDigitEntryViewController into
your application.
I'd like to invite Hans back up
on stage.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Marshall.
That was a great demo showing
just how easy it is to adopt a
common UI patterns, using
TVUIKit.
In addition, TVUIKit also has
built-in support for
localization, including
right-to-left language support,
and of course, accessibility.
TVUIKit is available in the
Developer Beta, so please
download and check out the
headers.
And, as you use it in your app,
we think it will really save you
time and resources so you can
instead, focus on what makes
your app truly shine.
So, that's TVUIKit.
This afternoon we've just looked
at a few areas where tvOS 12 can
improve your app's user
experience and performance.
We learned about Password
AutoFill, which makes it really
easy for your customers to sign
in to your app.
And, it's especially more
helpful if they have strong
password.
We've also saw how we expanded
tvOS's focus engine to support
all apps, regardless of how they
are rendered.
This is truly game-changing.
And, finally we looked at
TVUIKit, which makes it really
easy to adopt common UI patterns
on tvOS.
We have a session page with all
of this information and more.
And, we'll be available at the
tvOS labs, and Safari WebKit
labs throughout the week.
Please drop by and say hello,
and bring your questions and
code.
Thanks for joining us this
afternoon.
Have a wonderful WWDC.