[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Hello, everyone, and welcome
to Building Voice with Siri
Shortcuts.
My name is Amit, and I'm here
today with my colleague Ayaka
Nonaka.
And we are so excited to be here
and talk to you about Shortcuts.
And you all know, shortcuts
allow you to accelerate your
users to the things they value
the most in your apps.
What we are really excited about
is that your users can add these
shortcuts to Siri and perform
them with their voice wherever
they are.
So, it's paramount that we build
a great voice experience for all
of our users accessing them
through voice.
And that's what we'll focus on
today.
So, let's get started.
First, we'll talk about how your
users can add shortcuts to Siri
and how simple it is to write --
use it right away.
Then, we'll talk about how you
can provide downloads that can
be spoken by Siri, through
custom responses.
Then Ayaka will go over some of
the best practices that you
should adopt to create great
voice and UI experiences for
your shortcuts.
And finally, we'll go over how
you can bring the experience of
setting shortcuts to your apps.
So, before we dive into all the
exciting details of adopting
shortcuts and custom responses,
let's take a look at the
experience of setting a shortcut
with Siri.
My teammates and I have been
working on this app called Soup
Chef.
It lets you order soup.
Now Soup Chef adopts all our new
shortcut APIs, and every time a
user places an order, Soup Chef
lets the system know by donating
a custom intent to Siri.
So, yesterday, I ordered some
tomato soup.
And it was really great.
So much so, that I would like to
order it again.
And wouldn't it be great if I
can just do that from Siri?
Well, now we can.
So, when we go to Siri's
Settings UI, you see that Siri's
already suggesting that donated
intent to be created into a
shortcut.
So, let's tap on it.
And we are presented with this
screen, where we can set up a
phrase that you can say to Siri
and perform your shortcut.
There are also a lot of details
on this screen from Soup Chef
that convey to me as a user what
this shortcut would exactly do.
How to get these right, we'll
talk about that in a little bit.
But for now, I would like to
associate a phrase with this
shortcut.
Something that is short.
Something that's memorable and I
can say it again and again.
It's not always easy to come up
with that right in the moment,
so I figure that Soup Chef is
suggesting I call it, Soup Time.
I like that.
I'll take it.
Now, when I record the phrase, I
have a shortcut to order soup
with Siri.
Let's try it out.
Now, when I say to Siri, "Soup
Time," I'm asked to confirm
whether I would like to run the
intent, and when I say, "Yes,"
the order is placed.
And it's that easy.
Your users will set up shortcuts
for things they do most often.
And they can use these shortcuts
wherever they are, from their
iOS devices, from their wrist
using the Apple Watch, in their
homes using the HomePod, as well
as on the go with CarPlay.
So, we should pay a lot of
attention to the voice
experience that they encounter.
Towards that goal, let's talk
about custom responses.
Shortcuts allow you to provide
dialogues that can be spoken by
Siri, and this gives you the
ability to provide relevant
information, important
information, right with voice.
Fundamentally, shortcuts are --
custom responses are template
strings whose structure you
define in the Intent Definition
File.
And based on the type of
information you provide in your
responses, shortcuts can be one
of four types.
The first is a confirmation
custom response.
This gives you the opportunity
to provide critical information
before your users commit to
running the shortcut.
Next, is a success response.
And it gives you a chance to
provide an auxiliary relevant
information, after the shortcut
has run, and the structure of a
success response consists of
Siri letting the users know that
their order was successful, or
their shortcut ran successfully,
followed by any information that
you provide attributed to your
app.
The third type of custom
response is an informational
response.
And we are really excited about
this.
Informational response allows
you to provide information like
transit schedules or ski
forecast right within Siri, with
voice.
This opens the door for a whole
new category of apps which was
not possible before with Siri.
And finally, when things do not
work as expected, custom error
responses give you the
opportunity to explain what went
wrong instead of just saying,
"Something didn't work."
The structure consists of Siri
communicating to the users that
their intent did not
successfully execute, followed
by information from your app,
and the interaction punctuated
by Siri, advising users to
continue in your apps.
Now, that we understand what
custom responses are, let's take
a look at how you would adopt
them in your apps.
Custom responses work hand in
hand with custom intents.
So, the first step is to define
an intent that models the use
case you are trying to create a
shortcut for.
For Soup Chef, we created an
intent called Order Soup, and it
lets you, you guessed it, order
soup.
Alongside the intent, you have
to pick a category for your
intent.
And the category you pick
influences how Siri speaks about
it or what you see across the OS
like the order buttons.
So, pick something that feels
natural, that works well with
your use case.
Once we have defined our custom
intent, let's go over to the
Responses Tab.
And in the Responses Tab, you
see that we already have a
success and failure response
codes.
But these are just a generic
response codes which don't
convey much more information
besides the status of the
operation.
What I would like to do, is let
our users know how long it will
be until their order is ready
and they can to the store and
pick it up.
So, what I want to do is define
a custom success response for
that.
Towards that goal, the next step
is to declare the response
properties that you will use in
your templates to provide
information at run time.
So, if you go over to the
Properties Section, I'm going to
add a Wait Time and a Soup
Property.
With that in place, the only
thing left to do in our
definition of custom responses
is to define the template.
The template is what is spoken
out by Siri.
So, when we look at the template
section of our Intent Definition
File, now I'm going to add my
success template.
Not just that.
Our store is getting a little
popular and we tend to run out
of soup these days.
So, it will be great if instead
of just throwing a random error,
I can let the users know that
the soup is out of stock.
So, I will add another response
code called, "Failure Out of
Stock," with a template that
communicates that the soup is
out of stock.
With that, we have defined our
intent responses.
And when you do that, XCode
automatically cogenerates a
custom response subclass.
This subclass has all the
properties that you defined as
well as custom constructors for
your templates, which take all
the important properties that
you need to construct that
template.
Now the last step that is left
to do, is to use these responses
in our Intent Handler.
Handling a custom intent
comprises of two steps: confirm
and handle.
In confirmation, we are asked
whether we are ready to handle
this intent at this time.
So, we'll first find out whether
the soup the user has requested
is in our menu.
If it is, we'll let the system
know that we are ready to place
the order.
But this is our chance to also
check that the soup is available
right now, and that we can place
the order of that.
So, let's do that.
First, I'll grab a reference to
my menu item.
Then check if it's available.
And if it isn't, I'm going to
call the Completion Handler with
our new custom Failure Out of
Stock Response Code.
If everything looks great, we'll
continue as before.
This is also our chance to
provide custom response --
custom confirmation response.
Support for those will be coming
in upcoming [inaudible].
Alright, that was confirmation.
Now, it's time to handle the
intent.
For us, that means to place the
order for the soup.
So, I'm going to build an order
from all the information that is
present on my intent.
And then place the order with
our Order Manager.
And if it's successful, we'll
let the system know, by calling
the Completion Handler with the
Success Response Code.
However, since we defined the
Custom Success Response
Template, this is our chance to
provide the wait time.
So, let's do just that.
And with that, we have added
support for two really useful
custom responses to our custom
intent.
Let's see how it looks.
So before, all we could let the
users know was, "Your order was
placed."
But now, Siri can speak out that
it will be about 10 minutes
before they should come down to
the store.
And that's really helpful.
The improvement to the usability
is even more stark if you look
at the error case.
Before, "Sorry, there was a
problem with the app."
But now, we can let the users
know that the soup is out of
stock and then they can decide
what they would like to do.
Either, they can go into our app
and order something else or try
again later.
So, you saw that Siri and
shortcuts allowed you to provide
custom dialogues, but that's not
all.
As soup engineers, we work
really hard to build superb
experiences for our users.
[ Applause ]
And wouldn't it be great if we
can bring those experiences from
our apps to our shortcuts
wherever they are run?
With Intents UI extensions, you
can do just that.
Intents UI extensions allow you
to provide custom UI, familiar
UI from your apps, to shortcuts.
And it is displayed all across
the OS, on Lock Screen, in
Search , and of course, within
Siri.
To learn more about how you can
build great, Intents UI
extensions, please take a look
at the WWDC 2017 session,
"What's New in SiriKit?"
So, we built a custom Intents UI
extension for Soup Chef app.
And let's see how that looks.
Again, this is where we started
out with.
But with a custom Intents UI
Extension, now I'm able to show
the users the entire invoice and
convince that we got all the
details right, that it will be
2.95, before they place the
order, which is incredibly
helpful.
Once they place the order,
instead of just saying, "It's
done," we can now show them the
receipt and reaffirm that we got
everything right and it will be
ten minutes before they should
come down there.
Alright, so you saw how easy it
is to add support for Custom UI
and Custom Responses.
Now, let's take a look at how we
did that in Soup Chef.
Alright, what you see here is
our app Soup Chef.
If we go to the Intents
Definition File, you can see
that we have a custom order soup
intent defined.
This intent is off-category
order.
Now, let's look at the response
section that is associated with
my intent.
Here, I have properties and
template sections.
What I would like to do is add
the custom success response that
we just talked about.
So, let's start by adding the
wait time property.
I'll click the Plus button, and
name my property Wait Time.
I'll leave it of the Type
String, so I can format the date
however I see fit before
providing it into the dialogue.
To reaffirm which soup the user
ordered, I'm also going to add
the soup property.
Now, soup is a custom object in
our app.
So, I'm going to select the type
"Custom."
Now, let's take a look at the
response codes.
We have a failure and a success
code.
Here, I'm going to define the
template for our Wait Time
Response Template.
So, let's do that.
"Your Soup Will Be Ready in Wait
Time."
I would also like to add our Out
of Stock Error Code.
For that, I'll click the Plus
Button and create another
response code.
I'll call it "Failure, Out of
Stock."
Since this is an error code,
I'll uncheck the Success
checkbox.
And now, finally, let's define
the template for it.
"Sorry, Soup is Out of Stock."
And with that, we have defined
our custom responses.
Now, let's head over to the
Intent Handler file.
Alright, here we are.
As you see here, we have a
Confirm and a Handle Method.
Let's look at Confirm first.
We find out which soup the user
has requested, and then check
with our menu manager whether
that soup exists on our menu.
If it does, we return the
response code "Ready."
What I would like to do here, is
to check whether that soup item
is available currently to order.
So first, let's grab reference
to the menu item from our menu
manager.
Then, I'm going to check if it's
available.
If it isn't, I'm going to call
the Completion Handler with our
new Failure, Out of Stock Error.
And provided the soup object
that the user requested.
Alright, so we have provided the
custom error code here in
completion.
Let's take a look at Handle.
Handling this intent means
ordering our soup.
So first, we build the Order
Object from Intent.
Then we place the order, using
our order manager.
And finally, let the system know
that the order was successful.
But this is our chance to
provide users with more helpful
information like wait time.
So, let's call the Completion
Handler with our New Custom
Response Code.
This response template takes the
soup and wait time strengths.
So, I'll provide that from my
intent.
And we can grab the wait time
from our order.
And that's it.
So, you saw how easy it is to
add support for custom responses
to our custom intent.
You start by defining a custom
intent that works for your use
case.
You follow it up by defining
custom responses that you want
Siri to speak out.
And finally, you provide them in
your Intent Handler.
Now, I placed that order for
that soup earlier, so I better
head back and get it.
So, please welcome Ayaka Nonaka,
who will talk to you about some
of the best practices that you
should adopt in order to create
great voice and UI experiences
in your apps.
Thank you and welcome Ayaka.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks so much.
Hi, everyone.
So, as Amit just showed you,
it's super easy to get started
with Siri Shortcuts.
Once a shortcut is donated, it
is available for the system to
suggest as a shortcut to use
with Siri straight out of the
box.
I'm going to be showing you some
more new shortcuts APIs, and the
best practices to help bring the
greatest experience to our
users.
And I know you care about this
because your users are going to
notice these small details and
the large amount of care that
you put into your apps.
If you saw the first session,
"Introduction to Siri
Shortcuts," you learned that
there are two ways to donate
shortcuts.
The first way is through NS User
Activity.
User Activities are great if you
want to do a basic integration,
where you just want to open the
app and show your user a
particular piece of content.
And the second way is through
Intents.
Intents are great if you want to
do a deeper integration where
you can run things in the
background and inline within the
Siri experience, so you don't
have to context with your users
out of that to get things done.
And for both NS User Activities
and Intents, there are several
parameters that we can
configure.
The first one is the title.
So, in this case, Order Clam
Chowder, with the subtitle
underneath it and image next to
it, and finally, a suggested
invocation phrase which you'll
get to later.
For each of these, we're going
to go over how best to configure
them.
So, let's get started with the
title and subtitle.
So, when you're thinking about
titles and subtitles, there are
two high-level things that you
should keep in mind.
First, the title should
represent what happens when the
user runs the shortcut.
Your user is going to want to
know exactly what happens before
they run the shortcut or add
that shortcut to use with Siri.
And secondly, the subtitles will
provide more information, but
only if you need it.
So, let's dive into a little bit
more of the details.
The first easy thing to do is
see a sentence case.
This is to make sure that we
provide a consistent experience
across all different apps and
their shortcuts.
Next, it's important to keep the
title concise.
This is because we're dealing
with potentially a limited
amount of [inaudible].
And you can do this by dropping
articles like "a" and "an" if
your language allows for it.
Next, it's super important to
include critical information.
For example, if you have a
payments app that lets you send
money to your friends and you
have a shortcut for that, it's
important to put the dollar
amount or your currency amount
in that.
Probably in the title in this
case.
Next, if we're working with
Intents, it's important to
include a verb.
And if you're working with
English, we should put that at
the beginning and prepend the
verb to your phrase.
And last but not least, to make
sure that we provide the
shortcuts experience to everyone
around the world, it's very
important to localize.
So, not let's take a look at
some things that we should
avoid.
So, the first thing that we
don't need to include, is the
name of your app.
This is because our RUI already
attributes the name of your app,
and by not including this, you
can save even more space.
And second, we don't need to put
duplicate information in the
title and subtitle for similar
reasons to save space and leave
room for critical information.
And lastly, we don't want to use
quotation marks unless you're
actually quoting something
that's going to be used verbatim
in the shortcut.
For example, if you have a
shortcut to send a message, you
can put the content of the
message in the quotation marks.
So, let's take a look at an
example.
This example says, "A clam
chowder from Soup Chef.
The best way to get soup, Soup
Chef."
And just based on what we
learned about, I think we can
all agree that this is not a
good example.
So, let's try to make it better.
So, the first easy thing that we
can do is to drop the "From Soup
Chef," because as you see, Soup
Chef is already attributed in
this UI.
So, now we have "A Clam
Chowder."
But when I'm looking at this,
I'm not sure what's going to
happen when I run the shortcut.
Am I ordering the soup or just
looking at it?
Who knows?
So, let's fix that by adding a
verb.
And while I'm doing that, I'm
also going to drop the article
"a" to save some space.
So now I have "Order Clam
Chowder."
So, when I'm looking at this,
I'm thinking, "I want to order a
Clam Chowder, not a Clam
Chowder, which doesn't sound
very delicious and we're trying
to sell soup here, so that's
really not ideal.
But the good thing is, we can
fix this really easily by simply
dropping the quotation marks.
And now we have, "Order Clam
Chowder."
And I think at this point, our
title's looking pretty good.
But let's take a look at the
subtitle.
The subtitle says, "The best way
to get soup."
But that's basically Soup Chef's
tag line.
I already know that Soup Chef is
the best way to get my soup.
And it's not adding any extra
information that is specific to
the shortcut.
And, so that's already not good,
but a more critically bad thing
is that Soup Chef recently
started offering delivery
service, and I don't know where
I'm getting my soup delivered
to.
Am I getting it to my home, my
office, someone else's office,
no idea.
So, let's fix that by adding a
delivery location.
So, now I have "Order Clam
Chowder to 1 Apple Park Way."
And now I know exactly what
happens when I run the shortcut.
So, that is great.
And in the Settings UI, it might
look something like this.
And this is looking pretty good.
But I think we can do a little
bit better.
So, as you can see, the Soup
Chef app icon is used for both
the Clam Chowder and Tomato Soup
cases, but wouldn't it be great
if we can show an image of a
clam chowder for the clam
chowder case and an image for
the tomato soup for the tomato
soup case?
Sort of like this.
And for this, we provide two
APIs.
One for User Activities and
another for Intents.
So, let's take a look.
So, to set some context, the
user has just viewed one of
their past soup orders and we
want to donate it, so we can
associate it -- we can associate
that with a shortcut.
So, the first thing that we want
to do is create a CS Searchable
Item Attribute Set which by the
way is the same thing that you
want to use if you want to
provide a subtitle to your user
activity, but in this case, I
want to set an image
[inaudible].
First, make an image with
chowder.
Get the PNG data out of it and
set it as the thumbnail data
property on my Attributes.
And next, I'm going to take
those attributes, set it as the
Content Attribute Set on the
User Activity, and finally I'm
going to donate the User
Activity by setting it as the
User Activity property on my
view controller.
So, let's take a look at how it
works during Intents.
For Intents, I'm actually able
to set multiple images.
One for each parameter that is
defined as an intent.
So, I'm going to set an image of
a chowder for the parameter
named "Soup," and an image of an
office for the parameter named
"Delivery Location."
And once I have that, I'm going
to create an IN Interaction out
of it and donate it.
So, at this point, you might be
wondering, "If I have a shortcut
that is based on a shortcut type
that contains multiple
parameters that have images, how
do I know which image gets
used?"
For that, we're going to go to
our Intent Definition File.
And in particular, the
Parameters Section.
So, in the Parameters Section,
we want to make sure that these
parameters, at least the ones
with images are ordered from
least specific to most specific.
So, in my case, I care more
about the soup image than the
delivery location.
So, I'm going to make sure the
soup comes below delivery
location.
And once I do that, my list of
shortcuts might look like this.
So, in the first two cases,
where the shortcut type contains
both a soup and a delivery
location, I see an image of a
soup, but in the last case,
where the shortcut type just
contains a delivery location, I
just see the image of a delivery
location.
Now, these shortcuts are looking
so great, that I just want to
tap on one and add it to Siri,
so I can use it.
And our users are super excited
about this new feature too, and
they're all so eager to start
setting up new shortcuts to use
with Siri.
But as more users starting using
this feature, we noticed
something.
We noticed a problem.
When they got to the recording
screen, they had no idea what to
say.
They could use some creative
inspiration in choosing a great
suggested shortcut phrase.
And as Soup Chef app developers
and general soup enthusiasts, we
think we have some pretty great
ideas on what would make a great
soup ordering phrase.
You know, something like
"Tomato, Tomato" or "Chowder
Time."
So, would it be great if we can
show a suggestion like this?
"Hey user, you can say something
like, 'Chowder Time.'"
And of course, we have an API
for this, so let's take a look.
So, building on a previous
example, all we have to do is
add one line.
So, User Activity has a property
called Suggested Indication
Phrase.
And I'm going to set that to
Chowder Time.
And for Intents, it's the exact
same thing.
Intents also have a property
called Suggested Indication
Phrase which I'll also set to
"Chowder Time."
So, the API for this as you can
see, is super simple.
But what actually makes a good
suggested invocation phrase?
So, the most important thing to
keep in mind is that the
suggested invocation phrase is
both short and memorable.
You have to remember that your
users are going to have to say
this phrase exactly every,
single time they run their
shortcut.
So, ideally it would be
somewhere between two to three
words.
Next, it's important to not
include the phrase, "Hey Siri,"
in your shortcut phrase, because
if your user accidentally sets
their shortcut phrase as "Hey,
Siri, Chowder Time," when they
actually run the shortcut, they
might have to say, "Hey Siri,
Hey Siri, Chowder Time," and no
one wants to do that.
So, let's take a look at some
examples.
This example says, "Hey, Siri,
please place an order, thank
you."
Although this example is polite,
it's not a good example.
First, it contains, "Hey, Siri,"
which is pretty obvious, but
it's a little bit too long for
me to want to repeat it every,
single time I want to run the
shortcut.
So, that's out.
What about this example?
This example says, "Order a clam
chowder to my office."
Seems pretty reasonable, but
this is still not good because
it's still too long.
Like, it's not short and
memorable.
And I don't think I can or want
to remember to say this phrase
every, single time I want clam
chowder delivered to my office.
What about this example?
This simply says, "Chowder
Time."
This is both short and memorable
and doesn't include the phrase,
"Hey, Siri."
So, this passes all of our tests
and that's awesome.
But we can't [inaudible] in
order to provide a truly great
shortcuts experience to your
users, around the world, you
have to make sure it's
localized.
For example, I speak both
English and Japanese, and it
would be great if I can suggest
a Use Shortcuts in Japanese sort
of like this.
So, instead of "Chowder Time," I
can be like [foreign language
spoken] which means, "I'll eat
chowder."
To do this, we can localize.
And when we're thinking about
localization, there are a couple
of things to keep in mind.
So, in addition to localizing
your code, we want to make sure
to localize the content in the
Intent Definition Files, because
as you can remember, there are a
lot of strings in there.
And second, we have to think
about pluralization.
So, even if you're not
localizing to any other language
besides English, if you have to
handle things like, "Order one
clam chowder," versus, "Order
three clam chowders," you have
to think about localization.
And to learn about all of this
stuff, check out the
Localization Session and their
labs.
They'll teach you everything
that you need to know, and more.
So, cool.
For now, let's go back to
English.
Now, that we've followed these
best practices, when we go to
the Settings UI, you are
presented with a beautiful list
of suggested shortcuts.
And right now, these are based
on a combination of suggestions
based on the user's past
routines and the things that the
user did recently.
But in addition, we provide an
API to allow developers to
suggest their own shortcuts.
And this is useful because this
allows you to suggest things for
things that the user hasn't
necessarily done yet or hasn't
done recently.
For example, if you have a music
app, you might want to offer a
shortcut for playing a
particular playlist, even if the
user hasn't played it before or
hasn't played it recently,
because presumably, if a user
has created the playlist, they
probably ought to play it at
some point in the future.
So, in the Soup Chef app, I
think it'd be great if we can
suggest a shortcut for ordering
the soup of the day, even if
they haven't ordered it
recently, or have never ordered
it, because based on past
experience, our users seem to
love it because it's both
delicious and offered at a
special price.
So, let's take a look at the API
on how to do this.
So, for Intents, you can create
an IN Shortcut out of Intent,
well, and for User Activities,
you can also create an IN
Shortcut out of it.
I'm going to wrap it in a
suggestions list and pass it
into IN Voice Shortcut Centers
Set Shortcut Suggestions Method.
And once you do that, you'll see
my suggestions alongside all the
other system's suggestions.
And by the way, the same set of
suggestions is shown in the
shortcuts app, so you can create
custom shortcuts, using your
shortcuts.
So, now that we put in all this
work to provide a great voice
experience for your users, we
want to make sure that your
users know that they can add
shortcuts to use with Siri.
And the best way to do that is
bringing shortcuts into your
app, so that users can create
shortcuts right from inside your
app.
So, for example, I just ordered
a soup, and I'm going to need a
suggestion to add this to Siri.
And when I tap, "Add to Siri,"
I'm presented with the same
system UI that allows you to
configure a new shortcut to use
with Siri.
So, let's take a look at the API
to do this.
So again, I'm going to take my
User Activity and create an IN
Shortcut out of it, and then
using that, I'm going to create
an IN UI Voice Shortcut View
Controller, set the Delegate,
and present it.
And it's the same thing for
Intents.
So, instead of creating the IN
Shortcut with a User Activity, I
will create it with Intent,
create my View Controller, set
the Delegate, and present it.
And once I do that, your user
will see this setup screen,
right from inside of your app.
In addition, rewrite an API to
allow users to delete and edit
any existing shortcuts.
We also have an API that lets
you get a list of shortcuts that
are already added to Siri by our
users.
So, for example I can use this
information to indicate which
soups on my menu have the user
has already added the shortcut
to use with Siri.
So, as you can see, for clam
chowder, I have "Chowder Time"
associated and for tomato soup,
I have "Tomato, Tomato."
Awesome. So, to summarize, let's
go over what we learned about
today.
First, we learned that Custom
Responses are critical in
providing a great voice
experience to our users.
And Amit showed us just how
simple that can be.
Next, we saw how Custom Intents
UI can help bring the apps
experience into Siri and to the
other places in the system like
Search and Lock Screen.
We also saw that details matter.
Even something small like adding
an image to your shortcuts, or
just dropping the quotation
marks from around "clam chowder"
to make it a big difference.
And bigger details like
localization can make a huge
difference.
Lastly, we learned about the
various different APIs that you
can use to bring the shortcuts
experience into your app, so
that your users can create
shortcuts to user with Siri at
the most relevant moments in
your app.
So, the documentation on how to
do this is all on
developer.apple.com, and in
addition, we'll be holding
shortcuts labs throughout the
week, including one later today.
And we also have a Watch Session
right after this, that will show
you how to bring the shortcuts
experience to the Watch and to
the Siri Watch face so that --
and they're also going to show
you how it works, even if you
don't have a Watch app.
So, it's a total must watch.
Alright.
[ Applause ]
Alright, well, now you know
everything that you need to know
to create a great shortcuts
experience for your users.
We can't wait to see what you
build with our new APIs.
Thank you for listening, and I
hope you have a great rest of
WWDC.
[ Applause ]