[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Good morning, everybody.
My name is Pavel and Marin and I
will be talking to you about
ClassKit today.
Our talk is split in three
parts.
In first part, we will give you
a general overview of ClassKit.
We will show you how data flows
through the system.
In the second part of the talk,
we will list all the classes we
have in our system and we'll
mention a few interesting things
about each one class.
And in the end, Marin is going
to show us how to adopt ClassKit
in an existing cap.
So, let's get started with the
Overview.
ClassKit is an education-based
framework which means that it is
designed to work with in a
school environment.
It allows you to define
assignable content from your
app, so that teachers can assign
it to students as homework.
Then it allows you to report
progress on those pieces of
content that were assigned by
teachers.
And this is done with privacy in
mind.
What I mean by that is that you
can report progress on any
assignable piece of content
within your app, but teachers
will only see progress on the
things that they have explicitly
assigned to students.
So, why would you adopt
ClassKit?
Well, for one, this will get a
better student experience.
Teacher workflow, because they
will be able to know exactly
what's assignable within your
app and assign it to students.
It gives teachers insights
within how students are doing in
your app.
And this enables personalized
learning.
If a teacher knows how students
are doing within your app
exactly, they'll be able to
better cater future homework
assignments.
Lastly, well, it also gives you
a competitive advantage.
This is because with teachers
while the type of information is
surfaced back to them, chances
are that they will be advocating
for your framework to -- for
your app to be used within the
school.
Speaking of schools, there's a
related technology called Apple
School Manager, and school
admins and IT use this to create
managed Apple IDs for everybody
within their organization.
So, every teacher will get a
managed Apple ID and all
students will get managed Apple
IDs.
Admins also use it to create
classes within a school, so for
example, in mathematics class we
will have a teacher with --
which is a person with a certain
managed Apple ID and students,
which are people with other
managed Apple IDs.
This is also where schools
manage all of their content and
devices.
And as we mentioned for
competitive advantage, this is
where schools will be able to
enable student progress reports
in feature of ClassKit.
Also, this is where schools are
able to purchase apps in bulk.
And any app that has enabled
ClassKit support, we'll have
works with Schoolwork checkmark
next to its name.
So, Schoolwork is the new
education app that is coming out
soon.
Students use this app to view
handouts that were assigned to
them.
And teachers use it to create
homework assignments.
And homework assignments, we
call handouts within our system.
Handouts is just a collection of
tasks.
For example, a piece of content
might be a task within a
handout.
So, this is also the place where
teachers will view progress
reports of how students are
doing within your app for a
given handout.
So, let's actually take a walk,
what the life cycle of a handout
is.
But before we can create the
handout, your app actually needs
to be able to declare what
pieces of content are
assignable.
Within our framework, this is
done using a cross code CLS
Context.
And what a CLS Context is, is
that it allows you to represent
your content as a tree
structure.
So, there is one main app
context redefined for your app.
And this acts as the root
context of the content tree --
or the context tree.
Also, all of your content is
just a descendant of the main
app context.
So, we ask that you define your
content as accurately as
possible because the sooner you
define your content, the sooner
it will be available to teachers
in Schoolwork to assign to
students.
Assuming that you've created
your context tree, a teacher
will be able to go to
Schoolwork, they will be able to
tap the Create New Handout
button, which will create a new
instance of a handout.
Then they will point the handout
to a specific piece of content
within your app, and once
they've done that, they will
assign the handout to a student.
Once a student receives that
handout, they will then tap on
the handout which will open your
app.
At that point, your app should
create the necessary contexts.
And for a better student
experience, we ask that you
navigate the student to the same
piece of content.
Marin is going to show us later
how this is done in code.
So, assuming that now the
student started working on the
homework assignment, your app
starts reporting progress back
to students and all of this
progress will be sent to the
teacher's device and bundled in
what we call a progress record
-- a report, or activity report.
So, teachers, once this is done,
will have access to that report
from within the assigned
handout.
So, this entire flow involves
you having a teacher managed ID,
a student managed ID, and maybe
a couple of devices or even one
device from which you'll be
logging in and out, so you can
test.
But with all that, we can
actually make this a little
better and we created something
that we call Developer Mode.
What Developer Mode does is that
it allows you to act as a
teacher, so that you can create
handout assignments, assign them
to students, and view progress
reports for your students, and
it also allows you to act as a
student, so you can consume
those handouts and your app can
report progress back to
teachers.
There's also a way to reset the
development data and I
personally had to use this
button quite a bit, to be
honest.
With that, let's take a look at
the classes we have in our
framework.
At the very top, we have a Data
Store.
It is used to maintain the
Context Tree, within our app.
This is also where the main app
context is exposed as a
property.
And the Data Store also gives
tracks of all modified objects
within the system.
So, if you'd like to save those
object, you can call CLS Data
Store, Save with Completion.
I'd like to mention also that
there is one shared instance of
the Data Store that you use to
interact with.
So, next, let's talk about
contexts.
We saw that contexts are a three
hierarchy, and Marin is actually
going to go in detail later
about contexts, how to use them
and mention some interesting
properties about them, but I'd
like to concentrate on Context
Identity.
So, identity of a context in
ClassKit is two things.
The first one is the Identifier
Property, and the Identifier
Property allows you to uniquely
identify contexts across
siblings.
What I mean by this is that it's
okay for you to have a context
with the same identifier,
multiple contexts with the same
identifier, as long as they
don't have the same parent,
which will be fine.
So, that [inaudible] is
something we call Context
Identifier Path.
Context Identifier Paths are
what we actually use to uniquely
identify context within the
tree, within the context tree.
And what Context Identifier
Paths are, well, it's just an
area of Context Identifiers.
The way we use them is that we
traverse the Context [inaudible]
following the path, until we
reach a note there -- the last
note within the path.
Let's actually take a walk how
this looks in action.
In this example, we have a
context card that's pointing to
Section 1 Context within some
chapter, within some book.
And we also have our Context
Tree.
To find Section 1, we will first
visit the App Context.
Then we'll visit the Book
Context.
We will find the [inaudible] of
the Book Context with Identifier
Chapter 2.
We will visit that one, and we
will do the same for Section 1.
Since Section 1 is the last
thing on our path, then this is
what the path is referring to.
So, we have a few ways to look
up contexts with our system.
One is using absolute context
paths, and to do that, you would
call the CLS Data Store Context
Matching Identifier Path Method.
The completion block of this
method will return all contexts
among the paths.
So, for example, it will be an
array of the Up Context, Book
Context, Chapter 2 Context, and
Section 1 Context.
If for some reason, Chapter 2 in
Section 1 was missing, then that
array in the completion block
will just continue to Up Context
and the Book Context.
And that gives you a chance to
create the missing context as
something else.
There's also a way to look up
contexts using relative paths.
This is useful if you already
have a reference to a context,
but you would like to find a
descendent of it.
And the method for that is
called CLS Context Descendent
Matching Identifier Path.
The difference is that here you
will either get the context
[inaudible] if it doesn't match
the path.
There's also a genetic way to
[inaudible] contexts and this is
done using CLS Data Store
Context Matching Predicate.
On the example from the slide,
we're showing you how to find
all children of a given context.
So, there's also a Data Store
delegate.
This is used in conjunction with
the path quitting methods that
we just saw.
The definition of the decoration
of the delegation is on the
screen.
It's usually useful to use this
when your contexts are
downloaded on demand to -- when
all of your context is not
available, so you want to create
things on demand.
The way it works is that as we
start querying for a path, for
our contexts among the path, if
you don't find a context on that
path, we will call the Create
Context for Identifier Method
under Delegate that you've
defined, giving you a chance to
create the missing context.
And if you do create a context,
we will take the context and go
add it to the correct place on
the tree for you.
So, as I mentioned, it's useful
for app for -- with dynamic
content.
Let's actually take a look at
how this work in action.
Again, we have the same
identifier path, but in this
case, our tree is incomplete.
And we also have a delegate.
So again, we will visit the App
Context.
Then we'll visit the Book
Then we are going to try to
visit the Chapter 2 Context, but
it doesn't exist.
So, we are going to ask a
delegate to create it.
If a delegate creates it, we
will then attach it to the
correct place on the tree, and
we'll visit that context.
Then we're going to build the
same thing for our Section 1.
Again, since section 1 is the
last thing on the path, that
means that this is what a path
is referring to.
Next, let's talk about Activity
Objects.
So, Activity Objects are
actually the objects which you
will use to report progress back
to teachers.
And they actually translate to
Activity Reports.
Activity Objects are always
associated with contexts.
You can officially allocate one
on your own.
And the way you would create a
new one is by calling CLS
Context Creating New Activity,
which will return a new activity
object associated with the
receiver of the method.
If you would like to see if
there's currently an activity
associated with your context,
you can do so by querying for
the current activity property on
the CLS Context.
I'd like to mention that every
time you co-create a new
activity, this is the same thing
as starting a new attempt at
that activity, meaning that a
teacher would receive a new
progress report.
Let's take a look at how would
you add progress to an activity.
One way is to directly set the
progress property.
And that one is to add a
progress range, from a start to
an end.
Also, know that setting the
progress property directly is
the same thing as adding a
progress range for the start of
zero.
I'd like to also mention that
it's perfectly fine for you to
add overlapping progresses
arranges or even the same
progress arranged multiple
times.
Underneath, we take care of the
details to make sure that the
correct progress is reported to
teachers in the end.
So, there's one more object that
we should talk about and that's
Activity Items.
What an Activity Item is, is a
quantity that you would
[inaudible] to represent to
teachers as part of your report.
Each activity can have one
primary activity item, and this
would be the main piece of
information you would
[inaudible] to teachers that's
apart from progress.
For example, this is useful for
a final score of a quiz.
You can also have multiple
additional activity items, which
you would use to add and show
extra information to teachers.
Like for example, how many hints
were given to a student, answer
to individual questions, and
etcetera.
So, Activity Itemization and
Abstract Class, and in our
system, we have defined at the
moment, three subclasses.
One of them is CLS Quantity
Item.
This is useful for simple scalar
quantities like hints,
experience points, and things
like that.
We also have a score item which
is useful to represent X out of
Y quantities.
For example, final score of a
quiz might be useful for this.
And we also have a Binary Item.
And this one is used to answer
Yes or No questions, type of
questions.
Let's take a look at how would
you add a primary activity item
to an activity.
Well, you will do that by first
creating an activity item.
In the [inaudible], we're
showing you how to create a
Score Item with a title of Total
Score.
And then to associate it as a
primary activity item
[inaudible] activity, you will
set it -- you will set the
primary activity item property
of an activity.
To add an additional activity
item, you will again create a
new Activity Item.
In the [inaudible] size, we're
showing how to create a quantity
item with a type of hints, and
then some quantity.
To associate it with an
activity, you would call CLS
Activity Add Additional Activity
Item after passing the item you
just created.
At that point, this activity
item will be associated with
activity.
So, there's some best practices
when dealing with activity
items.
One of them is to always save
the subclass for a primary
activity item.
What I mean by that is that
imagine a teacher assigns the
same context to two students.
You know, Student A device, you
set the primary activity item as
a score item.
On Student B device, you set the
primary activity item as a
binary item.
Well, if you do that, we can't
actually generate an aggregated
report back to teacher because
there's no clear heuristic of
how to convert from a score item
to a binary, or vice versa.
Because of that, it is best to
always have the same subclass of
an activity item as the primary
activity item.
Also, please provide clear,
concise, but descriptive titles
to your activity items.
This is because the titles that
you set on your activity items
will be visible to teachers in
their report.
And please make use of
additional activity items.
They're a great way to provide
the extra information that
teachers will actually need to
truly understand how students
are doing within your app.
With that, I'd like to invite
Marin to the stage who is going
to show us how all of this works
in action.
[ Applause ]
>> Hello, everyone.
My name is Marin, and I'm an
engineer on the ClassKit Team.
And I would like to show you how
to adopt ClassKit into a
preexisting app.
So, to do this, Pavel and I went
ahead and built a sample app.
The sample app is called
Quizler.
It's a simple, math, quiz-taking
app.
The very first screen that you
get asks you to select what type
of math you'd like to be quizzed
on.
So, let's go ahead and select
the addition quiz.
Once we do that, we'll get
presented with another view that
asks us if we'd like to view the
scoreboard of all the users'
high scores, or if we just want
to start the quiz.
So, let's go ahead and tap Start
Quiz.
Then, we get presented with each
one of our questions.
We're just going to answer them,
and we get a total score at the
end.
So now that we understand what
this sample app does, let's talk
about the steps that we'll take
to adopt ClassKit.
So first we will talk about what
type of activity -- context data
makes sense for our sample app.
After we do that, we'll discuss
what type of student generated
activity data, might also make
sense.
We'll make sure that we support
deep-linking.
Now, there's two ways to do
this.
The first way is to use
universal links.
So, if you already adopted
universal links within your
applications, you can simply
just set the universal link
property that lives on CLS
Context.
Now, our sample app does not
support universal links, so I'm
going to show you the second
approach, which is to use NS
User Activities Continue
Restoration Handler.
Then we'll make sure that we
test our implementation using
Developer Mode and the
Schoolwork app.
So, now let's talk about what
type of context structure might
make sense for this app.
As a first approach, we might
decide to do a one-to-one map of
RUI to a Context Tree.
And if we did that, we would end
up with a structure that looks
something like this.
At the top level, we have our
main app context, which is our
Quizzler app.
Beneath that, we have our
Addition Context and a
Multiplication Context.
And then beneath each one of
those, we have the Scoreboard
Context and then the actual Quiz
Context.
Now, Pavel told us that a
context is a part of our
application that a teacher will
assign to their students.
So, if we keep that in mind,
let's first talk about the
Scoreboard Context.
Well, what is the Scoreboard
Context?
It's all the users' high scores.
Now, does that really make sense
for a teacher to assign to their
students?
Not really.
So, we're going to go ahead and
remove that.
Now, we're left with a structure
that looks something like this.
So, next let's focus on the
Addition Context.
What is the Addition Context
within our application?
Isn't it really just the
addition quiz?
It's really just one thing.
It's not two.
So, those really should be
combined into one.
So, let's go ahead and do that
and then the same goes for the
multiplication context.
Now, we're left with a structure
that looks something like this.
Now, Pavel and I talked about
it, and we decided that we may
add a subtraction quiz and a
division quiz in the future.
And if we did that, we could
easily add those as siblings.
Now, when you all are thinking
about which structure makes
sense for your applications,
don't just think about your
current feature set, but also
consider what you might be doing
in the future, and make sure
that your structure will easily
grow with you.
So now, let's talk about the
context themselves.
We want to make sure that we
have clear titles, and that's
because the title is the one
piece of information that both
students and teachers will have
to know what this context
represents.
We also want to define our
context as early as possible.
For our sample app, we have
static content.
And so, we'll know what context
to write as soon as the app
launches.
So, that's when we'll define
ours.
Now, we might also want to
always display our context in a
particular order for teachers
that makes sense.
So, for our sample app, that
might mean our addition context
should probably also be
displayed above the
multiplication context.
So, to do that, we'll take
advantage of the Display Order
Property that lives on CLS
Context.
Now that we've determined what
type of context data we're going
to write, let's talk about the
student generated activity.
Here, I have a screenshot of the
Schoolwork App, and this is a
sample of what some activity
data might look like.
For our quiz, I think it
definitely makes sense to track
the total amount of time that a
student spends taking this quiz.
So, to do this, we can go ahead
and call the Start and Stop
Methods that live on CLS
Activity.
Now, it might also be nice to
show what the total score was
that the student received.
And if we think about it, the
total score is probably the most
important piece of information
about this whole quiz.
So, we probably want to
highlight it within the
Schoolwork UI like we have here.
Well, to do this, we can go
ahead and create a CLS Score
Item, and then we'll set it as
the primary activity item.
That way, it will get
highlighted within the
Schoolwork UI.
Now, it might also be nice to
indicate whether an individual
question was correct or not.
So, to do this, we can go ahead
and create CLS Binary Items and
we'll add each one of those as
an additional activity item on
our activity.
So, now that we've determined
what type of ClassKit close
we're going to write, let's go
ahead and see what that actually
looks like in action.
So here, I'm mirroring my
display for you and have Xcode
on screen.
The first thing that I'm going
to do is select my project's
target.
Once I do that, I'm going to
select the Capabilities Pane,
and we're going to find the
ClassKit APIs right here.
Then, all we need to do is make
sure that we toggle that on, and
we're all set to start writing
some ClassKit code.
So, first we're going to write
our context and we said that we
could do that as soon as the app
launches.
So, let's go ahead and open up
the App Delegate.
And in here, let's go ahead and
create a function that will
publish our context for us.
Here we have our published
context function, and what we're
going to do is we're going to
instantiate an instance if CLS
Context, passing in the type of
context that this is, giving it
a unique identifier, and then a
nice, clear, and concise title.
Then we make sure to set our
display order because we want
our addition quiz to display
above our multiplication quiz.
Then, we're going to do the same
for our multiplication quiz and
[inaudible] a context and make
sure to set the display order.
Once we do that, we're going to
create a dictionary of our
context that we will need to
create.
Then, we're going to grab the
parent context that we want to
add these to.
Since our structure is flat, we
know that our parent context is
always going to be our main app
context.
Now, let's issue a query to see
if any of these contexts already
exist.
So, we're going to create a
predicate, looking for all the
context where the parent is the
parent we just defined.
Then, we're going to issue that
query to the CLS data store's
shared instance.
For all the context that match,
this predicate we just defined.
This will return an array of
context.
We're just going to iterate over
all of the context that we know
already exist.
Then, for each one of those
contexts that's already there,
we're going to remove it from
our dictionary of context that
we need to create.
Then, we're going to iterate
over the remaining contexts that
do not exist, and for each of
one those contexts, we're just
going to add it as a child
context to our parents.
Then we call Save to Save our
changes.
Now, what we need to do is call
this function when our app
launches.
So, let's go ahead and run this
code to test that our contexts
were actually created.
Here, I have a device and I'm
mirroring my display for you.
So, awesome.
Our Quizzler app launched.
But everything looks the same.
So, how do we know that these
contexts were actually created?
Well, this is where we use
Developer Mode and Schoolwork.
So, I'm going to hit the Home
button, and open up the settings
up.
Now, I'm going to scroll down
and I'm going to look for the
Developer Settings.
When I select the Developer
Settings, I'm going to see some
ClassKit APIs.
If I select the ClassKit APIs,
we can see that we can switch
and act as the role of the
teacher.
So, I just make sure I select
that.
And now, we can hit the Home
button and open up the
Schoolwork app.
Now, when the Schoolwork app
launches, I first get a Welcome
screen.
I'll go ahead and dismiss that.
And then if we look in the top
right-hand corner, I can see
that I have a plus button.
That's how I know that I'm
logged in as a teacher.
If I tap on that plus button,
I'll get the Create a New
Handout view.
And I can add an activity.
Then I can select Apps, and we
can see our Quizler app is
showing up.
If I select that, awesome, our
contexts are there.
So now, we've been able to
validate that our contexts
actually got created.
I'd also like to point out that
the addition quiz is displaying
above the multiplication quiz.
We've also now been able to
validate that our display order
was set correctly.
So, let's go ahead and select
the addition quiz.
That's going to add that context
to this handout.
And now, let's just go ahead and
send this handout to our class.
I'm going to tap on the To
field.
Select my class.
And let's just give a title to
this handout.
Now, I'm going to go ahead and
hit Post.
What this does is it sense this
handout to my class, and it
authorizes the context that's on
this handout.
So now, that context can start
recording progress data.
We can see that my handout
posted successfully, and I can
tap on it.
Here we see the context that
I've added, and I see my nice,
app icon is right there next to
the context name.
If I tap on the icon, it should
navigate me straight into the
addition math quiz.
So, let's go ahead and tap on
that.
Uh-oh. Schoolwork launched our
app, but this is not the
addition math quiz.
Oh, yes. That's right.
We forgot to add in
deep-linking.
So, let's go back to XCode and
add that in.
So, I'm going to go back to the
App Delegate, and let's add in
that Continue Restoration
Handler.
So here, the Continue
Restoration Handler will process
some user activity.
We're just going to grab that
User Activity and get the
Context Identifier Path.
Once we have the Context Path,
we're going to instantiate our
own internal quiz model that's
associated with this context.
Then, we're going to make sure
that we call our same published
context function, and that so,
if the context has not been
created, we'll make sure to
create them.
This will return an optional
error, and we'll make sure to
handle any errors.
Then, we're just going to sync
back up with our main thread and
instantiate our storyboard and
also instantiate the correct
view controllers for this quiz.
Then we're going to set our quiz
on our view controller, and push
on the appropriate views.
So, now let's go ahead and run
this code and test that our
deep-linking is working.
So, I'm going to switch back to
my device, and then we're going
to navigate back to the
Schoolwork app.
Here, let's tap on the icon one
more time.
Awesome. It launched us straight
into the addition math quiz.
So, now we're ready to start
writing our user generated
activity data.
So, let's go back to XCode, and
let's navigate to the part of
our code that gets called when a
quiz first starts.
So, here, we said that we wanted
to start the timer for our quiz.
So, what we're going to do is
we're going to issue a query to
our CLS Data Source Shared
Instance.
And then we're going to query in
our main app context for all of
the descendants, that match the
identifier path that's
associated with this quiz.
This will return an optional
context.
We're going to grab that
context, make sure that we
called the Become Active, and
then we're going to instantiate
a new instance of CLS activity.
And that's because when this
part of our code gets run, we
know that the student is taking
a new attempt at the quiz.
Then we're just going to cash
that activity and a property
that we have defined.
Then, we call Start on Activity
to start our timer.
We also said that we wanted to
report the answer for an
individual or question.
So, I'm going to navigate to the
part of my code that gets called
when a student taps on an
answer.
So here, what we're going to do,
is we're going to get that same
currently running activity that
we just created.
Once we have that, we'll
instantiate a CLS binary item,
giving it a unique identifier,
and then a nice, clear title.
Then we'll make sure to pass in
the type of binary item that
this is.
Now, we're going to set the
value of whether the student got
this question correct or not.
Then we're going to add this
binary item as an additional
activity item on our currently
running activity.
The last thing that we said we
wanted to do, was stop the timer
and set the total score.
So, we're going to navigate to
the part of our code that gets
called when a student ends an
attempt.
Here, we're going to get that
same currently running activity.
Once we have that, we're going
to create a CLS score item,
passing a unique identifier,
title, and then we're going to
pass in the score the student
received out of the total
maximum possible score.
Then, we're just going to add
that score item as the primary
activity item on our activity.
Notice, every time I'm doing
this, I'm always setting the
same subclass of CLS activity
item.
It's always a score item.
Then, we're just going to call
Stop to stop our timer and save
to save all of our changes.
So, now let's go ahead and run
this code to test that our
student generated activity data
gets set.
So, I switch back to my device,
and now we have to switch and
act as the role of a student.
So, I'm going to go ahead and go
back to my Developer's Settings.
And the settings are all up
here.
We can tap on student and now
I'm switched to act at the role
of a student.
Now, we can go back and open up
the Schoolwork app.
Here, if you look in the top
right-hand corner, there no
longer is a plus button, and
that's how I know I'm logged in
as a student.
And we can see that I have the
handout the teacher assigned to
me.
If I tap on that, we can see the
context that I need to complete,
and I can tap on the icon and it
navigates me straight into the
quiz.
Now, I can an alert saying that
progress data is going to be
recorded on my behalf and sent
to my teacher.
So, I'll dismiss this.
Then we just go through, answer
all of our questions, and we get
our total score at the end.
So, we can see we got 100%.
So now, let's go back to the
Schoolwork app.
Here we can see our activity
data showing up.
We can see the time and the
total score.
Notice the total score is
highlighted right there in the
main part of the [inaudible].
Now, we've been able to validate
that our activity item was set
correctly.
I can also tap on the cell, and
I get a popover of all the
activity data I've written.
I can see the total score and in
light gray, I see the title of
Total Score that I set.
And then at the bottom, we can
see the time, and then each
individual question.
And then also in light gray, we
can see the title that I set for
each one of those individuals
questions.
So now, we've been able to
validate that our activity data
was getting written.
So, with that, I would like to
reintroduce Pavel back on stage
to go ahead and summarize
everything that we've seen.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Marin.
So, I'd like to mention some
best practices about ClassKit.
For one, declare your contexts
as early as possibly so that
they're available to teachers to
assign.
And also, Marin showed us that
not everything [inaudible] needs
to be a context [inaudible].
If it makes sense, take
advantage of CLS Data Store
Delegate.
And also, please take advantage
of additional activity items.
They really are a great way to
provide extra information that
teachers might need to
understand what the student is
doing within your app.
There's also some general best
practices about education apps.
One of them is to StoreKit
dependence.
And this is because in-app
purchases don't really work
within a school environment.
That one is to support purgeable
storage.
This is a good idea in general,
but it's real important in
school environments where shared
iPods are common, and space is a
premium on those.
Lastly, implement setting access
via Managed App Config.
Doing that, makes school admin's
jobs a lot easier to configure
devices.
You can find links about all of
this and the going details at
developer.apple.com/education.
Now, with that, have a wonderful
rest of WWDC.
Thank you for coming.
[ Applause ]