[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Hello, everybody.
Welcome to Image and Graphics
Best Practices.
My name's Kyle.
I work on UIKit.
And today, I'm going to be
sharing with you some techniques
and some strategies for
efficiently working with
graphical content in your
applications.
We're going to take a tour of
the framework stack.
First, we're going to start with
UIImage and UIImageView, which
are UIKit's high level tools for
working with graphical content
in your app.
Then, we're going to focus on
how you can best do custom
drawing inside of your
applications with UIKit.
And finally, we're going to
touch, briefly, on integrating
advanced CPU and GPU
technologies into your
applications.
And throughout this talk we're
going to be focusing primarily
on our use of two scarce
resources on the device; memory
and CPU.
And we tend to think of these
things as separate quantities.
They have their own tracks in
the debug navigator.
They have their own instruments
in the instruments application.
But really, they're intricately
linked.
And it might be apparent that as
your application uses more CPU,
that has a negative impact on
the battery life and the
responsiveness of your
application.
But what might be less obvious
is that as your application and
other applications on the system
consume more memory, that also
causes more CPU utilization.
Which, has further detrimental
effects on battery life and
performance.
So, we're going to focus on how
to improve our use of these
resources.
What better context for
discussing this problem than an
application that works pretty
extensively with photographic
content, like the Photos app?
You see, we're editing a photo
here.
And as I mentioned previously,
UIImages, UIKits, high level
class for dealing with image
data.
So, we have a UIImage
representing this rich content.
And we tend to divide graphical
content in our applications into
two categories; rich content
like this photograph and
iconography.
UIImage is also the data type in
UIKit that we use to represent
things like the icon displayed
in this button.
And as I mentioned previously,
UIImageView is the class that
UIKit provides for displaying a
UIImage.
Now, in classical MVC style
UIImage can be thought of as a
model object.
And UIImageView, of course, as
the name implies, is a view.
And these objects in their roles
as model and view, have
traditional responsibilities.
UIImage is responsible for
loading image content.
And UIImageView is responsible
for displaying it, for rendering
it.
Now, we can think of this as a
simple relationship that we
establish once.
It's a one-way relationship.
Bu the actual story is a little
bit more complicated.
In addition to rendering being a
continuous process, rather than
a one-time event, there's this
hidden phase.
It's really important to
understand in order to measure
the performance of your
application.
And this phase is called
decoding.
But in order to discuss
decoding, I first need to
discuss a concept called a
buffer.
A buffer is just a contiguous
region of memory.
But we tend to use the term
buffer when we're discussing
memory that's composed of a
sequence of elements of the same
size, usually, of the same
internal construction.
And for our purposes, one really
important kind of buffer is an
image buffer.
This is a term we use for buffer
that holds the in-memory
representation of some image.
Each element of this buffer
describes the color and
transparency of a single pixel
in our image.
And consequently, the size of
this buffer in memory is
proportional to the size of the
image that it contains.
One particularly important
example of a buffer is called
the frame buffer.
And the frame buffer is what
holds the actual rendered output
of your application.
So, as your application updates
its view hierarchy UIKit will
render the application's window
and all of its subviews into the
frame buffer.
And that frame buffer provides
per pixel color information that
the display hardware will read
in order to illuminate the
pixels on the display.
Now, that last part happens at a
fixed interval.
It can happen at 60 fps.
So, every 1/60th of a second.
Or on an iPad with ProMotion
Display, it can happen as fast
as every 1/120th of a second.
And if nothing's changed in your
application, the display
hardware will get the same data
back out of the frame buffer
that it saw, previously.
But as you change the content of
the views in your application,
for example, you assign a new
UIImage to our image view, here.
UIKit will re-render your
application's window into the
frame buffer.
And the next time the display
hardware pulls from the frame
buffer it'll get your new
content.
Now, you can contrast an image
buffer to another kind of
buffer, a data buffer, which is
just a buffer that contains a
sequence of bytes.
In our case, we're concerned
about data buffers that contain
image files.
Perhaps, we've downloaded them
from the network or we've loaded
them from disk.
A data buffer that contains an
image file, typically, begins
with some metadata describing
the size of the image that's
stored in that data buffer.
And then, contains the image
data itself, which is encoded in
some form like JPEG compression
or PNG.
Which means that the bytes
subsequent to that metadata
don't, actually, directly
describe anything about the
pixels in the image.
So, we can take a deeper look at
this pipeline that we've set up.
We have a UIImageView here and
we've highlighted the region of
the frame buffer that will be
populated by the image view's
rendering.
And we've assigned a UIImage to
this image view.
It's got a data buffer that
represents the content of an
image file.
Perhaps, downloaded from the
network or read from disk.
But we need to be able to
populate the frame buffer with
per pixel data.
So, in order to do that UIImage
will allocate an image buffer
whose size is equal to the size
of the image that is contained
in the data buffer.
And perform an operation called
decoding that will convert the
JPEG or PNG or other encoded
image data into per pixel image
information.
And then, depending on the
content mode of our image view.
When UIKit asks the image view
to render it will copy and scale
the image data from the image
buffer as it copies it into the
frame buffer.
Now, that decoding phase can be
CPU intensive, particularly, for
large images.
So, rather than do that work
every time UIKit asks the image
view to render, UIImage will
hang onto that image buffer, so
that it only does that work
once.
Consequently, your application,
for every image that gets
decoded, could have a persistent
and large memory allocation
hanging out.
And this allocation, as I
mentioned earlier, is
proportional to the size of the
input image.
Not necessarily, the size of the
image view that's actually
rendered in the frame buffer.
And this can have some pretty
negative consequences on
performance.
The large allocation that is in
your application's address space
could force other related
content apart from content that
it wants to reference.
This is called fragmentation.
Eventually, if your application
starts accumulating a lot of
memory usage the operating
system will step in and start
transparently compressing the
content of physical memory.
Now, the CPU needs to be
involved in this operation so in
addition to any CPU usage in
your own application.
You could be increasing global
CPU usage that you have no
control over.
Eventually, your application
could start consuming so much
physical memory that the OS
needs to start terminating
processes.
And it'll start with background
processes of low priority.
And, eventually, if your
application consumes enough
memory, your application itself
could get terminated.
And some of those background
processes are doing important
work on behalf of the user.
So, they might get started up
again as soon as they get
terminated.
So, even though your application
might only be consuming memory
for a short period of time, it
can have this really long-tail
effect on CPU utilization.
So, we want to reduce the amount
of memory that our application
uses.
And we can get ahead of the
curve with a technique called
downsampling.
Now, here we see a little bit
more detail about our image
rendering pipeline.
Including the fact that the
image view we're going to
display our image in is actually
smaller than the image we're
going to display inside of it.
Normally, the core animation
framework would be responsible
for shrinking that image down
during the rendering phase, but
we can save some memory by using
this downsampling technique.
And what we're going to do,
essentially, is capture that
shrinking operation into an
object called the thumbnail.
And we're going to wind up with
a lower total memory usage,
because we're going to have a
smaller decoded image buffer.
So, we set up an image source,
create a thumbnail, and then
capture that decoded image
buffer into UIImage.
And assign that UIImage to our
image view.
And then, we can discard the
original data buffer that
contained our image.
And we're left with a much
smaller long-term memory
footprint for our application.
The code to do that has a few
steps.
So, I'm going to walk you
through them.
I'm not going to do extremely
low-level detail.
But I'll highlight the important
bits.
First, we're going to create a
CGImageSource object.
And CGImageSourceCreate can take
an option dictionary.
And the important option we're
going to pass here, is this
ShouldCache flag.
And this tells the Core Graphics
framework that we're just
creating an object to represent
the information stored in the
file at this URL.
Don't go ahead and decode this
image immediately.
Just create an object that
represents.
We're going to need information
from this URL.
Then, we're going to calculate
on the horizontal and vertical
axis.
Based on the scale that we're
going and point size we're going
to render at, which is the
larger dimension in pixels.
Calculate that information, and
then create an options
dictionary for our thumbnail.
There are a couple of options
listed here.
You can look in the
documentation for exactly what
these options do.
But the very important one is
this CacheImmediately option.
By passing this option here,
we're telling Core Graphics that
when I ask you to create the
thumbnail that's the exact
moment you should create the
decoded image buffer for me.
So, we have exact control over
when we take that CPU hit for
decoding.
Then, we create the thumbnail,
which is a CGImage, that we get
back.
Wrap that in the UIImage and
return it from our helper
function that we've written
here.
So, to give you an idea of the
magnitude of savings that this
technique gives us, we're just
displaying the full screen image
here.
This is a photograph.
It's 3,000 by 2,000 pixels.
If we do no optimization, just
throw UIImageView in the
storyboard and assign our image
to it, this application takes
31.5 megabytes just sitting
doing nothing.
Now, using this downsampling
technique and only producing an
image buffer that's the size of
the actual display, we can get
the memory usage of this
application down to 18.4
megabytes.
And that is a huge reduction in
memory usage.
[ Applause ]
Thanks for the applause, but you
should all get the applause for
implementing this technique in
your applications.
You can imagine how much of a
big deal this is for an app
that's displaying a lot of
potentially large input images
in a small space on screen.
For example, the Camera Roll.
You might implement such a view
using UICollectionView.
So, here we've implemented cell
for item at indexPath.
And we're using our helper
function that we wrote earlier
to downsample the images to the
size that they're going to be
displayed at when the cell is
actually put on the screen.
So, you think this is a pretty
good thing to do, right?
Like rather than having these
large allocations hanging
around, we're reducing our
memory usage.
Unfortunately, that doesn't save
us from another problem that's
common in scrollable views like
table views and collection
views.
It's a, probably seen this
before.
You scroll through an
application and it starts
hitching as you scroll.
What's happening here is that as
we're scrolling the CPU is
relatively idle, or the work
that it does can be done before
the display hardware needs the
next copy of the frame buffer.
So, we see fluid motion as the
frame buffer is updated and the
display hardware is able to get
the new frame on time.
But now, we're about to display
another row of images.
And we're about to ask Core
Graphics to decode those images
before we hand the cells back to
UICollectionView.
And that could take a lot of CPU
time.
So much so, that we don't get
around to re-rendering the frame
buffer.
But the display hardware is
operating on a fixed interval.
So, from the user's perspective
the application has just
stuttered.
Now, we're done decoding these
images, we're able to provide
those cells back to
UICollectionView.
And animation continues on, as
before.
Just saw a visual hitch, there.
Now, in addition to the obvious
responsiveness consequences of
this behavior, there's a more
subtle detrimental effect on
battery life.
Because iOS is very good at
managing the power demand on the
batter when there is a smooth
constant demand on the CPUs.
And what we have here are
spikes.
As new rows are about to come
into view on the scroll view,
we're spiking the CPU usage.
And then, returning back down to
a low level.
So, there are two techniques we
can use to smooth out our CPU
usage.
The first one is prefetching.
And if you want to know a whole
lot about prefetching check out
the A Tour of CollectionView
Talk from this year's WWDC.
But the general ideas here, is
that prefetching allows
CollectionView to inform our
data source that it doesn't need
a cell right now, but it will in
the very near future.
So, if you have any work to do,
maybe, you can get a head start.
That allows us spread out CPU
usage out over time.
So, we've reduced the maximum
size of the CPU usage.
Another technique we can use is
performing work in the
background.
So, now that we've spread out
work over time we can, also,
spread it out over available
CPUs.
The consequences of this are
that your application is more
responsive and the device has a
longer battery life.
So, to put this in action here,
we've got a implementation of
the prefetch method on our data
source.
And it's going to call our
helper function to produce a
downsampled version of the image
that we're about to display in
this CollectionView cell.
And it does this by dispatching
work to one of the global
asynchronous queues.
Great.
Our work is happening in the
background.
This is what we wanted to do.
But there is a potential flaw
here.
And it's a phenomenon that we
like to call thread explosion.
And this is what happens when we
ask the system to do more work
than there are CPUs available to
do it.
If we're going to display a
whole number of images, like 6-8
images at a time, but we're
running on a device that only
has 2 CPUs, we can't do all of
that work at once.
We can't parallelize over CPUs
that don't exist.
Now, to avoid deadlock when we
dispatch asynchronously to a
global queue, GCD is going to
create new threads to capture
the work we're asking it to do.
And then, the CPUs are going to
spend a lot of time moving
between those threads to try and
make incremental progress on all
of the work we asked the
operating system to do for us.
And switching between those
threads, actually, has a pretty
significant overhead.
We'd do a lot better if one or
more of the CPUs just got a
chance to get images out the
door.
So, we're going to borrow a
technique that was presented
last year in the Modernizing
Grand Central Dispatch Usage
talk.
And we're going to synchronize
some work, or I'm sorry.
Not synchronize, we're going to
serialize some work.
So, rather than simply
dispatching work to one of the
global asynchronous queues,
we're going to create a serial
queue.
And inside of our implementation
of the prefetch method we're
going to asynchronously dispatch
to that queue.
Now, it does mean that an
individual image might not start
making progress until later than
before.
But it also means that the CPU
is going to spend less time
switching between bits of work
that it can do.
Now, these images that we're
displaying can come from a
number of places.
They might come with our
application, in which case they
might be stored in an image
asset.
Or they might be stored in a
file instead of our application
wrapper.
Or they could come from the
network.
Or they could be in a document
that's stored in the application
documents directory.
They could be stored in a cache.
But for artwork that comes with
your application, we strongly
encourage you to use image
assets.
And there are a number of
reasons why.
Image assets are optimized for
name based and trait-based
lookup.
It's faster to look up an image
asset in the asset catalog, than
it is to search for files on
disk that have a certain naming
scheme.
The asset catalog runtime has,
also, got some really good
smarts in it for managing buffer
sizes.
And there are, also, some
features unrelated to runtime
performance that are exclusive
to image assets.
Including features like per
device thinning, which mean that
your application only downloads
image resources that are
relevant to the device that it's
going to run on and vector
artwork.
The vector artwork was a feature
that was introduced in iOS 11.
And you enable it by checking
the Preserve Vector Data
checkbox in the editor for your
image asset.
And the upshot of this is that
if your image gets rendered in
an image view that is larger or
smaller than the native size of
the image it doesn't get blurry.
The image is, actually,
re-rasterized from the vector
artwork so that it has nice
crisp edges.
One place that we use this in
the operating system.
If you turn on dynamic type to a
very large size in the
Accessibility settings.
And then you tap and hold on an
item in the tab bar a little HUD
shows up as a magnified view of
the item that you're currently
holding your finger over.
So, if you want your artwork to
look good in places like this
check the Preserve Vector
Artwork checkbox in.
I'm sorry.
The Preserve Vector Data
checkbox in the image asset
inspector.
Now, the way this works is very
similar to the pipeline we saw
before.
Rather than a decode phase, we
have a rasterize phase that's
responsible for taking the
vector data and turning it into
bitmap data that can be copied
to the frame buffer.
Now, if we had to do this for
all of the vector artwork in
your application we would be
consuming a lot more CPU.
So, there's an optimization we
make here.
If you have an image that has
Preserve Vector Data checked,
but you render it at the normal
size.
The asset catalog compiler has,
actually, already produced a
pre-rasterized version of that
image and stored it in the asset
catalog.
So, rather than doing the
complicated math of rasterizing
your vector artwork into a
bitmap, we can just decode that
image that's stored in the asset
catalog and render it directly
into the frame buffer.
If you're planning on rendering
artwork at a few fixed sizes.
Maybe, you have a small version
and a large version of an icon.
Rather than relying on the
Preserve Vector Data checkbox,
create two image assets that
have the two sizes that you know
you're going to render your
image at.
That will allow the optimization
to take the CPU hit of
rasterizing your artwork at
compile time, rather than every
time the image is drawn into the
frame buffer.
So, we've seen how to work with
UIImage and UIImageView.
But that's not all of the
graphical work that your
application does.
Sometimes, your application
draws content at runtime.
The example of this happening
might be seen in something like
this editing view in the Photos
application.
The UIButton that's displaying
an icon and UIButton can use
UIImageView directly.
But UIButton doesn't support the
style of this Live button, here,
that you can tap to enable or
disable the Live Photo.
So, we're going to have to do
some work here, ourselves.
And one implementation of this
might be to subclass UIView and
implement the draw method.
And this implementation here
draws a yellow roundRect, draws
some text, and an image on top
of it.
Don't recommend this approach
for a couple of reasons.
Let's compare this view subclass
to our UIImageView.
Now, as you may already be
aware, every UIView is,
actually, backed by a CALayer in
the Core Animation runtime.
And for our image view, the
image view creates the, asks the
image to create the decoded
image buffer.
And then, hands that decoded
image over to CALayer to use as
the content of its layer.
For our custom view that
overrode draw, it's similar, but
slightly different.
The layers responsible for
creating an image buffer to hold
the contents of our draw method,
and then our view, excuses draw
function and populates the
contents of that image buffer.
Which is then, copied into the
frame buffer as needed by the
display hardware.
In order to understand how much
this is costing us and why we
should, perhaps, pursue
alternative ways of implementing
this UI.
The backing store that we're
using here, the image buffer
that's attached to the CALayer,
the size of that is proportional
to the view that we're
displaying.
Now, one new feature and
optimization that we have in iOS
12 is that the size of the
elements in that backing store
will, actually, grow dynamically
depending on whether you're
drawing any color content.
And whether that color content
is within or outside of the
standard color range.
So, if you're drawing wide color
content using extended SRGB
colors, the backing store will,
actually, be larger than the
backing store would be if you
used only colors within the zero
to one range.
Now, in previous versions of
iOS, you could set the contents
format property on CALayer as a
hint to Core Animation saying,
''I know I am not going to need
to support wide color content in
this view'', or, ''I know I am
going to need to support wide
color content in this view''.
Now, if you do this, you're
actually going to be disabling
the optimization that we
introduced in iOS 12.
So, check your implementations
of layerWillDraw.
Make sure you're not going to
accidentally defeat an
optimization that could benefit
your code when running on iOS
12.
But we can do better than just
hinting at whether we need a
wide color capable backing
store.
We can, actually, reduce the
total amount of backing storage
that our application needs.
We can do that by refactoring
this larger view into smaller
subviews.
And reducing or eliminating
places that override the draw
function.
This will help us eliminate
duplicate copies of image data
that exist in memory.
And it will allow us to use
optimized properties of UIView
that don't require a backing
store.
So, as I mentioned, overriding
the draw method will require
creating a backing store to go
with your CALayer.
But some of the properties in
UIView can still work, even if
you don't override draw.
For example, setting the
background color of a UIView
doesn't require creating a
backing store, unless you're
using a pattern color.
So, I recommend not using
patterned colors with a
background color property on
UIView.
Instead, create a UIImageView.
Assign your image to that image
view.
And use the functions on
UIImageView to set your tiling
parameters appropriately.
When we want to clip the corners
of that rounded rectangle, we
want to use the CALayer
cornerRadius property.
Because Core Animation is able
to render clipped corners
without taking any extra memory
allocations.
If we, instead, use the more
powerful maskView or maskLayer
properties we'd wind up taking
in extra allocation to store
that mask.
If you have a more complicated
background that has transparent
areas that can't be expressed by
the cornerRadius property,
again, consider using a
UIImageView.
Store that information in your
asset catalog or render it at
runtime.
And provide that as an image to
the image view, rather than
using maskView or maskLayer.
Finally, for that icon, the Live
Photo icon, UIImageView is
capable of colorizing monochrome
artwork without taking any extra
allocations.
The first thing you want to do
is either check the, not check
the checkbox, but set the
property in the image asset
editor, the render mode property
to always template.
Or use the withRenderingMode
function on UIImageView to
create a UIImage whose rendering
mode is always template.
Then, assign that image to an
image view and set the tintColor
of that image view to the color
you want the image to render in.
UIImage, as it's rendering your
image to the frame buffer, will
apply that solid color during
that copy operation.
Rather than having to hold on to
a separate copy of your image
with your solid color applied to
it.
Another optimization built into
UIKit provided view, UILabel is
able to use 75% less memory when
displaying monochrome text than
when displaying color text or
emojis.
If you want to know more about
how this optimization works in
detail and how to apply it to
your custom subclasses of
UIView, check out the iOS Memory
Deep Dive session.
Goes into great detail about
this backing store format called
A8.
Sometimes, you want to render
artwork offscreen stored in an
image buffer in memory.
And the class UIKit provides to
do that is
UIGraphicsImageRenderer.
There's another function that's
older;
UIGraphicsBeginImageContext.
But please, don't use that.
Because only Graphics Image
Renderer is capable of correctly
rendering wide color content.
What you can do in your
applications is use
UIGraphicsImageRenderer to
render to an offscreen place.
And then, use UIImageView to
display that, efficiently, on
the screen.
Similarly, to the optimization
that we've introduced in CALayer
backing stores.
We've, also, made
UIGraphicsImageRenderer capable
of dynamically growing the size
of its image buffer, depending
on the actions you perform in
the actions block.
If you are running your code on
a operating system prior to iOS
12, you can use the
prefersExtendedRange property on
UIGraphicsImageRendererFormat to
tell UIKit whether you plan on
drawing wide color content or
not.
But there's a medium middle
ground here.
If you're primarily rendering an
image in to a graphic image
renderer, that image may use a
color space that required values
outside of the range of SRGB.
But doesn't, actually, require a
larger element size to store
that information.
So, UIImage has a image renderer
format property that you can use
to get a
UIGraphicsImageRendererFormat
object preconstructed for
optimal storage of re-rendering
that image.
Lastly, we're going to talk a
little bit about how to
integrate advanced CPU and GPU
technologies that we provide in
iOS into your applications.
So, if you've got a lot of
advanced processing to do to
your images, perhaps, in real
time, consider using Core Image.
Core Image is a framework that
allows you to create a recipe
for processing an image and
handle that on the CPU or on the
GPU.
If you create a UIImage from a
CIImage and hand that to
UIImageView, UIImageView will
take care to execute that recipe
on the GPU.
This is efficient and it keeps
the CPU free for doing other
work in your application.
In order to use it create your
CIImage as normal, and then use
the UIImage ciImage initializer.
There are other advanced
frameworks for processing and
rendering graphical content that
are available on iOS, including
Metal, Vison, and Accelerate.
And one of the data types that
is common among these frameworks
is CVPixelBuffer.
And this is a data type that
represents a buffer that can be
in use or not in use on the CPU
or on the GPU.
When constructing one of these
pixel buffers make sure to use
the best initializer.
The one that's closest to the
representation you have at hand.
Don't unwind any of the decoding
work.
It's already been done by the
existing UIImage or CGImage
representations.
And be careful when moving data
between the CPU and the GPU, so
that you don't just wind up
trading off work between the
two.
You can, actually, get them to
execute in parallel.
Finally, check out the
Accelerate and simd session for
information on how to properly
format your buffers for being
processed by the Accelerator
framework.
So, to summarize a few key
points.
Implement prefetch in your table
views and collection views, so
that you can get some work done
in advance and avoid hitching.
Make sure that you're not
defeating any optimizations that
UIKit is providing to reduce the
size of the backing stores
associated with your views.
If you're bundling artwork with
your applications store it in
the asset catalog.
Don't store it in files that are
associated with your app.
And finally, if you're rendering
the same icons at different
sizes don't over-rely on the
Preserve Vector Data checkbox.
For more information there is a
couple of related sessions,
including one about actually
investigating your performance
problems.
And we'll also have labs,
tomorrow and Friday.
And if you have any questions,
come see us in the labs.
Thanks for watching.
[ Applause ]