[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you.
Thank you.
Good afternoon, everyone.
My name is Phil Azar, and I'm a
software engineer on the Power
Team at Apple.
Today, along with my colleague,
David, I'm excited to share with
you what's new in energy
debugging.
Battery life is hugely important
to our customers.
The Power Team strives to make
sure that everyone can get
through the day on a single
charge without having to plug
their device in.
We work with our developers here
at Apple to try and optimize
battery life by guiding them and
helping them make design choices
that are energy efficient.
Apps are also hugely important
to our customers.
In fact, we find that most usage
on device is directly attributed
to third-party apps.
This is incredible, and it makes
it more important now than ever
before to focus on energy
efficiency in the design of your
application.
To that end, we're going to talk
about three things today.
First, we're going to talk about
some battery life concepts that
you can employ in your
application to make sure that
you are being as energy
efficient as possible.
Then, we're going to talk about
some tools that we have
available for you to understand
and quantify where energy is
going in your application.
And finally, I'll pass it on to
my colleague, David, who is
going to talk about a new tool
that we have available to take
your energy debugging one step
further.
So, let's go ahead and get
started and talk about some
general concepts.
To make a battery life great for
our users, we have to start with
first principles and understand
what makes battery life battery
life.
So, let's start.
What is energy?
Fundamentally, if you think back
to physics, energy is the
product of power and time.
As your app is running on any of
our platforms, it'll be
consuming energy at various
rates.
This is because the different
things that your app does
consume different amounts of
power.
Additionally, the more time it
spends consuming that power the
more energy consumption you'll
face.
We can plot this graphically.
Here, you can see as your app is
running there are various peaks
and troughs of power
consumption.
It will follow that the area
under that curve is energy, and
this relates directly back to
your application in its various
modes of running.
When your app is active and when
your app is idle, it's going to
consume different amounts of
power.
When your app is active, we say
that the power being consumed is
at its highest point.
This is because the user is
directly using your application
for whatever it was or intended
for.
Then, when your app is idle but
still running, the power
consumption drops.
Finally, when your app is
suspended, there's still a basal
level of power consumption, and
that's interesting to note.
When your app is doing any of
the work that it's been designed
to do, it's going to be asking
the system to bring up hardware
that it needs to do that work,
and the energy associated with
that hardware being brought up
and used is called overhead.
Your app doesn't have direct
control over overhead, but it
really does influence through
anything that it does.
Then, when your apps first
utilize those hardware
resources, this is called active
energy.
So, now, your app has access to,
let's say, the radio or has
access to, let's say, the
camera, and it's using that
subsystem, this energy being
consumed is going to be called
active energy.
So, then, it stands to reason
that the battery life problem is
actually a two-part optimization
problem.
We have to think about being
efficient about the active
energy that we are consuming,
and we also need to be thinking
about the overhead that we'll be
incurring by asking for
different hardware resources on
the system.
So, I've mentioned hardware and
these subsystems that supposedly
consume energy.
So, what exactly consumes energy
on the system?
As an app developer, you're
going to run into a number of
different hardware subsystems in
your app development process.
But there are four subsystems
that we think on the Power Team
will contribute most highly to
your energy consumption.
These are as listed here;
processing, networking,
location, and graphics.
Let's run through these and try
to understand what they mean.
Processing is what you might
imagine.
It's going to be the energy
consumed when your app utilizes
system resources on, let's say,
the SOC.
Such as DRAM, CPU, etcetera.
It's really the workhorse
component.
Energy consumed here is going to
be highly dependent on the code
that your app is executing and
the workload that you've asked
your app to perform.
So, in a nutshell, the more
operations and code your app
executes, the more energy it
will consume in the form of
processing.
Networking is the next major
subsystem that we think about
when we talk about what consumes
energy on our devices.
Networking energy is what you
might imagine.
Whenever your app asks to do any
form of networking over
cellular, Wi-Fi, and Bluetooth,
it's going to consumer energy in
the form of networking.
This energy is
traffic-dependent.
The more traffic that your app
asks to be sent over any of
these technologies, the more
energy it will consume.
So, put it bluntly, the more
network requests that your app
asks for, the more energy you'll
consume in networking.
Location follows suit but it's a
little different.
In a location subsystem, when
your app asks to fix location
using GPS, Wi-Fi, and cellular,
it's going to consume energy in
the location system.
The location energy is going to
be accuracy and frequency
dependent.
If you're asking to fix a user's
location with a high degree of
accuracy and at a very high
cadence, you're going to get a
lot of energy consumed in the
form of location.
So, putting it all together, the
more time spent tracking
location in your application,
the more energy you'll consume
as location energy.
Finally, we have graphics.
In the graphics subsystem, you
would imagine that process
components such as he GPU and
the CPU contribute to the energy
consumed by graphics.
This is going to be animations
and UI dependent.
So, when your app is asking for
any animations to be displayed
or any UI to be rendered, it's
going to consume energy in the
form of graphics.
This is highly complexity
dependent.
The more complex your animations
and UI are the more energy that
you'll consume in the form of
graphics.
Finally, a good rule of thumb is
to say that the more rendering
that your app does, doing
animations or UI, the more
energy you're going to consume
in the form of graphics.
So, we talked about these four
subsystems, and what's the
take-away message?
There's a common thread ties
them all together in our app
development, and so that the
more work you do, the more
energy you're going to consume.
We can't necessarily say do less
work because that means our app
might do less.
So, then, the point here is that
we need to optimize the work we
do and make it as
energy-efficient as possible.
But it's not so simple.
Thinking about energy efficiency
is a process.
It's not just so that we can
make an optimization and
suddenly our energy is going to
be more efficient or our app is
going to be better for battery
life.
We have to get into this mode of
thinking that our app has a set
of resources that it's using,
and we need to use those
resources efficiently.
So, with that being said, let's
take a look at some examples of
real-world situations where we
can think about energy
efficiency and really start this
process off.
Let's talk about when our app is
in the foreground.
When our app is in the
foreground, it will likely be
providing the main user
experience.
For many of us, this is the most
important and critical part of
our application.
With that being said, energy
efficiency in the foreground is
about focusing on providing
value to your user, ensuring
that whatever you're doing
provides some immediate impact
for the user experience.
One tenet we can follow is to
only do work when required.
Sounds pretty straightforward.
Well, let's take a look at an
example and illustrate why this
is so important.
Let's say you're building a
media application, and the
primary goal of the media
application is to present
content to the user at a regular
cadence.
Well, a really robust solution
would be to implement a sort of
timer-based approach to refresh
the content feed.
This will ensure that the
content of the user is seeing is
as fresh as possible without any
sort of interaction.
This isn't a very
energy-efficient approach, and
let's sort of understand why.
If we plot the power over time
curve for a solution like that,
we see that every time our timer
fires, we have a little bit of
active energy that's consumed.
But the really important part
here is that we have a ton of
overhead, and this is because
every time we ask to display new
content, we likely have to bring
up subsystems such as
networking, graphics, and
processing to do all that work
and display that content, and
the user might not actually want
it.
So, we'll end up burning a lot
of energy consistently while
that application is running.
We can do better.
If we think about what the user
actually wants, the fresh
content, we can implement a
solution that is on demand.
Now, in this new solution, user
interaction or some kind of a
notification from our server
will provide us the new content
and display it to the user.
This solution isn't that
different, but it's an
energy-efficient approach and
makes a dramatic impact on our
power over time.
Let's take a look at why.
Now, if we imaging that our app
is running in the foreground,
and a user interaction occurs,
we would refresh our content
feed and display it to the user.
Then, our app will go idle as
our user is using it, let's say,
to scroll or just to read the
content that's been displayed.
You'll notice that the overhead
here is still a little bit high,
but it's been significantly
reduced.
The trick here is that we've
allowed the subsystems we no
longer need to go to sleep and
idle off.
Another tenet that we can follow
to reduce our energy consumption
in the foreground is to minimize
complex UI.
So, I mentioned before that in
graphics our energy consumption
is highly complexity-dependent,
and we always want to make our
apps look as good as possible.
So, we're going to spend a lot
of time building this UI that
looks great and animations that
are pleasing to view.
However, this can have
unintended side effects, and
let's look at an example to
illustrate why.
If I'm a video player, my goal
is to let a user watch a video.
Simple.
But I could be tempted to add
new controls and UI above that
video, let's say, in the form of
related videos or a scrubber or
maybe volume controls.
This allows a greater degree of
control to the user to use this
application and enjoy the video
they're watching.
This is actually insidiously
energy inefficient, and let's
understand why.
On many of our devices, there's
a display optimization in place
that allows for video playback
to be very energy efficient when
there is no UI on screen.
This is something that is not
immediately clear when you're
building an application like
this.
However, it makes all the
difference.
So, a good approach to take
advantage of this optimization
and counteract this sort of
energy inefficiency we see is to
have a simple auto dismissal of
our UI controls.
And this could mean that any
related content that we put on
the video or in the UI layer
simply goes away if the user is
not interacting with it.
This makes a big difference on
our energy consumption during
video playback, as this display
optimization is critical for
maintaining quiescent
energy-efficient playback.
So, we've talked a lot about the
foreground, but what about the
background?
Many of us who are building
applications such as music
players, or maybe even alarm
clocks, are focused on the
background.
Our main experience comes from
our app running effectively in
the background.
Well, when we're in the
background, we have some things
that we need to be aware of.
Likely, our app is going to be
running in conjunction and
concurrently with other systems
on device.
Let's say I'll be using iMessage
or maybe even Facetime.
To that end, we should focus on
minimizing our workload to
ensure energy efficiency when
we're in the background.
Well, this is a pretty broad
statement.
So, let's kind of try to
understand it.
When you're in the background,
you may be able to utilize
subsystems that are already
being used by other apps on the
system.
However, it's important to note
that the majority of the
priority for the energy
consumption is going to go to
those applications that are in
the foreground.
So, then, we should focus on
minimizing our workload to make
sure we don't interrupt those
experiences.
One way we can start thinking
about this is to coalesce all of
our tasks.
If there's a lot of maintenance
work, let's say, that we need to
do in the background, or we have
a lot of networking activity
that needs to be performed,
let's say, then it would be best
for us to group those together
and do them all at the same
time.
That way, we have the minimal
impact on anything else
happening on the system.
A really common example that
many of you may face is to
upload analytics and working
with application analytics.
It's likely that when you're
collecting these analytics
you'll be sending them
immediately because this is a
very robust solution, and it
allows you to build a dataset
that is protected against
crashes in your application.
Well, doing that may not be very
energy efficient.
If we were to send our analytics
every time we went into the
background, we would risk
overusing our networking
hardware.
And here's how that looks like
when we take a look at the power
over time curve.
Every time we enter the
background, we would spin up
networking resources to send
these analytics, and then we
would come down and go idle
again.
This may not look like a lot
with just three on this graph,
but you can imagine if your
application is experiencing
heavy usage, this adds up over
time.
The right way to do this is
super straightforward, and it's
simply to send these in deferred
batches.
We have a lot of APIs that
support this coalescing
principle, and one of the
biggest ones is NSURLSession.
Using NSURLSession with a
discretionary property and a
background session will enable
you to take advantage of this
sort of an optimization very
quickly,
and this is the right way to do
it.
Let's take a look at what the
energy over time looks like now,
if we've done this.
We can see here that while it
might take a little longer for
our app to do any sort of
uploading for analytics, the
energy that we're going to
consume is going to be far less,
and it's going to be condensed
to one single burst.
This is effectively the result
of coalescing any tasks when
you're running in the
background.
You get a high energy for a
short period of time completing
those tasks, but then once
you're finished you no longer
have to worry about doing those
tasks and potentially
interrupting an experience of
another application.
Another example that seems sort
of straightforward is to end
your tasks quickly.
With many APIs on the system
that allow you to take advantage
of background running, things
like UI background task and
UIKit, or VOIP and PushKit.
And these APIs have ways for you
as an app developer to indicate
that you no longer need to run
in the background.
So, it stands to reason that as
an app developer, if you're
using any of these background
modes, you would call these
completion handlers, let's say,
to let the system know you're
done.
Well, that doesn't always
happen, and in a lot of cases,
we might actually forget or not
want to end our task.
So, we let our tasks expire.
There's a great energy impact to
this, and it's really something
that people don't necessarily
see when they're developing
their application.
Let me demonstrate why this is
energy inefficient with the
power over time curve.
You could imagine if you enter
the background for any reason
and your task starts, you finish
some time afterwards.
Then, if we let our task expire,
as we've said, we enter this
sort of idle phase where you're
consuming energy and our app is
running in the background for
whatever reason we've asked our
API for, but there's not really
much else happening.
And then, we have a long tail of
overhead because we've kept the
system awake and subsystems we
thought they needed to be using
their own resources are now
waiting for us to finish.
The quick solution to this is to
simply call your completion
handlers whenever they're
available.
And as I mentioned, UI
background task is one of the
biggest ones.
When we enter the background
from the foreground, we can call
this API and UIKit.
If we don't let our system know
that we don't need, if we let
our system know that we don't
need to do any work anymore, we
save a lot of energy and allow
hardware systems to go idle when
they need to go idle.
Here's what that looks like if
we call these completion
handlers.
You could see here that the tail
of active energy that we saw
before is gone, and now we've
greatly reduced our tail of
overhead as well.
A simple solution, but it has a
big impact on your overall
energy consumption.
So, we've talked about some ways
that we can start thinking about
energy efficiency as a process.
If we focus on optimizing the
work we do in all of our use
cases, we can really work on
optimizing the energy that our
application consumes.
For a deeper dive into the
things we talked about and to
maybe get a little bit more
hands-on with the code behind
some of these optimizations we
discussed, I really recommend
that you check out our video
from last year, How to write
energy-efficient apps.
In that session, you'll find
that there are a lot of
interesting resources and more
examples on how you can use
energy-efficient designs in your
application.
So, now that we've talked about
some ways that we can improve
energy efficiency in the design
of our application, and we've
spent a lot of time talking
about ways that we can improve
our energy efficiency through
thinking about the hardware
systems behind our application,
what are the ways that we can
quantify this?
Let's say we've made a change,
and we want to understand the
real impact in our application.
Well, right now, let's talk
about some tools that we have
available for you today to do
that sort of work.
Today, we have two tools
available that you can use to
quantify your energy impact.
The first tool is the energy
gauges, which are accessible
directly through the Xcode
debugger.
The energy gauges are a great
way for you to rapidly iterate
on your codes energy consumption
and to help you understand at a
very high level where your
energy consumption is going by
subsystem.
And then, if the gauges aren't
good enough, you can jump right
into the instruments from the
Developer Toolkit.
The instruments will allow you
to do a deeper dive into the
various subsystems on the
device.
And understand at a lower level
how these actual subsystems are
performing and what they're
doing.
Let's take a look at the energy
gauges first.
As I said, these are accessible
directly through the Xcode
Debugger UI, so they're pretty
easy to use.
Let's jump into the UI.
As you can see, we've selected
the row that says energy impact,
and now we have this main area
in the UI that's composed of
three major sections.
On the top left, we have the
canonical gauges themselves.
These gauges range from low,
high, and very high, and
represent the average energy
impact of your app at an
instantaneous moment.
It's important to know that
where the gauge actually falls
doesn't necessarily mean good or
bad.
It means that whatever your app
is doing, it's consuming this
much relative amount of energy.
It's important because it's up
to you as an app developer to
think about your use case and
whether or not you would expect
it to do that.
To the right of that, we have
the average component
utilization, and this is going
to be a pie chart that shows you
all of the different components
relative to the total amount of
energy that you're consuming,
what percentage those components
are consuming.
This is really useful because
it's representative of those
subsystems we talked about
earlier, and it helps to
identify if you have an excess
amount of overhead or maybe if
one component is taking too much
energy, and you don't expect it.
And then, immediately below
that, building off of the
average component utilization
chart, we have a time series
that represents the average
utilization of each component as
your app is running in real
time.
We could also see here that you
have the state that your app is
actually running in, foreground
and background, and also it
would list suspended.
This is a really awesome tool
for understanding how your app
is behaving in real time.
So, as I said, the energy gauges
are really great for doing
high-level characterization work
and rapid profiling.
That's the key.
When you're iterating on your
code, you're trying to get
something to work as an app
developer, and you're trying to
put something together, it may
not seem immediately clear how
you could really think about
energy, but the gauges are a
great way to start.
But let's say that you've done
that and the gauges aren't
really enough for you.
That's where the instruments
come in, and directly through
the energy gauge's UI, we have
access to three instruments that
we think best correlate to the
subsystems we talked about
before.
These include the time profile,
the network profiler, and the
location profiler, and if you
were to click through into any
of these from the energy gauge's
UI, you would be able to
transfer your current debug
session into any of those
instruments.
Let's take a look at one of the
instruments here, the Time
Profiler, and try to understand
the UI.
Now, the instruments have a very
standard UI, but what's
interesting about it is that
it's very useable.
And let's take a look.
Here, we can see the Time
Profiler UI, and on the top, you
see a bar that's representative
of the different controls that
you have of the actual
instruments.
On the top left, ou can see you
have a Play and Pause button as
well as your target that you're
using to profile.
And then, on the right, you see
a plus button that allows you to
very quickly drag and drop other
instruments into you profiling
pane, which can be found here.
And now, this profiling pane
actually allows you to see what
instruments are running and
currently profiling your
application.
Here, since we're using a Time
Profiler, we see the CPU usage
and a graphical representation
of how much CPU usage is being
consumed over time.
Directly below that, we have a
weighted call graph.
Since we're using the Time
Profiler, we're trying to
understand how our CPU is being
used by the application.
To that end, there's a weighted
call graph that allows you to
see exactly what is being called
in your application and how much
weight it has on CPU time.
And then, directly to the right
of that, you have a summation of
the heaviest stacked race in
your application that basically
says what is the heaviest stack
during this profiling run?
There are a lot of other great
instruments that you can use,
and here are some of them now.
This means that the instruments
are really great for a couple of
things.
The first thing is that the
instruments are really great for
root cause analysis.
Let's say you have a problem in
a specific subsystem, so just
processing or networking.
You would be able to identify
pretty rapidly what that problem
might be using the Time Profiler
or the Network Profiler.
The instruments are also really
great for doing in-depth
profiling of your application.
If you implement a CPU
efficiency improvement of some
kind; let's say you cut down the
time that it takes for an
algorithm to execute, the
instruments are a really good
way to understand if that's the,
if the intended effect of your
optimization is going through on
that subsystem.
But there's also one more thing
that the instruments are really
awesome for that I haven't
talked about today, and that's
untethered profiling.
There's a single instrument that
you can use called the Energy
Log, which allows you to do an
untethered profiling run on a
provision device while using
your application.
It's accessible directly to the
developer settings, and when you
start running it, you can use
your phone as you normally would
and use your application as you
might expect for any number of
use cases.
And then, afterwards, when
you're finished, you can stop
the recording directly from the
developer tools and jump into
Instruments and upload that
trace.
This is really useful for
understanding if there are any
environmental problems that
you're having that might be
impacting your energy
consumption.
Now, we've talked about the
tools; we've talked about the
concepts; now, I want to do a
demo and work through an example
about how we can actually use
these in tandem and solve energy
problems and make our app more
energy efficient.
So, today, we've prepared a
simple game called Energy Game,
which draws sprites onscreen and
allows the application to inject
a number of bugs.
It's a very simple application
that we've built, and it only
has an app delegate in a View
Controller, but the primary
purpose is to show you how to
use our tools rapidly to iterate
through your code.
So, I'm going to go ahead and
build Energy Game here through
the Xcode UI and let it run.
Then, you'll see on the right
side that all it really does is
draw a little little battery
sprite at a random time.
There it is.
Very simple.
If I jump straight into the
Xcode debugger and jump to
energy impact, now, I can see my
gauges.
And so this is the UI that we
just talked about.
It's the same three areas that
we discussed, and you could see
right now that all my app is
doing that we've designed it to
do is just placed some sprites
onscreen.
But you notice that I'm doing
networking, and my overhead
seems to be high for simply no
reason.
Well, this is because we're also
doing a little bit of networking
and uploading the spike count
every time a new spike is drawn
onscreen.
And so, through the Xcode energy
gauges, you can actually see the
impact of doing that.
So, I'm going to go ahead and
stop this now and jump into my
code to understand where this is
coming from.
So, if I go to my View
controller, where I actually add
a new sprite, I've had a
function here to upload the
sprite count, which creates a
simple connection object and
uploads the sprite count every
time a new sprite is added.
I'm going to go ahead and
comment the cell and then jump
into my app delegate and move it
to the only upload the sprite
account when I'm in the
background.
And for the sake of this demo,
I've named that my networking
optimization.
I'm going to go ahead and
rebuild Energy Game and show you
the effect this has on the
energy gauges.
Now, Energy Game is running
again.
I'm going to jump back to the
Xcode Debugger UI, jump back to
Energy Impact, and now we don't
see any networking energy, and
we don't see any overhead, which
is good.
So, that's simple optimization,
simply moving a networking
request from one area to the
other and preventing it from
happening often allowed us to
greatly reduce our energy impact
in our quiescent use case.
So, now, I'm going to go ahead
and inject a bug and try to see
how we can see a bug when we use
Xcode energy gauges.
Bug1 is a simple bug that you
can see on the bottom left here
that will essentially cause a
CPU spin in the background.
This is a case that many of us
might face in regular and real
world development.
I'm going to go ahead and inject
this bug.
And now that I've injected it,
I'm going to background Energy
Game, and as you can see in the
Energy Gauge's UI, we transfer
to the background.
We do a little bit of networking
because I moved that networking
call to the background.
But now, we also see that our
CPU is going wild.
So, this is the power of the
gauges.
We've now, we know that we're
injecting a bug, but we can see
that bug directly in the gauges.
So, now, to find the root cause,
I'm going to go ahead and jump
into the Time Profiler and
transfer my debug session, as we
discussed before.
So, now, I transferred my debug
session, and it will begin
running automatically.
And as you see, the weighted
cobra apples start populating in
a moment; here, we can see that
the dispatched thread here is
consuming the most CPU time.
Let's go ahead and dig into it.
And we can see that we have
closure at something called
appdelegate.compute.
Well, let's jump back to our
application and try to
understand what that is.
So, for the purpose of this
demo, when we entered the
background in Energy Game, we
called something called
computation.
Computation is a really terrible
function.
It basically starts spinning
wildly with a while true loop
when we inject Big1.
So, it's very simple for the
purpose of this demo, but using
both the gauges and the time
profiler, we were able to dig
back directly to where this was
happening, and we can see that
this while true loop is not
good.
So, I'll go ahead and comment
this out because I love
commenting out code instead of
deleting it, and I'll go ahead
and rebuild Energy Game.
We'll just jump back into the
gauges to see that everything is
okay, and now we'll go ahead and
inject Bug1 again, and I'll go
to the background.
And we see our expected
networking activity but no CPU
spin.
Voila! We've solved it, using
two tools in about 30 seconds or
a minute.
That's the power of these tools.
They're able to let you rapidly
iterate and root cause problems
that you might face on
day-to-day development.
So, let's go back to the slides.
So, there's some takeaways from
this demo.
The first takeaway is that the
gauges, as we said, are great
for rapid iteration.
They allow you to quickly see
where your problem might be
happening, and they allow you to
take the next step in figuring
out how to solve it.
The second takeaway is that the
instruments are great for
in-depth profiling.
And finally, the third takeaway
is that we want you to think
about energy efficiency as a
primary objective in your
application development.
We have powerful tools available
for you to quickly understand
where your energy is going and
to root cause problems that
might be energy related.
So, let's say you've done all of
that, and you've shipped your
application.
From the App Store it's getting
used; all your customers are
greatly thankful that you
shipped it on time.
What's next?
Let's say you still see
customers saying that your app
is bad for battery life.
What sort of recourse do you
have?
Well, now, I'm going to pass it
on to my colleague, David, who's
going to talk to you about how
you can face those challenges
and solve them using our new
tools.
David.
[ Applause ]
>> Good afternoon.
Hi, I'm David, and I'm here
today to talk about some new
great tools for energy
debugging.
If you're an iOS developer with
an app in the App Store, or in
TestFlight, then this part of
the talk is for you.
I'd like to start with the
following question, now that
you've shipped your app, how do
you know how our app is doing in
the wild?
In other words, how do you know
if your customers are
experiencing energy issues that
are leading to bad battery life?
Now, a customer may leave a
review on the App Store, saying,
"My battery went down a lot
while using this app."
But they might not be able to
tell you what happened.
Or even worse, they may delete
your app and not leave any
feedback at all.
So, it can be challenging to
find out if you have energy
issues in the wild.
And even if you know that there
are energy issues, how do you
debug an issue that occurred on
your customer device?
You can make use of tools like
instruments and gauges that Phil
talked about, but unless you
know what to test for, it can be
challenging to reproduce.
There can be environmental
factors such as poor Wi-Fi
conditions that occurred for
your customer whereas on your
desk, you have great Wi-Fi
conditions.
So, these are some really
challenging questions.
So, to help answer these
questions, I'm excited today to
talk about a new way of
debugging energy issues using
Xcode Energy Logs and Xcode
Energy Organizer.
First, I'll talk about Xcode
Energy Logs, which is a new way
of reporting energy issues on
device.
Later, I'll cover Xcode Energy
Organizer, which is a new tool
for viewing Energy Logs.
With these tools, for the first
time ever, you'll have the data
that you need to find and to fix
energy issues.
So, let's get started.
Xcode Energy Logs are a new way
of reporting issues from device.
We start with high CPU energy
events, which is when your app
is using lots of CPU.
Each Energy Log will have a
weighted call graph, which will
point out the energy hotspots
within your code.
These logs will be made
available from TestFlight and
the App Store, so you'll have
real world data, what's actually
happening with your customers.
And with these logs, you'll be
able to begin improving the
battery life experience.
Let's talk about when an Xcode
Energy Log is generated.
Let's say your customer is using
your app, which starts to put a
really heavy load on the CPU.
This can be natural, depending
on what your app is doing.
Well, let's say it's putting a
really heavy load on the CPU for
a long time.
This causes a high CPU energy
event to be detected.
Now, there are two key
thresholds that are checked for
for a high CPU energy event.
The first threshold is when your
app is spinning 80% CPU for more
than three minutes while in the
foreground, and the second
threshold is more than 80% CPU
for more than one minute while
in the background.
In this latter case, your app
may actually get killed to
prevent runaway background
usage.
Each instance of a CPU Energy
Log indicates that your app uses
so much CPU that it was worth
flagging.
What this means in practical
terms is that it was responsible
for up to a 1% battery drop in a
typical case.
Now, you may be saying to
yourself, 1% battery doesn't
sound too bad.
But to put this in context, on
an iPhone 6S with an additional
1% battery, your user could have
had eight minutes of additional
talk time or six minutes of
additional browsing or 30
minutes of additional music.
And if your app continues to
burn at this rate, the battery
would have dropped even more.
So, writing CPU-efficient apps
is really important, and your
users will notice.
An Energy Log has three things
that can help you figure out
what has happened.
First is the context by which
what happened that triggered the
report.
For example, it will say that
your app spent for 8% over three
minutes.
The second piece of information
is the metadata about where the
Energy Log was created; for
example, on an iPhone versus an
iPad and on, say, Build 30 of
you app.
The third and most important
piece of information is the
weighted call graph that will
show you the energy hotspots in
your code.
So, let's talk a little bit more
about the weighted call graph,
how it was generated, and how
you can use it to debug energy
issues.
Let's say your program is
comprised of a main function and
a number of methods, Method 1,
Method 2, Method 3, and Method
4.
Your code begins to execute
until a high CPU energy event is
detected.
Up to this point, backtraces are
continuously sampled at a
periodic interval of once per
second, where each backtrace is
a sample of an active frames in
execution.
The first backtrace, for
example, shows that main Method
1 and Method 2 were active.
The second backtrace shows that
main Method 3 and Method 4 were
active and so on.
Now, we can try to combine these
backtraces together to form an
overall picture.
What we see here is a weight
call graph, and this weighted
call graph is really useful.
Here, we can see that main was
present in six out of the six
samples that we collected,
meaning that main was running
100% of the time.
Of that, we see that Method 1
had five samples whereas Method
3 had only one sample.
And within Method 1, we see that
Method 2 and Method 3 had three
samples and one sample
respectively.
So, this gives us an overall
picture of where the code was
being executed and how much time
was being spent.
So, when an Energy Log is
created, there's a collection of
periodic backtraces sampled at
one per second.
For each backtrace contains a
list of the active frames being
executed by the CPU, these
backtraces are aggregated by
sample count into a tree where
the samples, where more samples
mean more heavily executed code.
And you can use these weighted
call graphs to identify
unexpected workloads in your
app.
So, now that we know what an
Energy Log is, how do we access
them?
First, Energy Logs are created
on device.
Then, your beta testers and your
customers, who have opted in,
will upload these logs up to
Apple.
Now, there might be hundreds or
even thousands of these logs, so
we will aggregate these logs for
you, sort them, and present them
in a list of top energy issues
to you.
And you can download and view
these logs using the new Xcode
Energy Organizer tool.
The Xcode Energy Organizer is
your command center for
debugging energy issues in the
wild.
Energy Organizer makes it really
easy to view energy logs.
The Energy Organizer is
connected to TestFlight in the
App Store, so you'll see a list
of all your iOS apps.
You'll be able to see some
statistics of how often these
energy issues occur in the wild.
You'll have a list of the top
energy issues sorted by how many
devices that was impacted.
You'll have a view of the
weighted call graph for a number
of different logs, which you'll
be able to page through, using
page through logs, and you can
use Open in Project to jump
directly into your code base so
you can begin debugging these
energy issues.
And now, I'd love to show you a
demo.
Now, I've made sure that I've
signed into my developer account
and that I've uploaded our
Energy Game app up to TestFlight
in the App Store.
To bring up the Energy
Organizer, I could just go into
Window here, and click
Organizer.
And this is the Energy Organizer
UI.
I make sure that the Energy tab
is selected at the top, and if
you've used the Crashes
Organizer, you will already be
familiar with this UI.
On the left, we have a list of
all of our apps.
Next to that, we have a list of
our top energy issues.
In the center is our Weighted
Call Graph, and on the
right-hand side are some
statistics about the energy
issue.
So, let's go ahead into the left
here and select Energy Game,
which is the game that we're
working on.
And then, make sure that we're
on the correct build.
We see here a list of our top
energy issues, sorted by how
many times it's affected.
Let's jump into this first
energy issue, which hit 64 of
our devices.
On the right-hand pane here, we
have some more details about
what happened, as well as a
breakdown of how often that
energy issue happened, and we
can see that it happened across
a mix of iPads, iPods, and iPod
Touches, and we can see a
distribution of how often it
happened in the past two weeks.
Let's take a look at the
weighted call graph.
We see that a lot of time is
being spent in this dispatch
call block calling into this app
delegate computation function.
Now, I can use this button here
to jump us directly into our
code base.
So, we are back directly into
our code.
On the left here is one of the
sample backtraces from our
weighted call graph.
We can see that we're spending a
lot of time in this computation
function.
Now, this is the very function
that Phil was talking about
earlier on his demo.
And we can see that he's already
commented this part of the code
out, so he's already addressed
this energy issue.
So, let's jump back to the
organizer.
I can go ahead and click this
button here and mark this issue
as resolved.
And what this does is the next
time we open the Energy
Organizer, we'll see that we've
already taken care of this
issue.
All right, let's jump to the
second issue, which hit 42
devices.
Now, before going into the
weighted call graph, I'd like to
draw your attention to three
features at the bottom here.
First is this page through logs
where I can select one out of
five sample energy logs out of
the 42 that we've hit in the
wild.
As I page through these, you can
see that the weighted call graph
looks a little bit different,
which is okay because these
backtraces and these weighted
call graphs are samples.
However, we've grouped these
together by similarity, so these
logs should look fairly similar
to you.
This button here, when I click
it, shows that all the system
library frames that were hidden
previously.
And this button here clicks all,
shows you all the frames that
had low sample counts.
Now, by default, we've hidden
most of these frames for you so
that we only show you the most
important frames.
Let's take a look at this
function.
It looks like a lot of time is
being spent in this heavy timer
function.
Actually, I heard Phil talking
about this bug off stage, and he
said that he was going to take a
look at it, so I'll let him deal
with it.
I can go ahead and rename this
and move on to the next bug.
Let's take a look at one more
bug.
Here, I can see there's a lot of
time being spent in set next
update timer and add new sprite.
What is this function?
Let's investigate.
I'll jump directly into the
code,
and I can see that a lot of time
is being spent in this add new
sprite function.
Okay.
Adding new sprites can be
expensive, but the question to
ask ourselves is, is this an
expected workload?
And the answer is, in this case,
not really because we only
expect to be adding sprites once
every few seconds.
So it doesn't quite make sense
why this is chewing up so much
CPU.
Let's take a look at the
backtrace to see who is calling
us.
We're being called by set next
update timer.
So, what is this function doing?
We see that within set next
update timer, we're calling in
to this add new sprite.
At the end of a function, we're
calling in to this update timer
to schedule the next time this
function is called.
This timer is set to fire
sometime between now and next
update interval.
Now, next update interval is
decremented by 1 until it hits
0, and then it's re-initialized
according to this line of code
here.
Now, here's where the problem
is.
Time interval since last update
date can potentially be
negative, and we've seen cases
of this happening, especially
when users try to game the
system.
Maybe they're playing a game,
and they want to reset the
clock.
Maybe they want some extra lives
or some extra chances, so they
go into System Settings and
change the clock to 24 hours
ago.
Well, in this case, this causes
next update interval to be
negative, and when we schedule a
timer for a time that is
sometime in the past, that timer
will fire immediately and then
call itself again and again.
So, we effectively have an
infinite loop here.
Fortunately, this is really easy
to fix.
We just go into this function
here and change this to less
than or equal to 0 so that even
if next update interval is
negative, we can break out of
the loop.
Now, this is a really great
example of an energy issue that
is really difficult to catch
during normal testing but is
made obvious once you have the
data from the field.
That's the power of Energy Logs,
and that's the power of Energy
Organizer.
Let's take a look at the three
key takeaways from this demo.
You can use the Energy Organizer
to discover top energy issues in
the field.
Take a look at the top issues,
take a look at how often they're
happening, and take a look at
what kind of devices and builds
are affected.
Second, you can view energy
hotspots using the weighted call
graphs.
So, look out for the frames with
unusually high sample counts,
and watch out for the unexpected
workloads.
Finally, use OpenEnd Project to
jump directly into your code so
you can make and inspect fixes
with what's going on.
Let's summarize what we've
learned today.
First, think about energy use
and treat energy as a
first-class citizen in every
aspect of your design,
development, and testing.
Second, make use of the great
tools like energy gauges and
instruments to profile your app.
And third, take a moment to
explore the new Xcode Energy
Organizer to understand and fix
energy issues in the field.
For more information, please
come check out the following
URLs, and feel free to come by
the Power and Performance Lab on
Friday from 9 to 11.
Thank you and have a great
evening.
[ Applause ]