[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Good morning.
My name is Michael LeHew, and I
worked on the collections for
the foundations team at Apple.
And today, I want to talk about
specific things that you should
know about to ensure that your
use of collections in Swift is
as effective as possible.
I'm going to cover a lot of
territory today about details
and all aspects of collections
available for use in Swift.
We're going to explore some
common pitfalls and how to avoid
them including performance
issues, and I'm also going to
offer very specific advice about
when to choose to use specific
collections.
So let's begin.
I want you to imagine a world, a
world without collections.
And in this world, we may not
have arrays, but it still has
bears, but every time we need
another bear, we're going to
need to define another variable,
and we want to do things with
these bears.
We're going to need to repeat
ourselves.
Pretty scary, right?
It gets worse though.
This world also doesn't have
dictionaries, but thankfully
being clever developers, we can
work around that with the
function, where we painstakingly
define each case that we care
about, and using this function
is very similar to using a
dictionary, except none of those
dynamic capabilities that we
need.
But who likes a mutable state,
right?
Fortunately for us though, we
don't live in this world.
Thankfully our world has bears
and collections along with a
rich first-class syntax for
defining them.
And APIs that help us not repeat
ourselves when we iterate or
retrieve the elements that they
may store.
Collections are so pervasive and
share so many common features
and algorithms that in Swift
they all conform to a common
protocol.
Not surprisingly, it's called
collection.
And in Swift, collections are
sequences whose elements can be
traversed multiple times,
nondestructively, and whose
elements can be accessed via a
subscript.
Let's see, look at how they do
that but considering an abstract
representation of a collection.
This could be an array defined
contiguously in memory, a hash
table, a red black tree, a link
list or anything else that you
can imagine.
What matters is that it supports
the concept of an initial index
called start index.
It can be used to access the
initial element of the
collection.
It has an end index, which
identifies the end of the
collection, and collections
support the ability to iterate
from their start index to their
end index.
They can do this multiple times,
and they also support a
subscript to retrieve elements
from the collection itself.
Let's see what this looks like
in code.
Indeed, if we look at the
definition of collection, it's
declared as a sequence of
elements.
It also has an additional
associated type called index,
which must be comparable.
It offers a subscript to
retrieve elements from, or using
that index, and we define a
start and an end index
identifying the bounds of our
collection.
And finally, we have a function
called index after, which lets
us get from one index to
another.
And this last function is so
important because it allows the
standard library to define many
useful and powerful default
behaviors with the incredible
power of protocol extensions.
Let's look at some of these.
When you conform to collection,
you gain access to an incredible
range of functionality with
properties that let you get the
first and the last element or
identify the count or check to
see if a collection is empty.
You also gain API that lets you
iterate through a Collection
using 4N syntax.
And super useful functions like
map, filter, and reduce.
Now let's go ahead and make
Collection even more powerful by
adding our own extension.
Collection already provides a
way to iterate through every
element, but I want a function
that will let me iterate through
every other element, skipping
some of the values along the way
and will do this by adding an
extension to Collection.
Let's start with the methods
signature.
We're going to call our function
every other, and it's going to
take a closure that will call on
each element that we care about.
We'll get the bounds of our
iteration, and to find another
variable, that starts at the
start, which will mutate along
as we go.
We'll call the closure on the
current element and advance our
current index to the next one.
And we may have invalidated our
index at this point, we may have
reached the end of the
collection, so we need to make
sure that we did that, and if we
did, we can then advance our
index one more time and thus
skip every other element.
And if we call this we see, if
we call this on the close range
from one to ten, we see that we
skip the even elements.
And so we see that Collections
let us describe some really
powerful behavior, but it turns
out collections aren't alone.
In fact, Collection is not the
only protocol that we have.
In Swift, we have access to a
rich hierarchy of collection
protocols, each greatly
improving on the kinds of
assumptions that we can make
about our types.
Let's go ahead and talk about a
couple of these.
We've already established that
Collection lets you go forward
from a given index, but there
are also bidirectional
collections, which let you go in
the other direction.
Now, of course, bidirectional
collections are collections
themselves, and so we can still
iterate forward as well.
The next most flexible form of
collection is what's known as a
random access collection, and
with these, these add the
requirement that it would be
constant time to compute, or
compute another index from
another or to compute the
distance between two indexes.
The compiler cannot enforce
this, and so when you conform to
random acts as a collection,
you're making a promise.
But if you satisfy this promise,
if you can deliver on this
promise, the protocol gives you
the power to access any index in
the collection in constant time.
And of course, random access
collections remain collections,
and so you can still iterate
forward and backward.
Now as Swift developers, we have
access to many useful
collections that conform to
these protocols, collections
such as array, set, and
dictionary.
But thanks to the general
purpose utility of these
protocols, many other types
conform to these collection
protocols as well, such as data,
range, and string.
Or the index collections, and
they all gain access to all of
this rich functionality by
simply conforming to Collection
in their own fashion.
Indeed, once you know how any
one of these types works, you
can apply that knowledge to any
of the others, and there are
quite a few.
So I'm going to talk about the
details about how a type
conforms to Collection, and it
all begins with describing how
it is indexed.
Each collection has its own kind
of index.
And that index must be
comparable.
In some cases, the indices can
look like integers, like arrays,
but just because an index
happens to look like an integer
doesn't mean that you should use
it like one.
Now I want to ask a few
questions that might have
surprising answers.
The first is how do we get the
first element of an array, and
instantly you probably all
thought, well I'll just call
array subzero.
An array's index happens to be
it.
So you can sometimes say this
and get exactly what you intend.
But it isn't the best way to do
this.
I'm going to go ahead and ask
the same question, but this time
about a different collection.
What's the first element of a
set?
Now this might seem like a
really weird question, right?
Sets are unordered.
However, they are collections,
and being collections, you can
iterate through them, and when
you iterate through a set,
you're going to iterate through
one element first, and so that's
really the question we're asking
here.
So can I say set subzero?
Happily, the compiler will say
no, and that's because set's
index type is an int, the type
system wants us to use the
correct index type.
Lucky for us we already know how
to do that.
We know the collection protocol
tells us that all collections
have a start index, so let's go
ahead and use that, and if we do
this, this will actually work
with all collections.
Start index is always going to
be the element of the first item
that you would see when you
iterate.
But there's a nuance to watch
out for when using indices to
directly subscript into any
collection.
And that is, it can crash.
I haven't actually asserted that
these collections have contents
in them, and so when you're, I'm
just using start index, and
these collections could be
empty.
It turns out though that
accessing the first element in a
collection is such a common task
that there's an even better way.
Simply call first.
And if you call first, this is a
lot safer, because the return
time of this is optional,
reflecting the fact that not all
collections have a first
element.
So I have another question.
It's the second element of a
collection, and I want to
emphasize collection here.
It could be any collection, an
array, a set, or something that
doesn't even exist yet.
Let's go ahead and add a new
property to collection via
protocol extension, and we'll
call it second, and just like
first, it's going to return
optional, because not all
collections have two elements.
So, let's try writing this by
subscripting 1.
But here our zero-based indexing
instincts are going to lead us
astray, and then we'll be caught
by the compiler again.
We want this code to work with
every collection, and not all
collections use integers to
index.
So let's try a different
approach.
What I really want is one
greater than the start index.
But lucky here, the compiler
will catch this as well.
You can't add 1 to an arbitrary
index type.
Index types are supposed to be
opaque or can be opaque.
And what we really need to be
doing here is we need to be
using the API provided by the
collection protocol to do this.
So let's go ahead and do this.
I commented out a sketch of the
things that we're going to need
to do to find the second
element.
The very first thing that we
need to do is we need to check
to see if the collection is
empty.
Collections are empty when their
start index is exactly
equivalent to their end index.
So let's check for that and
return nil, because such a
collection doesn't have a second
element.
Oh, and so now we can assume
that our collection has one
element in it.
We can use index after to get
the second element or the second
index, but we need to make sure
that that index is valid, and
let's see this visually.
We advance after, but if the
collection only had one element
in it, we have now actually
produced an invalid index, and
if we tried to subscript with
that index, we'd get that fatal
error that we saw just a moment
ago.
So we check for it to be valid,
and this is very similar to the
empty [inaudible].
We just make sure that our index
is not equal to the end index
returning nil.
Again, because two-element
collections don't have a, or
one-element collections don't
have a second element.
At this point, we have all the
assumptions we need to know that
our collection has at least two
elements in it, and so we're
safe to use the subscript
operator with that index,
retrieving the value that we
desire.
Now, it turns out, or that looks
like a lot of code, but it's
worth pointing out that this
general purpose index math will
work with any collection, which
is pretty awesome, and it turns
out Swift has a better way to do
this though.
There's something called slices,
but before I show how to do it
with slices, I want to talk
about what slices are and how
they work.
Slices are a type that describe
only part of a collection.
And every slice has their own
start and end index, and slices
exist separately from the
collections, from their
originating collection.
And what makes slices so
efficient is they occupy no
extra storage.
They simply refer back to the
original collection, and when
slices are subscripted, they
read out of the original buffer.
And they can do this because
they share the same indices as
their underlying collection.
And let's take a look at how
that works.
We can prove this to ourselves.
We'll start with an array, and
we'll ask that array to drop its
first element, producing a slice
that's one element shorter.
And because we care about
proving about the indices, we'll
actually get the second index of
the array by asking to advance
one after the start index, and
then we'll compare those.
And indeed, they are the same.
Now this dropfirst function
looks exactly like we need to
succinctly get the second
element of our collection.
So let's go back to our previous
solution, and see how much more
expressive we can be with
slices.
Remember all that fancy index
[inaudible] code we had to write
earlier?
Well, by using dropfirst, we're
going to let slices take care of
all that fancy index bounds
checking for us.
And since first returns an
optional, this will work as
expected with empty and single
element collections.
Let's visualize what's happening
here.
We start with an array, and we
form a slice by dropping the
first element.
We then use the first property
to subscript into the slice,
retrieving the element from the
original collection.
Now I don't know about you, but
I'd much rather maintain this
code.
Now every type is free to
describe its own slice type, and
many do.
For instance, arrays define
array slices that are especially
attuned to the most common use
cases that arrays work with.
Similarly, string defines a
substring slice type, and
substrings, again, are tuned to
the special cases that are most
common with strings.
Some types, like set, will make
use of the generalized slice
type defined in the standard
library.
That's because sets are
unordered.
There's not very much else that
they can do.
They just basically need to
maintain a start and an end
index [inaudible] to the
original collection.
Data and range on the other hand
are their own slice types, and
so there's a lot of options that
you have here.
And there's one more thing about
slices that I want to talk about
before we move on.
Let's suppose that we had a
really large collection, like
thousands and thousands and
thousands of elements.
And we add a couple of small
slices to parts of that
collection.
It's important to remember that
the slice keeps the entirety of
the originating collection alive
as long as the slice is around.
And this can lead to surprising
problems.
Let see how this works in code.
Let's suppose I have an
extension on an array that
allows me to return the first
half, and I'm using the droplast
function here to do so.
And we have an array of eight
numbers, and we call our
extension, producing the slice,
and then to try to get rid of
that original storage of eight
numbers, I go ahead and assign
that array to an empty array.
Our first clue that something
interesting is happening occurs
when we ask our slice for its
first element.
We're somehow able to return
one, even though we threw away
the storage for the original
array.
Either there was a copy or
something magical is going on.
And so if we wanted to eliminate
that buffer though, and oh the
magic that's actually going on
is that we're holding onto the
buffer.
And so if we wanted to eliminate
that, what we could do is we
could form an actual copy of the
array from the slice, and then
if we set that slice to an empty
array itself, that copy would
still be valid.
Let's visualize what just
happened.
We started with an array.
We then formed a slice on the
first half of that array.
We then created a copy of that,
setting the array to be empty
and setting that slice to be
empty.
And only after we did that did
the underlying storage go away.
So in this matter, slices sort
of work like lazy copies.
You get to choose when you make
a copy of the elements yourself,
and it turns out that this
concept of being lazy and doing
something later is really useful
in other contexts too.
One such context is function
calls.
Now function calls in Swift are
eager by default.
That is, they consume their
input and return their output as
demanded.
Consider this example.
We start with a range from one
to 4000, and ranges are a really
succinct way of representing a
lot of numbers.
It's just a start and an end,
and it knows how to produce
them.
We then map this though
multiplying each value by two,
and so we've now actually
allocated an array of 4000
elements and performed our
mapping function on each of
them.
We then filter that down to four
elements.
And so at this point, we've
actually gone ahead and
allocated 4004, you know, space
for 4004 elements, but we only
really needed the final four.
And that's an awful lot of
intermediate computation that
maybe we don't always desire.
It would be great if there was a
way just to not do any of it,
unless it was absolutely needed.
And Swift's answer for that is
called being lazy, just like in
real life.
We'll start as we did before
with the range, and then we'll
tell that range to be lazy.
And when we do this, what
happens is we wrap the original
collection with a lazy
collection, and when we perform
operations on this lazy
collection, what's going to
happen is we're going to wrap it
again.
And so when we wrap the, when we
call map on it, we actually
aren't mapping.
We're not doing anything with
that closure other than storing
it for later should we ever need
to use it.
Further, if I filter that lazy
map collection, the filter
simply wraps the map collection,
noting that it's going to filter
later on demand, but not right
now.
Now let's go ahead and ask our
lazy filter collection for it's
first element.
When we do this, we'll start by
asking the lazy filter
collection for it's first
element, but the lazy filter
collection doesn't know.
It wraps something that might
know.
And so it'll defer to the map
collection.
And the map collection also
doesn't know it's first element,
but it wraps a collection that
might, and indeed, the range
knows it's first element.
The first element of the range
is the value one, which it
returns to the lazy map
collection where now the lazy
map collection can actually
perform it's closure, computing
the value 2, which it returns to
the lazy filter collection as a
candidatefirst element.
Now lucky for us in this case, 2
happens to be less than 10, and
so the lazy filter collection
finds it first element on the
first try, which it returns back
to its caller.
Now that's a lot of different
computation.
And I mentioned that lazy aims
to only do calculation as needed
on demand, but another thing
that it avoids is creating
intermediate storage.
So I want to show an example of
that.
Let's suppose we had an array of
different kind of bears.
However, I want to point out
that some of these bears are
redundant.
We already know that they're
bears.
They don't need to tell us
again.
So let's write some code to find
those silly, redundant bears,
and we'll do this using a lazy
filter, as before.
And in this case, producing a
lazy filter is going to be a
lazy filter collection that
wraps an array of strings.
In our closer here, were going
to print out which bear we're
currently iterating on before we
do our predicate check.
And we're doing this because I
want to understand how filter
works a little better, and then
we'll call first, and when we do
this, we'll defer to the lazy
filter collection, and then the
lazy filter collection will in
turn defer to the original
storage where we'll print out
Grizzly, check the predicate,
which in this case is false,
Grizzly does not contain the
word bear, and advance on to
panda.
When we get to panda, when we
get to panda, we'll again print
out panda, check to see if it
contains the word bear, and
advance on to spectacle.
Spectacle gets printed, also
doesn't contain the word bear,
and we advance finally to gummy
bears, which mercifully has the
word bear in it, and which the
lazy filter collection can now
return to its caller.
Now what would happen if we
called first again?
Well, it's the same story.
We ask the lazy filter
collection, which defers to the
underlying collection, which
repeats that calculation,
returning it to its caller.
Now this might not typically be
what you want, and so if you
find yourself needing to
repeatedly ask the lazy
collection to calculate its
result, there's a way to make
sure that that happens just
once.
We can ensure that the lazy
collection is iterated exactly
once by creating a new nonlazy
collection from the lazy, and
when you do this, it will still
defer to the lazy collection,
but now the iteration will
proceed through the entirety of
your underlying collection,
producing essentially, you know,
the nonlazy version of that lazy
calculation.
And so in this case, we get an
array containing the string
gummy bears.
And if we print the first
element of that ray, we don't
need to consult the closure at
all or the lazy collection at
all.
We basically stamped out the
laziness and now have an eager
array.
So when should we be lazy?
Well, lazy collections are a
really great way to eliminate
the overhead of chained maps and
filters.
They excel when you find
yourself only needing part of
the result of a collection
calculation, or we should avoid
using lazy if your closures have
side effects, and your closures
should rarely have side effects.
And be sure to reify back, or I
should say, be sure to consider
reifying back into a regular
collection when you cross API
boundaries.
Lazy should often be an
implementation detail.
Now up until now, we've been
able to do a lot of cool things
with just mutable collections,
but of course Swift lets us
mutate our collections as well.
Let's talk about the two kinds
of collections that we haven't
talked about yet.
The first of these is mutable
collection.
This adds a setter to the
subscript so that you can change
the contents of a collection but
not its length.
And you have to be able to do
this in constant time.
The next is called a Range
Replaceable Collection, and this
is the kind of collection that
you get when you can remove
elements from a collection or
insert them.
And now I want to talk about one
of the questions I get asked all
the time.
Why does my perfectly reasonable
collection code crash?
And like all good question
answers, I almost always follow
up with a few questions of my
own.
Sometimes I start with the
classic, well what are you
trying to do?
And I usually quickly follow up
with, well how are you using
your collections?
Are you mutating them?
Are you sure you aren't
accessing your collections for
multiple threads?
And I ask these questions
because their answers often lead
to the root cause of the
problem.
Well, let's begin with the
assumption that threads aren't
involved.
I'm not ready to think about
threads yet.
It's not even 9:30.
Suppose we had an array, and we
get the index of an element that
we know is there, in this case
the value e.
And then we mutate the
collection, say by removing its
first element, and we go ahead
and print the element associated
with that index.
Well when we do this,
unfortunately this will produce
a fatal error.
The index is no longer valid.
In fact, the index became
invalid the moment we mutated
our collection.
A far safer approach would be to
mutate our collection first and
then calculate the index.
It's worth pointing out that
mutation always invalidates
indices.
This doesn't just apply to
arrays.
Let's take a look at how this
problem could manifest with
dictionaries.
Let's suppose that we have a
dictionary showing a few of a
bear's favorite things.
We'll grab the index of our
bear's favorite food and print
it out, confirming that, indeed,
it's salmon.
Next, we'll add a couple more
favorite things that this bear
has, and then we'll make sure
that our favorite food is still
salmon.
And we'll see that, wait a
minute, our favorite good isn't
hibernation, it's salmon.
And just like arrays, we
invalidated our index the moment
we mutated the dictionary.
It's also worth pointing out
that this code can crash.
So how do we go about fixing
this?
Well, it turns out it's the same
exact fix that we used with the
array.
We just simply recompute the
index after we mutate.
Well, one thing to keep in mind
that when you're recomputing
indices this is something that
can sometimes be expensive.
Some index search methods take
linear time.
And so you want to take care to
only find the indices that you
need.
So here's my advice if you want
to avoid finding yourself in
these kinds of situations.
Remember that mutation almost
always invalidates your indices.
You might get away with it
sometimes, but it's really best
to just treat this as a hard
rule.
You'll be much happier for it.
Also remember that slices hold
on to the underlying original
state of the collection even
after it was mutated, and
because of that, really think
twice about holding onto indices
or slices when the underlying
collection is mutable.
And keep in mind that index
computation can sometimes take a
nontrivial amount of time.
So take care to only calculate
indices as needed.
So a little bit later, let's
bring threads into the
discussion.
I mentioned that one of the
questions that I ask is are your
threads accessible for multiple
threads?
And the reason why I ask this is
because our collections assume
that you will access them from a
single thread.
And this is a really good thing
for reasons of performance.
It makes it so that all
single-threaded use cases don't
have to pay the tax of locks or
any of those other primitives
that you could use to ensure
mutual exclusion.
And when threads are involved,
only developers using the
collections will have all the
information needed to restrict
access with the appropriate lock
or a serial queue at a much
higher level abstraction than us
lowly framework developers could
ever offer.
So let's see what these kinds of
problems could look like.
Let's suppose we have an array
that we aim to fill up with
sleeping bears, and to simulate
each bear being their own bear
and in charge of themselves,
we're going to get access to a
concurrent dispatch queue that
we'll use to tell each bear to
go to sleep.
And because this is a concurrent
dispatch queue, it's some time
helpful to like imagine the code
running at the same time, which
I'll simulate by putting them on
the same line.
And later in our application,
let's go ahead and check in on
those sleeping bears, and
sometimes we'll see grandpa and
cubs snoozing happily.
Other times, cub will go to
sleep first, and then it'll be
grandpa.
Sometimes, quite mysteriously,
only grandpa is sleeping in.
And other times, it'll be the
cub, and sometimes our program
just up and crashes, and nobody
bear's getting any sleep.
All of these possibilities
suggest that there's a possible
race condition, and indeed, it
seems likely given all the
potential threads involved in
this example.
And we can prove this to
ourselves using the thread
sanitizer or TSAN that's
included within Xcode.
And if we were to do so, we'd
get output that kind of looks
like this, and indeed, TSAN
would catch the race.
It would tell us there's a Swift
access race.
It would tell us which threads
are involved and give us a
summary at the end telling us
which line to actually go start
looking for our problem.
And all that evidence is
actually going to be really
helpful to find the bug.
So we've proven that there's a
bug here.
TSAN has never lied in my
experience with them.
So we can fix this by
eliminating the bears' ability
to go to sleep at the same time,
and we'll do that with a serial
dispatch queue.
And now only one bear can go to
sleep at a time.
And so if we peek in on our
sleeping bears again now, taking
care to do so on the appropriate
queue, we see that sure enough
grandpa and cub are snoozing
away peacefully like we
expected.
So my advice for working with
collections for multiple threads
is try to isolate your data so
that it can only be seen from a
single thread, and when you
can't do that, make sure that
you have an appropriate form in
mutual exclusion, such as a
serial dispatch queue or locks.
And always use the thread
sanitizer to double check your
work.
It's far better to catch bugs
before they ship in your app
than after.
And I have a little bit more
advice for working with mutable
collections.
The first of which is if you can
avoid it, don't use mutable
state at all.
So far all the difficulties that
I've described have come about
because we've been working with
mutable state.
You can avoid all the potential
for this complexity by avoiding
mutable collections in the first
place.
Many times you can actually
emulate the mutations that you
want to perform by using a slice
or using a lazy wrapper, and
it's almost always easier to
understand data that cannot
change.
And thanks to mutability being
built into Swift, the compiler
will help you if you're leaving
a state mutable when you're not
actually mutating it.
Now I have one more piece of
advice that actually concerns
how best to use mutable state
when you have to.
And that's when you're forming
new collections.
You can help performance if
you're lucky enough to know an
exact count or a really good
approximation of how many
elements you're actually going
to need.
Most collection APIs have a way
of being able to provide this
hint, and when you do this, you
get exactly the size you need
with no overhead.
If you don't, our collections
are general purpose tools.
They're meant to work on a wide
variety of cases, and as you
incrementally add elements, you
may actually end up over
allocating the amount of storage
that you need, but taking care
that you don't over estimate
when providing such hints,
because otherwise you'll find
yourself in the same exactly
situation where you're using up
more storage than you actually
need.
And now, I want to move on to my
final topic for today.
And that's the wide range of
collections that become
available for you when you
import Foundation and when you
should consider using them.
In addition to the standard
library collections, when you
import Foundation, you gain
access to the great
reference-type collections that
objective C developers have been
using for decades.
And many of these also gain
conformance in Swift and thus
behave just the collections that
we've been talking about.
That said, there are a couple
important things to keep in
mind.
First thing to keep in mind is
that these NS [inaudible]
collections are reference types.
And this is best examined by
considering an example.
We're going to define value
types and reference types and do
the same things with them on two
sides.
So with our value type, we'll
call it x.
It will be an array of strings.
We get an empty array called x.
With a reference type, we get an
empty array, but x is pointing
to it.
We then mutate that array with
the value type.
That array is mutated in line.
With the reference type, that
array is, the reference, the
array that is being referenced
is mutated in line.
We add another variable.
With the value type, something
really special happens.
We actually don't copy the
storage at this point.
Why is an array that knows that
its storage is actually owned by
x?
And why is that actually going
to perform that copy until
either of those collections is
mutated.
The reference type is a little
bit different.
Y is just another pointer to the
same underlying array.
So let's go ahead and mutate y.
We'll put another bear in that
array.
With the value type what happens
is first we invoke that copy on
write machinery.
We're writing to a y, so we need
to copy it, and then we can
insert the next bear.
With the reference, it's a
little bit simpler.
There's only one array.
We simply put the panda in the
array.
There's a second thing that you
need to keep in mind when
working with the foundation
collections in Swift.
And that is, all objective-C
APIs in Swift appear as Swift
native value types.
And this is actually really
wonderful because it let's code
in each language speak naturally
with the types that they work
with best.
But how can this work?
The two languages have
completely different
implementations for these
collections.
And the reason why it works is
something known as bridging.
Bridging is how we convert
between the two different
runtime representations, and
this is something that's
necessary because Swift and
objective-C, I'm sure you've
noticed, are very different
languages with very different
compile and runtime features.
And while we've optimized
bridging to be as fast as it can
be, it's not free.
There will always be a cost when
bridging between the two
languages.
So what happens when we bridge?
Well, when we bridge between the
language, we have dispersed set
up new storage, equivalent
storage, so if you're taking n
things in one language, you'll
take up n space in the next one.
Then we need to go element by
element and convert potentially
between them, and this
per-element bridging can
sometimes be recursive.
For instance, if I have an array
of strings, first we'll bridge
the array, and then we'll bridge
each individual string.
And when this happens at the
boundary between the two
languages, we call it eager
bridging.
And collections will always be
bridged eagerly when the
elements of the collection need
bridging as well.
And this arises most often with
dictionaries keyed by strings.
When collection bridging is not
eager, we call it lazy.
And this happens when the
element types of the collection
aren't bridged themselves, such
as NSViews.
In this case, bridging will be
deferred until the collection is
actually first used.
Let's make this concrete with
some examples.
We'll first consider an
objective-C API describing an
NSArray of NSDatas.
Now NSArray is bridged to array,
and NSData is bridged to
value-type data.
And so such a collection would
be bridged eagerly.
I mentioned a moment ago that
NSViews are not bridged in
Swift.
They remain reference types in
And so an NSArray of NSViews
will be lazily bridged.
The bridging won't happen until
you first access or try to use
that array.
And finally, an NSDictionary
with keys that are NS strings
will be bridged eagerly because
the strings need to come across
in Swift as value-type strings.
So now that we know what
bridging is, how it works, and
when it happens, we can move on
to the most important question
of all, which is when should you
care about it.
And the answer is really
straightforward.
When you measure it negatively
impacting your app.
Specifically, when you take a
time profile or trace an
instrument, pay special
attention to where your code
crosses between the languages,
especially when this happens
inside a loop.
Some bridging is going to
happen, and that's totally okay.
What you're looking for though
is a disproportionate amount of
time or a surprising amount of
time spent in code that you
didn't write that has the word
bridge in it.
Let's look at a concrete
example.
Suppose I have a manuscript for
a great children's story that
I'm working on, but it's really
long, so I'm only going to show
a little bit here, but to really
make it pop, I want to make
every word or every instance of
the word brown actually be the
color brown, and in the interest
of space, I'm only going to show
highlighting the first word.
To do this, I'm going to use an
NS mutable attributed string.
I'll pass my story in there.
And then using the attributed
strings string property, I'll
ask for the range of the Swift
string brown, which will produce
a range of strings native index
type.
And as mutable string works with
NS ranges, and so I'll use the
convenience initializer that we
introduced last year to convert
to an NS range, and this, I'm
calling again attributed strings
string property to do the
conversion.
And then we'll color the first
instance of the word brown.
And when I go to run this code,
I notice it's a little slow.
So I profile it.
And I see that, to my surprise,
I thought all the time would be
spent coloring the word brown,
but indeed, it's actually
computing the indices, and why
is that?
And the reason for that is that
we're actually bridging our
string multiple times across
languages.
Mutable attributed string is an
objective-C reference type, and
so when we're asking for the
string property, we're actually
having to convert from an
NSString to a string.
And we're doing it once here
when we calculated the first
range, and we're doing it a
second time when we convert for
the NSRange.
You can imagine how expensive
this would be if we did this in
a loop looking for all the text
to color.
Now let's look into why this is
happening.
Every time I call text.string,
we start in a Swift execution
context.
However, the implementation of
NSMutableAttributedString is
objective-C, and so in order to
provide the result, we actually
have to consult the original
implementation.
The original implementation
returns an NSString, which is
the reference type, and so when
return to string, it needs to be
bridged, graphing cluster by
graphing cluster, character by
character.
And bridging happens whether
it's a return type or a
parameter.
So now that we know those
details, we can make, now we can
actually make this a little bit
better.
Let's just bridge once.
And let's remeasure our code and
see that indeed we've improved
our performance by half.
But it turns out this year we
can do a little better.
Oh, and also, now we're not
bridging where we do that.
But this year we can do a little
bit better.
This year, if we actually
[inaudible] to an NSString when
we ask for the text.string's
property, when we get the
variable out, no bridging is
actually going to occur.
And further, by doing so, now
that string is an NSString, when
we call the range of property,
we're actually going to get an
NSRange out of it automatically.
We won't need to do any of the
range conversion between Swift
native types and the NS ranges,
which is pretty excellent.
So let's measure this code and
see how it is, and sure enough,
this looks pretty good.
Much, much faster than the, you
know, almost 800 milliseconds
that we were consuming
previously.
However, I do want to point out
that we're still bridging here.
And it's a teeny, tiny bridge,
but we're still bridging.
Brown here is a Swift value type
string.
And every time we call into the
objective-C API range of
[inaudible] NSString, we're
actually going to bridge that
teeny, tiny string back to an
NSString.
This is inexpensive in this
case.
I'm only doing it once, but you
can imagine, if this was in a
loop, that small amount would
add up over time.
And so you want to take care to
avoid bridging the same small
strings repeatedly.
However, before you do such
optimizations, always measure.
And so now that we've seen the
details of bridging, I want to
offer a little bit of advice
about when to use Foundation
collections.
You should consider using them
explicitly when you need a
collection with reference
semantics.
Don't need to write one of those
for yourself, we already have
many great ones.
You should also use it when
you're working with types that
you know to be reference types.
Things like NS proxies or core
data managed objects.
And the final time to consider
using them is when you're round
tripping with objective-C code,
but I'd recommend strongly doing
this only after you've measured
and identified that bridging is
indeed the culprit for whatever
performance problems you may be
seeing.
And now, we've reached the end
of today's dive into the
incredible power of our world's
collections in Swift.
I want you to use this new-found
understanding to review your
existing use of collections.
Look for places where you can
improve your code through more
effective use of indices and
slices.
Measure your code.
And look for places where you
could benefit by being lazy or
by tuning how you bridge.
Use the thread sanitizer to help
audit your mutable state, and
further hone your mastery of
collections by apply all the
concepts discussed today in
Playgrounds and you own apps.
Be sure to visit our last few
labs today if you have any
questions about collections.
We're here to help.
Thank you so much for you time.
Now go out and be effective.
[ Applause ]