[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Good morning everyone.
Happy Friday.
My name is Skylar Peterson.
I am an engineer on the iOS
Accessibility team at Apple, and
with me today I have Bhavya, an
engineer on the Mac
accessibility team at Apple.
And together we're going to
delve into what it means to
create an exceptional experience
in your app when it comes to
accessibility.
As a quick refresher, we tend to
think of accessibility as
meaning making technology usable
by everyone.
At Apple, we categorize the way
in which we make that technology
accessible into four areas of
focus, cognitive, motor, vision,
and hearing.
Now we have a bunch of great
features that we work on to
address all of these areas, but
at the end of the day, it's the
work that you do in tandem with
our assistive technologies that
make our platforms stellar
places for people with
disabilities.
Making sure that all the great
content you work on is
accessible to everyone creates a
better, more inclusive community
for all of us and fundamentally
improves the lives of millions
of people around the world.
For today's talk, we're going to
skip past a lot of the basics of
making apps accessible.
However, if this is your first
exposure to accessibility or
you've never checked out any of
our accessibility APIs before,
then I highly recommend that you
check out some of the sessions
from last year's WWDC.
There's still a lot that you're
going to be able to gain from
our session.
It may just feel like it's going
a little fast for you because
today we're going to focus on
going beyond the basics, and I
want to start by focusing in on
this one word, usable.
Usable is great, making sure
that all of the content of your
app is even visible to an
assistive technology is a
critical first step.
But when it comes down to it, we
don't want our apps to just be
usable, right.
No one's going to be out there
bragging that their app is
usable.
They want it to be exceptional.
We want people who use them to
be delighted when they do.
It may not be clear to you
exactly what that means when it
comes to accessibility, and
that's what we're here to talk
about today and hopefully
provide you with some helpful
guidance on how to do that.
I'd like to focus on two main
areas and the different
considerations that you'll want
to make for each when evaluating
the accessibility of your own
app.
First, visual design, and
second, the way that an
assistive technology user
experiences your app.
So let's start with visual
design.
I'd like to begin by addressing
transparency and blurring.
We use blur and transparency
across many parts of iOS.
It creates a vibrant, unique
look and feel for our operating
system.
But for some people,
particularly those with low
vision conditions, blur and
transparency can have negative
impacts on legibility and even
cause a degree of eye strain.
So we provide an accessibility
setting to reduce blur and
transparency, and it can have
dramatic effects like this.
Instead of blurring the
backdrop, we fade it so that you
still have the context of where
you are in the system, but the
visual noise is reduced, and the
controls which before had color
bleed-in from behind are more
legible on their solid backdrop.
Same with folders and finally
spotlight.
Now this is a particularly good
example, because we've taken a
sample of the user's wallpaper
so that we can color the
backdrop, and they could still
feel personalized and contextual
to the device, but we still get
that increased contrast and
legibility of having a solid
background.
As a developer, you can cater
your own use of blurring and
transparency by checking whether
or not the reduced transparency
setting is enabled and adapting
your UI accordingly.
On iOS, you would use is reduce
transparency enabled on UI
accessibility, and on macOS,
accessibility display should
reduce transparency on NS
Workspace.
Next, I'd like to talk about
contrast.
Contrast between content and
it's background is hugely
important when it comes to
perceivability.
As colors get closer to one
another, they become more
difficult to distinguish.
As well, certain colors that are
legible at bigger sizes don't
work when content is scaled
down.
For example, with text, the
letters bleed together more
easily at smaller sizes.
Now you can compute the contrast
ratio between a particular color
combination to see whether or
not it's going to be legible,
and we followed the
recommendations laid out in the
web content accessibility
guidelines that states that the
minimum contrast ratio you
should aim for is 4.5 to 1.
Obviously, the highest contrast
that you're going to be able to
get is between black and white,
which comes out to be 21 to 1
and obviously works great at all
text sizes.
Now let's take a look at a shade
of gray.
This particular gray will work
great for larger text, but it
isn't so great for smaller text
because your eyes can't
distinguish the shapes of the
letter forms.
It's contrast ratio 4.5 to 1 is
right on the line of passable.
Let's like take a look at one
last gray.
It may not be apparent on this
really large display, but this
text is really hard to see on a
small device, even at a large
font size.
It's contrast ratio of 2.9 to 1
is just too low.
And you can use the built-in
tool in our accessibility
inspector in Xcode to show you
what the contrast ratio between
a particular color combination
is and what text sizes that
color combo passes for.
And we follow the same
guidelines that I mentioned
before in this tool.
However, even with a ratio that
exceeds the recommended contrast
ratio of 4.5 to 1, for people
with low vision conditions,
colors that meet the bar can
still be problematic when it
comes to legibility.
So we provide a setting for
increasing the contrast across
the system.
In previous versions of iOS,
this setting was referred to as
darken colors.
So in your code you can use is
darker system colors enabled to
check.
Though if you're using a
standard UIKit control that you
set a tint color on, you will
actually get this work for free.
On a macOS, you can use
accessibility display should
increase contrast.
Next we have sizing.
Changing the content size of
your device can have dramatic
effects in the way that content
is displayed and perceived.
And this is hugely beneficial to
low vision users.
So let's take for example a
calendar.
On the left, we have this view
at the default text size, and on
the right I've blown it up
several sizes to one of the
larger accessibility sizes.
If we simulate what this looks
like to someone with a low
vision condition, then the
benefits become immediately
apparent.
That text on the right is
actually still legible.
On iOS, you can check what
content size a user has set
their device to, and there are
seven standard sizes with large
being the default, but you can
also enable even larger
accessibility sizes, which
increase that by five more.
Now there's a lot more that I
could say about dynamic type,
but I'm going to leave it at
that and instead encourage you
to check out some of the
fantastic resources that we have
to figure out the best way to
get dynamic type working in your
own apps.
Now for some, changing the size
of text is overkill, but the
default weight of fonts and
glyphs can still make it
difficult to read.
So on iOS there's a setting for
enabling bold text, which will
also increase the stroke weight
of glyphs.
If you're using stand built-in
UI controls and a system font,
then it's likely that you don't
need to do anything to get bold
text working in your app, but if
you're using your own text
solution or a custom font, or
you simply want to do something
like making the dividing lines
in your app thicker when bold
text is on, then you can check
whether or not the setting is
enabled and adapt as necessary.
Next, we have motion.
Animation is fun, and it often
makes content feel more alive.
It can provide a direct
correlation between user
interaction and what effects
their actions are having.
However, certain conditions,
particularly inner ear
conditions that affect the
balance center of the brain can
make motion and animation
problematic, which often results
in things like dizziness or
imbalance or even nausea.
Now I'm going to go through some
examples of animation types that
can be problematic, so if any of
you in the audience have a
problem with motion, then you
may want to look away
momentarily as I play the
default animations, which I am
going to preface.
The first is scaling and
zooming.
On the left, we have the default
animation for opening an app,
specifically the clock app,
which I'm going to show now.
We zoom into the location of the
app's icon while it's UI scales
into view.
And on the right, we have the
same interaction but with reduce
motion enabled, which will
replace that with a simple cross
fade.
Next, spinning and vortex
effects.
If we take a look at the full
screen echo effect in messages,
which I'm going to show now, we
can see that content is spinning
along the Z axis while also
changing in scale, and these
types of motions paired together
can cause issues.
In the case of message effects,
if reduced motion is enabled,
then we provide the user with a
specific prompt to play the
message effect instead of having
it autoplay.
So they can choose whether or
not they want to see it.
Next, we have plane-shifting
animations.
What I want to show here is the
Safari tabs animation.
So I'm going to tap on the show
tabs button, and you see that
the plane of the web cards is
shifted to simulate a 3D space.
And on the right, we have the
reduced animation, which again
is a simple cross fade, but we
also blink the card so that you
have the context of which one
you're coming from that you got
in the original animation.
Multidirectional or multispeed
motion is another trigger.
I'm going to show the movement
of the messages bubbles in a
conversation.
It's a little hard to see in
this video, but it's a lot more
obvious on device.
As I scroll the messages, they
have a springiness to them where
they contract and expand away
from one another.
If we have reduce motion
enabled, then we disable this
effect and have them just scroll
normally.
Finally, we have peripheral
movement.
The weather app on iOS has
subtle animations that play in
the background to indicate the
current weather condition.
You cans see on the left that
the clouds are sort of drifting
through the air and the sun is
sort of shimmering and shining.
But if you're scanning the
forecast below, then this
animation is in your peripheral
view, and this can be
problematic in the same way that
reading while riding in a car
can make you feel sick.
The horizontal motion above your
area of focus triggers a
reaction in your brain.
With reduced motion on, we
disable the background
animation.
Now typically we don't want to
just remove all animation, so of
course we have a setting that
you can check to see if motion
should be reduced and adapt
accordingly.
On iOS, you check is reduced
motion enabled, and on macOS,
check accessibility display
should reduce motion.
It's important to note that
simply removing an animation is
often not an adequate
experience.
You don't want to lessen the
You just want to add something
else equally fun or engaging but
different that works for the
user.
Finally, I'd like to finish
talking about design by
addressing UI complexity.
Apps play key roles in our lives
now, and it's critically
important for all of us that our
technology is simple and easy to
use, that it enhances our lives
instead of adding extra
unnecessary burden.
In the United States alone, one
in six children have a
developmental disability ranging
from speech and language
impairments to more serious
developmental disabilities like
autism.
For people with cognitive
disabilities or even a chronic
illness, using an app can expend
more energy than for someone who
is neurotypical.
So how do we make sure that our
apps are simple and the least
burdensome that they can be?
Well they should be easy to
navigate by having them
similarly structured and through
clear, logical cause and effect.
We should be able to start using
our apps and complete the most
common tasks without
encountering any barriers.
And finally, our apps should
behave in a consistent manner so
that when I learn something one
place, it applies to another.
Using this standard UIKit views
is great because people get
familiar with way they work, but
UIKit also functions as a design
language for iOS.
So if you're doing something
custom, consistency with a
parallel control in UIKit will
help people intuit how to use
your app.
This really all boils down to
the way in which people
experience your apps, which is
just as important for people who
use assistive technologies like
VoiceOver or Switch Control.
So I'd like now to spend some
time speaking to how you can
improve the experience for those
accessibility users.
The experience for assistive
tech like VoiceOver and Switch
Control can be quite different
from your typical user
experience.
VoiceOver uses many gestures
like swipes and multifinger
taps,
while Switch Control scans
groups and offers logical quick
actions.
For both, there are built-in
equivalents for any standard
gesture or interaction, but what
makes experiencing an app with
these technologies exceptional?
We want to go from the bare
minimum of it works to it works
well.
While despite the fact that
assistive tech users experience
your app in ways that are
different, the same design
principles that drive a good
experience for a
nonaccessibility user applies
here.
You want easy navigation,
predictable behavior,
prioritizing our action, and
consistency.
It's also important to note that
if something is communicated
contextually by separate
elements, that same context is
conveyed to our accessibility
users.
I'd like now to bring Bhavya up
on stage to run through a quick
audit of the accessibility
experience of an app.
Bhavya.
[ Applause ]
>> Good morning, everyone.
My name is Bhavya, and I'm a
software engineer on the
Accessibility team at Apple.
Today, I'd like to talk to you
about enhancing the
accessibility experience of your
app by sharing with you an app
that Skyler and I have been
working on.
The name of this app is
Exceptional Dogs, and the goal
is to help make the dog adoption
process easier by allowing users
to browse a collection of dogs
who are in need of a loving
home.
Let's take a look at this app.
This is Exceptional Dogs.
At the top, I have a carousel
like UI, which is essentially a
collection view of all the
different dogs that I can
browse.
In the bottom left corner, I
have a favorite button so that I
can favorite particular dogs I
like, and in the bottom right
corner, I have a gallery button,
which brings up a modal view
with additional photos of the
dog.
However, not all dogs have a
gallery button.
Notice how this button fades
away as swipe to Layla, who has
no additional pictures.
Beneath the carousel I have a
stats view with information
about the dog like its name and
breed.
Notice how this information
updates as I swipe to the next
dog in the carousel.
Finally, at the bottom I have
the name of the shelter with two
buttons which can open the
location of the shelter in maps
or call the location.
So there's quite a bit going on
here in terms of visual
complexity, but Skyler and I
done our due diligence, and
we've sprinkled in a little bit
of accessibility, just enough to
make sure that VoiceOver can
reach every element on screen.
So let's turn on VoiceOver now
and see how a nonsighted or low
vision user would digest all of
this complexity.
>> VoiceOver on.
Exceptional Dogs.
Pinky.
>> So VoiceOver lands on the
image and correctly announces
the name of the dog.
Great.
I'm going to swipe from left to
right now to scroll through the
carousel.
>> Layla, Bro, Pudding.
Favorite off button, Pudding,
Bro.
>> So VoiceOver was able to
correctly scroll through the
carousel, but we weren't able to
reach the favorite button until
we hit the very end of the
carousel.
I could, of course, still get to
the favorite button by placing
my finger on it like this.
>> Favorite off button.
>> But it's important to
remember that this is not how a
typical VoiceOver user
navigates.
Rather, VoiceOver users swipe to
reach to the next element, and
currently, using swiping we
aren't able to reach the
favorite or gallery buttons
until we hit the very end of the
carousel.
This isn't a great or
exceptional experience because
it really limits my ability to
favorite or view the galleries
for virtually all of the dogs in
the carousel.
I'll place my finger over the
modal view now to activate the
gallery button.
>> Show gallery.
Show gallery.
Picture one of Bro.
Image.
>> Let's scroll through our
gallery.
>> Picture two of Bro.
Picture three of Bro.
Pinky.
Layla.
>> So, we were successfully able
to scroll through the gallery
with VoiceOver but focus went
behind the modal view to the
content in the background.
This experience might seem
workable because it gets the
user to the content that they
need to, but it's not great or
exceptional because allowing
focus to go behind the modal
view is confusing and
distracting for the user.
I elected the modal view now by
double tapping on the close
button.
>> Close, Layla.
>> Let's swipe through our stats
view.
>> Name, breed, Layla, Labrador.
>> When I hear a name, I expect
to hear the actual name of the
dog right after, but instead I
hear breed.
Visually, the layout of all this
information makes sense, but to
VoiceOver, its structure causes
it to announce information out
of order.
This creates a lack of context
for the user and places
unnecessary cognitive load on
them.
I'll place my finger over the
name of the shelter now and
swipe to the buttons next to it.
>> Skyler's animal shelter.
Open address in maps.
Button.
Call.
>> Once again, these buttons are
perfectly accessible like the
labels from the stat view, yet
they lack context.
When I hear call, it isn't clear
to me what this call action is
referring to even though
visually this is pretty evident
since the call button is right
next to the name of the shelter.
>> VoiceOver off.
>> So we found a couple of
issues here.
These issues don't completely
render our app unusable, but
they do place unnecessary
cognitive load on the user.
Remember, our goal here is to
create an exceptional
accessibility experience.
I'd like to invite Skyler back
to the stage now to talk about
how we can elevate our
experience for Exceptional Dogs
to be exceptional.
[ Applause ]
>> So we found some issues with
our app.
So let's take a look at some of
our accessibility API that we
can leverage to resolve them.
From Bhavya's audit, we found
some issues with our carousel.
We could get to the favorite and
gallery buttons but only after
reaching the end of the list
instead of for each individual
dog.
As well, we couldn't get to that
display data below for the dog
until reaching the end of the
list.
We need the actions and data for
each dog to be quickly
reachable.
So what we can do is use UI
accessibility element to create
a new element in place of the
collection view.
UI accessibility element is a
class used to create custom
elements oftentimes for
representing parts of your UI
that are inaccessible, like
something you've drawn in Core
Graphics for instance.
But we can also leverage it to
create a custom experience,
which is what we're going to do
in this case.
We'll need to return any custom
elements from the accessibility
elements property for the view
that would contain them.
This tells our assistive
technology what the accessible
sub elements of a given view are
and the order that they should
be navigable.
So if we get our custom element
in place, we can swipe to the
content for each dog easily.
Great.
But then how do we change dogs?
Well, we can take advantage of
accessibility increment and
accessibility decrement.
By adding the adjustable trait
to our custom element, we'll let
the assistive technique know
that our element responds to
these callbacks so that in the
case of VoiceOver when a user
swipes up or down with their
finger, then the collection view
will scroll to the next or
previous item.
Now, next let's take a look at
these information labels.
When Bhavya was swiping through
them, they were out of order,
and the value labels lack the
context of what information they
were providing.
Context is hugely important.
If I just touch on the value
label for whether or not the dog
is fostered, all I'm going to
hear from VoiceOver is yes.
Well, yes what?
What does that mean?
What does that correspond to?
As well, we have an issue with
navigation.
We're looking at having to swipe
through 14 different labels just
to find what we're looking for.
But combining them would cut
that in half and makes
navigation much, much faster.
It makes more sense to group
these labels together as a
single element so that I
understand the relationship
between label and value.
We again can use UI
accessibility element to
accomplish this by creating
elements for each pair of labels
and returning them from the
containing views accessibility
elements property.
We also saw that when Bhavya was
swiping through elements in the
app that the shelter info view
was split up into three distinct
elements, the name of the
shelter, the location button,
and a call button.
The buttons have the same issue
of lacking contexts as labels.
If you reach them first without
reaching the name of the
shelter, then it's unclear what
they correspond to.
Having these three elements
exist separately increases the
amount of elements that a user
is going to have to navigate
through to find the content
they're looking for.
So it makes more sense to
combine them into one and give
us quicker navigation.
As well, we want to think about
what the priority is here.
The most relevant piece of
information is what shelter the
dog is housed in.
So we'll provide that first and
add supplementary actions for
locating and calling the
shelter.
To accomplish this, we can use
our accessibility custom actions
API.
This allows us to add actions to
an element that the user can
cycle through until they find
the one they're looking for and
activate it.
You can return an array of
custom actions for a given view,
and then for each action, you
have a name, which is conveyed
to the user as what's going to
happen when they activate that
action, and a target selector
relationship, which will execute
the action in your code.
So we'll make that whole shelter
view accessible and add custom
actions to it for getting the
location and calling.
Finally, we have the gallery
view.
When Bhavya brought this up, we
could swipe through all of the
elements in the background, and
though this view apps modal,
that isn't the case, because
instead of housing this view in
a view controller and presenting
it modally, we instead opted to
just add it on top of a view
hierarchy.
And so since the content in the
background is still visible,
VoiceOver doesn't know that it
should exclude it.
Although everything in the
gallery is accessible to
VoiceOver, it gets confusing to
the user whose lost the context
of where they are and what
effect their actions are having.
To fix this, we want to override
accessibility view is modal on
the presented view, which will
tell our assistive technology
that only the elements of that
view should be accessible right
now.
We'll also want to post a
notification to let the
assistive technology know that
our on-screen elements have
changed and that it should
attempt to refocus.
We can use the screen change
notification to do so.
I'm going to turn things back
over to Bhavya now to show you
how to use all the API we just
covered to implement our
solutions.
Bhavya?
[ Applause ]
Thanks Skyler.
Let's elevate accessibility
experience of our app from great
to exceptional.
I'll jump into Xcode.
Let's start with enhancing the
experience of the carousel at
the top.
Here, I have a class called Dog
Carousel Container view which
houses our collection view of
the dogs, our favorite button,
and our gallery button.
As Skyler mentioned, we'd like
to implement the increment and
decrement functionality so that
we can swipe up and down to
scroll through our carousel.
To do this, we can create a
property on this class called
carousel accessibility element,
which will be a custom UI
accessibility element that
supports those gestures.
Let's implement carousel
accessibility element.
This will be a subclass of UI
It also needs to know about the
current dog object it's
representing, so let's create a
property for that.
We'll give it an initializer
also, and let's give it some
basic accessibility like the
label and the value.
Our label will be dog picker,
and the value will be a
combination of the name of the
dog and it's favorited status.
Okay. Let's get into the
increment and decrement
functionality.
First, we'd like to override
accessibility traits to return
the adjustable trait.
Let's first implement
accessibility increment.
We want our increment function
to scroll the collection view
forward.
So let's create a function that
does exactly that.
Here, I have a function called
accessibility scroll collection
view.
It takes in a bullion, which
determines if the collection
view will scroll forwards or
backwards.
Let's dive into this function.
I get a reference to my
container view, my current dog,
and my list of all the dogs.
If I'm moving forwards, I get
the index of my current dog, and
I validate that it doesn't
exceed out of bounds, and if
doesn't, I'll ask my collection
view to scroll forward by one
index.
I'll do something similar if I'm
going backwards except I'll make
sure that my index won't become
negative, and then I'll ask my
collection view to scroll
backwards by one index.
Let's go ahead and make use of
this function in our increment
function.
I'll pass in true to indicate
that I want to scroll forwards.
And similarly, I can implement
accessibility decrement, the
only difference being that I'll
pass in false since I want to
scroll backwards.
And that's it for the carousel
accessibility element.
Let's scroll back up to our
container view.
Here, we need to expose the
carousel accessibility element,
and to do that, we can override
accessibility elements.
Within this function, I'll get a
reference to my current dog and
make sure it's valid before I go
ahead and create my elements.
Let's start by instantiating the
carousel accessibility element.
I'll first get a reference to
the carousel accessibility
element if one already exists,
and if it doesn't, I'll
instantiate one here.
I'll set it's accessibility
frame to be the frame of the dog
collection view, and then I'll
store a reference to it here.
And at the end, I'll return this
array of elements.
Before I do that, I want to add
some elements to my array.
I'll check to see if my current
dog has more than one image, and
if so, I want my array to
comprise of the carousel
accessibility element, the
favorite button, and the gallery
button, but if the dog doesn't
have more than one image, we
should probably omit the gallery
button.
One thing I need to remember to
do is to update the current dog
property on the carousel
accessibility element if that
corresponding property gets
updated on my container view.
We're almost done.
Recall that when I swipe to the
carousel, the information, the
content of the stats view is
changing.
However, when I'm swiping with
VoiceOver, I need to let the
app, I need to let VoiceOver
know to update it's
understanding of the
accessibility elements on
screen.
To do that, I can post a layout
change notification whenever a
scroll occurs.
I'll head over in my view
controller file, and inside my
scroll view did scroll view at
the very end I'll post that
layout change notification like
this.
And that's it for the carousel
container view.
A core part of this solution was
using and creating accessibility
elements, and I can use this
same concept to help me solve a
different problem in the stats
view.
Recall that in the stats view
all the information was
separated, and it lacked
context.
I can use this same concept to
help me group the information
for the stats view together and
to add context.
I'll head over to the doc stats
view where all of these stats
are laid out.
I'll start by overriding the
accessibility elements to create
my elements.
I want to cache the elements I
create from this function so
that I don't have to recompute
them every single time I make
them.
To do that, I can create a
private property called
underscore accessibility
elements, which will act as that
cache and store these elements.
Let's get into my function.
First, I'll see if my cache is
empty, and if so, I'll go ahead
and populate my elements.
I'll iterate over all my title
labels, and I'll get a reference
to the title label, which would
be something like breed, and
it's corresponding value, which
would be something like
Labrador.
With the references to both the
title and it's corresponding
value, I can now create an
accessibility element, which
encompasses the information for
both of these together.
I'll start by creating my
accessibility element here, and
I'll set it's label and it's
accessibility frame to be a
combination of the corresponding
values of both the title and the
value.
I'll add this element to my
array of elements, and once I'm
done looping over all the title
and value pairs, at the end I'll
set my cache equal to this
array, and I'll return these
elements.
One thing we need to remember to
do is to reset our cache every
time the dog object on this gets
updated so that we can compute
the new elements for the new
dog.
To do that, I can simply set it
to no over here.
And that's it for the dog stats
view.
Next, let's work on adding some
context to the call and open
location buttons.
I'll head over to the shelter
info view where I have a
reference to the name of my
shelter, the map button, and the
call button.
We'd like the actions of both of
these buttons to be custom
actions on their containing
view, and to achieve this, we
can start by exposing that
containing view as an
accessibility element.
Let's go ahead and give this a
descriptive label, which would
be the name of the shelter.
>> Finally, let's override
accessibility custom actions.
Within this function, we'll
create two custom actions, the
map action and the call action.
VoiceOver will describe these as
open address in maps and call,
but be sure to correctly
localize these strings.
Each of these actions will call
a corresponding function, which
activates that button.
So, for example, map action will
call activate map button, which
activates the map button.
I've conveniently defined this
function right here.
Be sure to return to [inaudible]
to indicate that your method was
successful.
And that's it for the shelter
view.
Last but not least, let's work
on improving the experience of
the modal view.
I've defined my modal view in
dog modal view, and as Skyler
suggested, to help VoiceOver
recognize this as a modal view,
I need to override accessibility
view as modal.
We're almost done.
One thing to remember is that
when I press the gallery button,
we need to let the app know that
the layout of the content on the
screen has changed so VoiceOver
can focus to the right content.
To do that, I can post a screen
change notification whenever the
gallery button gets pressed.
I'll head over to my view
controller file, and within my
gallery button press function,
once I animate in the modal
view, I'll post a screen change
notification like this.
And that's it.
I already have the app prebuilt
with all this new accessibility
work, so let's take a look at
what the new and improved
experience is like.
I'm going to turn on VoiceOver.
>> VoiceOver on.
Exceptional Dogs.
Dog picker.
Pinky.
Adjustable.
Swipe up or down with one finger
to adjust the value.
>> VoiceOver tells me I can
swipe up or down on this.
Let's go ahead and do that to
scroll through our carousel.
>> Layla.
>> And I'll scroll down, sorry,
swipe down.
>> Pinky.
>> I can also swipe from left to
right to get to the favorite and
gallery buttons like this.
>> Favorite, off, button, show
gallery, button.
>> Now, not only is every dog in
the carousel accessible to me
but so are the favorite and
gallery buttons from every dog
in the carousel.
I can swipe once more from left
to right to skip the carousel
and get to the stats view like
this.
>> Name, Pinky.
>> So I don't have to navigate
to the whole carousel.
This feels like a much better
experience now.
Let's go ahead and keep
navigating through our stats
view to see what the experience
is like.
I'm going to swipe from left to
right to navigate through it.
>> Breed, mixed.
Age, 7.0 years.
>> Since this information is
grouped together now, it
provides me with way more
context and navigation is faster
since I don't have to navigate
through each and every
individual label.
I'll place my finger over the
name of the shelter now.
>> Skyler's animal shelter.
Actions available.
>> VoiceOver informs me that
there's actions available on
this, so let's swipe up to hear
them.
>> Open address in maps.
Call.
>> Swiping up makes it clear to
me that these actions are in
reference to the name of the
shelter and will be performed on
them.
It gives me way more context.
Finally, I'll activate the modal
view by double tapping on the
gallery button.
>> Show gallery, button.
Picture one of Pinky.
Image.
>> I'll swipe from left-to-right
to navigate through it.
>> Picture two of, picture
three, close, close, close,
button.
>> Focus no longer goes behind
the modal view.
This is a much better experience
now.
>> VoiceOver off.
[ Applause ]
>> Well you just elevated the
accessibility experience of our
app from simply working to
exceptional.
We've achieved this by shaping
the experience around the user
and modelling the interaction
around this experience, and in
doing so, we've lifted a huge
cognitive burden off the user.
Your users will love this extra
bit of effort you put towards
the accessibility of the app so
they can love it as much as
anyone else.
I'd like to hand it back to
Skyler now.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Bhavya.
Hopefully Bhavya's demo
demonstrated for you how small
tweaks can transform the
accessibility experience for the
better.
It's important to note that
creating custom interfaces for
the accessibility of your app is
not always the right answer.
Sometimes the simple fix is the
best fix, but what you really
should be doing when making your
apps accessible is thinking
through beyond the surface level
what it will really mean for
someone who's using an assistive
technology to use your app.
To wrap this up, I'd like to
return to where we started
today.
Usable is a great first step for
making apps accessible, but we
can do better.
We can and we should provide our
users with exceptional,
delightful experiences that
cater to their unique needs.
There are a lot of ways to take
an accessible app from being
functional to being exceptional.
Designing for accessibility up
front can get you a lot of wins.
Doing things like making sure
your colors meet minimum
recommended contrast ratios or
that your layout can adequately
adapt to changing size have
benefits for all users.
But you should also extend you
default design to accommodate
the settings that users have
enabled.
Finally, when crafting the
accessibility experience for
assistive technologies, do so
purposefully.
Prioritize your content.
Make it easy and intuitive to
navigate and provide context
when necessary.
For more information as well as
access to a simplified finished
version of the sample app you
saw there, you can visit our
session link on the developer
portal.
As well, right after this
session we're going to be going
over to tech lab 9 for an
accessibility lab where you can
bring any questions you have
about making your apps
accessible or about elevating
the experience of your own app
in terms on accessibility.
So please come on by if you have
any questions.
Thank you and have a fantastic
rest of your WWDC.
[ Applause ]