[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Good morning.
My name is Josh Graessley, and I
am really excited to be here
this morning to tell you about
Network.framework.
Network.framework is a modern
alternative to sockets.
Today, we're going to talk about
modernization transport APIs.
This will help give you some
context to understand what
Network.framework is and how it
fits into the system and whether
or not it's the right thing for
your application to be using.
We'll introduce you to the API
by walking you through making
your first connections.
We'll talk about how you can use
this API to really optimize your
data transfers and go way beyond
the performance of anything you
can do with sockets.
We'll talk about how this API
can help you handle some complex
mobility challenges, and we'll
wrap up with information on how
you can get involved and start
adopting.
First, I'd like to spend a
little bit of time talking about
modernizing transport APIs.
Now when I say transport API,
I'm talking about any API that
lets you send and receive
arbitrary data between two
endpoints on a network, and
that's a pretty broad
definition, and there are a lot
of APIs that could fall under
this category.
Perhaps the most ubiquitous is
sockets.
Sockets has been within us for
over 30 years, and I don't think
it's an exaggeration to say that
sockets has changed the world,
but the world has kept changing.
And as a consequence, using
sockets to write apps for
today's internet is really hard.
There are three primary areas in
which it's very difficult to use
sockets well.
The first one is Connection
Establishment.
There's a whole host of reasons
that establishing connections
can be really difficult with
sockets.
For starters, sockets connect to
addresses, so you have to, most
of the time you have a host
name, so you're going to have to
resolve that host name to an
address.
When you do that, you often end
up with way more than one
address.
You'll have some IPv4 addresses,
some IPv6 addresses, and now
you've got this challenge, which
address should you try and
connect to, in what order?
How long do you wait before you
try the next one?
You can spend years trying to
perfect this.
I know because we have.
Once you get past the dual stack
host problems, you run into a
whole bunch of other issues.
There are some networks that use
something called Proxy Automatic
Configuration or PAC.
On these networks, there's a
JavaScript that you get, and you
have to pass a URL into the
JavaScript, and the JavaScript
runs and spits out an answer
that says either you can go
direct or you have to use this
SOCKS proxy over here or that
HTTP connect proxy over there.
And now your app has to support
SOCKS proxies and HTTP connect
proxies, and this can be really
difficult to do well.
And the most difficult thing is
that you may not have one of
these networks to test on, so
you may get a bug report from
one of your customers, and they
may complain that it's not
working well on their
environment.
And you may want to add code to
fix the problem, but that once
you've got it in there, you
really don't have a good way to
test it.
You have to end up building the
whole environment to reproduce
the same environment they have.
It can be a real challenge.
So connecting with sockets is
really hard.
The second thing that becomes
challenges with sockets is data
transfers.
There's a lot of reasons that
transferring data with sockets
can be really difficult.
The primary problem is the read
and write model itself.
If you're using blocking
sockets, it pretty simple, but
you're tying up a thread, and
it's really not a great idea to
be tying up a thread while
you're waiting to read or write
data.
You can switch to nonblocking,
but then you end up with a whole
lot of other challenges that you
run into.
When you're using nonblocking,
you may tell the kernel I'd like
100 bytes, and the kernel will
come back and say, I've got 10
bytes for you, why don't you
come back later.
And now you have to build a
state machine to keep track of
how many bytes you read versus
how many bytes you want to read.
This can be a lot of work, and
getting it to perform well can
be a real challenge.
On top of all of that, you
really shouldn't be reading and
writing to sockets directly
because you should be using
something like transport layer
security or TLS.
Sockets don't support TLS, so
you're probably using some other
library that is handling TLS for
you and reading and writing to
the sockets on your behalf, or
you're writing the glue code
between that library and
sockets, and you have to figure
out how to get all this to work
with all the crazy connection
logic that you put in ahead of
time.
There's a lot here that can be
really difficult.
Finally, mobility can be really
challenges with sockets for a
variety of reasons.
I think a lot of this boils down
to the fact that when sockets
came out, a lot of the devices
required more than a single
person to move them, and they
were connected with a single
wire, and they had a static IP
address, and everything was
stable and simple.
And today, we have these
incredibly powerful devices in
our pocket with multiple radios
that may be on at the same time,
and some of them are moving from
network to network, and your
application has to handle all
these transitions well to
provide a seamless experience to
your customers.
Sockets does nothing to help you
with this.
You can use routing sockets, but
it's really, really difficult.
We think a transport API should
do better.
Fortunately, on our platform as
an application developer you
have a great API in URLSession.
URLSession handles all of these
problems for you.
It's really focused on HTTP, but
it also has stream task that
gives you raw access to TCP and
TLS connections.
Now you might be looking at
this, and you may not have
cheated by looking at the
description in the WWDC app.
You might think that URLSession
is built on the same primitives
that you would use yourself.
But it turns out that's not the
case.
URLSession is built on top of
something we call
Network.framework.
URLSession really focuses on all
of the HTTP bits, and it
offloads a lot of the transport
functionality to
Network.framework.
Network.framework is something
we've been working on for a
number of years, and in
supporting URLSession, we've
learned a lot, and we've taken a
lot of those lessons to the
IETF.
A number of our engineers
regularly participate in the
IETF and meet with engineers
from other companies, and
they've been discussing a lot of
what we've learned in the
transport services working
group.
And in those discussions, we've
got some great feedback, and
we've brought that back in and
improved Network.framework based
on that.
We are really excited to
announce this year that your
applications can take advantage
of this same library directly
now.
[ Applause ]
Now we know that one of the
things people love about sockets
is that it gives them very
fine-grain control over just
about everything, and they're
really loathe to give that up.
So as we developed
Network.framework, we wanted to
make sure that it did the right
thing by default in the way that
sockets doesn't, but it gave you
all the knobs that sockets does.
And it's kind of got this
gradient, so the more knobs you
turn, the more complex it
becomes.
It gives you all the power you
need, but you don't have to pay
for the complexity unless you
actually need some of it.
Network.framework has incredibly
smart connection establishment.
It handles the dual stack cases.
It handles IPv6 only networks.
It handles PAC.
It handles proxies.
It will help you connect on
networks that are otherwise very
difficult to deal with.
It has an incredibly optimized
data transfer path that lets you
go way beyond the performance of
anything you can do with
sockets, and Tommy will cover
that in a little bit.
It has support for built-in
security.
It supports TLS and DTLS by
default.
It's really simple to use.
It has great support for
mobility.
It provides notifications about
network changes that are
relevant to the connections that
your application is
establishing.
It's available on iOS, macOS,
and tvOS as a CAPI with
automatic reference counting, so
it's easy to use from Objective
C, and it has an incredible
Swift API.
With that, I'd like to turn it
over to Tommy Pauly, to walk you
through making your first
connection.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> All right, hello everyone.
My name is Tommy Pauly, and I'm
on the networking team here at
Apple.
And so I'm sure a lot of you are
really excited to start seeing
how you can start adopting
Network.framework in your apps.
And the best place to start and
just dive right in is by making
your first connection.
And you're going to be making
your connection from your local
device, to your server, or to
some other peer device that's on
your local network.
But you may be wondering, what
kind of connections are
appropriate to use with
Network.framework.
What are the use cases?
And so let's explore first some
scenarios of apps that may be
using sockets today and would
really benefit a lot by taking
advantage of Network.framework
going forward.
So the first one of these I want
to highlight is gaming apps.
Gaming apps often use UDP to
send real-time data about the
game state between one device
and another.
And they really care about
optimizing for latency and
making sure there's no lag or
anything being dropped there.
If you have an app like this,
you're going to love how
Network.framework allows you to
really optimize your UDP,
sending and receiving to be
faster than ever before with the
least latency possible.
Another type of app that would
take a lot of advantage from
Network.framework is
live-streaming apps.
So live streaming often will use
a combination of UDP and TCP in
their apps, but the key point
here is that it's generating
data on the fly.
If you have new video frames or
audio frames, you need to make
sure that those are paced well
and you're not incurring a lot
of buffering on the device or on
the network.
The asynchronous model for
reading and writing in
Network.framework is going to be
perfect for making sure you
reduce that buffering.
And the last case I want to
highlight are mail and messaging
apps.
So these are going to be using a
lot more traditional protocols,
just TLS over TCP.
However, it's really critical
for apps like this to handle
network transitions really
gracefully.
Oftentimes if you have a
messaging app, your user is
going to be using your app as
they're walking out of the
building, texting their friend
to let them know that they're on
their way.
And you want to make sure that
you're handling that transition
from the WiFi network in the
building to the cell network
that they're going onto and that
you don't hand a long time for
that message to actually get to
their friend.
And these are just three
examples of the types of apps
that may use low-level
networking like this.
There are many other types of
apps that could take advantage
of this, so if you have an app
like one of these or some other
use case that currently uses
sockets, I invite you to follow
along and see how your app can
benefit.
So to get started, I want to
focus on that last case, the
simplest case of mail and
messaging apps and looking at
how they establish connections.
So when you want to establish
your connection to a server,
let's say it's for a mail
connection, iMap with security,
with TLS, you start with your
hostname, mail.example.com.
You have a port you want to
connect to, port 993, and you
want to be using TLS as well as
TCP.
So how would this look in
sockets traditionally?
Something like this to get
started.
You would take your host name.
You would call some DNS API to
resolve that host name.
Let's say this is getaddrinfo.
You'll get back one or more
addresses.
You'll have to decide which one
you want to connect to first.
You'll call socket with the
appropriate address family.
You will set a series of socket
options.
Let's say you want to make your
socket nonblocking like Josh
mentioned before.
Then you call connect to start
TCP, and then you wait for a
writable event.
And this is before you do
anything with TLS, and that's a
whole host of other problems.
So how does this look in
Network.framework?
And we hope that it looks very
familiar to you but a little bit
simpler.
So the first thing you do is you
create a connect a connection
object.
And a connection object is based
on two things.
You have an endpoint, which
defines the destination you want
to get to, and this could be the
address, the IP address that you
had before, but usually, like in
this example, we have a host
name and a port, and so our end
point can just be that host name
and port.
It could also be a bonjour
service that I want to connect
to.
And then I also have parameters.
Parameters define what protocols
I want to use, TLS, DTLS, UDP,
TCP.
It defines the protocol options
that I want as well as which
paths I want to use to connect
over.
Do I want to just connect over
anything, or do I only want to
use WiFi?
Once you've configured your
connection, you simply call
start to get things going, and
then you wait for the connection
to move into the ready state.
And that's all you need to do to
bring up a full TLS connection
to your server.
And I think you're going to love
how this looks in Swift.
So here's what you do.
You first import the network
module.
Then, you create an NWConnection
object.
So an NWConnection in either
Swift or in C is the fundamental
object for reading and writing
data.
In this case, we have a
convenience that initializes
your endpoint with a host in the
port, so I give it my hostname,
male.example.com, and the port.
And in this case, it's a
well-known port.
It's imaps.
So I can just put that in Swift
very easy, but I could also put
any other numeric literal there.
And then to define what
protocols I want to use, I pass
parameters, and since this is a
client connection, I only want
default, TLS, and TCP
parameters.
It can be as simple as just
writing dot TLS, and now I have
a fully-fledged TLS connection.
The next thing I do is I said
estate update handler to handle
all the transitions that my
connection might go through.
The first state and the most
important one that you want to
handle is the ready state.
Ready means that your app is
ready to read and write data on
this connection, it's totally
established, and if you're using
TCP and TLS, this means that the
TLS handshake is finished.
We also though let you know
about the waiting state.
So last year in URLSession, we
introduced waits for
connectivity, and the waiting
state of an NWConnection is
exactly the same thing.
And this is on always by
default.
So when you create your
connection and when you start
it, if there is no network
available, we won't fail, we'll
just tell you we're waiting for
a network to be available.
We'll give you a helpful reason
code, but you don't have to do
anything more to watch network
transitions yourself.
Mobility is an essential,
critical part of this API.
And we'll also let you know if
there's a fatal error.
Let's say we had to reset from
the server or TLS failed, and
we'll give you that as a failed
event.
So once you've set this up, you
simply call start and provide
the dispatch queue upon which
you want to receive callbacks.
So I want to dig into what
happens when you call start.
What's actually going on?
So here's a little state
machine, the innards of the
NWConnection.
When we begin at the setup state
and we call start, we move into
the preparing state.
So the preparing state does a
lot more than just calling
connect on a TCP socket.
For TCP socket, that would just
send out a SYN packet across to
the server that you're trying to
reach.
But when you call start on an
NWConnection, it actually
handles all of the things that
Josh was mentioning earlier.
It evaluates the network you're
on and tries to make the fastest
connection possible for you.
I want to dig into that a little
bit more.
So this is what we call Smart
Connection Establishment.
So the very first thing that we
do when you call start is that
we take your endpoint, and then
we evaluate what are all the
networks that are currently
available to me.
In this case, we have WiFi and
cellular.
And generally we prefer the WiFi
network because it has less cost
to the user.
So we'll look at that one first.
Then we check, are there any
special configurations on this
network.
Is there a VPN?
Is there a proxy?
And we'll evaluate that for you.
In this case, let's say that
there is a proxy configured with
an automatic configuration file
that also lets you go direct if
the proxy doesn't apply to your
connection.
So we'll evaluate both of those
options.
We'll check if we need to use
the proxy, go ahead and connect
to it, create a TCP connection
there.
But if we don't need it, we'll
do DNS on your behalf going
directly, get back all of the
DNS IP address answers, and
connect to them one after the
other, leaving them going in
parallel.
We're racing them to get you the
fastest connection possible.
And then, if something goes
wrong with WiFi, let's say the
WiFi radio quality goes really
bad because you're walking away
from the building, we can
actually take advantage of the
feature called WiFi assist and
fall back seamlessly to the
cellular network, do DNS
resolution there, and try the
connections one after the other.
So this way your connection
establishment is very resilient,
handles VPNs, handles proxies
for you, and gets you the best
connection possible.
Now, of course, you may not want
to try all of these options.
You may want to restrict what
the connection establishment
does, and so we have many
different knobs and controls to
let you do that, and I want to
highlight just three of them
today.
The first is you may not want to
use expensive networks, like a
cellular network, because this
connection is only appropriate
to use over WiFi.
So within the parameters for
your connection, there are
options to control the
interfaces that you use.
So if you don't want to use
cellular, simply add cellular to
the list of prohibited interface
types.
It's even better, actually to
also prohibit expensive networks
in general because this will
also block the usage of personal
hotspots on a Mac let's say.
Another way that you can
restrict your connection
establishment is by choosing
specifically the IP address
family that you want to use.
So let's say that you really
love IPv6 because it's faster
and it's the future.
You don't want to use IPv4 at
all on your connection.
And you can do this by going to
your parameters, digging down
into the IP-specific options,
and here you'll have options
that you'll find familiar from
your socket options on a socket
today, and you can also define
specifically which IP version
you want to use.
And this will impact your
connection as well as your DNS
resolution.
And lastly, you may not want to
use a proxy on your given
connection.
Maybe it's not appropriate for
your connection to go through a
SOCKS proxy.
In that case, you can simply
prohibit the use of proxies as
well.
So that's what happens in the
preparing state.
I mentioned before that things
can go wrong.
You can have no network when you
try to establish, and what we'll
do after going to preparing is
if we find there are no good
options, DNS failed, there was
no network, maybe you're in
airplane mode, we'll move into
the waiting state and let you
know the reason for that.
And we'll keep going back into
preparing every time the network
changes and the system thinks,
yeah, there's a good chance that
your connection will become
established now, and we'll
handle all that for you and let
you know every time that we're
reattempting.
Eventually, hopefully your
connection does get established.
At this point, we'll move into
the ready state.
And the ready state, as I
mentioned before, is when your
connection is fully established.
So this is all of the protocols
in your stack up to TLS, for
example.
At this point, you can read and
write, and this is also where we
give you callbacks about the
network transitions that you're
going through.
So if your connection is
established and then you change
networks, we'll give you updates
about that so you can handle the
mobility gracefully, and we'll
be talking about this later on
in the talk.
If there's an error on the
connection, either during the
connection establishment or
after you've already connected,
we'll give you the failed state
with an error, and then once
you're totally done with the
connection, let's say you
already closed it or you
received a close from the other
side, and you want to just
invalidate the connection, you
call cancel, and we move into
the cancelled state.
And this is guaranteed to be the
very last event that we will
deliver to your object so you
can clean up any memory that you
have associated and move on.
So that's it.
That's an overview of the basic
lifetime of a connection object
in Network.framework, and to
show you how you can use this to
build a simple app, I'd like to
invite Eric up to the stage.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks Tommy.
I'm Eric Kinnear, also from the
networking team here at Apple,
and I'm really excited to build
with you an example application
using Network.framework.
We're going to use the live
streaming example that Tommy
mentioned earlier to build an
application that can take the
camera input on one device and
send it over a network to be
displayed on another device.
Because we're going to be
continuously generating live
video frames, we're going to use
UDP to send those packets across
the network.
So how do we do this?
Well, first, we need a capture
session with the camera so that
we can receive the video frames
from the image sensor.
For the sake of this example,
we're not going to use any video
codecs or other compression.
We're simply going to take the
raw bytes from the camera, ship
them across the network, and
display them on the other side.
In order to make this happen, we
need to divvy those frames up
into smaller chunks that we can
send in UDP packets.
Of course, to send those UDP
packets on the network, we need
a connection.
Switching over to the other
device, we need a listener that
can receive that incoming
connection and read the data
packets off the network.
From there, we simply reverse
the earlier process,
reassembling the video frames
and sending them to the display
so that we can see them on the
screen.
To keep things simple, we've
already abstracted out the
camera and the display
functionalities so that we can
focus just on the parts that use
Network.framework.
There's one piece we haven't yet
covered here, and that's the
listener.
So we're going to take a minute
to do that now.
Listener functionality is
provided by the NWListener
class, which you can create
using the same parameters
objects that you used to
configure connections.
It's really easy to set up a
listener to advertise a bonjour
service.
In this case, we'll use
camera.udp.
When a new connection is
received by a listener, it will
pass that connection to a block
that you provide as the
newConnectionHandler.
This is your opportunity to
perform any configuration that
you choose on that connection,
and then you need to call start
to let that connection know that
it's time to get going.
Similarly, you need to call
start on your listener, and
again, just like with
connections, you provide a
dispatch queue where you want
these callbacks to be scheduled.
So that's listeners.
If you think about it, we just
implemented the equivalent of
calling listen on a UDP socket.
Except listen doesn't actually
work on UDP sockets.
Now we're ready to build our app
in Xcode.
So here we've got our
application, and we've got a
bunch of files over here that
already handle the camera and
the display functionality, so
we're going to focus just on the
UDPClient class and the
UDPServer class.
The UDPClient is going to be
responsible for creating the
connection to the other side and
sending the frames across.
Likewise, the server is
responsible for creating the
listener, accepting incoming
connections, reading the data
off those connections, and
sending them up to the screen.
Let's start with the client.
My client class has an
initializer that takes a name,
which is a string describing the
bonjour name that we want to
connect to.
I'll create my connection by
simply calling NWConnection and
passing in a service endpoint.
Using the name that I was
provided and camera.udp as the
type.
We also passed the default UDP
parameters.
As Tommy mentioned, we can use a
state update handler to check
for the ready and the failed
states.
Here, when our connection is
ready, we'll call
sendInitialFrame, which we'll
implement in a minute.
Because we're using UDP and
there's no other handshake,
we're going to take some data
and send it across to the
network to the other device and
wait for it to be echoed back
before we start generating lots
of video frames and dumping them
on the network.
We need to remember to call
start on our connection, and we
provide the queue that we
created up above.
Let's implement send initial
frame.
Here we're going to take the
literal bytes hello and create a
data object using them.
To send content on a connection,
we can call connection.send and
provide that data object as the
content.
We provide a completion handler
in which we can check for any
errors that may have been
encountered while sending.
Since we expect this content to
be immediately echoed back, we
turn right around and call
connection.receive to read the
incoming data off of the
connection.
In that completion handler, we
validate that the content is
present, and if so, we let the
rest of the application know
that we're connected, and it
should bring up the camera
hardware and start generating
frames.
When those frames are generated,
the rest of the application
knows to call send on our
UDPClient class and pass it an
array of data objects
representing the video frames
that we're trying to send.
Because we're going to be doing
a lot of send operations in very
quick succession, we're going to
do them within a block that we
passed in connection.batch.
Within this block we're going to
go through every frame in that
array of data objects and pass
each one to connection.send.
Similarly to above, we use the
completion handler to check for
any errors that were encountered
while sending.
And that's it.
We've got our UDPClient class,
and we're ready to go.
Let's look at the server.
On the server side, we need a
listener that can accept the
incoming connections.
We need to respond to that
handshake that we just sent from
the client, and we need to read
data off the network so that we
can push it up to the display.
Starting with the listener, we
simply create an NWListener
using the default UDP
parameters.
If I wanted to, this is also my
opportunity to use those
parameters to tell the listener
to listen on a specific local
port.
But since we're using a bonjour
service, we don't need to do
that.
To set up that service, I'm
going to set the service
property on the listener to a
service object of type
camera.udp.
Notice that I don't pass the
name here because I want the
system to provide the default
device name for me.
I also provide a block to the
serviceRegistration
UpdateHandler, which is going to
be called anytime the set of
endpoints advertised by the
system changes.
Here, I'm interested in the case
where an endpoint is added, and
if it's of service type, I tell
the rest of the application the
name that is being advertised,
that default device name that I
ask the system to provide so
that I can display it in the UI
and have my users type it in
somewhere else.
I'm going to set a new
connection handler on the
listener, which will be called
every time the listener receives
a new incoming connection.
I could do some configuration on
these connections, but the
default settings are fine here,
so I simply call
connection.start and pass it to
queue.
Here, I notify the rest of the
application that I've received
an incoming connection, so it
can start warming up the display
pipeline and become ready to
display the video frames.
I'll also call receive on
myself, which we'll implement in
a minute, to start reading that
data off of the network and
shipping it up to the display
pipeline.
Just like with connections,
listeners have state update
handlers, which I'll use to
check for the ready and the
failed states.
I need to not forget to start my
listener, which I do by calling
listener.start and passing it
that queue we created up above.
So I've got my listener ready, I
just need to read data off the
network and implement this
receive function.
Here, we start by calling
connection.receive and passing
it into completion handler.
When data comes in off of that
connection, we'll see if we're
not yet connected.
If we weren't connected, this is
probably that handshake that the
client is starting by sending.
We'll simply turn right around
and call connection.send,
passing that same content back
so it will be echoed over to the
client.
We then remember that we're
connected, and on all subsequent
received callbacks, we will
simply tell the rest of the
application that we received
this frame, and it should send
it up to the display pipeline so
that we can see it on the
screen.
Finally, if there were no
errors, we call receive again so
that we receive subsequent
frames and send them up to the
display to book together a video
from each of these individual
images.
So that's it.
We've got our UDPClient, we've
got our UDPServer, let's try it
out.
I'm going to run the client on
my phone here, and I'm going to
run the server on my Mac so we
can see it on the big screen.
Here, the server just came up,
and we see that it's advertising
as Demo Mac, which is where I
told the rest of the system to
just give me the name.
That's on my phone.
If I tap connect, all of a
sudden, I can see video frames
being streamed across the
network over UDP Live.
[ Applause ]
So here we just saw how quickly
I was able to bring up a
UDPClient that could connect to
a bonjour service, it can send a
handshake, wait for that to be
processed, take the video frames
coming from the camera, and ship
them across the network.
The server side brought up a
bonjour listener.
It advertised a service, it
received incoming connections,
responded to the handshake, and
sent them all to the display so
that we could see them.
And now to take you through
optimizing that data transfer in
a little more detail, I'd like
to invite Tommy back up to the
stage.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Eric.
It was a really cool demo.
It's super easy to get this
going, and so now we've covered
the basics, and we know how to
establish connections outbound,
how to receive connections
inbound, but the real key part
of Network.framework that's
going to be the killer feature
here is the way that it can
optimize your performance and
that we can go beyond what
sockets was able to do.
And I want to start with the way
that you in your application
interact with your networking
connections in the most basic
way, which is just sending and
receiving data.
And these calls are very simple,
but the nuances about how you
handle sending and receiving and
really make a huge difference
for the responsiveness of your
app and how much buffering there
is going on on the device and
the network.
So the first example I want to
walk through is when we're
sending data, in the application
very much like what Eric just
showed you, something that's
live streaming, something that
is generating data on the fly.
But in this case, let's talk
about when we're sending it over
a TCP stream, a TCP stream that
can back up on the network, that
has a certain window that it can
send.
So how do we handle this?
So here's a function to send a
single frame.
This is some frame of data that
your application has generated.
And the way that you send it on
the connection is you simply
call connection.send and pass
that data.
Now if you're used to using
sockets to send on your
connections, you either are
using a blocking socket, in
which case if you have a hundred
bytes of data to send, if
there's not room in the send
buffer, it'll actually block up
your thread and wait for the
network connection to drain out,
or if you're using a nonblocking
socket, that send may actually
not send your complete data.
It'll say, oh, I only sent 50
bytes of it.
Come back some other time to
send the next 50 bytes.
This requires you and your
application to handle a lot of
state about how much you have
actually done of sending your
data.
So the great thing about a
network connection is you can
simply send all of your data at
once, and you don't have to
worry about this, and it doesn't
block anything.
But then, of course, you have to
handle what happens if the
connection is backing up,
because we don't want to just
send a ton of data unnecessarily
into this connection if you want
a really responsive, live stream
of data.
And the key here is that
callback block that we give you.
It's called contentProcessed.
And we'll invoke it whenever the
network stack consumes your
data.
So this doesn't mean that the
data has necessarily been sent
out or acknowledged by the other
side.
It's exactly equivalent to the
time in which a blocking socket
call would return to you, or
when the nonblocking socket call
was able to consume all of the
bytes that you sent.
And in this completion handler,
there are two things you can
check for.
First, you can check for an
error.
If there is an error, that means
something went wrong while we
were trying to send your data,
generally it indicates a overall
connection failure.
Then, if there wasn't and error,
this is the perfect opportunity
to go and see if there's more
data from your application to
generate.
So if you're generating live
data frames, go and fetch
another frame from the video
stream, because now is the time
when you can actually enqueue
the next packets.
This allows you to pace all of
your data out.
And so as you see here, we
essentially form a loop of using
this asynchronous send callback
to continue to drain data out of
our connection and handle it
really elegantly.
The other thing I want to point
out about sending is the trick
that Eric showed earlier that's
great for UDP applications that
are sending multiple datagrams
all at one time.
So if you have a whole bunch of
little tiny pieces of data that
you need to send out or
essentially individual packets,
you can use something that we've
added called connection.batch.
So a UDP socket previously could
only send one packet at a time,
and this could be very
inefficient because if I have to
send a hundred UDP packets,
these are each a different
system call, a different copy,
and a context switch down into
the kernel.
But if you call batch within
that block, you can call send or
actually receive as many times
as you want, and the connection
will hold off processing any of
the data until you finish the
batch block and will try to send
all of those datagrams all as
one single batch down into the
system, ideally have just one
context switch down into the
kernel, and send out the
interface.
This allows you to be very, very
efficient.
So that's sending.
Receiving, like sending, is
asynchronous, and the
asynchronous nature gives you
the back pressure that allows
you to pace your app.
So in this case, I have a
TCP-based protocol, and it's
very common for apps when
they're reading to essentially
want to be reading some type of
record format.
Let's say that your protocol has
a header of 10 bytes that tells
you some information about what
you're about to receive, maybe
the length of the body that
you're about to receive.
And so you want to read that
header first and then read the
rest of your content, and maybe
your content's quite long.
It's a couple megabytes let's
say.
Traditionally with a socket, you
may try to read 10 bytes.
You may get 10 bytes, you may
get less.
You have to keep reading until
you get exactly 10 bytes to read
your header.
And then you have to read a
couple megabytes, and you'll
read some, and you'll get a
whole bunch of different read
calls and essentially go back
and forth between your app and
the stack.
With an NWConnection, when you
call receive, you provide the
minimum data that you want to
receive and the maximum data.
So you could actually specify if
you want to receive exactly 10
bytes because that's your
protocol, you can just say, I
want a minimum of 10 and a
maximum of 10.
Give me exactly 10 bytes.
And we will only call you back
when either there was an error
in reading on the connection
overall or we read exactly those
10 bytes.
Then you can easily just read
out whatever content you need
for your header, read out the
length, and then let's say you
want to read a couple megabytes,
and you essentially do the same
thing to read your body, and you
just pass, well I want to read
exactly this amount for my
connection, and this allows you
to not go back and forth between
the stack and your app but just
have a single callback of when
all of your data is ready to go.
So it's a really great way to
optimize the interactions.
Beyond sending and receiving,
there are a couple of advanced
options that I'd like to
highlight in your network
parameters that allow you to
configure your connection to get
very good startup time as well
as behavior on the network when
you're actually sending and
receiving.
So the first one is one that
we've talked about many times
here at WWDC, which is ECN.
This is explicit congestion
notification.
It gives you a way to smooth out
your connection by having the
network let the end host know
when there's congestion on the
network so we can pace things
out very well.
The great thing is that ECN is
enabled by default on all of
your TCP connections.
You don't have to do anything.
But it's been very difficult in
the past to use ECN with
UDP-based protocols.
And so I'd like to show you how
you can do that here.
The first thing you do is that
you create an ipMetadata object.
ECN is controlled by flags that
go in an IP packet, and so you
have this ipMmetadata object
that allows you to set various
flags on a per-packet basis, and
you can wrap this up into a
context object, which describes
all of the options for the
various protocols that you want
to associate with a single send
as well as the relative priority
of that particular message.
And then you use this context as
an extra parameter into the send
call besides just your content.
So now when you send this, any
packet that's going to be
generated by this content will
have all the flags that you
wanted marked.
So it's really easy.
And you can also get these same
flags whenever you're receiving
on a connection.
You'll have the same context
object associated with your
receives, and you'll be able to
read out the specific low-level
flags that you want to get out.
Similar, we have service class.
This is a property that is
available also in URLSession
that defines the relative
priority of your traffic, and
this affects the way that
traffic is queued on the local
interfaces when we're sending as
well as how the traffic works on
Cisco Fastlane networks.
So you can mark your service
class as a property on your
entire connection by using the
service class parameter in your
parameter's object.
In this case, we show how to use
the background service class,
and this is a great way to mark
that your connection is
relatively low priority.
We don't want it to get in the
way of user interactive data.
So we really encourage you if
you have background transfers,
mark them as a background
service class.
But you can also mark service
class on a per packet basis for
those UDP connections.
Let's say that you have a
connection in which you have
both voice and signaling data on
the same UDP flow.
In this case, you can create
that same IP metadata object
that we introduced before, mark
your service class now instead
of the ECN flags, attach it to a
context, and send it out.
And now you're marking the
priority on a per-packet basis.
The other way that you can
optimize your connections is to
reduce the number of round trips
that it takes to establish them.
So here I want to highlight two
approaches to do this.
One is enabling fast open on
your connections.
So TCP fast open allows you to
send initial data in the first
packet that TCP sends out, in
the SYN, so that you don't have
to wait for a whole handshake to
start sending your application
data.
Now in order to do this, you
need to enter into a contract
from your application with the
connection saying that you will
be providing this initial data
to send out.
So to enable this, you mark
allow fast open on your
parameters.
You then create your connection,
and then before you can call
start, you can actually call
send and get your initial data
sent out.
Now I want to point out here
that the completion handler here
is replaced by a marker that
this data is item potent, and
item potent means that the data
is safe to be replayed because
initial data may get resent over
the network, and so you don't
want it to have side effects if
it gets resent.
Then, you simply call start, and
as we're doing the connection
bring up, all the attempts that
we mentioned before, we will use
that initial data if we can to
send in TCP Fast Open.
There is one other way I want to
point out to use TCP Fast Open
that doesn't require your
application to send it's own
data.
If you're using TLS on top of
TCP, the first message from TLS,
the client hello, can actually
be used as the TCP Fast Open
initial data.
If you want to just enable this
and not provide your own Fast
Open data, simply go into the
TCP-specific options and mark
that you want to enable Fast
Open there, and it will
automatically grab the first
message from TLS to send out
during connection establishment.
There's another thing that you
can do to optimize your
connection establishment and
save a roundtrip, and this is
something that Stuart mentioned
in the previous session, which
we're calling Optimistic DNS.
This allows you to use
previously expired DNS answers
that may have had a very short
time to live, and try connecting
to them while we do a new DNS
query in parallel.
So if the addresses that you had
previously received that did
expire are still valid, and you
mark the expired DNS behavior to
be allow.
When you call start, we'll try
connecting to those addresses
first and not have to wait for
the new DNS query to finish.
This can shave off a lot of
set-up time from your
connection, but if your server
has indeed moved addresses,
because we're trying multiple
different connection options, if
that first one doesn't work, we
will gracefully wait for the new
DNS query to come back and try
those addresses as well.
So this is a very simple way
that if it's appropriate for
your server configuration, you
can get a much faster connection
establishment.
The next area I want to talk
about for performance is
something that you don't
actually need to do anything in
your app to get.
This is something that you get
totally for free whenever you
use URLSession or
Network.framework connections,
and this is user-space
networking.
So this is something that we
introduced last year here at
WWDC, and it's enabled on iOS
and tvOS.
This is where we're avoiding the
socket layer entirely, and we've
moved the transport stack into
your app.
So to give you an idea of what
this is doing, I want to start
with what the legacy model of
the stack generally is.
So let's say that you're
receiving a packet off the
network.
It's the WiFi interface.
That packet will come into the
driver, will be sent into the
TCP receive buffer within the
kernel, and then when your
application reads on a socket,
that's going to do a context
switch and copy the data up from
the kernel into your app, and
then generally if you're doing
TLS, it will have to get another
transformation to decrypt that
data before you can actually
send it up to the application.
So how does this look when we do
user space networking?
So as you can see, the main
change is that we've moved the
transport stack, TCP and UDP, up
into your app.
So what does this give us?
Now, when a packet comes in off
the network, comes into the
driver like before, but we move
it into a memory mapped region
that your application
automatically can scoop packets
out of without doing a copy,
without doing extra contexts
switch, and start processing the
packets automatically.
This way the only transformation
we're doing is the decryption
that we have to do anyway for
TLS.
This really can reduce the
amount of CPU time that it takes
to send and receive packets,
especially for protocols like
UDP in which you're going to be
sending a lot of packets back
and forth directly from your
application.
So to show how this works and
the effect it can have, I want
to show you a video that was
taken using the same app that
Eric showed you earlier to
demonstrate UDP performance with
user space networking.
So in this example, we're going
to have two videos running
simultaneously.
The device on the left is
receiving a video stream from an
application that was written
using sockets.
And the device on the right is
going to be receiving exactly
the same video stream from a
device that has an app written
using Network.framework so it
can take advantage of the user
space networking stack.
And in this case, we're
streaming the video.
It's just raw frames.
It's not compressed.
It's not great quality or
anything, but there's a lot of
packets going back and forth.
And we chose specifically for
this demonstration to not lower
the quality when we hit
contention or when we couldn't
send packets fast enough or to
not drop anything but just to
slow down if we had to.
Now this is probably not what
your app would do in real life,
but it highlights exactly the
difference in the performance
between these two stacks.
So let's see it right now.
So there's exactly the same
data, exactly the same frames
being sent over as fast as they
possibly can, across this
network, and we see the one on
the right is pretty easily
outstripping the one on the
left.
And in fact, if you look at the
difference, it's 30 percent less
overhead that we're viewing on
the receiver side only.
And this is due to the huge
difference that we see in the
CPU percentage that it takes to
send and receive UDP packets
when you compare sockets and
user space networking.
Now, of course this is just one
example.
This is not going to be what
every app is going to be like,
because you're going to be
compressing differently.
You're going to be already
trying to make your connections
more efficient.
But if you have an app that's
generating live data, especially
if you're using UDP to send and
receive a lot of packets, I
invite you to try using
Network.framework within your
app and run it through
instruments.
Measure the difference in CPU
usage that you have when you're
using Network.framework versus
sockets, and I think you'll be
really happy with what you see.
So the last topic we want to
talk about today is how we can
solve the problems around
network mobility, and this is a
key area that we're trying to
solve with Network.framework.
And the first step of this is
just making sure that we start
connections gracefully.
So we already mentioned this,
but I want to recap a little
bit.
The waiting state is the key
thing to handle network
transitions when your connection
is first coming up.
It will indicate that there's a
lack of connectivity or the
connectivity changed while you
were in the middle of doing DNS
or TCP.
We really encourage you please
avoid using APIs like
reachability to check the
network state before you
establish your connection.
That will lead to race
conditions and may not provide
an accurate picture of what's
actually happening in the
connection.
And if you need to make sure
that your connection does not
establish over a cellular
network, don't check up front is
the device currently on a
cellular network, because that
could change.
Simply restrict the interface
types that you want to use using
the NWParameters.
So once you've started your
connection and you're in the
ready state, there are a series
of events that we will give you
to let you know when the network
has changed.
The first one is called
connection viability.
So viability means that your
connection is able to send and
receive data out the interface
it has a valid route.
So to give a demonstration of
this, let's say that you started
your connection when the device
was associated with a WiFi
network.
Then, your user walks into the
elevator, they don't have a
signal anymore.
At this point, we will give you
an event, letting you know that
your connection is no longer
viable.
So what should you do at this
point?
Two things.
We recommend that if it's
appropriate for your app, you
can let the user know that they
currently have no connectivity.
If they're trying to send and
receive data, it's not going to
work right now.
But, don't necessarily tear down
your connection.
At this point, you don't have
any better interface that you
could use anyway, and that first
WiFi interface may come back.
Oftentimes, if you walk back out
of an elevator onto the same
WiFi network, your connection
can resume right where you left
off.
So the other event that we give
you is the better path
notification.
So let's take that same scenario
in which you connected over the
WiFi network.
You walk out of a building let's
say, and now you no longer have
WiFi, but you do have the
cellular network available to
you.
At this point, we'll let you
know two things.
First, that your connection is
not viable like before, but
we'll also let you know that
there is now a better path
available.
If you connected again, you
would be able to use the
cellular network.
And the advice here is to, if
it's appropriate for your
connection, attempt to migrate
to a new connection, if you can
resume the work that you were
doing before.
But only close the original
connection once that new
connection is fully ready.
Again, the WiFi network may come
back, or the connection over
cellular may fail.
And the last case I want to
highlight here is a case in
which you connect initially over
the cellular network, and then
the user walks into a building
and now they have WiFi access.
In this case, your connection,
the original one, is totally
fine.
You're still viable, but you now
also have a better path
available.
In this case, again, if you can
migrate your connection, this is
probably a good time to try to
establish a new connection and
move your data over.
That will save the user their
data bill.
But, continue to use the
original connection until you
have the new one fully
established.
Just to show how this looks in
code, we have the viability
update handler that you can set
in your connection, we'll give
you a boolean back to let you
know whenever you're viable or
not, and a better path update
handler to let you know when
there's a better path available
or is no longer available.
And now the better solution to
all of this to handle network
mobility is something that we've
talked about in previous years,
which is multipath connections,
Multipath TCP.
So if you were able to on your
server enable Multipath TCP and
you can enable it on the client
side with the
multipathServiceType in your
parameters, then your connection
will automatically migrate
between networks as they come
and go.
It's a great seamless experience
that doesn't require any work in
your application to handle.
And this is also the same
service type that's available in
URLSession.
A couple points I want to
highlight here, specific to
Network.framework.
If you restrict the interface
types that you allow to be used
with your NWParameters that will
apply to MPTCP, so you can still
not want to use the cellular
network with a multipath
connection, and instead we'll
just seamlessly migrate between
different WiFi networks as they
become available.
Also, the connection viability
handler that I mentioned before
is slightly different from
Multipath TCP because whenever
we change a network, we'll
automatically move for you, your
connection is only not viable
when you have no network
available to you at all.
So between waiting for
connectivity, viability, better
path, MPTCP, we really hope that
all of the use cases in your
apps for using tools like SC
Network Reachability to check
network changes manually have
been replaced.
However, we do recognize that
there are some scenarios in
which you still want to know
what's the available network,
when does it change.
For that Network.framework
offers a new API called the
NWPathMonitor.
So the Path Monitor instead of
watching the reachability and
trying to predict the
reachability of a given host
simply lets you know what is the
current state of the interfaces
on your device and when do they
change.
It allows you to iterate all of
the interfaces that you can
connect over in case you want to
make a connection over each one,
and it will let you know
whenever those networks do
change.
So this can be very useful if
you want to update your UI to
let the user know, are they
connected at all.
And as Stuart mentioned in the
previous session, there could be
scenarios in which the user has
a long form to fill out and they
don't necessarily want to go and
fill out something just to
realize that there's no
connectivity anyway.
So use Network Path Monitor in
any of these scenarios in which
just having a waiting connection
is not enough.
So between all of these things,
we'd really like to see people
move off of reachability and
handle network transitions more
gracefully than ever before.
So with that, I'd like to invite
Josh back up to the state to let
you know how you can get
involved and start adopting
Network.framework.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Tommy.
So I've got a great new API for
you that we think you're going
to love.
We'd like to talk about the
things that you can do to start
using it today, but first I want
to talk about a few things that
we'd like you to stop doing so
we can really take advantage of
the new technologies like user
space networking.
If you're on macOS, and you have
a Network Kernel Extension, and
there's something you're doing
in that Network Kernel Extension
that you can't do any other way,
please get in touch with us
right away.
We need to provide you a better
alternative because Network
Kernel Extensions are not
compatible with User Space
Networking.
We wanted to give you a heads-up
that with URLSession, FTP and
file URLs are no longer going to
be supported for Proxy Automatic
Configuration.
Going forward, the only
supported URL schemes will be
HTTP and HTTPS.
There are a number of APIs at
the CoreFoundation layer that we
would like you to stop using.
They will be deprecated
eventually.
They are not yet marked as
deprecated.
These are
CFStreamCreatePairWith, anything
related to sockets as well as
CFSocket.
These cannot take advantage of a
lot of the connection
establishment that we've put in
there with the new
Network.framework, and they
can't take advantage of the new
User Space Networking.
So we really want you to move
off of these to take advantage
of the incredibly robust
connectivity improvements that
you'll get with
Network.framework and URLSession
and the improved performance.
There are some foundation APIs
as well that we'd like you to
move away from.
If you're using any of these
NSStream, NSNetService, or
NSSocket for APIs, please move
to Network.framework or
URLSession.
Finally, if you're using
SCNetworkReachability, we feel
that the Wait for Connectivity
model is a much better model, so
we'd really like you to move to
that.
And for those few cases where
Wait for Connectivity isn't the
right answer, NWPathMonitor is a
much better solution going
forward.
So now that we've talked about
some things we'd like you to
stop doing, I want to focus on
the things we really want to see
you do.
Going forward, the preferred
APIs on our platforms for
networking are URLSession and
Network.framework.
URLSession is really focused on
HTTP, but Stream Task provides
pretty simple access to TCP and
TLS connections.
If you need something more
advanced, Network.framework
gives you great support for TCP,
TLS, UDP, DTLS.
It handles listening for inbound
connections as well as outbound
connections, and we've got Path
Monitor to handle some of the
mobility stuff.
Next steps, we really want to
see you adopt these, adopt
Network.framework and
URLSession.
Your customers are going to
appreciate how much better your
connections, how much more
reliable your connections are
established, and they'll
appreciate the longer battery
life from the better
performance.
While you're working on these,
focus on how you're handling
your sending and receiving to
really optimize that
performance.
And take a lot of time to get
that support for the viability
and better route changes in
there.
It can make all the difference
for providing a seamless
networking experience.
Now we know that
Network.framework doesn't
support UDP Multicast yet, so if
you're doing UDP Multicast, we'd
really like to understand your
use cases so we can take those
into account going forward.
In addition, if you have any
other questions or enhancement
requests, we'd love to hear from
you.
Contact developer support or
better yet, meet us in one of
the labs.
We have a lab after lunch at 2
p.m. and another one tomorrow
morning at 9 a.m. For more
information, see this URL.
Don't forget the labs tomorrow
morning and after lunch.
Thank you so much and have a
great WWDC.
[ Applause ]