[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> So hello everyone.
My name is Doug LeMoine.
My background is in interaction
design.
And here at Apple I'm on a team
of people who works with
developers like you.
As a designer I focus on user
interfaces and the ideas to
deliver great user experiences
to the people who use your apps.
Today I'm here to talk about
intent.
I think there's a thread running
through great apps and really
great products.
And it has to do with a
conscious focus on people, on
humans, and what they want and
what they really need.
So I'm going to talk about
focusing on the person you want
to serve.
And I'm going to focus on being
intentional.
The intent that I'm interested
in talking about today is less
about a specific design vision
or a specific outcome and more
on a mindset.
How to keep a sharp focus on
those people that you're trying
to reach and create apps that
feel simple.
And when an app feels simple
users perceive it as natural, an
extension of what they know.
It feels like it arises from
their experience and it flows
naturally from what they expect.
So I know simple and natural are
sort of designer cliches, we say
this stuff all the time.
Like, what do we mean?
I think these terms are
shorthand for discussing
qualities of apps that create
feelings of comfort and
confidence.
When people feel comfortable and
confident, when we understand
how a thing works, we can move
through it seamlessly without
needed to learn or figure it
out.
So intent is the kind of thing
is hard to define but you know
it when you see it.
So I'm going to show you some
examples of apps that I found in
the last year that really
deliver real value to people and
really connect with them.
And I'm going to talk about five
elements of intentional design
that we can learn from these
apps and that you can apply to
your work.
So let's dive in.
So before mobile devices came
around when you traveled abroad
you'd carry a paper map.
And the advantage of the paper
map is that when you would
approach a local they would
instantly recognize what kind of
help you needed.
So mobile maps have made people
more independent, right?
We probably approach fewer
locals when we're traveling
abroad.
But in the same way that a paper
map invites an interaction,
there's an app called iTranslate
Converse that makes it easy to
approach a local with your
iPhone in your hand to ask a
question or get directions.
Some of you may have seen this
on Monday night at the Apple
Design Awards.
I'm going to go through a demo
to really bring out what I think
is really intentional about this
app.
So first of all there's very
little UI.
The screen is essentially one
big button.
I tap and hold and start
talking.
So I'll show you that in a
second.
And to be clear the goal of
iTranslate Converse is to make
conversation easy.
The developers have intended
this app to be used together.
So two people together, one of
whom most likely has never used
this app before, probably never
even seen it.
So I launched this app really
for real in in the Naples train
station when I was trying to get
on an express train to Rome and
the platforms were really
confusing.
So I pulled out my phone, I
launched the app, and I walked
up to a conductor.
So I said is this the express
train to Rome?
[Computerized Speaking Italian]
>> The app translated it into
Italian and the conductor heard.
Then I could flip the phone
around and again, what I find
interesting in this situation
that other person has probably
never seen this app before.
And they speak in a language
that I didn't speak but the app
is smart enough to know that
it's ether going to English or
Italian to listen for.
So the conductor spoke into the
microphone.
>> Platform Nine.
>> And the app translates it for
me.
So in reality he spoke English.
[ Laughter ]
[ Applause ]
But he did want to see how the
app worked and I showed him and
he was impressed.
I think the real beauty of this
is that you can make a
connection with a person, right?
You can get on the right train
like I did, but you also make a
human connection in the process.
So the developer's intent here
is to enable communication
between two people in real time.
Just touch the screen and talk.
So the first element of
intentional design is what I'm
going to call radical
simplification.
So how did they do this?
Well, I think they considered
the context really well, the
context that this will be used
in.
They took into account where and
when people would pull out their
phone and launch their app.
You're probably in a foreign
country, like this guy you're
jetlagged, lost, tired, your
hair is uncombed, your jacket is
rumpled.
I'm not even sure if that's a
map that he's carrying at this
moment, it kind of looks like a
book.
So they remove the UI and allow
people to focus on what they
need, which is to find
something, to ask a question, to
get their bearings.
And it's amazing how much an
experience can change when
actions are removed from the UI.
So I want to show you another
example.
This is an app called Vanido.
It helps you learn how to sing.
So if you're the kind of person
who wants to learn how to sing
with literally no one hearing
your or judging you, this app is
amazing.
This is the UI.
It's so simple.
The app tracks the pitch of my
voice while I'm singing and it's
continually giving me feedback.
Am I hitting my notes or not?
So let me show you.
[ Laughter ]
I'm actually not going to do a
live demo.
[ Laughter ]
But I am going to sing along
[harmonica note]
because I've been practicing and
I want you to see how it works.
[ Music ]
[ Cheering ]
You can leave feedback in my
session.
[ Laughter ]
So what I love about Vanido is
that it has stripped away what
music education looks like,
right?
There's no charts or notes.
It's colorful, it's animated,
and it's fun.
And you should have heard me
sing before I started using this
app.
It really works.
And there's only one interactive
element on the screen when
you're singing and it's way up
at the top left.
So you can hold your phone like
a microphone and really belt it
out without worrying about
accidentally exiting your
lesson.
So this is radical
simplification and that's what I
mean, that's the first
manifestation of intent and
intentional design.
Being radical means taking
risks, right?
Removing a bunch of stuff from
the UI could be jarring if you
don't do it right.
But I think there's a way to
reduce your risk.
So next I want to talk about
people and about orienting your
design around what people really
want.
So what do they want?
I think this is worth exploring
because it's almost never
obvious.
The first needs that you see
when you start kind of looking
at people and the users that you
might want to serve are
superficial and you need to dig
past those.
They might be the first ones
that you think about addressing
or they might be the ones that
pulled you into the problem in
the first place, but you need to
keep digging because those
superficial needs often mask
deeper needs, right, you could
solve them but not really solve
the persons' problem.
So you have to keep digging.
The second element of
intentional design that I want
to get into here is called deep
understanding.
So knowing the person that you
want to reach and the actually
problem that they have.
The deeper you dig the more
likely you are to see where the
real opportunity to meet their
needs is.
And the app that really shows
this off, in my opinion, is
called Streaks Workout.
So it's a workout app but I want
to go behind the scenes a little
bit.
On the surface it looks like
many workout apps.
It guides your workouts.
This is the primary screen and
it looks pretty simple.
You pick a workout duration and
you go.
But personally, I'll confess
that I don't love working out
and I've tried many workout apps
that I just don't stick with and
I want to thank any developers
that are here who have developed
workout apps that I've tried
because I respect your effort
and I'm really trying to get fit
so thank you for that.
But what I struggle with is
staying motivated.
It's easy to get bored or burnt
out and this isn't an unknown
problem, right?
Many people feel this sense of
inertia when facing something
challenging like a workout.
So inertia, just to be clear, is
a disinclination to move.
And that's what I feel.
I feel a sense of disinclination
when I think about working out.
So I want to walk you through
how Streaks Workout helps users
handle this.
So when you first launch the app
you select movements that you
want to do, these exercise
movements on a screen like this.
And there's dozens of these
things.
You can scroll down and pick as
many as you want.
After that when you want to
start a workout there's just one
tap.
You just pick a duration and you
go.
And the app does the rest.
It auto selects from your
movements and it picks a
sequence and then you're in the
workout.
[ Heartbeats ]
You guys psyched up?
So let's fast forward a bit.
Now I'm doing ten seconds of
crunches.
>> Crunches ten seconds.
>> I'm actually not going to do
the crunches.
But as you can see I can't see
what's next, right?
The question mark means it's
random.
It's a surprise.
>> Burpees ten seconds.
>> Yeah, I'm not going to do
those either.
Specifically, what I think works
well is that the app confronts
the inertia that people might
feel by introducing a sense of
randomness and removing work.
So the developers recognize that
each step in the process of
doing a workout requires a
choice, requires someone to
think about what they want and
these decisions are not things
that everyone wants to make.
So you only choose movements
once.
After that the app does it for
you.
And you never choose the
sequence or the reps so half of
the work, half of the potential
inertia is gone.
You could say that Streaks
workout -- it takes the work out
--
[ Laughter ]
Of workouts!
[ Applause ]
Really bad.
They've taken half of the work
out anyway.
So this launch sequence reveals
the movements that you'll do and
it helps each workout feel new.
Of course there are probably
many of you in the audience that
perceive that this app actually
lacks essential features.
Choosing reps is amazing.
Picking a sequence isn't work.
If this is you I have great
news.
There are lots of apps that
allow you to do those things.
But I'm curious about what
inspired this.
Whenever I see something unique
like this I wonder what's behind
it because it's unique and it's
implemented really well.
So I asked the developers of
Streaks Workout.
And it's such a common story to
hear about how an app originated
with an idea that came out of
prison.
So specifically, their idea
originated with how inmates in
prison keep workouts new and
interesting.
So I want to walk you through
how that works.
So in prison you take a normal
deck of cards and at the
beginning of each workout you
would assign a movement to each
suit.
So today diamonds are crunches.
The numbers on the cards
represent the number of reps per
movement.
So at the beginning of the
workout you'd put the deck face
down and you'd start drawing and
each card would deliver a
movement and a rep count.
OK, everyone eight crunches.
So the original app concept was
a literal recreation of this.
This is an early comp and they
also prototyped shuffling and
flipping cards to try to kind of
replicate the origin of this
prison workout.
But they quickly moved past the
literal approach.
They didn't stick to the literal
deck of cards because it carried
too many constraints.
Four suits would limit the
number of movements that you
could do in each workout and
people would somehow need to
remember that diamonds
represented crunches in that
particular workout and that's
work, right?
So instead they focused on the
value that they wanted to bring.
They wanted to help people make
a habit of working out.
So they acknowledged that people
felt inertia when they were
going to launch a workout app
and they removed as much as
possible that might trigger that
and they stayed true to the
original intent of the prison
workout, which is that spirit of
randomness and surprise.
And that's what I mean by deep
understanding.
Knowing the person that you want
to reach and the actual problem
that they might have.
So the superficial approach to
this workout would have been
just a typical workout app,
right?
Of course people want to get
healthy.
But what people really want, or
what I really want anyway is to
get past the boredom and that
inertia and they've addressed
that for me.
So knowing users is nothing new.
I'm guessing a lot of you here
have personas and market
segments and you do surveys and
other kinds of user research
focus groups.
Maybe you create experience maps
and customer journeys and user
stories.
All of those can be useful
models.
But they have to feel authentic,
right?
They actually have to feel like
people.
That can make focus easier and
it can help teams kind of come
together around a vision.
As long as you share a common
understanding and you feel a
real empathy for the person that
you're designing for.
Those can work.
But too often those artifacts of
needs and goals and skills, they
just feel artificial.
They may not connect with
everyone.
They feel complicated or distant
or corny.
So for a moment I want to talk
about how much easier it is to
make some something when you
really care about the person
you're making it for.
So I first heard about this
story that I'm going to tell you
in a book.
It's by a guy named Alan Cooper,
he's a software developer from
the early days, and his claim to
fame is that he created a
prototype that became Visual
Basic.
And this is an actual pixel
resolution of Visual Basic 1.0
on a 4K display.
It's pretty amazing.
So Alan built this with a small
team and as he did it he began
to recognize a problem in
maintaining a focus on what
people really want.
And he tells this great story in
a book about another invention
and that story is a parable of
how powerful knowing people can
be, knowing the person that
you're designing for.
So apologies if I got your hopes
up about Visual Basic.
I'm actually not going to talk
about that.
I want to focus on this story
and kind of extend it a little
bit.
So the invention that he talks
about is the Rollaboard
Suitcase.
So this is the patent form for
the Rollaboard.
So nowadays the suitcase might
seem pretty unremarkable.
For most of us this is just a
suitcase, big deal.
But it actually hasn't been
around for that long.
The patent was filed in 1989.
People have been traveling
forever though.
So why did it take so long to
design something so obvious?
The inventor was a guy named
Robert Plath.
I'm guessing not a household
name, but more on that in a
minute.
So what was innovative about
this?
Well, I think the innovations
are subtle.
It wasn't the wheels.
Many patents had been filed for
wheeled suitcases before.
This is from the '70s.
So the wheels are underneath and
it's also got some kind of leash
thing.
Suitcase manufactures had been
trying to put wheels on
suitcases as far back as the
'40s and this actually has some
kind of other leash thing, some
grabber thing that you can see
right there.
So clearly people have been
trying to figure out a way to
not carry heavy things.
So if you worked in the luggage
industry in 1989, you probably
thought you'd already innovated.
You weren't worried about this
new patent I'm guessing.
But we all know what happened,
right?
The new design became the de
facto design of suitcases.
And the improvements in
retrospect are totally obvious.
There's a handle at the top so
the whole suitcase it oriented
to be upright.
It's easy to grab and pull and
pivot.
That is the evolution of the
leash.
Second the wheels, right?
The wheels are placed on the
edge so they're only fully
engaged when the suitcase is
tilted.
And finally the size, it's small
enough to lift and place in an
overhead bin.
So nothing particularly
revolutionary but the inventor
Robert Plath made each decision
to serve a really specific
person, a person who traveled
for a living.
Robert Plath was a pilot for
Northwest Airlines.
He intimately knew the pain of
lugging and lifting heavy
things.
He did it every day.
And he deeply understood what
people like him wanted, to move
with ease while looking
professional, and he made
something perfectly suited for
that.
So what I find really
interesting is that at the
times, 1989, there were only
about 100,000 travel
professionals as the Census Data
called them, but pilots, flight
attendants, people in the travel
industry.
That 100,000 might seem like a
lot, but when you compare that
number to the overall market of
people who traveled a couple
times a year, just like more
than 100 million at the time,
and that's just Census Data from
the U.S., his target user,
quote-unquote, was a really
specific person that represented
only 0.1% of 1% of the market.
So what I'm saying is that
typical methods of market
identification probably would
not have led Robert Plath to
focus so narrowly.
He focused on an extreme use
case, a person who traveled all
the time.
So I'm using extreme
intentionally to emphasize that
he focused on what we might call
an edge case.
The market size was really small
and his solution was kind of
whacky.
It looked really different.
It implied a new kind of default
way of interacting with your
luggage.
So he focused on the needs of
people he intimately knew and
that extreme focus allowed the
real needs of a lot of people to
come to the surface.
So his focus gave him the
freedom to arrive at an extreme
solution.
So the third element of intent
is extreme focus.
So what might seem like an edge
case could be what frees you to
reorient or refocus your design.
Make it more coherent.
Make it simpler.
And therefore actually reach
more people.
So let's relate extreme to our
work.
Is there a way to relate extreme
to the work that we do?
I think there is and I think
being extreme can be really
worthwhile but you have to nail
it.
So you might not immediately
associate the words extreme and
weather app.
But Carrot Weather is a really
compelling illustration of being
extreme.
So on the surface it's a weather
app.
So let's check the weather
forecast.
>> I wonder how many licks it
takes to get to the center of a
human skull.
>> So right, they're not typical
forecasts.
The voice of Carrot, which is
the robotic voice that you
heard, has personality and
attitude and a little bit of an
edge.
You probably think this sunshine
means that things are starting
to look up for you.
They're not.
So you might ask is that even a
forecast [laughing]?
So sometimes when I read these
things I just feel like it's
being mean to me.
It's definitely got an attitude
but the key information is super
readable and the screen is
really nicely organized.
The color scheme changes
according to the time of day and
it's really playful.
And it's got those illustrations
along the bottom that are
sometimes bizarre and often
really funny.
So the forecast is only one of
quite a few unique elements in
the app.
So I ask the developer whose
name is Brian Mueller, to help
me understand where this came
from and he told me something
interesting.
He said that when we writes in
the voice of Carrot, he's
channeling the personalities of
people really close to him --
his wife, his sister, and his
mom.
And these forecasts are a form
of conversation with them.
So the lesson is that the people
that Brian is trying to reach,
the people that he's speaking to
with these forecasts are
actually really specific.
And I think that's what makes
his apps stand out.
The edginess helps him connect
with people.
And it's not surprising to me
that he's had so much success in
the app store.
The personal touch is what
allows his app to deeply connect
with the rest of us.
Obviously personality isn't the
sole province of weather apps.
All apps can deliver something
like this.
All apps can feel handcrafted
and special.
And that's the fourth element of
intent that I want to talk
about.
Intentionally designed apps feel
personal.
They create a personal
connection.
So the point isn't to spice up
your copy, right?
The point is that spicy copy in
the right context feels
memorable.
And it must be said that the
personality of Carrot is
probably not for everyone.
And I talked with Brian he
commented on this.
So you can probably imagine the
email and Tweets that he gets
from people who are surprised or
upset or offended by the
forecast after they download the
app.
Like, you know, how dare he
insult meteorologists like this?
So he offers an olive branch --
[ Laughter ]
To these disgruntled souls.
They can adjust the personality
from the default, which as you
saw was Homicidal.
You could go the left for less
edge and to the right for more.
But the bottom line just to be
clear is that edgy text would be
less funny or perhaps not funny
at all if the app didn't work,
right?
It's a good weather app with
simple navigation and a playful
UI.
The extreme personality though
is what gives life and sprit to
it.
So when I get a Carrot
notification it's similar to the
feeling that I have when I go
out to a local restaurant or bar
where everyone knows my name,
right?
It's enjoyable, it's personal,
and it's comfortable.
So we've got four things that
characterize intent and the
behavior of intentionally
designed apps.
And I want to flip things around
for a moment and talk about what
happens when you're not
intentional.
In other words, where does bad
UI come from?
So I think the best friends and
the worst enemies to designing
intentionally are all of the
systems and patterns that we've
internalized as we've gained
experience in the work that we
do.
This experience allows us to
make decisions quickly and to be
really efficient in that work.
But these familiar patterns get
in the way of our ability to
reckon with new problems.
Sometimes we won't even
recognize that the problems are
new and this is true of anyone
who has tried to make anything
new ever, right?
Suitcases once had a form.
They were rectangular and the
long side was down.
That form was adjusted but the
fundamental elements were always
taken as a given.
The wheels were tacked on but
the overall form stayed the
same.
For decades smart people
considered this form and stopped
there.
It took someone with a very
sharp focus on an extreme
audience to break out of this
pattern, right, and turn the
form on it's head [laughing].
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
So we apply patterns
automatically.
Our brains make connections
quickly and that has benefits,
right?
It helps us work efficiently.
It helps us be consistent, but
it also prevents us from
noticing the obvious and
challenging it, asking
fundamental questions, why does
this thing need to be this way?
So as a UI designer it's really
tempting always to draw on
familiar UI elements to solve
new problems.
I'm sure you're familiar with
the house icon.
It made sense in a desktop
browser.
A browser is a frame for the
Internet universe.
A browser home button will lift
you out of whatever corner of
the dark web that you found
yourself in and allows you to
get out of there.
So that notion of home was
extended to iPhone and the
behavior is similar.
It's a shortcut, it's an easy
button, home is a starting
place, and unlike in real life,
home is a place that you can
always return to with a simple
gesture.
You can go home whenever you
want.
So home is also a familiar
notion in the finder.
Here the spirit is more like --
you followed the river to it's
headwaters.
On the Mac, home represents a
container.
Everything is in here.
You don't need to look anywhere
else.
you have reached the source.
Home in these contexts offers
reliability, safety, an ability
to return as you navigate
outward.
And it's clear obvious utility
elsewhere on the platform might
seem like a reasonable choice as
a tab bar icon, right?
Except there's a crucial
difference in using the notion
of home in a tab bar.
To be blunt, an app isn't a
frame containing god knows what.
A typical app offers specific
things, specific contents,
specific tools, specific
actions.
And a tab bar is a quick
expression of the overall
utility of your app.
It's a high-level map of your
app.
So let's use an example that's
close to home -- the tab bar of
WWDC app.
So we all can get a quick
understanding of the scope of
information that's available in
the app simply by scanning the
tab bar.
We can guess at what content
might be in each tab.
So tab bar icons and tab bar
labels should be as direct as
possible.
And this directness will then
limit what each tab can contain
and that's great.
Directness creates
predictability.
So the app may not do
everything, right, no app does
everything.
But people won't have to hunt
around to figure out what it
does and doesn't do.
So when I talk about home I'm
talking about a metaphor,
homeland, a home base.
So let's just dig in to why home
doesn't work.
First it's overly broad and it
feels generic.
And I think it's a copout.
You're avoiding a decision by
naming a tab Home.
The perceived comforts of home
as an icon in a label are
getting in the way of being
direct, of clearly and directly
communicating the scope of
what's in your app.
If your app is a meditation app
and offers content related to
meditating and building a
meditation practice, imagine the
impression that it would leave
on people if not only the tab
bar was more direct, but the
directness of the tab bar
enforced a simplicity and an
order on the content that you
display.
And that content was predictable
and directly organized.
So indirect labels feel
conventional and they feel safe
but they mask utility.
Like a storage locker you're
putting your valuable stuff
behind a door that's anonymous
and inscrutable.
And this is what I mean by
unintentional design.
No one intends to be indirect.
Being intentional will lead to
cleaner and clearer
communication.
And this brings me to my final
element of intent.
Direct communication.
Intentionally design things.
Clearly communicate to the
people who use them.
And the way to achieve this is
to draw on what people learn on
the platform and in the world.
So I want to show you a couple
of last quick examples of apps
that rely on a familiar form to
make interactions feel useful.
So the core concept of an app
called Tinycards is to bring
flashcards on to a mobile
advice.
You can use them to memorize
pretty much anything --
languages, flowers, leaves,
almost anything.
So the interaction within the
app is super direct.
People expect cards to have
dimension, so that periodic
pulse is inviting you to
interact with the card.
You flip the card over by
tapping it.
So these cards have two sides.
They've respected the metaphor
of the card.
People appreciate that.
So the entire experience of
Tinycards is based on quickly
flicking through these cards as
you commit things to memory.
Like for instance the flags of
Canadian provinces.
Does anyone know this one?
Ontario. Let's try it.
Oh my gosh.
You've done that quiz before,
right?
So the UI of Tinycards is so
clear you don't even think about
it.
Working with cards feels
completely natural and you can
just focus on your goal, which
is learning stuff.
So what Tinycards demonstrates
to me is that if you implement a
metaphor well, people will
instantly become immersed.
They'll forget that they're even
interacting with a UI.
And once they're immersed, you
even have the opportunity to
extend the metaphor, to really
surprise and even delight
people.
So I want to show you a game.
It's called Gorogoa and it
extends the metaphor of the card
in a way that I feel like
creates a truly unique
experience.
So Gorogoa is a puzzle game.
You move cards around a grid and
you advance in the game and in
the story by getting them into
the right positions.
But you could see that these
cards do things that no actual
cards can do.
They can be torn off and as
you'll see in a moment they can
actually stitch themselves
together into a scene.
Yeah, this is an incredible
game.
[ Applause ]
And it's a great example of how
you can extend the metaphor
farther than you might think and
create something truly amazing.
This moment right here where
you've got this card metaphor
that suddenly kind of
disappears, that's purely
delightful and it's really I
think a great testament to how
well he's implemented the
metaphor of cards.
Bending and extending metaphors
doesn't work if the result
doesn't extend the utility, or
value, or delight of your app.
That's why the home tab on the
tab bar doesn't work, right?
It doesn't extend the utility of
the app or create any additional
value.
So the last app I want to show
you is an example that combines
metaphors from the real and
digital world in a really simple
way.
It's called Rosarium.
Yeah.
[ Applause ]
I think the developers are here.
It's a rosary that you wear on
your wrist and I believe that is
Latin and the font is really
communicating to me that it's
Latin anyway.
So the beads are represented by
circles.
Each time you turn the digital
crown you get a slight haptic
tab.
So when I met the developers
they told me that they were
inspired by the similarity
between the feel of rotating the
digital crown and the feel of an
actual rosary bead.
So the app has translated this
real world object, just a strand
of beads, into the virtual world
in a way that feels really
natural.
So I'm no suggesting that it's a
replacement for rosary beads or
any prayer beads because the
physical beads can have deep,
you know, personal meaning.
But I love how they've
thoughtfully carried that real
world experience into a digital
form in a way that's so
radically simple and clear.
And I think it really
illustrates each of the points
that I made earlier -- the
simplicity and the understanding
of people, the extreme kind of
focus on a problem and the
direct communication of a
solution.
And this is intent in action.
This is being intentional in
design.
It's a matter of turning off the
automatic part of your brain, of
slowing down, and challenging
the obvious.
It requires a level of intention
that will enable your decisions
to become more conscious and for
you to become aware of the
patterns and the familiar things
that might get in the way and
block you and focus on people,
right?
The people that you want to
serve, the person who inspires
you, the family member who
allows you to be the best
version of yourself, the
coworkers with whom you share a
real need for something better,
and you can take that
inspiration and use it to
discover newer and better ways
to connect with people and to
create something really great.
So you can check out more about
my session here.
Thank you very much.
And please, please stick around
for the next talk.
The next talk is designing fluid
interfaces.
It's a great talk.
Easily one of the top seven
design talks at this year's
WWDC.
So thank you.
[ Applause ]