[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Hey, everyone.
Welcome to the AR design
session.
My name is Grant Paul, from the
human interface team at Apple.
And, I hope you've been having a
great WWDC this week.
So, for this session, we're
going to start off by, I'm going
to talk about how to design
great AR apps and games with the
user interfaces and
interactions.
And then, Omar's going to come
up, and he's going to tell you
all about making 3D models that
look great in AR, and feel great
in AR.
So, before we get to that, I
want to quickly talk about the
basics.
So, if you're new to it, you
might be wondering exactly what
it is that we mean when we talk
about AR.
But, even if you're an AR
expert, I want to talk about
what we mean for this session.
So, AR, of course, stands for
augmented reality.
And, let's break down what that
means a little bit.
And, we can start with reality,
because it's a little bit easier
to get into.
So, reality means is that AR
deals with things in the real
world.
And, that's a little bit
different than other things we
might have done on our devices,
that take place on the device,
or they take place on the
internet.
But, with AR, things happen in
the real world.
They happen in the room around
you, in the environment you're
in, or in your place on the map.
Where you are.
But, the important thing is,
it's a little bit different.
And the other part of augmented
reality, is augmented.
And, that can mean a few
different things.
So, augmented can mean -- it can
mean augmenting what you know
about the world.
It can mean getting information
that the device can understand
about the world, and giving that
to you.
It can mean placing virtual
things out into the world,
giving the virtual this physical
context.
And, it can mean taking
something that is real, like
your face, when you put an
animoji on as a mask.
Taking something that is real,
and enhancing it, augmenting it.
So, that's what we mean when we
talk about AR, when we talk
about augmented reality.
And, with that, I want to get to
the first half of this session.
I want to start talking about
how to design interfaces, and
design interactions for your AR
apps and your AR games.
And, the first part of that is
to talk about how to get people
into AR.
How to help guide people into
AR.
So, I'll show you how iOS 12's
built-in AR experiences help
guide people into AR.
And then, how you can take those
principles, and apply them in
your own apps.
Next, we'll talk about the
different ways you can present
content in AR.
The different possibilities that
ARKit opens up, and also some
tips and tricks that are great
no matter what kind of AR app
you're making.
And finally, we'll talk about
interactions in the world.
It's a little bit different when
you're building an AR app than
when you're building a 2D app,
for what kind of interactions
make sense, and what kind of
interactions you're going to
want to use.
So, we'll figure out what still
works great in AR, and then,
where we might need some new
kinds of interactions.
But first, I want to get started
with talking about how to get
into AR.
And, what I'm talking about here
is after somebody's downloaded
your app, after they've found
the AR experience in the app,
they've opened it up, what I'm
talking about here is when ARKit
needs to understand the world.
Because for every AR app, ARKit
needs some level of
understanding of the world in
order to start the AR
experience.
In order to get it going.
Because every AR app needs to --
needs that understanding in
order to place its objects into
the world, or show the user that
information.
And, the way ARKit builds that
understanding of the world, is
by getting you to move your
device, by having you move
around.
And, that's a little bit
different from other places that
you might have looked through a
device, seen a camera preview,
in the past.
Like, for example, when you're
taking a photo, you just need to
point the device where you want
to frame the shot.
But, in AR, you really do need
to start moving, looking at the
same place from different
positions, and looking at it
from some different angles.
So, the trick here is to let
people know what they need to
do.
Let them know how to move, that
they need to move their device.
And, the way to do that is to
give them a fixed reference.
Give them something to base that
understanding off of.
And, let's talk about that.
Let's take a look at an example.
So, this is the game Euclidean
Lands.
And, what it's showing here, is
the device moving around inside
of a room.
And, that's really great,
because you can see here,
without any text exactly what it
is you need to do, that you need
to move the device within that
room, and just turning the
device to look at a different
angle isn't going to be enough.
So, without any text, it's
really clear from that fixed
reference of the room, exactly
what you need to do.
And, usually, most of the time,
that is all you're going to
need.
ARKit is even faster to build
that understanding of the world
in iOS 12.
So, in even more cases that is
all you're going to need.
You just need to start moving,
and you're ready to go.
But, of course, there are some
situations that aren't quite as
well suited to AR.
Maybe you're in a dark room, or
it's really reflective, and it's
not as easy to -- for ARKit to
start building that
understanding.
So, it can take ARKit a little
bit of time to get ready.
It might not happen immediately.
And, in those situations, if
you're still being told to move
your device, you're still
looking at something that says
to you, move your device around,
people might start to wonder,
why is the app not working?
Does the app not understand the
movement that they're making?
And, it might get -- start to
get confusing.
So, what you need is some kind
of feedback that lets people
know that they're not doing
anything wrong.
They're doing exactly what they
should be doing to get into AR.
And, they should just keep doing
it.
So, let's take a look at an
example.
So, this is how iOS 12's
built-in AR apps help guide
people into AR.
You can see the device moving
over the fixed reference of that
surface, by showing you that you
need to move it.
You can't just keep it in one
place, or rotate it.
And then, once you've started
moving the device, the surface
transitions into a cube.
And, that cube spins with the
movement of the device, giving
you real, connected, direct
feedback that you're on the
right path, and you're doing the
right thing.
And then, once ARKit has built
that understanding, it's all
ready, the cube spins away, and
you're ready to go in your AR
experience.
So, that's how the built-in apps
in iOS 12 help guide people into
AR.
And, your apps should follow
those same principles.
They should help people know
that they need to move their
device, and give them that
feedback that they're doing the
right thing.
But, your apps don't need to
follow that same style.
They don't need to look like
line drawings.
AR should feel like an
integrated part of your app.
It should feel native to your
app's style.
And, it shouldn't feel like
something that's attached on, or
this flow is something that's
added on after the fact.
So, the important part is to
help people down the right path,
but it should feel like part of
your app while you're doing
that.
And, the last thing I want to
talk about for helping get
people into AR, is that it's
important to balance your
instructions, your guidance, how
you're helping people get into
AR with being really efficient
when people already do know what
to do.
So, if somebody already knows
what to do, they're just going
to start moving their device
right away.
They don't need any kind of
instructions.
They don't need anything to tell
them to do that.
So, don't make them sit through
any kind of guidance.
Since ARKit is so much faster,
in a lot of cases, they'll start
moving, ARKit will understand
the world, and they'll be ready
to go right away.
Alright. So, that's getting into
AR.
That's how you help guide people
into your AR experiences.
Now, let's talk about how to
present your content in AR.
The different ways that you can
show things in AR, and tips and
tricks for all kinds of AR apps
and AR games.
And, I want to start with some
of the more radical
possibilities of things you can
build in ARKit.
Because not every AR experience
has to look like looking through
your device, seeing a camera
preview of the world, and then
placing objects out into space.
There are other options as well.
So, one of those options is to
build an AR experience entirely
in two dimensions.
You don't need to show a camera
preview.
You don't need any kind of 3D
graphics.
You're using that information
that ARKit gets about the world
to present a great AR
experiences entirely in 2D.
So, let's take a look at an
example of that.
This is the game "Rainbrow."
And, in Rainbrow, the way you
control you character is by
moving your eyebrows up and
down.
[ Game Music ]
[ Applause ]
So, there's no need of any kind
of camera preview here.
There's no need for any 3D
graphics.
It's a lot more fun entirely in
2D, but it's still a great AR
experience.
So, that was AR in 2D.
But, another way, another thing
you can do with ARKit is you can
build things that I would
consider to be full virtual
reality experiences.
And, what I mean by that, is
that the experiences take you to
a different place.
They really make you feel like
you're somewhere else.
You can walk around the
environment.
You can move around within it.
You can look in all directions.
And, to me that makes something
really into a virtual reality
experience, even if it is
through a device.
And, there's some benefits to
that.
You don't need any extra
equipment.
It works everywhere.
You don't need to wear a headset
on your head.
It works everywhere you are with
the device you already have.
You don't need any kind of
trackers or anything else.
And, there's some benefits to
looking through a device rather
than being fully immersed.
Like, you're never going to
accidentally walk into a wall
because you always have your
peripheral vision.
So, ARKit can be a great way to
make virtual reality
experiences.
We'll take a look at one.
So, this is the virtual reality
experience called "Enter the
Room."
And, it was developed by the
International Committee of the
Red Cross.
And, in this experience, once
you walk into the room, you can
look around in all directions.
You can move closer to things.
You can inspect them.
You can move farther away.
And, the sound comes in, and it
feels like it's coming in from
outside the room, from all
around you.
And, that makes it into a really
powerful experience.
And, that's what you can do with
virtual reality using ARKit.
So, those are some of the more
radical options of things that
you can build with ARKit.
We can also look at some tips
and tricks that make sense no
matter what kind of app it is
that you're building.
Whether it's a game, or a
productivity app, these can work
for everything.
So, the first thing I want to
talk about here is showing text
in AR.
Because text is really
important.
All kinds of AR apps have
different reasons to show text.
If it's a game, maybe you want
to show the title of a level, or
some instructions.
Or, maybe for other kinds of
apps, you want to label
something in the world, label a
virtual object.
Maybe show some annotations.
But, the important part, no
matter what reason it is that
you're showing this text, is to
keep that text readable.
Make it really easy to read.
So, the simplest way to show
text in AR, is to put it out
into the world, to put it in
perspective.
And, you know, that can look
really cool.
But, it also has some drawbacks.
And, one of those drawbacks is
what happens when you look at it
from an angle.
The letters can, sort of, squish
together.
It can be a little hard to read.
And, another issue is what
happens when you take a step
back, when you're looking from
further away.
The text can get really small.
It's like trying to read a piece
of paper from all the way across
the room.
So, if you're showing titles, or
other kinds of things that maybe
people already know, or could
get in another way, it can be
really cool to show that in
perspective.
But, if you're showing something
that people really need to read,
need to get information from,
you might want to try a
different option.
So, a different option that you
can use, is to show your text in
screen space.
And, what I mean by screen
space, is that the text is
always the same size.
It's always facing you.
It's always head-on.
And, that makes it really easy
to read.
It doesn't have those problems
of what angle you're looking at,
or how far away from it you are.
But, the important part of
showing text in screen space, is
that it's still attached to a
position in the world.
It's still fixed to the place in
the world that you attach it to
an object, or attach it to some
physical feature.
And, that makes it really feel
like part of the AR scene.
So, screen space text is a great
way to label things, put some
annotations into AR, but still
make them really readable.
So, here's an example of screen
space text.
And, this is from Measure, which
is part of iOS 12.
When Measure shows the
measurements, it shows them in
screen space.
So, no matter what angle you're
looking at those measurements
from, or how far away you are,
they're always incredibly
readable.
So, screen space text is great
for readability.
But, you should still try and
keep how much text it is that
you're actually showing in AR to
as little as possible.
And, the reasons for that is
when text is placed in the
world, you always have to keep
pointing your device at it in
order to read it.
If you turn your device to a
more natural reading position,
the text is going to go away.
So, if you have more detailed
text, if you're showing details
about some kind of object, or
something in the world, you
should show those details on the
display.
And then, people can use all
that experience that they built
up using iOS and reading things
on their devices, to read those
details directly on the display.
And, when you're showing those
details, when you're coming out
of AR, it's important to have a
transition.
Because those transitions can
make it really clear what it is
you're looking at.
What text, what object it is
that those details are
referencing.
What it is that you're getting
details about.
So, let's look at an example
there.
And, this is also from Measure.
In Measure, when you tap on a
measurement, it comes out of AR
to show the details about that
measurement flat on the screen.
And that's great because it's
really easy to read.
You don't have to point your
device or your phone at the
measurement in order to read it.
But, it's also really clear,
because of the transitions.
The transitions show you what
measurement it is that you're
looking at details for.
And, they comes out of the
measurement, so you're never
going to be confused.
So, transitions.
They're really great when you're
coming out of AR, and going back
into AR, for showing details on
the display.
But, they're also really
important when you're just
showing objects in AR.
And, that's because it makes it
feel like there's one version of
the object.
It makes it feel like that
object has its own identity.
And, that's important, because
things in AR are so physical.
They have that physical sense.
When you see them in AR, they
look real.
And, things in reality, you
can't just copy them.
You can't just make multiple
copies.
So, it's important to keep that
same principle when you're
showing objects in AR.
So, this is what happens when
you Quicklook at objects in AR.
And, it shows a great example of
keeping that identity.
When you switch from the object
tab to the AR tab, the object
stays in place.
It always stays visible.
It doesn't disappear and then
come from somewhere else.
And, even when you're deciding
where to place the object here,
it always stays visible on the
display.
So, it's really easy to see that
there's one version of this
object.
And, even when you go back into
the app that you were
Quicklooking the object from, it
still shows the object
transitioning back to where it
came from.
So, it feels like there's one
object moving between different
parts of your app.
And then, into the world, and
back out of the world.
It doesn't feel like there's
multiple copies.
Alright. So, that was a bunch of
information in a row about the
different ways that you can
present your content in AR.
So, let's do a quick recap of
that.
So, first, we looked at the
different ways you can make AR
experiences, and we talked about
using AR to create entirely 2D
experiences, with no camera
preview, and no 3D graphics.
We talked about how VR can be a
great way to build experiences
with ARKit, and make you feel
like you're somewhere else, that
can be really powerful and
really immersive.
We talked about using screen
space to show text in AR, to
make it really readable from any
angle, and readable from any
distance.
We talked about showing your
details on the screen, so that
they're easy to read without
pointing your device at some
specific place in the world.
And that you can use all of that
same knowledge that you've built
up reading things on iOS.
And finally, we talked about
transitioning into AR, and out
of AR, for showing details flat
on the display.
But, also to give objects that
sense of identity, that sense of
physicality that's so important
in AR.
Alright. So, that's presenting
content in AR.
So, different ways that you can
present it.
And some tips for different
types of content that you're
going to want to show in your AR
apps.
Now, let's talk about how we can
interact with that content.
Let's talk about interactions
that make sense in the world.
And, let's start with touch,
because touch has been really
important all the way back to
the beginning of iOS.
Multi-touch was there right from
the start, and it's been the
most important way to interact
with our devices.
And the reason touch is so
important, the reason touch is
so great, is that it enables
direct manipulation.
And, direct manipulation is when
you interact directly with
things on the screen, like
they're physical objects.
You're not using controls to
scroll or to pinch to zoom.
You're interacting directly with
the content.
It's like there's a physical
thing that you're manipulating.
And, that's even more important
in AR.
Because in AR, as I said before,
things are really physical.
Objects feel like they're real.
They feel like part of the real
world.
So, it's really important to use
direct manipulation to make it
feel like you're interacting
directly with those objects.
And, direct manipulation is also
great because it uses gestures
that you already know, that you
have experience with from iOS.
Because those gestures will be
the same as any other content on
iOS.
They're things that you've been
using for probably a long time.
So, the first one there is how
you can move objects in AR with
direct manipulation.
If you want to move objects, you
just put your finger down and
drag them to a new place.
And, it feels like you're
picking up the object, because
it stays under your finger.
You get this physical connection
to the thing that you're moving.
Another gesture you can do, is
scaling objects.
So, in AR, things start out at
their physical size, at their
natural size.
But, if you want to change that,
you can pinch the object to make
it bigger.
And, you can pinch out on the
object if you want to make it
smaller.
The important things to think
about when you're scaling
objects in AR, is to give some
feedback when you're doing it.
Because the change is really,
really big when you take an
object and scale it up to 4
times the size.
So, it's important to give
people feedback, so they
absolutely know what happened.
And, the second thing is to make
it really easy to go -- to take
the object back to its natural
size.
Back to the size that it would
be in the physical world.
So, you can snap back to 100%,
maybe with a haptic, to make
that really easy.
Another thing you can do is
rotate objects, by putting two
fingers on the display, and
twisting to rotate.
And, that can be really great,
but with all of these two finger
gestures, another thing you
should think about is your tap
targets.
Because things in AR are always
moving as you're moving the
device, and they can get really
small if you get further away,
or if you scale them down.
You should make sure to use
really generous tap targets.
So, it's easy to land two
fingers on the object.
And, be sure to use the center
of those two finger touch
positions to figure out which
object to interact with.
Because you might not be able to
land two whole fingers, even on
a generous tap target in AR.
Alright, so direct manipulation
is really great in AR.
It's really important because AR
is so physical.
But, it's also not quite enough
for most AR apps.
Because if you have a lot of
objects, it can make it hard to
touch the right one.
As I said before, the objects
are always moving on the display
as you're looking at different
places in the world.
And, they're staying fixed to
that place in the world.
So, it can be a little hard to
aim for those objects on the
screen.
But, the fundamental reason, the
number one reason, the real
reason that touch is not enough
for AR apps, is that it's
fundamentally two-dimensional.
The surface of the display is
two-dimensional, and you're
touching on that surface.
That is what made it so great,
multi-touch so great for flat,
2D apps in iOS.
But, AR content, it's placed
into the world.
It's part of the world.
So, that means we need some way
to interact with that content
also in three dimensions.
Because the world is
three-dimensional.
The answer there is moving your
device.
Because moving your device, it's
natively three-dimensional.
It's three-dimensional
inherently.
You can move up and down.
You can move left and right.
You can move forward and back.
You can turn in all directions.
You can stand up and move across
the room if you want to go a
little bit further.
But, the important part is that
moving your device is fully
three-dimensional, and that
really makes it the number one,
the primary interaction in AR.
In fact, I would say that moving
your device is more important
than touch for AR apps.
In fact, it's so natural, it's
built in to every AR app by
default.
The way that you look at
different things in AR is by
moving your device to look at it
from different angles, and
different positions.
So, it's really natural, and
it's also really powerful.
And, moving your device, it
accomplishes many of the things
that you would have done in a 2D
app by using multi-touch.
So, in a 2D app, if you want to
see more content, the way you do
that is by scrolling on the
display.
You scroll down to see something
new.
And, that's great in a 2D app,
but in AR, you do that in 3D.
You see different content, by
moving your device to look at
the content from different
positions, and from different
angles.
So, it solves that same problem
of wanting to see more, but it
solves it fully in three
dimensions.
Similarly, in a traditional 2D
app, if you want to see
something bigger, you pinch in
on it to make it bigger.
You pinch to zoom.
If you want to see it smaller,
you pinch out.
You pinch to zoom out.
But, in AR, if you want to see
something bigger, you can just
get closer to the thing you're
looking at.
You can just move closer in.
And, if you want to see more
things at once, you want to see
things from a wider angle, you
can just take a step back, and
look at all of the content at
once.
So, moving your device, it also
replaces what you might have
done by pinch to zoom to see
more content in a 2D
application.
So, movement is really great.
It can replace some of those
things you might have used
multi-touch for.
You can also use it to build
totally custom interactions for
your AR apps.
And, those can be really
natural.
Just like using your device to
look around at different things,
or to get closer and further
away.
So, let's take a look at an
example of that.
This is Swiftshot, the
multiplayer AR sample game that
you might have seen in the
Keynote, or you might have
actually tried it.
In order to fire a slingshot in
Swiftshot, the way you do it is
you move close to that
slingshot.
You don't have to pick which
slingshot you're going to fire
from a list.
You don't have to reach out and
try and aim for it on the
screen.
You just move close to it, and
when you want to fire the
slingshot, you just pull back
and release.
So, it's incredibly precise,
because you can fire in three
dimensions.
You have three dimensions of
precision while you're moving
that slingshot, while you're
pulling it back.
And, that's more than you could
ever do using touch.
So, moving your device, it's not
only really natural, but it's
also more precise than you could
ever do using touch in AR apps.
So, moving your device is great,
but sometimes we need to combine
the best of touch and the best
of device movement to create the
absolute best interactions.
So, let's look at some examples
of that.
And, let's start with combining
direct manipulation with moving
your device.
So, Quicklook in AR also offers
a great example of combining
device movement and direct
manipulation in AR.
If you want to move an object,
of course, you can just drag it
to the new position, the same as
you saw before.
Touch on the screen and move it
to a new place.
But, you could also touch down
to pick up the object and then
turn the device and release in a
new place.
And, that's great, because it
gives you the full
three-dimensional control of
moving your device to pick where
you're going to place it.
And, it lets you move objects to
places that you can't see on the
screen, by picking them up and
turning.
But, it still keeps that sense
of physical interaction.
That sense of direct
manipulation that you had from
picking up the object directly.
So, if you support any kind of
moving objects in AR in your
apps, you should definitely
support picking up an object
with direct manipulation, and
moving the device to find a new
place to put it.
Alright. So, moving your device
and direct manipulation is one
way to combine touch.
But another way to combine touch
with moving your device is
through indirect controls.
And, what I mean by indirect
controls, are controls that are
flat on the display.
They're not placed in the world.
They're not attached to
anything.
They're in a consistent position
on the display, and you can
learn that position.
And, that's really great,
because that means they get out
of the way.
Once you've learned that
position of that control on the
display, it stays in one place.
You can rest your finger above
it while you're speeding your
time focusing on the rest of the
app.
So, let's look at an example of
that.
Here's Zombie Gunship AR.
You're flying in a gunship above
a horde of zombies, and you
really need to aim at them.
You want to focus on aiming.
You don't want to focus on
moving your finger, trying to
figure out where you need to aim
your finger on the display in
order to fire.
Instead, you can just rest your
finger above the fire button,
and spend all of your time using
that full 3D precision of moving
your device in order to aim
where it is you're firing, to
aim at those zombies.
So, indirect controls are really
great combined with moving your
device.
But, they're also really great
because they let apps work
one-handed.
In AR, no matter what, you
always have to use one hand to
control where it is that you're
looking, at least one hand.
So, if you want to build a
one-handed AR experience, you're
going to need to use really
reachable controls that are
really easy to access.
So, an example of that is
Measure.
Measure uses an indirect
control, the plus button, the
add button at the bottom of the
screen to add points.
And, that control is in a really
reachable spot.
So, even while you're using one
hand to focus the reticle on the
center of the screen, to
precisely place your
measurements, you can keep a
finger placed above that plus
button to easily add your
measurements, to easily place
those points.
So, using indirect controls can
be a great way to make it not
only easy to use AR experiences,
but one-handed ones as well.
Alright. So, that's how to pick
interactions for AR.
You can use direct manipulation
to give that sense of
physicality, and physical
interaction.
You can move the device, the
primary interaction in AR.
And, you can use really
reachable indirect controls to
focus on the content, rather
than on controls or buttons
interacting with it.
And, that's what I wanted to
talk to you about today.
Getting into AR, guiding people
down the right path, and giving
them that direct feedback that
they're doing the right thing.
The ways you can present your
content in 2D and VR, and how
you can show content to make it
easy to read, and give objects
that physical identity
transitioning in and out of AR.
And, the interactions that you
can use in the world, especially
and primarily moving your
device.
So, now I want to bring up Omar,
who's going to talk about making
your models, your 3D models look
really great in AR.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Grant.
Hey, everyone.
I'm really excited to be up here
to talk about some best
practices that you need to keep
in mind while you're developing
your content for your AR
experiences.
So, we have a lot of different
pieces of information to cover
today.
And, whether you're an engineer,
designer, manager, or an artist,
we wanted to provide you with a
utility belt of tactics and
definitions, so that you are
best equipped to craft your own
exceptional AR contents to
delight people with.
So, to begin with, let's start
with some essential concepts to
keep in mind while you're
developing your AR experience.
AR is incredible.
Having the ability to take
anything you can imagine, and
place it into the real world is
absolutely magical.
And, because of this, people
tend to expect a lot out of
their AR experiences.
They expect your 3D content to
render at a smooth and
consistent rate.
It's incredibly distracting when
you're really engaged with the
content, and you start to move a
bit closer to it, and then, you
want to appreciate those fine
details, and all of a sudden,
wham!
Poor optimization has caused
performance to tank, and now
it's as if you're watching a
slideshow.
So, to ensure your -- the most
smoothest performance at all
times, and to keep people fully
engaged with your AR scene, your
app needs to render at a
recommended target of 60 frames
per second.
Now, it's really important to
maintain this target throughout
the entire experience.
Really stress test your content.
View it from every possible
angle.
You know, move in close, move
back from it, and just make sure
that the performance does not
ever degrade.
You know, maybe someday in the
future, batteries will run for
days.
But, today, make sure that your
experience is able to have as
minimal of an impact to battery
life as possible.
Don't give people the chance to
blame your app for draining
their battery.
The more power you save, the
more you want people to come
back to your experience and try
it again.
I mean, I don't know about you,
but whenever I see a battery
indicator in this stake, I
seriously feel like I'm going to
have a panic attack.
And, we definitely don't want to
have our AR experiences cause
widespread battery chaos
throughout the lands.
Remember, only you can prevent
excessive battery drain.
I like to look at AR as having
the power to take anything you
can imagine and to transport
into the real world.
People want to explore your
content, so you definitely want
to bring your A game.
Take the time to craft those
nuanced details into your 3D
content.
Build a cohesive story and
style.
And, remember that every little
detail, every little touch is an
opportunity to surprise people.
So, let's say we wanted to make
an AR experience to be about an
aquarium.
Even in its most abstract form,
I think I would be really
hard-pressed to find anybody who
would believe that this
marshmallow blob represents a
fish.
On a positive note, though, our
app will pretty much rock the
performance numbers if this
little guy's flopping around.
So, let's try that again.
Ah, now this is much better.
That is one properly
dead-looking fish.
See how it exhibits some nice
details, that once it's running
in AR will really want to entice
people to move closer to it to
see all those nuanced details
and explore its features.
We should strive to maintain
this level of quality with all
the fishes swimming in our
aquarium, or just floating in
the top in this case.
Finally, it's important to
remember that people really want
to use your app in a wide
variety of environments.
You want to avoid having your
content stand out in real world
locations where potentially the
lighting ambient conditions
could conflict with the story
that you're trying to tell.
So, when working with your
assets, try to avoid using
colors that are either too
bright or too dark.
And, make sure that you light
your AR scene in a way that it
casts even lighting on all the
objects that you're planning to
render, and at no matter what
angle you view them from.
You want your AR content to work
whether it's day or night.
Now, spoiler alert, we're going
to go over some really nice
features in ARKit that will
enable you to really delight
people when they see your AR
content blend and react
seamlessly to the real world
environment.
So, as you're building your AR
content, one great tool to help
evaluate your progress is by
using one of our recent
announced iOS 12 features, AR
Quicklook.
Throw some of your assets up on
iCloud drive, view them using
the Files app on iOS, and
quickly have the ability to
project it into AR.
Heck, you can even show off your
masterpiece by throwing it onto
a website so that your friends
can look it up, and you can view
it anywhere, right from Safari.
It's pretty awesome.
Definitely go back and check out
the session with Dave and David,
who go over details of best
practices of how you use AR
Quicklook, and I'm guarantee
you, it'll probably change your
life with how you develop your
assets.
So, now you've taken some time
to consider what people expect
from our AR experience, let's
quickly plan out what type of
app we're going to build today.
You know, it's always a good
idea to start thinking this
through before you begin
creating your 3D content.
As knowing what you want to make
will help narrow down how best
to optimize your content and
your assets for AR.
So, you're sitting at your desk,
and suddenly you're struck by
inspiration.
You just came up with the most
absolute brilliant AR experience
ever.
Alright? So, let's step back and
ask ourselves a couple questions
first.
Does this experience really need
to render hundreds of AR
objects, or will we focus on a
single hero asset?
How much detail do we actually
want?
And, what graphical style best
represents what we're trying to
convey?
Have we really paid attention to
Grant earlier and are thinking
about the level of interaction
we want people to have with our
experience?
Having a clear answer to
questions like these will help
determine where best to put your
rendering budget when you're
developing your app.
For example, imagine you're
building an AR experience
similar to the IKEA Place app,
where people can preview
different pieces of furniture by
being able to place them in
their home, or in our case,
outside on their patio.
Now, the stars of the show are
actually the different furniture
pieces, so you need to present
highly detailed objects that
closely mirror the real world
counterparts.
In this case, it is a good idea
to make sure that you spend a
little extra time in your
rendering budget on these single
hero assets, because their level
of quality can essentially make
or break a sale.
On the other hand, you decide
that you've had enough of
accidentally stepping on those
little, tiny, plastic bricks of
agonizing pain that your kids
start laying around the house.
So, in order to preserve your
sanity, you build an AR
experience so they can play
around with as many of these
blocks as they can possibly
imagine, similar to Playgrounds
AR.
And, save yourself from ever
having to experience brick pain
again.
In an app like this, where you
potentially have a lot of
objects being rendered and
interacted with, you want to
basically create very simple,
low-poly models with a flat
colorful material, so that you
can have a ton of them onscreen,
and still have really good
performance.
So, now that we've asked
ourselves these important
questions, it's time to set up
our AR canvas.
Just like painters like to set
up their canvas in space before
they begin work, we would like
to have a couple suggestions of
how to set up your project up
front, in order to position
yourself for optimal success.
We are big fans of creating a
focus square to determine where
to start placing your AR
content.
And, if you're using SceneKit,
right there on the bottom of the
screen, you have the option to
actually activate the statistics
panel.
This will allow you to see your
current frames per second, as
well as how many polygons there
are visible on the screen at any
given time.
Which should be very helpful as
you start to build out your app
and put all the different
elements into it.
So, now that we have a starter
scene up and running, I was
thinking, what will be a good
example AR app to help get over
these best practices?
So, I'm not really an outdoorsy
guy, but coming to California, I
find that here a lot of people
are.
So, I've been trying to connect
with nature.
You know, go camping, maybe make
a campfire for once, and yet it
really didn't happen.
So, instead I thought, let's
just throw it into an app, and
see how it goes.
And we're going to call it
CampfiAR.
I know, it's perfect, right?
Now, we can work on building out
a detailed, single object, and
bring all the joys of being
outdoors without the fear of any
of those bugs or fresh air.
We decided to render with a
stylized, semi-realistic, and
playful graphical style.
And, apply unique details to the
use of careful application of
some key, physically-based
material properties.
These choices mean that we could
potentially use a lot of
polygons to render the content
on the screen, but why deprive
people of the ability to spend
multiple hours staring at our
beautiful campfire?
Let's avoid going down that
route, and work towards
optimizing our scene by using a
few tricks of the trade.
So, we'll begin by focusing on
the foundational structure of 3D
objects, the mesh.
And describe the typical
development flow that will allow
you to create highly detailed
models, but still maintain a low
poly count for all the models in
your scene.
And, for those of you who might
not know, poly count is
essentially the number of
polygons, typically triangles,
that a mesh is composed of.
So, one of the first things we
like to do, is lay out the basic
structure of an AR scene by
using these simple meshes.
We find using this type of
white-boxing technique to be
really helpful for testing out
some basic interactions, as well
as seeing how well the objects
fit into the real world, what
kind of scale are they at?
You know, actually, I think this
campfire looks really great.
I think we're going to call it a
day here.
Let's just call this done and
ship it.
Thanks everyone.
I'm off to the afterparty, and
-- wait.
So, that didn't look like a
campfire to you guys?
Oh, alright.
Sorry. Really?
My bad. Let's jump back to
actually building out this
campfire mesh.
I want to give a quick high/low
review of what a mesh is, and
the basic data structures that
comprise it.
So, now you can think of a mesh
as being a collection of
triangles that are arranged in
3D space that will form a
surface for you to apply
materials on.
And, the corners of these
triangles are actually made up
of points called vertices, which
hold different pieces of
information, such as its
position in space, UV
coordinates for texture
application, as well as a very
important property that we'll go
over later called the normals.
Well, since I got busted for
trying to ship early, I wanted
to redeem myself by building out
one of the most gorgeous
campfires in the world.
Take a look at the details of
this camp.
Look at that fish and those
branches.
You can see all the intricate
details of the scales, as well
as the etchings found on the
bark.
But, man, my performance has
tanked.
And, that poly count has gone up
to almost about a million
polygons for this screen.
So, I'm already in hot water,
and I don't want to get in any
more trouble, so we better go
back and fix this.
As I'm concerned about the
impact that this will have on
battery life, as well as how
people are able to perceive and
interact with this AR scene.
So, let's see what we can do to,
kind of, help reduce the number
of polygons here.
Most 3D authoring tools have
specific functions that make it
easy for you to reduce the
actual complexity of your
models.
Here, we've reduced the number
of polygons associated with the
high-density model of the fish.
But, notice that, as we zoom in,
many of the details have been
lost.
But, don't fret.
We can use certain material
properties later on that will
bring back a lot of those
missing details.
The key here is to build a solid
foundational mesh that uses a
minimal amount of polygons.
So, let's put aside the
high-density mesh for now.
And, let's focus on building up
this low-density mesh as we move
forward.
Alright, so I'll admit that this
isn't looking quite as good as
before, but man, you can take a
look at that performance.
Not only have you saved a crazy
amount of overhead by reducing
the number of polygons found on
the screen, but we're able to
add a bunch of 3D objects to
this scene to make it even more
robust.
And, if you recall, in our
previous high-density mesh, we
were running at about 30 frames
per second.
But, now we're back to 60
frames.
And, we were close to about, I
think about a million polygons,
and now it's down to 9,000.
This is incredible.
Because of this, we are well on
our way to having those
performance specification that
we desire.
A really solid frame rate with
minimal impact to the battery
life.
So, now that we have this
optimized model in our campfire
scene, let's see how we can
bring back some of those details
that we lost by working on what
some of these different material
properties and techniques that
will ensure that our model looks
as good as possible while still
maintaining that great level of
performance.
So, you may have heard this time
before, physically-based
rendering thrown about regarding
modern 3D rendering.
It's a pretty complex topic that
will take a lot more time than
we actually have in this session
to go over.
But, the basic concept describes
the ability to take the
application of your different
material properties onto your
mesh, in order to have it react
realistically to the simulated
lights found in your AR scene.
And, moving forward, all the
materials that we'll be
discussing will conform to this
shading technique.
If you want further details
about this concept, there's a
great WWDC 2016 talk that goes
over details about
physically-based rendering as it
applies to SceneKit, called
Advances in SceneKit Rendering.
Now, with that said, let's start
talking about our first material
property, albedo, or what is
sometimes lovingly referred to
as the base or diffuse color
property.
So, let's jump back into
CampfiAR.
Previously our base measure's
looking a little bit boring,
with the gray material
associated with it, but after
you apply albedo, you start to
see that it looks a lot better.
But, the campfire is still
missing a lot of those small,
finite details that were
originally found in that
high-density mesh.
As you move closer to the
campfire, you'll notice that all
the surfaces are relatively
flat.
And, this is something that
we'll definitely correct later,
but first let's dive into the
albedo property a little bit
more.
Think of the albedo as basically
being the base mesh of the
various objects in your AR
scene.
This is the material property
that you typically use to apply
textures to the surface of your
model.
If you recall, your mesh
contained different vertices,
that held different pieces of
information.
The ones you see here are
actually called UV coordinates,
which help map out how pixels
from various texture maps are
actually applied to the model.
And, after we've worked with
these textures, we've applied
the abel material to this
property on the fish.
So, now we've essentially
applied a texture to our fish, I
want to remind you about the
fact that you never know where
people are never going to
experience your app.
You want to be able to have your
content fit in as many different
scenarios as possible.
So, you want to take care in
selecting the right albedo value
that are neither too bright or
dark.
As, you want this to work in a
wide variety of different
situations.
So, our fish has got a skin, but
we're still missing a lot of
details from this, and the other
objects found in the scene.
So let's go back into how we can
start bringing back a lot of
those details through the use of
the normal material property.
So, as we jump back into
CampfiAR, let's see how we can
bring back some of those details
that we moved from optimization.
This can be done through the use
of a special texture called a
normal map, which you can see
here as the blue tinted maps
that are now applied to our AR
scene.
These maps allow you to add
those fine surface details back
into your models, without the
need to add any additional
geometry.
Now, after applying the normal
maps, you can see how the fish
exhibits some scales, as well as
making the branches show just a
tiny bit more detail.
Also if you take a look at the
statistics panel, you'll notice
that there was absolutely no
change in the number of polygons
related to this model.
It's magical, isn't it?
So, how do we make this normal
map?
Let's see a closer look at one
of the branches, and see what we
can do to make this work.
In most modern 3D modeling
applications, artists have the
ability to generate these normal
maps by projecting details from
a high-density mesh over to a
low-density one.
So, here you can see what the
normal map looks like on the
branches after they've been
generated from this high-density
mesh.
And, after applying the normal
map, you start to notice all
those nice details that were
originally lost come back into
this model.
But we still are able to
maintain that high performance,
of the low-poly mesh.
So, you may be wondering why the
normal map looks kind of
strange, well the colors of the
normal map actually represent
visual representations of the
vector data.
And, determine how the normals
on the surface model will be
offset in order to change the
way that light is being
reflected, and our key to making
this effect work.
That was a bit of a mouthful, so
let's dive a little bit more
into this property, because
normals we feel are a really
important topic.
And, we want to spend a couple
more minutes just going into how
truly spectacular these can be.
The art of manipulating normal
vectors are one of the key tools
that AR creators have in order
to add a lot of the significant
details back into their model.
So, what the heck is a normal
vector, and are there strange
vectors as well?
Well, no there's no strange
vectors unless you forgot your
high school trig, but normal
vectors lie perpendicular to the
surface of the mesh, and are
associated with each mesh
vertex.
So, why do we need these
normals?
Well, in order to see our
object, you need to place
simulated lights into your 3D
engine.
Normal vectors allow 3D engines
to calculate how these lights
are actually reflected off the
surface of these materials.
Similar to how light behaves in
the real world, and are
essential to making sure that
your AR scenes mimic reality.
What's interesting is that by
modifying these normals, you can
trick the engine to thinking
that your surface is actually
more detailed than it really is,
without need to add any
additional geometry.
If you take a look at this
example, you can see a simple
sphere, being rendered with flat
shading.
What this means, that the
normals associated with each
face of the mesh are pointing in
the exact same direction, as
seen by the 2D diagram.
Now, when you -- when light
reacts to this surface, you'll
be actually able to notice all
the different polygons
comprising this mesh due to
being evenly lit across each
face.
Here, though, we're using the
exact same model, but leveraging
a technique called smooth or
phong shading.
Notice that the normals are
actually gradually changing as
you move across the surface of
the polygon.
With the engine calculates the
reflection off of this model,
it'll give the impression of a
smooth, curved surface due to
the gradual interpolation of
these normals.
What's really awesome is that
these two models have the exact
same number of polygons
associated with them.
But, through this normal
manipulation, the object will
seem to have a much more
smoother and detailed surface,
without the need to, again, add
or change any of the geometry
associated with this mesh.
Whew. Alright, so we've gone
through enough about normals.
Let's, kind of, go over what it
takes to add a little bit more
shiny to your scene.
CampfiAR is definitely starting
to look better.
But, some of these normal maps
[inaudible] but some of these
parts seem a bit dull,
especially the objects that you
expect to be shiny or
reflective, kind of like the
kettle or the fish in this
scene.
What we see here is the results
of applying a metal map to our
AR scene.
A metal map is used to determine
which object surfaces should
exhibit reflective properties.
Once the material property's
activated, notice how shiny and
reflective the area's we've
designated as being metallic
are.
And, on the kettle as well as
the scales of the fish.
So, let's focus specifically on
the kettle.
We'll begin by taking the
original albedo map, and then
apply a metal map to the
metalness property of this
material.
After the application of the
metal map, the 3D render will
actually designate the surface
to be reflective in the areas on
the map that were actually
white.
And, despite begin called
metalness, it doesn't
necessarily mean that your
object needs to contain metal.
Rather, we're just letting the
3D engine know that this object
should exhibit, kind of, a
reflective surface.
Now, it's best to use the
metalness map on your model,
like our kettle here, when it
has both a mixture of metallic
and non-metallic surfaces.
It's a simple grayscale map,
where the level of metalness
ranges from being black, for
non-metal surfaces, to white,
for metallic surfaces.
And, it allows for a single
material to be used to represent
both reflective and
non-reflective surfaces on your
single object.
However, this kettle's a bit
crazy reflective.
And, doesn't really quite
provide the look that we're
hoping for.
So, in this case, we want to
potentially vary the amount of
reflectivity, as well as
simulate the fact that all
surfaces are not perfectly
smooth.
And, they actually might exhibit
slight small, microabrasions to
their surface.
And, this is where the roughness
material property comes into
play.
So, returning back to CampfiAR,
you can see how the reflective
surfaces are a bit too smooth.
As we layer on the roughness
maps, you can see that we are
going to modify both the kettle
and the fish to adjust the way
that they're reflecting.
And then, after we apply the
roughness material property to
both of these objects, you can
clearly see the reduction of the
reflectivity.
This combination of roughness
and metalness properties are
another important concept to
focus on.
So, let's dive a little bit
deeper into the roughness
material property.
Use roughness to simulate micro
surface details, which in turn
will affect the way light is
being bounced off that surface.
If the roughness property is set
to completely smooth, then light
will bounce off of your surface
like a mirror.
As you increase the roughness of
the material, light reflects
over a wider range of angles.
Here, we're slowly scaling a
constant roughness value between
no roughness to max roughness on
the kettle itself.
And, this is a good way of being
able to simulate the concept of
having microsurfaces, and
blurring reflection to the point
where you might not see any
reflectivity depending on which
range you put your value to.
So, for the kettle, we've taken
the original metal surface, and
instead of just applying a
constant roughness value to it,
we actually applied a roughness
map.
And, this will help designate
the surfaces where we will be
scattering the light more often,
and more than others.
Once we've applied the roughness
map, we get to see the real
final look of the reflectiveness
of this kettle, which is a lot
less shiny as before.
Now, a combination of this
metalness property and this
roughness property really make
your reflective AR models look
phenomenal.
Roughness can be used to tweak
how much of your objects will
reflect the environment.
And, can really be used to add a
lot more realism to your
metallic surfaces.
You can use this roughness map
to add additional minor details
as we've done here, to make our
kettle look a little more
scuffed up.
Now, to close out materials, we
have two more material
properties that I want to
discuss to further refine your
models, and have a good balance
between performance and
aesthetics.
Ambient occlusion is a material
property that is used to provide
your model with self-shadowing,
which in turn can lead to adding
additional depth and details to
your AR models.
Now, while normal maps are great
for applying significant amount
of details back into your AR
model, you can use ambient
occlusion to really hammer in
those details.
Here, we're visualizing the
ambient occlusion maps for
CampfiAR, and it's a bit of a
difficult effect to demonstrate,
as it's meant to be relatively
subtle.
But, see if you can notice the
additional shadows on the logs,
as well as certain areas near
the bottom of the kettle.
In our case here, it's kind of
like playing Where's Waldo?
with shadows, so let's focus in
on the logs in the scene.
So, here we're showing you the
normal maped logs before.
Now, there's some great details
found in the ridges, but we can
definitely improve some of these
areas.
Now, as we look at the ambient
occlusion map, you can see how
we've added some regions of
self-shadowing.
So, lower portions of the log,
as well as around the small
embedded stumps.
And, after we apply the map to
our ambient occlusion property,
I hope you can see the benefits
of adding those baked detail
shadows without the need of
using expensive dynamic lights
in your scene.
When working in AR, we recommend
that you actually bake your
ambient occlusion into a map.
Which is what we've done for
CampfiAR.
Rather than use the alternative,
such as screen space ambient
occlusions, which is a
camera-based post-process
effect, and can potentially lead
to poor rendering performance in
your scene.
And, last but certainly not
least, be frugal with the use of
your transparency in your
materials materials.
If you must use transparencies,
we recommend that you use
separate materials for objects
where you see a combination of
transparent and non-transparent
surfaces.
In general, when working with AR
content, the use of a lot of
transparent surfaces can
potentially have a huge impact
on performance, especially if
you are having transparent
surfaces that are, kind of,
stacked in front of each other
when you're viewing them.
This is known as overdraw, and
it's something that you
definitely want to avoid when
you're working in AR.
Whew. Alright.
I hope everybody's still with
me, as that was quite a lot to
go through.
So far, we've focused mostly on
how the AR content will react to
the simulated spotlights found
in our 3D engines.
But now, it's time to focus on
some ways to make our content
seem like it's actually part of
the real world.
A fantastic option to use to
compensate for varied lighting
conditions is to leverage one of
ARKit's well known features, and
light estimation.
Let's begin by activating this
functionality and see how it
affects our kettle.
Notice that how when the ambient
light changes in intensity in
the real world, a similar
adjustment is made to the
ambient light in our AR scene.
The way this works is that ARKit
analyzes each frame of the
video, and uses them to estimate
the lighting condition of the
real world.
It is an absolutely magical
feature that helps assure that
the amount to light applied to
your AR content matches what you
see in the real world.
Now, that we have magical light
wizards living in our AR scene,
let's discuss shadows.
Shadows in AR are really, really
hard to get right.
Your shadow needs to be able to
work in a wide variety of
situations.
Remember that people can be
potentially using your app
anywhere.
And, if your AR shadows differ
from the ones that are seen in
the real world environment, it
can be relatively jarring for
your experience.
Here, we have tried to
incorrectly cast a dynamic
shadow by using a directional
light as a sharp angle in our 3D
engine.
Shadows are a great way to make
objects actually feel grounded
in the real world, but in this
case, it doesn't really match
the shadows being seen in the
surrounding environment.
It's like we're purposely trying
to defy the laws of physics
here.
Instead, we suggest that you
place your directional light
directly overhead, and play a
little bit around with the
intensity of that effect to make
sure that it actually feels a
little bit more subtle.
This will allow your shadows to
work in a lot more different
situations, and a lot more
different scenarios.
An alternative to this is
actually using a method where
you can create your own drop
shadow, rather than using
dynamic lights in your scene,
which can get expensive, and can
severely affect performance if
you're rendering a lot of 3D
content.
Take the time to craft those
really good shadows.
And ensure that they will fit in
as many real world situations as
possible.
Ah, environment maps.
If you really want to astound
people, you definitely want to
use these maps, especially on
those AR objects that exhibit
reflectivity.
It'll make it seem like your AR
content exists right here, in
the real world.
And, to make it super easy to
leverage their powers we want to
show you how one of the new
features in iOS 12 and ARKit
2.0, automatic environmental
mapping, can help you achieve
this effect.
If you take a close look at the
kettle, originally we're using a
baked environment map that has a
kind of blush tinge to it.
Once we've activated the
automatic environmental mapping,
notice how the kettle now
reflects a lot of the ground,
and the surrounding color of the
current environment that we're
in.
You can even see a little bit of
the green from the grass that
this kettle's sitting in.
This is a fantastic feature
that'll really help ground your
objects into the real world, and
with careful use of roughness,
can really enhance the
believability of your scene.
So, now why is automatic
environmental mapping so
actually incredible?
Typically, these maps are used
to simulate the ability of
metallic surfaces to mirror the
environment around them.
You can see example of a cube
environment map here.
Now, before ARKit added
automatic environmental mapping,
you had to provide your own
image, and hope that it was
generic enough to work in a
large variety of situations that
your app may be used in.
But now, with ARKit 2.0, you can
kiss those sleepless night,
fretting about whether your
environment map is actually
ruining your AR experience.
For more information about
environmental mapping, and other
new features found in ARKit 2.0,
please check out the talk by
Arsalan and Reinhard called
What's New in ARKit 2.
And now, to close out CampfiAR,
let's put all this together, and
add the final touches to the
campfire.
With a little bit of animations
and [inaudible] effects, along
with the applications of all the
techniques discussed today,
CampfiAR is ready for primetime.
Now, if I ever get the crazy
urge to go outside, I can
suppress those urges, and stay
safely at my desk, enjoying the
joys of simulated outdoors with
CAmpfiAR.
Who needs EpiPens?
Not this guy.
We went through lot of different
topics today.
So, I quickly want to reiterate
some of the important things to
keep in mind while you're
developing your app.
Remember that your app can be
used in a wide variety of real
world conditions, so always make
sure aesthetic choices allow
your content to blend almost
anywhere.
Once you've decided what kind of
AR experience you wish to build,
adhere to what you think your
rendering budget is, and work as
many optimizations as you can to
get that smooth performance and
efficiently use your power.
And, finally leverage the use of
various material properties, as
well as the built-in features of
ARKit to get your AR content
looking great, in order to
delight people who use your app.
And, for your reference, here's
a table of all the material
properties we worked with today
to build out CampfiAR.
You can get additional
information at the link
provided.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]